I'll start recording immediately because
I forgot to start recording for the
lecture of Claire at least for part of
it let me see here
all right can everyone hear me
yeah I see shaking ass that's good
I now also open to chats I finally found
out how to deal with the chat while
being in a formal uh presenting mode
um I think it's about time to start
um welcome to the second lecture for
um Urban social geography where I'll be
spend in the next two hours uh let's see
if yeah how how much time we need
um for election Urban cultures so um as
you remember in the last session I
largely gave a historical overview of
what I consider to be essential let's
say core coordinates of thinking about
culture in urban geography and more
widely some other let's say related
disciplines starting with a brief
discussion well but it's a relatively
specific discussion on Frederick Jameson
and his notion of post-modernism moving
to the shift of moving to let's say the
1980s early 1990s debate on um
post-modern urbanism and the LA School
of urbanism and then shifting to a to a
wider or but also related debate on the
symbolic economy those were the key
coordinates that I tried to to get
across one of the questions well you
can't see the slides can can everyone
see the slides oh that's odd thank you
for asking the question because I'm
actually screen sharing now
um let me just see I'll just
stop share you should be able to see the
slides
another sec
um
share screen
I'll do it like this done simply this
just a sec
okay you now see my screen
except that I can't see you now just a
sec
this is odds uh one here we are
yeah never see the slides now
I see you one yes thank you so I hope
that's okay perfect okay yes okay thanks
a lot yeah feel free to unmute sometimes
that's easier than uh than working with
uh sign language
um the only thing is I can't see you now
let me see
um where is that
just want to say ah here we are okay now
I see you and hopefully you see me and
we see the slides you did hear what I
was saying right so okay let's let's
keep it from there
um so what I try to get across last week
is what I just discussed I tried to give
an historical overview of some of the
core elements that I thought I think
were are important thinking about Urban
culture over the last 30 40 years
actually oh and some people are in the
waiting room
my life is so so easy let me see
[Music]
before you start working here where are
we no no no no
um I'll stop sharing again that will
admit all again
but at some point it becomes a bit
tricky then people just have to wait for
the last the next uh
the next pause is otherwise it becomes
difficult because with the session of
clear I could actually manage this but
since I don't have an assistant next to
me this is uh what we'll work with Okay
next round we'll we'll go for another
run here we go uh
chat
and start
and now I just need to slip this
do we disadvantage that I don't see you
anymore ah here we are there we are
okay getting there
so for the third time uh I tried to give
an historical overview one of the
questions I received last week is okay
are we going to learn more about actual
cultures so cultural expressions stuff
that interests interests us as 20 20
year olds 20 year olds that's what I
remember so the question to the answer
to that question is yes uh in the
session today I will focus a bit more in
detail on specific well I I will always
focus on research on Urban culture but
look at zooming in more specifically on
Research that looks at actual cultural
expressions but always from the
perspective as to how this has been done
in urban studies there are many other
disciplines of course that focus on
culture or cultural expressions coming
from the humanities in particular
but I will largely zoom in on how this
has been approached within within Urban
studies
um
that will hopefully become clear or
clearer in a minute
before doing so I have I want to broaden
the debate a bit beyond urban geography
per se and and I show some of the slides
and discuss some of the slides that I
also already mentioned uh last uh last
week
because if you look at the way urban
geography has has undergone its own
cultural turn as I'm as I hinted at last
week what we saw happening in in
parallel is that many other disciplines
within the social science the humanities
have also undergone a kind of spatial
turn so we've seen a kind of meeting
halfway a kind of rakash more between
geography becoming a more cultural
discipline but other disciplines also
becoming more cultural becoming more
geographical becoming more spatial
um so this cultural this spatial turn
had a number of reasons as I already
mentioned I think last week one of them
being a post 1989 obsession with
globalization so the moment you start
thinking seriously about globalization
you quasi-automatically start thinking
about spatial issues about geographical
issues because what if it's here but
also somewhere else you start thinking
about Connections
the other one being a kind of critique
of modernity which had really shaped I
think most of the social science and
Humanities debates up until the 1970s
which primarily sort of uh paid
attention to temporal issues to time
because that's the very logic of
thinking in terms of modernity so what
we've seen over the years since the late
1970s roughly speaking is we see this
kind of de-emphasizing us of temporal
issues and emphasizing
uh of of spatial issues and this is
where the let's see the spatial turn
comes in so this in turn and this is
what I want to briefly focus on for the
opening of this today's session led to
an increased interaction between urban
geography Urban anthropology and
cultural studies many other disciplines
also but for me those are some of the
core disciplines that really
um shaped I think the future of uh of us
the the the the research on Urban
culture at Large
now there are
a number of core teams in urban
anthropology and and or cultural studies
that have shaped the late 20th century
early 21st century trajectory of what I
consider to be let's say
interdisciplinary Urban studies I'm not
going to give a review here of urban
anthropology or cultural studies they're
both fascinating disciplines I learned a
lot from both disciplines
um I mean I was trained in cultural
studies myself before becoming a
geographer you could say
um but there are two let's say teams
that I want to briefly flag here which I
think
um I have a much longer history in in in
anthropology and cultural studies but
have which have really been picked up in
in into this finale Urban studies and
shaped this debate up to the present day
the first debate uh being around what I
label here is informality
it's the kind of debate that that
emerged in anthropology and and
development studies largely focusing on
informal economy labor markets
precarious work migration issues of
workers legality and illegality
distinction but also the regulation so
the political governance of uh of
informality I'll give a few examples in
a minute
the second core team that I think is
important to to keep in mind as a kind
of understanding of the history of
research on Urban culture is research on
everyday life that's a term that is you
don't see the term used that much
anymore I would say in the last 10 years
or so you still see it a lot but then
less so as a theoretical concept but it
was it was a term that was pretty much
dominant almost in dominance in the
1980s 1990s 2000s largely used as a kind
of shorthand or a kind of buzzword for
referring to issues around agency
community community building also
resistance issues as well as consumption
and identity questions and related
representational questions which then in
turn uh had an often a lot to do with
how things were represented in in media
so everyday life
refers to many things just as
informality refers to many things but if
you would have to give a kind of
nutshell summary this slide pretty much
covers it I think
now briefly if you think about
informality within biology Urban
anthropology and development studies
it's a term that is last was less use in
in cultural studies it's a classic team
especially from the early 1970s onwards
the the core reference and perhaps uh
the the first person who coined the idea
of the informal economy that many others
of course who did research on the
informal economy without labeling it as
such was key to heart and one of the
classic articles or one of the first
articles there is this article from 1973
which is titled informal income
opportunities and urban employment in
Ghana now the article is actually case
study as such is less relevant than
um than the understanding as to what he
coined in this article how this is
shaped let's say subsequent debates so
heart primarily focused on a number of
things you focused on actual employment
so people making a living beyond
government jobs Beyond factories and
Beyond large-scale companies yeah I said
okay there's a whole world out there of
how people make a living especially in
Ghana but he then sort of extrapolated
this through Urban Africa at large say
okay there's a whole world out there of
work that we actually don't see we don't
capture it we don't matter we don't see
it because we don't have the vocabulary
to really pay attention to it
so that's that's the first observation
he makes there yeah that makes it uh he
bases this on a distinction between
informal and formally where he says well
all the vocabulary that we have is
largely catering to especially from
economics to capturing registering and
registering and measuring uh formal
labor so labor that actually shows up in
in GDP uh values Etc yeah labor that is
actually taxed and a lot of the labor
that we see in urban Africa you argued
is not taxed as such or we don't see it
for that reason
so he introduced the distinction
informal labor formal economy formal
employment and informal employment
he also then makes a distinction between
illegitimate and legitimate labor where
he said okay legitimate activity which
is not the same as informal and formal
he says okay we can have informal
activity according to him so economic
activity which is not measured as such
which is still legitimate which he then
argues those are activities that do
actually make a contribution to economic
growth but at a small scale so if you
let's say uh sell uh uh Foods on on a
local market but this is not this is not
captured you're not registered as an
official business this according to them
is legitimate in for a legitimate
informal activity which I think most of
us can actually agree with and then
there's illegitimate informal activity
where he says well that can refer to
criminal activities but also for example
to bagging or bribery or corruption
which he considers to be a illegitimate
so there's a kind of fourfold
Distinction which is uh which has really
shaped the thing to debate and you can
question and disagree with some of the
species of his arguments but the way he
structured this idea has uh has been
quite important
now I mentioned this here not because I
want to discuss with you Urban Africa or
1973 Keith Hart but because I think some
of the the let's see the landmark
studies that he and others have done in
the early 1970s have informed the
debates that followed elsewhere
informality is an interesting concept
because it's one of the few Concepts You
could argue that has really seen a
concept travel from the global styles to
the global North so where most of us are
very well aware of critiques to what
let's say Urban studies saying well it's
actually eurocentric or at least Western
Centric informality is one of those
Concepts which you could say started in
the global South and actually has been
picked up increasingly in order to
understand also practices within the
global North to such an extent I would
argue that as one of the few Concepts
which really transcends this kind of
global style Global nor divides and
really sort of contributes to thinking
in terms of a global Urban studies so if
you look at work for example of of
ananya Roy or Jennifer Roberson they've
picked up on the on the informality
topic as a way of also thinking about
Urban studies in more Global terms
without being being let's say
eurocentric or Western Centric
um there are all kinds of related terms
and they all have to do let's say this
disciplinary specifics that are pretty
much try to cover the same field but I
won't discuss here such as unregistered
economy Black Market the non-observed
economy Undeclared work or the Shadow or
hidden economy and for those that say
more trained and feminist Theory it's
quite obvious let's say that the
distinction between informal and formal
but actually also maps on to the
distinction between public and private
with public with public activities often
being seen as part of the former economy
but let's say private activities such as
care work being seen as the informal
economy often also not measured and thus
supposedly not worthy of attention yeah
and of course this is as overlapped and
and been involved in rethinking the
terms of that debate to an important
extent also
so on Urban anthropology when thinking
about informality you get the research
on the opportunities but also precarious
created by unregulated economic
activities uh I will give some examples
later but it's quite obvious for example
if we fast forward let's say to research
on creative and cultural Industries and
research that is now being done on
precarious uh precarious uh artistic
labor for example it's it's it struggles
with a similar attention where to a
large extent artistic labor is also
unregulated which creates all kinds of
freedoms and opportunities but is at the
same time this let's say this
unregulated nature which makes it very
precarious because there's no way you
can actually support or let's say where
a state or a welfare state of other
mechanisms can actually structure the
kind of economic activities
Urban anthropology historically speaking
has also seen a strong interest in the
gender dimensions of informal works I've
already hinted at this partially in the
home situation partially mostly females
being women working on markets Etc so
all kinds of uh gendered in exclusions
that are part of this discussion and
again these have shaped debates in the
in the decades that followed
also important things that Urban
anthropology we see informality being
linked strongly to transnational
Dimensions yeah so with the idea that
informal uh labor market in formal Urban
labor markets are often also highly
transnational labor markets on one level
with
diaspora connections people sending back
their their their earnings or part of
their earnings to their home country but
also with many migrants actually
occupying in former labor markets in in
country in cities across the world so
there's a kind of transnational
connection which urban anthropology
certainly was among the first uh to pay
uh to pay attention to oh which has seen
an increasing amount of research in in
urban and interdisciplinary Urban
studies
to use an example of the mandir was in
Barcelona for example who often have an
African background uh and who have who
live in relatively precarious situations
well very precarious situation in Spain
being sort of legal illegal semi-legal
in different different kinds of statuses
and trying to make a living uh in in
this case Barcelona
so that's a five minute summary of a 40
40-year debate in urban anthropology so
apologies for any sort of uh lack of
selfies but my discussion is relatively
instrumental here and that I want to get
across some of the key uh let's say
conceptual elements uh conceptual
nuggets you could say that that should
also shape debate and interdisciplinary
Urban studies a second term that that
I'm sure you've come across before in in
your reading is everyday life
now but wasn't anthropology but
especially I think in cultural studies
this notion of everyday life really
shaped the debate and and and signifies
in many ways a concern with the lift
experiences and meanings constructed by
subjects in their own worlds
um partially emerging you could save in
in the 1970s as a chronic critique of
supposedly structuralist Marxist theory
paying more attention to agency so it's
part of that 1970s 1980s debate but then
also um
increasingly moving into a let's say
substantive Empirical research
where uh where research started paying
attention to the actual lift experiences
and the meanings of of people yeah so
people as active creative agents rather
than as passive consumers uh this is
kind of what the the broad
interdisciplinary sprawling debate of
everyday life uh signifies
now there are many
I think within different supplies that
have in one way or another try to engage
with everyday life with or without using
the concept one which I will only hint
at I think here but which might be
discussed in some more detail by those
that follow not I know what not everyone
does but depending on your program those
that follow Urban sociology of Ava
swimkidao there's a kind of tradition of
community studies and anthropology and
cultural studies which historically has
focused on participant observation and
extensive periods of field work to
really gain trust and insight knowledge
of everyday practices so basically an
anthropological stance you could say you
become part of a community and only
through this inside knowledge you will
actually understand the meanings and and
interpretations attached to certain
practices
it of course also has a history going
back to the Chicago school with research
on also ethnographic research on on
urban areas and various let's say Urban
topics such as gangs ethnic segregation
lifestyle delinquency
but there's also a rural connection
whereas especially within our sociology
let's say partially in parallel to the
Chicago school which was always more
urban in its orientation where some
classic Community studies especially in
the 1950s and 1960s
um sort of started applying you could
say rural concepts of classic Community
studies to Urban settings so look going
into a supposed community in an urban
setting and then focusing on let's say
family and kinship relations or
traditions and rituals yeah this kind of
community studies literature has been
quite heavily criticized over the years
largely for being too localists or for
assuming Community as relatively
homogeneous which was already
problematic you would say in a in a
rural setting but certainly you is
problematic in a much more dynamic
dynamic Urban setting so this idea that
communities actually share same values
was increasingly questioned but the
tradition there of let's say focusing on
everyday life of these communities uh
was already was established by this kind
of uh this kind of literature
excuse me uh there's somebody waiting on
their waiting room let's see because
every time when I have to well I might
be able to do it like this
nope where are we
participants here we are okay four more
because I can't do this all the time
because it's quite interrupting so but
I'll now I'll start again
okay you can still see me
perfect now we'll continue
um
so especially from the 1980s onwards I
think we've seen a Revival of the of the
community studies uh that moved beyond
the kind of nostalgic notion of
community and this is where sort of
again the everyday life uh Notions uh
um well returns in a way or becomes more
present in in in in theorizing uh urban
communities
some basic Trends and again I just
mentioned them here but I think they
basically still structure the debate up
to this day is that artists started
using conflict theoretical approaches
instead of cohesion theoretical
approaches so looking at
let's say interactions obviously social
interactions between uh actors between
people but also not sort of assuming
let's say cohesion theoretically but
assuming that's the conflict
theoretically you could say very bluntly
speaking you could say instead moving
from a dual Crimean perspective to a
Marxist perspective that's very
simplistic but basically that's is what
covers to a certain extent the debates
also focus on network ties local and
trans local I already mentioned this
with Urban anthropology
uh care and support and unequal and
changing our settings and because of the
let's say the interest in let's say
conflicts and how communities are
constructed not how they I say are
assumed to be there was increasing
interest to let's see the shifting
symbolic boundaries between communities
so the sort of the the making connection
but also making distinctions between uh
between communities and between groups
and that of course then opens up let's
say the base to not just communities as
let's say an aprily facts of social life
but more into debates around communities
of choice and elective belonging so they
can move into subcultures or lgbtqi
communities but also gated communities
for example in urban settings where
people choose to belong to a very
separate community
now the everyday is really a striking uh
coincidence let's say the career of this
concept because it's a truly
transdisciplinary concept perhaps even
more so than uh than the informal or
informality truly transdisciplinary
maybe with a strong Humanity background
but really connecting cultural Theory
with philosophy with Marxism with
ethnography with more structuralism with
sociology and with Aesthetics and that's
that's precisely what makes this concept
I think so interesting or so influential
for research on Urban cultures now you
have to be careful here because the
simple fact that a concept is used and
all these different let's say Traditions
or disciplines doesn't mean of course
that is used in the same way so if you
look for example that's and there's no
no time to discuss this here but if you
look for example that everyday life in
in let's say ethnography it's quite
different than everyday life and
Aesthetics and quite different than
everyday life let's say in more post
post-structural literary Theory yeah
um so you have to be quite careful there
but for every studies I would argue
there are a number of approaches which
have really let's say let's see Eternal
references in a way those those artists
that are continually continuously
referenced one is the unavoidable Humvee
Lafayette
everyone references hallway Lafayette
who sees the everyday as a side of
utopian possibility but in in line with
let's say it's Marx's credentials also
sees the everyday as colonized by the
commodity form so a commodification
logic also shaping the everyday that has
been of course Very differential thing
in in in our studies to a large extent
also because it it's pretty compatible
with the kind of critical political
economic Urban studies approach so
people can claim or can become more
interested in culture but don't actually
don't have to leave let's say the house
of political economy too far they can
stay pretty close to that kind of debate
but I would ask you to also pay
attention to other more let's say
perhaps empirically minded research that
was still very theoretical and I can I
will only mention two here which which
have been equally at least influential I
think in in urban studies one being uh
worked by Stuart Hall
um who is a massive towering figure I
think within cultural studies British
cultural studies at least
um who looks at let's say the everyday
life Elijah tour you could say
especially in this book here which is an
additive book and a compilation of let's
see classic uh papers of the British
cultural studies
Center at that point in time uh to the
looks at it to the subcultural lands and
the notion of subculture was coined by
British cultural studies and even though
subculture is also where we tend not to
use anymore many of the let's say
practices that we assumed to uh to shape
subcultures are with us today so we
might not name them subcultures anymore
we might talk about them it seems or
about the networks or something along
those lines but the idea that
subcultures are let's say every day but
also are also kind of symbolic
opposition to a dominant social order
this idea that they're in one way or
another resistance uh is is very
influential I think so if you look at
the literature on let's say subcultures
or let's say neural literature on on
protest movements or let's say clubbing
culture it's it's it still uses these
kinds of this kind of vocabulary
so that then directs attention allows
you to Urban practices of resistance but
also style of fashion of social
practices or the particular codes that
are used within within a community and
interacts attention I think also to a
particular let's say generational
category namely Urban Youth
um which I think was really has always
been a researched in a way but British
cultural studies tradition as as perhaps
directed most of his attention to let's
see this particular category uh of this
particular generational layer
typical however also for British
cultural studies at that point in time
is a certain gender blindness if you
look at let's say the early cultural
studies tradition uh those that did
research on subcultures by and large
looked at new sculptures as you could
say boyish masculine use cultures yeah
so there's certainly a certain gender
blindness in the kind of resistant youth
cultural literature
however this has increasingly been
addressed in subsequent work partially
this kind of Club cultures literature
that I mentioned also by the work of
artists such as Angela mcrobbie who was
part of the early British cultural
studies tradition is now a professor at
the goldsmiths college and it was really
addressed this kind of literature this
kind of gender dimension of uh of
cultural studies
another order and this is certainly a
book I can well the other book also but
I can certainly um recommend you to read
this book if only because it's a very
pleasant read it's beautifully written
and it's not a thick book I think it has
around 200 Pages Max I think it's pretty
uh pretty readable
uh and his and then he's written many
things on everyday life but this is
perhaps the most heavily cited book the
practice of everyday life from 1984 the
having said the term that the English
translations from 1984 if I'm not
mistaken it might be later that the
original French day is actually from
that time I I will need to look it up I
forgot
is beautifully written it's perhaps more
poetic I would say and less political
than British cultural studies or at
least Less in your face political uh but
it has a vocabulary I think that is um
uh has been very influential
um according to the Sato where Society
is is largely shaped and I think the by
the binary nature of it the way he
phrase it has been has been criticized
but still the the
um it has been very influential but
according to this the society's largely
shaped by tactics versus strategies or
strategies versus tactics in that order
perhaps with a kind of states
by and large he's French right so to see
who puts the states very Central perhaps
even more so than the economy
um devises all kinds of let's say
strategies structures orders of social
life against which uh we as Citizens as
as groups although it has a relatively
individual Focus device all kinds of
tactics in order to resist to to avoid
to intervene
um so all kinds of creative ways of of
dealing with dealing with strategies and
sort of turning it around and doing
something else with it this is the kind
of literature right that which as I said
the binary nature of it that this idea
that there is such a thing as strategies
let's say top-down strategies versus
bottom-up tactics because that's the
kind of image you see is problematic
it's too simplistic I think but it has
very much shaped this idea that we have
let's say uh media cultures shaping uh
shaping things but we are also creative
consumers we can actually change and
creatively interpret things yeah
gives a very Urban angle to this it
really talks a lot about let's say
walking in the city for example some of
the walking literature and walking
um there's a door is one of the key
artists there and it really looks at
okay obviously there's a city which has
been designed and structured and
constructed in a certain way but we as
soon as we can walk in the city and sort
of adapt and use a different line route
of walking Etc and in ways not intended
by the designers
so it doesn't lead to a kind of
literature any kind of reading reading
which looks at tactics everyday
practices I would say the practice of
everyday life as situated it's often
very local sometimes as defensive in in
defense uh yeah in defense too but also
sometimes opportunistic you sort of pick
up on some structured elements and do
something else with it so that's the
kind of literature and especially kind
of vocabulary which again has shaped a
lot of things this idea of of of
achieved a lot of research uh on on
Urban sorry on everyday life
okay
that's my first part I will I'm just
going to quick look but I see no one
entering anymore because now I have
pretty much all
chat box not a box is open
um are there any questions on this first
part as a kind of
uh first corner I see a question from
Vera as James Scott can you maybe
explain this very critical brief
question
I don't see you so you're gonna have to
sort of speak up now I was just thinking
about the the work of uh the the circle
Michelle that you mentioned yeah and
actually also James Carter is from the
the same period he published the the
everyday life experience of the pleasant
Etc yeah and he spoke about this uh
infrapolitics and Mathis stuff
absolutely no it's it's very much part
of the state the same reasoning so one
of the other books that I could have
mentioned deep raps but it has been less
influential in in urban studies but
there's a great book by by James Scott
also seeing like a state
which is basically this this kind of
logic it's the kind of see like States
you could replace that with the with the
dosato vocabulary of strategies and then
you have citizens people communities
these profitable community oriented
they're partially shaped I think by his
anthropological backgrounds which is
which devise all kinds of tactics as
ways of resistance no absolutely it's
it's that kind of that kind of debate
yeah good question
any other questions on this first point
if so just speak up because that's easy
for me than go through the whole list of
people
no
okay
then I'll continue with the second Parts
well yeah indeed
so a couple of lines of research that
are let's say more contemporary so
current lines of research within Urban
studies that focus on Urban culture
with an interdisciplinary over studies I
think here we definitely move beyond the
realm of urban geography narrowly
defined and I want to discuss with you
today
um
the reason why I spend a fair amount of
attention to the previous argument to
the previous debate is also because as
you will see in the discussion that now
follows is that the kind of vocabulary
that these kinds of debates use are very
still influenced knowingly or
unknowingly unknowingly so by the
previous discussions so by both issues
on the symbolic economy postmodern
urbanism informality in everyday life so
that really still shapes I think some of
these current debates
I will now discuss all possible
directions uh in in interdisciplinary
over studies on Urban culture if only
because culture is such a let's say
a slippery concept and and research has
to really explode in all kinds of
directions and as led to all kinds we
could say sub-disciplines uh or or let's
say certain strands of research that
that would be impossible to do uh in uh
in a two-hour uh lecture so I've been
quite let's say uh selective the
selection has been purely based on my
own preferences in a sense that I'm
going to discuss with you the number of
strands of research that I consider to
be interesting or the most interesting
strands of research obviously I also
consider to be this the more to be the
more productive strands of research and
a lot of research is being done in this
uh in this kind of field
the first round of research I want to
discuss with you and again I'll pause at
the end of this trend is around the Arts
activism and urban engagement
um
research on the Arts of course there is
an established tradition obviously
primarily in the humanities of aesthetic
analysis of the Arts yeah so of painting
of music of theater mostly actually as
an increasingly so diverse uh
differentiating into different
disciplines so we'll have musicology you
will have tiered studies you will have
let's see art history or visual studies
and those are established editions
afterwards histories reaching back 100
years yeah
Urban studies and even as an
interdisciplinary field Builds on these
Traditions but actually it's primarily
uses a sociological and or political
economic approach towards the arts and
culture so some of the elements I will
discuss here they certainly do not
capture the diversity offer let's say
research on the Arts that is out there
yeah but um they do pretty much capture
I think what's out there within within
nervous studies
social scientific approach towards the
Arts obviously shapes the kinds of
questions being asked so one the result
of this is that we also see through the
let's say the critical focus on let's
say the political economy of the Arts we
also see it about in many or with many
orders and many in many Publications and
interest in the political or critical
potential and practice of the Arts yeah
this is partially also a response to
um and that's something I will not
discuss in detail here to a relatively
dominant debate on the creative and
cultural Industries which has really
shaped I think the debate on the Arts uh
in the last 20 years this idea that
creative and cultural Industries
contribute to to let's see our
contemporary knowledge economy that
there are key economic sectors in in our
in our current cities and thus with a
strong focus on economic dimensions of
culture
is interesting you could say the
political potential uh the critical
potential of the Arts is also partially
irresponsiveness there are longer
Traditions I will discuss some of them
but this is a way of also trying to look
at the creative Industries debate
critically and say okay well actually we
miss out on a lot when we do not address
the let's say the the resistant
dimensions of the Arts
now that dream well there are many of
course but I'm summarize them here as as
three main lines of urban research on
the Arts and I will discuss them uh
briefly in turn one and perhaps the most
established line of research uh also
because it ties in I think with a with a
history of research in the
uh well in in in our Theory basically in
an art history is research on public
arts and or site-specific Arts the terms
overlap
a second line of research is research on
artists and urban social movements the
relation between artistic practice and
urban social movements and of course
with social movements we can establish
debate within Urban studies also
and the third literature is literature
that is perhaps the most cultural
studies oriented literature is
literature on popular culture and urban
politics so it's literature that that's
increasingly
um I say engaged with with let's see
also theoretical and philosophical
literature on the political uh and how
public culture plays a role in relation
to Urban political questions
and I will discuss of course what I mean
with the political here because it's not
institutional politics per se or if at
all
now the first line of research within uh
within this this section
as public art or site-specific art
um for your readings I I added an
admittedly relatively long uh chapter uh
by Rosalind Deutsche a New York theorist
so apologies for the length of the of
the chapter but I I included it because
it's well for two reasons one goes in
Deutsche is a key art theorist a key
cultural theorist who very early on I
think understood the the productive
connections between our Theory and urban
studies or geography critical geography
yeah and who wrote in the 1980s and
1990s a few foundational papers on uh on
the Arts and the urban
the the paper here is called uneven
development public art in New York City
and it basically covers how you could
say a history of dealing with or
engaging with public art in New York
City
um both by let's say local governments
local the real estate developers more or
less in Project developers and uh and
artistic communities
I could have chosen other articles there
are many other articles possible
um in the same book by the way and I
think I included the full book there's
also a great uh critique the feminist
critique of uh of Jameson and Harvey by
the way I think the the the chapters
called men in space if I'm not mistaken
so basically she devises it develops a
feminist ethnographic critique of
Jameson and Harvey so I could definitely
advise you to read this also
um but in this particular paper she
basically
develops a critique of the
instrumentalization of public art so an
emotion of the public by local
governments and developers so this idea
that public Arts the way is presented or
used by local governments and developers
let's say for those working more on
planning in many countries you will have
if you have a kind of building scheme or
a local local planning project a certain
percentage of the budget needs to be
spent on public art now for those who
know this in most cases this rarely
leads in many cases in most cases this
does not lead to very interesting types
of art it's a kind of tick to box
exercise in some cases of course it does
so she develops the kind of critique of
how public art is instrumentalized in
order to further you could say the
uneven development of New York City so
it kind of shaped by Elite concerns and
shape of political political economic
concerns
so public garden becomes a kind of
legitimation device for uneven
development uneven development
the issue briefly refers and I mentioned
here because I like the term to the term
pseudo pseudo public sphere which is a
critique of Alexander klug and another
theorist on the sort of this idea of
Harvard Martian kind of Ideal public
sphere as a field of deliberation where
he says well actually there's very
little actual dialogue taking place but
she also hints that and this is
something that for example Nancy Fraser
and other theorists later data also
developed in more detail perhaps to this
idea of the emerges oppositional public
spheres yes there is uneven development
but it kind of pseudo public sphere but
we also see kind of oppositional public
spheres emerging public spheres which
which on top of that have a heavy
emphasis on let's say cultural and
aesthetic Dimensions so basically often
artistic communities are related to
actors being engaged in the design of
oppositional public spheres and again of
course this especially for those
interested in the Arts has been of
massive influence and thinking to what
kind of role can the Arts play in in the
urban and in urban development at Large
now here's a nice quote Thing by
Deutsche that summarizes like uh
basically this this kind of idea and the
critique also so the idea that art
cannot assume the existence of a public
what must help produce one and that the
public sphere is less a physical space
than a social nullify to a considerable
considerable extent accepted divisions
between public and non-public art
potentially any exhibition venue is a
public sphere and conversely the
location of artworks outside privately
owned galleries in parks and plazas or
simply Outdoors hardly guarantees that
you will address the public
now I'm sure that the the this quote
perhaps needs a bit of unpacking right
um but basically what she's trying to
get at here is in the first sentence is
that we cannot assume that by simply
let's say putting public art on a Public
Square for example we cannot assume that
we automatically address the public yeah
people just don't mind not engage with
it uh people just that might just be
there but but that doesn't really make
it public right we can only make it
public if it actually is actively engage
with people so you actually you actually
have to construct a public and this is
more than what most public Arts
supposedly public art achieves yeah
at this so this this is the first
question the question you're the first
critique she has the second line is okay
we we this actually leads If You Think
Through The Logical conclusions of this
it means that
it uh simply by putting uh arts in the
out in the open doesn't make public art
but it also means that for example we
can have public arts in a gallery yeah
as long as you engage with the public
this obviously would constitute public
art so she critiques this distinction
within much of our theory of that time
uh that that relied on this idea that uh
a critique of let's say Modern Art is
that you move out of move out of the
gallery and into the public she says
well actually yes that's a good idea but
it doesn't really make for public art
per se
so this is basically the kind of let's
say dichotomy she's playing with and
that are important I think to uh to um
well to keep in mind
short summary most important thing to
keep in mind is that that we have an art
object but this art object needs actual
engagement with an audience with the
public in order to become public yeah
that's that's important to keep in mind
here
to make it a bit more uh concrete she
she has one very famous example
um by an equally famous artist although
not not at the time I think he was still
relatively let's say young in his career
at that point in time
um which is Richard Sarah's tilted Arc
this example is also discussed in the in
the paper by
um uh by uh by Deutsche
now as you can see on the on the image
here
this is quite obviously an intervention
in public space right it's a massive
piece of work it's a 37 meter long and
3.7 meter tall steel plate on Foley
Square which is uh in lower Manhattan
New York yeah
so if anything this this is this is a
kind of public artwork that you cannot
ignore obviously
now the way sort of this
um according to Deutsche the way sort of
this
um uh this artwork has been sort of uh
um let's say interpreted or let's say
received and it really shows some of the
problems of of public art as she she
made as she sees it
um some of you could say some of the
more conservative voices or sort of use
of the public space heavily criticize
this this piece of piece of art because
it basically it blocks their way of
Passage obviously right if you look at
the image uh it it it completely makes
impossible the usage of of the of the
Public Square by um by uh let's say
workers working moving from one building
to the next yeah at the same time uh
Deutsche argues well this doesn't
necessarily make it public arts and some
of the exaggerated claims made by
critical let's say Defenders of of this
piece of work uh they have really
focused you could say on assumptions as
the shifts in behavior of disposed uses
of this space so without actually
talking to people without actually
engaging with their own interests they
have assumed that the very fact that
people had to sort of re-articulate
their let's say everyday practices that
that led to a more aesthetic engagement
with the public space
now according to Deutsche the main
problem of the the discourse around this
this piece of art as well as the piece
of art itself is that it relied on a
very narrow aesthetic reading so
ignoring actual uses of urban space to
very generic claims on ecstatic uses of
the square yeah so actually it's a kind
of public art Intervention which refuses
to be public because it doesn't engage
in any sense with the public so this
idea that the public involves a dialogue
is completely ignored in this sense it's
basically and ultimately a strong artist
figure putting an art piece in a Public
Square without actually becoming part
and engaging with the public now this
piece was also removed in 1989 after
years of of critique but that's perhaps
a side note for the debate here
the counter example uh perhaps
oppositional public sphere You could
argue that that Deutsche uses and I
think this is a an artwork that that has
also been picked up by artists such as
Neil Smith who also wrote a piece on
this
um it's just of what just caused the
homeless vehicle project also a public
art space but a different kind of animal
so here in this case the vehicle decided
that I had a lab by the way when looking
at this picture because I'm pretty sure
it is the Trump Tower in the back but
that's something else
[Music]
which at that point in time had less of
a less of symbolic value perhaps in it
than it has now
um that's a different kind of animal
it's also public art
um also metal in many ways but here it's
a vehicle designed by artists by the
artist sorry and singular in
consultation with homeless people and it
was seen in a different way it was seen
as a practical tool for managing
everyday life of the homeless so in this
thing which you can let's say expand
when uh once when when when uh placed
somewhere uh it was a space for washing
for sleeping but also for storage space
for example for collecting empty bottles
or something
um so all this in into one one vehicle
vehicle sorry
this was both an exhibition object which
was exhibited in you could say classic
galleries as well as an objects for
actually making visible the homeless in
public space
so it's it I think on the base of this
example you already feel a bit to kind
of did let's say different approach uh
used uh towards the public by this this
piece of work or by the previous piece
by by Richard Sarah because here there
is an engagement with specific Urban
users highly marginalized you use on top
of this uh and thus implicitly or
explicitly a critique of uneven Urban
developments because it's a piece of
work that is situated in public space
and makes visible you could say the
effects of on the Urban Development on a
wider group of let's say Urban users
see whoops all right to my screens here
okay maybe to wrap up here on this on
this first strand of of research so
these are all examples of site-specific
art that that that moved art beyond the
exhibition space into the urban so there
was a thing within our Theory and art
and art history kind of internal
critique of the art worlds we have to
move out of the museums out of the
galleries but also a broadening or and
and sort of as a result of that also a
broadening of aesthetic debates to wider
social concerns
so this then leads to to Notions such as
going by critically in this case by by
Health Foster such as the Artist as a
sonographer which looks at the role of
the artist in the collaborative process
or the or the Artist as a participant
Observer so the artist has an
ethnographer
um so a critique of foster is also I
think this has been picked up in in
later work also is that the
globalization of our market and this is
where let's say different disciplinary
debates also become interesting that the
globalization of the Art Market this is
something rarely addressed sufficiently
I think in urban studies leads for
example to commissioning of artists to
produce a community-based site-specific
artworks however without the clear
knowledge of the local context so we see
let's say the bayonet by and biannual
Logic for example the Art Festival logic
where artists are are flown into
particular sites in order to develop
community-based work but they rarely
know the community so often these are uh
let's say only superficially speaking uh
Public Works uh of works of public Arts
and again so much of this was
foreshadowed a thing by the work of
Deutsche also but of course also others
at this point in time
okay
so that's the first strand of research
a second strand of research is around
Artisans Urban social movements and of
course I'm making analytical
distinctions here in practice some of
these debates overlap and there are
interactions but for the purpose of
discussion I think it's helpful to keep
them a bit separate
so the second strand of research tries
to look at artists and Earth social
movements so there's a long-standing
tradition obviously
of artists engaging in social movements
but mostly those have been researched I
would argue outside of urban studies
again within let's say the the the the
the field specific debates such as
theater or such as as our visual studies
Etc or art history
within our studies I think uh most of
the recent debates in this area has been
on the critique of the creative class
and creative Industries policies has
already hinted that or perhaps
neoliberal or entrepreneurial urbanism
more widely so what kind of role do
artists play in or part of urban social
movements and critiquing you could say
the neo-liberalization of of the urban
now it is a nice paper actually by
Johannes Novi and Claire colon who many
of you have seen attended today who
wrote a nice paper on struggling for the
right to the creative City in Berlin and
Hamburg and where they give a nice brief
brief but nice overview I think of urban
social movements uh so it's a kind of
literature which I'd well we don't
really discuss a thing in our social
geography that's an important literature
which moves from the history of
squatting and demonstrations against a
renewal uh politics to Urban Counter
Culture
um and then zoom in on the role of
artists and cultural workers in
contesting uh called creative class and
creative Industries politics now there's
a lot that can be said about this but
what is interesting here of course is
that automatically the debate becomes
you could say sociological or social
scientific because the moment you start
looking at artists within social
movements you can no longer look just at
their aesthetic Expressions but you
automatically have to look at what is
practically speaking their role with an
often quite heterogeneous diverse
composition of protest movements so we
see artists collaborating with diverse
set of actors and that of course shapes
their artistic practice
the role of artists here at least this
is what no vehicle highlights uh
highlights strongly I think they they
are definitely on to something there is
that artists and to some extent have a
privileged role or a particular role
within Urban social movements because
they have access to an experience with
media networks and a familiarity with
communication techniques so this then
leads to a discussion around the role of
artists in in how let's say particular
Urban conflicts are framed and reframed
by artists in an often in visual or
other ways
now there are many examples you can
discuss here this is one example
discussed also in the in the article of
the media protest in Berlin uh for those
that know Berlin you will know probably
also know sort of the history a bit of
media I should be I will now discuss
this here it's a big Urban Development
uh area uh on let's say well the
southern part of free design northern
part of course pack
um
partially which really let's let the
counter mobilization uh because this is
also the area which is let's say you
have a a concentration of artistic and
and and Leisure and clubbing activity so
here's a one
simple example where sort of artists you
could say have been involved in
developing different let's say visual
Aesthetics in a sense this basically
ironically Builds on the B Berlin
branding scheme so for those who don't
know it just Google it and it uses the
same kind of design but then changes the
kind of language right and sort of
ironically so instead of being hip being
creative and being uh how to translate
that if I can translate that being
well used and thrown away so to speak
modifiable yeah commodifiables perhaps
the closest yeah thank you very very
good point for real bus sounds better
though but you're right commodifiable
and they replace it by size
so it could be self
Again difficult to try itself uh
um
independent something along those lines
solidarity solidarity uh and be
resistance so stop gentrification so
this is one example
other examples of course not discussing
this particular article but um
uh from other
um other sites of course this kind of
artistic let's say framing of political
and urban conflicts ties in with a much
much longer history of Art and pro-step
protest most obviously in street art as
well as graphic design so there are a
couple of examples that are let's say
illustrative of this but certainly not
exhaustive so on the top right you see a
performance protest of an extension
extension Extinction Rebellion uh
protest in London uh do the middle left
I think has been quite a similar visible
to most if you would think black lives
matter paint the street I think this one
indeed Washington DC or to the bottom
right
a a
claim State well if a painting stating
the load to the debt repayments uh on
Street Arts intervention in Buenos Aires
yeah and I could have used many many
other examples but just to give a sense
of uh of the various sort of artists
play a role in in urban social movements
or at least early protests if it's less
organized than than a social movement
and again this has a much much longer
history uh going back uh many many years
some would argue since the emergence of
industrialization in many ways
about where are you
so the last
one yeah sorry
so the last round within this section
that I want to discuss with you
um is popular cultural and urban
politics
um this is last you could say less
around Urban social movement it also
lasts around the art world as such but
more about more broader cultural
expressions so here we really go back to
the classical core of cultural studies
that I discussed before with you to use
the focus on popular culture
as in everyday life as questioning
Authority but also as imagining
political Alternatives so the kind of
language that we then uh use or see use
in this kind of research is that there's
a it's about politics Beyond governments
and politicians to work on the street
Politics As I said about called it or
also kind of informalization and this is
where the informality the term pops up
again as you see informalization of the
State uh as for example Julian Boudreau
has called it a nice nice book by the
way
again there are many many examples here
to to to to to to to discuss the classic
case I would argue in this in this field
of research is hip-hop or rap rap music
more narrowly
which has been studied by now I think by
multiple multiple disciplines range from
musicology cultural studies anthropology
but also Urban studies which
traditionally has Focus I think strongly
on account of classic cultural studies
Community orientation Urban localities
and so the hood the ghetto as classic
Urban teams but which also I think in a
more critical literature uh has paid
attention to let's say the way rap
hip-hop culture has become less they
commodified in in its globalization of
of of its cultural form yeah but also
how it has been picked up by people from
outside of let's say the us as as
opposed to the source of of hip-hop
culture so that's the classic case the
library is full of books by now I think
on hip-hop there's some more interesting
than others this book by Murray Foreman
is quite uh quite an interesting example
though
similar research has also been done in
other genres uh typically a lot of
attention has been paid to music we see
it in other fields of activity also but
music has received perhaps most
attention in relation to popular culture
and the political
ranging from clubbing culture but also
Opera a lot of political perhaps less
obviously there to punk to Jazz to all
kinds of other cultural expressions
laughs
now with all these strands um
amount to is that they point to
different aesthetic strategies to engage
the urban yeah and this is something
that uh well as as also increasingly
received attention within Urban studies
um in an article about team and bias I
put a reference at the bottom of the
slides it points to a number of
different aesthetic strategies they as I
said as a right here they are
analytically distinct but in practice of
course they are they can they are
Messier it's some some let's say
aesthetic practices might be uh involved
in a number of things at the same time
here we said okay we basically we have
spectacle Grassroots Social Work
arousing the census and you can
automatically see a thing to have some
of the examples I've I've shown before
can be one or more of these things so
let's say for example the black lives
matter
um let's say Banner on the street so to
speak in a way you could argue this is
Grassroots uh you could argue this is
also social work you could argue with
some some I would also arouses the
senses because it's it's sometimes it
questions the Norms of what these trees
are for and questions different let's
say media representations but quite
obviously it's also spectacle because it
has really sort of traveled widely and
can easily be used any kind of
commodification strategy almost of
branding almost particular cities yeah
so there are all kinds of different
dimensions and it's it's an empirical
question ultimately to look at concrete
artistic practices to look at what the
different dimensions uh let's say their
relation to each other is
okay that's a long stretch for one uh
one slide but it might also be one of
the longer uh longer discussions
uh I'll take a short break here four
questions so please
um just either type them in the chat or
just start unmuting and speaking if if
there are any questions on this section
it gives me a chance to drink a bit of
water
wow that was a pre-prepared question
that was a fast or unless you type very
fast
so already can answer the question uh or
or a point I want to raise attention to
your related phenomenon where an
artistic creative approach
is used in part uh of a broader
participatory and Redevelopment strategy
here's some sort of institutionalizing
of arts and their movements is happening
as small quirky teams of Architects
planners activists and artists are
leading the process and through an
example and then there's a website maybe
you can so if if I understand you
correctly we won't look at the example
now
then it's your point being that artists
can actually be become Urban developers
themselves
will be good
I don't see you so you have to I have to
unmute the weekend now I see you but
you're immunity all right sorry
um yeah uh exactly like artists are
becoming part of the planning process or
more I think that the
um I think the low threshold uh approach
of like artistic experimental like
creativeness
as being employed in order to like
justify maybe participatory processes or
lead to a more like inclusion of people
or like let them participate participate
in the first place but also just to uh
get uh the people on board and create
some sort of tolerance so they this one
would be like the creative what is it
called the Festival of creative Urban
living in Milton Keynes
um the UK England uh so yeah it's like
uh it sounds like coming from a very
like dry urban planning background this
is like a weird thing to do because
people who are attending this they're
usually not aware of the broader scope
of this whole development that's
happening to them
um so that's just interesting to to also
take absolutely it's a good addition
something that I don't explicitly
mention here but it's a it's a
relatively new trend I think certainly
something that we see more and more of
the last I mean it was there before but
it has become more visible I think in
the last 10 years
um I would still argue though that the
same kind of critical vocabulary already
introduced by Deutsche is also necessary
for these projects because in some of
these projects or initiatives at least
we do see a relatively instrumental or
instrumentalization of artists I.E not
the one artist is not the other artists
right so we see certain artists
um standing up as entrepreneurs you
could say and becoming project
developers in relatively uncritical ways
and I can name some examples also in
Brussels where there's um where this is
happening which actually leads to a fair
amount of uh critique also within the
artistic Community yeah and I wouldn't
say uh that this is like necessarily
like a bad or a good thing like the
themes that are involved are like really
good uh teams but it's just uh like
always like look look very critical
because also the urban governments try
sometimes to use this strategy in a very
deceiving way yeah okay excellent thank
you I see another calendar or comment
literally by Vera
please unmute
yeah but but you already write this
critic from the what is her name yeah
and he's also the critic from zurkin
like did this tricky fact of the art to
be also the vehicle of the
gentrification and and stuff so uh
it's always super tricky to speak about
the art and it's potential in urban
space let's say yeah absolutely so I'll
give another example later on I think
also which which is and the article I
mentioned by uh sorry was uh I can't go
back I can't go back I buy Timon base
also mentioned some of these
ambivalences that are seemingly
unavoidable so to speak there's no pure
space in that sense okay excellent and
then there's Max also has a comment
yeah just to add on this point that uh
urica raised and this theme of
institutionalization and
instrumentalization of of Art and
artists I think Amsterdam is actually an
interesting example because there is
this Municipal policy which could be
translated as the breeding ground policy
whereby the city assigns certain
buildings as available for workshops and
for artists
to work there and often it's also very
related to
um
yeah strategy actually to gentrify a
particular area I don't know whether
there's any research done on this plus
maybe you know uh yeah it has been
definitely also by the Amsterdam
colleagues who also have a strong Urban
studies research Tradition at the
University of Amsterdam but also others
uh no no that has been critical research
being done at the Netherlands is a
particular case it's an interesting case
in any case because it's it's very less
the advanced and professional and it is
instrumentalization of the Arts on the
urban level and the brute plus and the
breeding policy policy is yeah it's it's
striking in the way it's sort of
well use and test positive side effects
also but the way it literally uses the
Arts in in relatively classical Urban
Development strategies that's that's
that's definitely uh true yeah no the
research has been done in that yeah
okay excellent thank you for the
comments they they really add some very
important uh additional thoughts here
other points
if not I continue with the third part uh
of the presentation and that's the the
another section or direction of research
on the
uh on the Arts well also on on culture
uh and the urban this is what I would
call or this this is basically my label
but I think it's what I would call
research on cultural infrastructures and
informal urbanism so that's whether
that's in the literature on your formula
actually starts uh broadening to let's
say a literature on on informal urbanism
which might be a phrase that you've come
across also a number of times
and this overlaps the thing in recent
years where increasing attention has
been paid to let's see the
infrastructural dimension of urban
cultures some Scholars have already
talked about an infrastructural turn I I
dislike talking about terms because it's
very
claiming a new fashion and it helps to
get cited more but uh yeah there's some
all these things built on all on older
interest also having said that there is
obviously more and more attention being
paid within Urban studies to let's see
questions of infrastructure uh and not
just narrowly defined but a very diverse
types of infrastructure as you will see
now let's hear one example I think which
is a good example of it discussed by the
team and base article that I mentioned
before
um which you discussed in this article
is it is is the work of the
chicago-based artist yester Gates as
some of you might know him
um where to the left you see a piece
that you did for the documentary
well not biannual but documentary five
yearly uh Festival in Castle so the
documentary 2013 which I think was in
2012. if I'm correct uh 12 ballasts for
eugenotes house which basically is a
restoration of an empty building in
castle using labor and materials from
the south side of Chicago
so it's an interesting case because it
was a kind of rundown building in Castle
and where he had let's say we had the
thoughtiest against the artists had
materials but also workers moved
transported so to say from Chicago to
Castle to actually renovate the building
and to actually perform in the building
Etc
so here's space and let's say the
infrastructure of this space really
emerged as a kind of social space while
at the same time directing attention to
migrant labor and in the case of of the
SD Gates that is work and the kind of
the issues he engages with with black
cultural expression in a very particular
space in Castle so there's a very let's
see concrete artistic intervention
to the right you see let's say the
in a way the reference project for for
the castle uh the castle case which is
the Dorchester project or projects in
Chicago which is basically you can argue
and it links back I think to the
previous
um uh uh well addition raised by by the
week but perhaps in the last let's say
uh uh planner mode but basically this is
a kind of urban development project led
by Siesta gates in the south side of
Chicago where the gate started buying up
abandoned property after the 2008
financial crisis and has redeveloped
these buildings with local communities
with other artists uh often creating a
mixed of outer spaces of community
spaces of let's say local restaurants or
in this particular case also a library
and and archive uh so the the Dorchester
project
now what's interesting here of course is
that we we
um we we are still in the realm of let's
say issues around Urban culture but
we've started paying more and more
attention to okay where practically
literally materially speaking are these
are these located so this really leads
them to the material infrastructure
dimension of urban culture and some of
what I consider to be some of the more
interesting more productive line of
research on Urban culture in the last
years has really looked at these kind of
infrastructural dimensions
another pushing this a bit broader and
perhaps also becoming less local and his
orientation towards infrastructure
is um a book that I that I added for the
reading for today uh by Brian Larkin
from 2008.
signal and noise media infrastructure
and urban culture in Nigeria
which is for those that have rats I
don't I don't expect you to have read
the full book but maybe it may be the
introduction at least
which is an anthropological study on the
cultural work of media Technologies
this is the quote and their role in what
in producing what we call Urban Africa
focusing on Kano and a Muslim City in
Northern Islamic City and Northern
Nigeria
the Larkin book is interesting because
it's just a very interesting book but
also because he Flags a number of
debates that that are let's say
essential in research on infrastructures
or in general or cultural
infrastructures in particular
one being it's not just about let's say
pipes Etc and literally infrastructure
but also a lot about the symbolic of
representational logic of
infrastructures so what do
infrastructures mean how are they
interpreted how are they envisioned how
are they imagined this really receives a
lot of attention I think in in most of
the infrastructure research
also in terms of governments to go to
govern or control these infrastructures
uh it gives examples of uh of this in
the case of Nigeria
um at the same time also the unexpected
or unintended consequences of an
infrastructural development governments
for example or let's say our local
developers can have a plan okay can have
an idea as to why they want to develop a
certain infrastructure but it doesn't
necessarily mean that infrastructure is
also used in this way so here we back a
thing to perhaps to the older discussion
around strategies and tactics but
transpose to an infrastructural
discussion
and the other and the last element
related to this of course is that around
these infrastructures we see all kinds
of informal social practices in everyday
life emerging yeah which then are word
of attention but also worthy of of
research so the example here I gave for
example you can easily get very
concretely imagine how around these
spaces social practices emerge and are
and are developed and they would perhaps
not exist without these these
infrastructures and that's the thing the
importance important to keep in mind
here
foreign
for me the most interesting
chapter in the book is perhaps the what
is the last chapter if I remember
correctly on on the role of piracy in in
Nigeria so the examples he gives for
example is is how Nigerian video
and piracy a circus of distribution
emerged in Nigeria uh and how this
actually relates to a kind of what
perhaps which goes called a full
ecosystem of cultural but also obviously
economic activity largely informal in
the sense that it's barely regulated uh
perhaps also uh illegal or
illegitimate or something because it's
uh often at that point in time when he
did his research late 1990s early 2000s
uh often copies illegal copies of
Hollywood and Indian films but we're a
bit at the same encano as a northern
Nigeria City really emerging literally
literally as a kind of Distribution Hub
for The Wider African region yeah so
with people on the right for example
selling it on the street but also the
same people or other people actually
moving the the goods so to speak the
material from one city to other cities
often crossing boundaries
now from the 1990s onwards I think we've
seen an increase in production also and
this is the the the argument developed
by Larkin of Nigerian and especially
hausa language videos leading to a quite
organized system of how is that video
Film Production but it building on the
existing pirate infrastructure yeah so
again a classic case of informal
urbanism a very slippery or unclear
distinction between where when is
something still informal when does
something become full because it has
also become part to a certain extent of
a formal registered economy with some
businesses growing bigger and bigger but
at the same time with for example how is
the films aesthetically and
organizationally still being shaped by
you could say the older uh pirate
Aesthetics and infrastructure yeah this
is also the kind of a research which has
received a lot of attention in recent
years and which I have labeled here as
being part of let's say research on
cultural infrastructures and informal
Urban them
or to give another example a paper I
wrote myself together with a with a PhD
student a while ago
gold spaces of openness Urban
citizenship and cultural infrastructures
have come alive in Istanbul
which focused in let's say a more
institutional way perhaps less
ethnographic way on the institutional
geography of collaboration and support
to sustain local cultural spaces and
networks in the shadow of the states so
the argument we develop here is that in
in a turkey and and partially also
nistable increasingly being let's say
shaped by a kind of authoritarian
semi-authoritarian state in any case we
discuss in some detail how particular
cultural organizations salt and pepper
for those that know as Istanbul they
might know the organizations how they
act as kind of cultural infrastructures
of let's say common life or a different
way would be saying oh actually Public
public life in Istanbul largely by
actually collaborating with very many
other organizations but also offering
spaces and this is what the image to the
right shows sorry what this image shows
offering spaces
um uh well no sorry offering actual
space in their buildings to all kinds of
different organs positions so you see a
kind of let's say
hidden or semi-hidden cultural
infrastructure which doesn't easily show
when you look at just the main cultural
organizations but which really shaped
you could say cultural practices in this
particular City and which is only
possible or or in any case is made
possible by the actual existence of
these actual spaces in in these cities
of salt and Depot
so again another
possible let's say entry point into
research on cultural infrastructures and
informal urbanism
last Point perhaps for this slide well
not not the level yeah last example is
what we see happening in the research
and cultural infrastructures much of the
research on Urban culture is research
that is both you could say fundamental
let's say basic basic real academic
research but it also has a strong
applied nature and the notion of
infrastructure has also started to
emerging or started popping up in policy
documents across the world
um that has many consequences not all of
them positive but to a large extent I
think it's an interesting development
where we let's say cultural policy
documents and cultural actual cultural
policy practices did not refer to
infrastructure let's say 10 years ago we
see in the last five years or so we see
various organizations very local and
Regional governments actually using the
notion of infrastructure in order to pay
attention to certain let's say
infrastructural dimensions of of of
cultural of the cultural Industries also
so here are a few examples on the top
left creative City News cultural
infrastructure an integral component of
Canadian communities this is quite
strong and again I think it's critique
of the creative Industries literature
even among policy makers where you say
okay we actually need a wider diversity
of cultural infrastructures that
actually connect with our local
communities whatever that may mean but
that's let's say the game
or for example sustaining London as a
cultural capital why London needs a
cultural infrastructure plan this again
is not a strand of the debate I think in
policy communities where we see because
of the increasing let's say
gentrification and increasing real
estate price and especially Global
cities even policy makers let's say or
let's say mainstream policy has started
realizing that if we continue like this
we will have no artists left in the city
so we need to actually start thinking
about the availability of cultural
infrastructure in our cities and to make
this available literally in order to
sort of uh keep let's say the status of
London as a global City but also as a
cultural City so why London is the
cultural infrastructure plan
a similar debate around cultural
infrastructure in New South Wales which
is this mixer thing also of the Canadian
example I just mentioned and the London
example of availability of space or
another example in Brussels and this is
one I'm partially involved in by
permanent so permanent uh the the name
of the of the association pretty much
sums it up which is a kind of practice
based research I'm also now involved in
where we try to develop an
infrastructure for permanently
affordable and a valid social and
cultural space in Brussels so basically
claiming a space in Brussels which is
open not just to artists but also other
types of users such as refugees such as
social housing such as University
researchers Etc in order to look at
different models of ownership also where
ours are no longer Reliant and other
users on let's say temporary use but I
can actually let's say permanently
literally permanently claim a space
through all kinds of ownership models
partially building on issues around
unless the community land for us or
social cooperatives
cheese
okay that's a lot of information
um just to sum this up if you look at
the cultural infrastructures and
informal urbanism literature I see at
least the following analytical shifts
we have moved the thing from a concern
with the informal economy and
anthropology and development studies and
everyday life tactics and cultural
studies to INF to informal urbanism this
is the term that is perhaps most present
now it's no longer informality as such
but the phrase informal urbanism you see
uh constantly
so we've moved to a situation where
um sorry here we are
we see a continued interest in labor
questions social embeddedness of
economic relations and interrelation of
informal networks and the formal
institutions so all the classic
informality discussions but at the same
time we see a diversification of topics
so it's no longer just about we would
say beautiful labor markets no it's also
about di urbanism it's also about
co-working space it is also about
Guerilla gardening about co-housing or
about artistic interventions in public
space it's also about squatting it's
also about self-built housing and the
list is endless yeah all these kinds of
practices of course each but they're all
with their own and I see approaches and
styles you see all these kinds of
practice being
labeled as expressions of informal
urbanism
there's a legitimate question to ask how
useful such a slippery term is but it
has certainly led to a broadening of
empirical interests
as already mentioned before I think the
the term informal has really helped to
move Beyond a global South versus global
North studies on cities and to really
look at the informal urbanism AS Global
urbanism where the informal in a way has
become foundational to our understanding
of cities at Large
uh and the last point I'll skip uh for
now is less essential
okay I need a sip of water
um questions please or or comments or
additions uh on this on this part
if any
um maybe I could ask a question about
um let's say these structures these
infrastructures growing in the shadow of
the state as you have mentioned it so we
noticed that
um actually a lot of communes in
Brussels are trying to set themselves on
the let's say cultural map and we are
working in urban analysis on the
community Forge that has its own like a
very active plan and wants to be a
leader and a new place for art and
culture in Brussels yes I wonder what
your take on that was also working with
um with the association that you
mentioned you must be seeing also a
different side of of the the influence
of of local yeah local government in
Brussels on that yeah exactly yeah
I mean I mean asking a question about a
city in which which I live of course is
always difficult because I can talk
about this for hours but
um
it's a tricky I mean I would say for
that to a large extent has become a a
creative or cultural hub for artists
which is really which it obviously is uh
despite for a municipality uh as as
often happens in Russell is not because
of the government that we see uh
interesting activity happening somewhere
Russell is a city that really relies a
thing on on strong let's say um uh well
social movements and citizen activity uh
and this also applies a thing to
Artistic activity in Forever have you
said that what of course what you now
see happening is that because for the uh
it has become let's see uh let's say a
concentration uh let's say for for
artists uh we do see of course that
local municipality is increasingly also
using this to in a way to to to to Brand
itself right to to uh as such there is
nothing wrong with this
uh I mean I don't live in Florida we
need to look into a very specific local
details at the same time I don't have
the feeling
that they have a strong strategic
perspective and for that on the role of
of arts and culture in their
municipality so it doesn't and that's
apply this applies to process as a whole
I think it doesn't get to my knowledge
move Beyond a kind of offering of
temporary interim use spaces for artists
so there doesn't yet seem to be a kind
of broader let's say more substantial
perspective on this but maybe you
already know more about this through the
urban analysis and and the work that
you've done so far
I think we we definitely see a lot of
policy claims for sure and a lot of use
of it
um so now indeed it's a next challenge
to look into how that actually plays out
on the ground and whether that actually
translates into action but thank you for
your reaction yes okay thank you
a comment as well
um last year I did uh literature study
about gentrification in Brussels yeah
especially in the region of um
since molenberg
and we saw
um in the 80s there come a lot of
artists start living there
so it became very popular to to live
there and the results was poor people
poor people need to move out
so I guess there is always
a small dark sites of this one let's do
gentle Creations especially in in
Brussels yeah yeah I mean I can only say
I showed yes to that
um yeah I mean I mean I mean there's
there are different opinions on
gentrification and Brussels I mean some
would say well there's clear
gentrification and B and there's there's
expulsion
um
if you look at the numbers that my the
actual expulsion of people from a
certain localities might be limited
still but it's clear that certain
certain areas are changing rapidly
um one of the things we're trying to do
which for example the permanent project
I'm permanent project I mentioned is to
also think about spatial because one of
the problems is let's say artists move
into certain spaces they're looking for
let's say work and Living Spaces but in
a way unintendedly so data and actually
lead to a push out effect for other uh
for adolescent poor poor citizens in
most cases
at the same time it's not as if artists
are belong let's say to an urban Elite
in general
so one is on a very small level what
we're trying to do with the permanent
project is also try to think of let's
say spaces that are that are co-owned
and where let's say the the move of
artists into a certain area does not
automatically translate into the move
out of other citizens uh
realistically speaking of course my
position on this is that
this can only partially be solved on the
project level because practically
speaking you simply need more social
housing for this and muscles is is a
disastrous City when it comes to
percentage of social housing let alone
qualitative social housing we're really
talking about a few percentages
uh of the total housing stock which is
social housing which is completely
different for example in a city such as
such as Amsterdam which has also seen
gentrification obviously but that's the
social housing stock definitely helps
there which all is all is its own
complexities and problems so yeah
any other comments
no okay then I'll move to the like the
last section I think of the
of the the the session I think we're
more or less okay on time
which is good so I I what I did I
promised last week that I would also
have a separate section on tourism I
don't so I didn't manage to fit it in
and uh it's it's picked up in some of
these elements implicitly I think so
um I'm also less of an expert on Urban
tourism I know the literature quite well
but it's not something that I do
research on myself uh but this is
certainly also a let's see another
strand of research which would be is
interesting from an urban cultural
perspective
however the last strand I want to
discuss with you today is is literature
which is perhaps more closely related to
the humanities than some other elements
I that I that I discussed with you today
um which I flag here as the research on
sensory urbanism visual cultures or
sensory urbanism and then two examples
visual cultures and sounds
um the Brian largest text that was on
your reading for today already
highlighted I think how media
Technologies and Aesthetics shape Urban
places so this idea that actually by
building certain distribution
infrastructures by having certain places
you actually shape Urban places through
through these Technologies and
Aesthetics in turn and this you could
see is let's say the more experiential
phenomenological or or user point of
view this implies also that places are
experienced through multiple senses
seeing listening smelling touching
tasting now historically most research
has focused on the visual Dimension but
increasingly we also see it and this has
a long long history I'll give a few
simple examples in a minute
but increasingly you also see the
attention paid to other sciences and
I'll briefly discuss tourists to
research which I think is pretty
interesting but obviously I'm biased
because I I tend to like mostly or Focus
mostly on on Music and Sound myself
um but I'll briefly discuss uh some of
the research on let's see auditory
culture Sonic cultures or Music and
Sound
now to start with the visual ecology
spots so remember Jameson so this is
let's say the the the hotel that was
already discussed uh in the in the
Jameson text 1984. basically you could
say one element of if not star
architecture but at least let's see very
sort of in your face uh phase
architecture and within Urban studies a
lot of attention has been paid to this
kind of architecture so basically
buildings designed to leave a strong
visual impression because that is what
these buildings do and what they aim to
do now the analytical Focus starting
already in the 1980s some elements have
let's say survived the years others have
not has been on cognitive disorientation
but also on Landmark statements in a
city with an emphasis on spectacle and
surveillance with emphasis and
consumption Landscapes and an emphasis
on representation and Global
attractiveness so this is all you see
well rehearsed territory within Urban
studies and which has a long history of
of analysis now star architecture you
literally adds value to world cities or
aspiring world cities so the
architecture becomes you could say an
urban icon in global rankings it really
helps and years there is a tourism
reference it really helps to put world
cities on the map for tourism and
consumption purposes
uh these sites or or the surrounding
areas become size for business
Investments uh or also for up Market
residential housing so they literally
add value to aspiring the world cities
true you could say strong visual claims
now this has this of course has a
history right this is not we have we
should not be naiveless historically a
leaf and pretend that this is something
of let's say the post for this age or
something that we've only seen since the
late 20th century although it probably
has increased and probably let's say
more let's say professional and
strategic attention is now being paid a
paid to let's say the visual dimension
of cities compared to the let's say the
the
the decades before but it has a much
longer history the most and most obvious
or let's say a classic example of course
being the Eiffel Tower which itself was
built to put Paris on the map or to make
it more visual Again part of let's say a
broader broader exhibition setup you
know originally intended temporary but
has been there for quite some time and
which now is a classic Landmark case in
uh or example in oops sorry
around the world when people think about
Paris sorry
or another example
um
so I'm working with two two computers
here so this is sometimes confusing uh
another example the Opera housing City
again an example even if you've never
visited Sydney you will know this
building the Opera House in Sydney
architect you're on utsan uh or another
example which I think by now also
everyone knows which is perhaps you in a
way the more recent example the gubernet
museum in Bilbao Spain which in its very
setup uh was intended to leave Legacy a
visual impression and you will see that
many people visit the Google night
Museum in Bilbao without seeing anything
else or any or very little of Bilbao as
such so I would I would dare to to claim
that the vast majority of people that
visit the Google Museum in Bilbao will
leave the city Without Really knowing
much about Bilbao yeah I mean there's
not a question if they should be it
should but it's clear that this kind of
a visual attraction plays a key role and
it has played out at the same time in
almost role in increasing tourism flows
towards Bilbao
or an even more recent Example The
Helpful Harmony the Opera House in
Hamburg uh 800 million euros enormously
over budget which is very typical also
for some a lot of the star architecture
but in general though and not
surprisingly perhaps also is that many
of these buildings are cultural
landmarks that both offer you could say
culture and a design space for tourism
and consumption yeah
so this as I said this is well rehearsed
territory still a lot of interesting
research is being done on this but it's
it's quite established in in the base
I'll give some examples of course that
leads to all kinds of discussions also
about
um who has the biggest tower I won't go
into sort of the masculine connotations
of building the world's tall tallest
building but it's quite obvious here uh
the Burj Khalifa and also I think and
this is perhaps a shift which is newer
uh although and also not completely new
is that especially unless the world
global cities such as New York such as
London we see a lot of intention being
paid by private developers to very
up-market elite residential housing yeah
so this is height one uh in in London
for example
it is interesting also because these
there's some of these space for up
Market residential housing they are
built to leave a visual impact they are
built to attract buyers multi buyers but
let's say the running joke in a way or
low the sadness of the story in many
ways is that if you look at uh how well
for which period of the Year these are
Partners or builds are actually occupied
by actual actual inhabitants is often
quite limited some of these are just
Apartments to park uh to park like money
but not Nest or do laundry money but not
necessary to actually live there for for
a sustainers well substantial period of
the year
foreign
or another example in New York for 423
Park Avenue
um perhaps less spectacular but maybe
intend in a similar Direction at least
visually speaking uh is this building at
the in the Canal Zone the upside Tower
in Brussels but the prices are certainly
more affordable than what the price you
will see in uh in New York or London
now what's interesting about this this
visual cultures especially in sort of
New Media times is that these let's say
these Landmark statements these are
actual buildings these are buildings
very much let's say uh very costly
investments in urban space uh but the
vast majority of people will know these
buildings they will see these buildings
through social media and online
magazines or maybe the let's say a
coffee table book magazines yeah so
these these buildings play a massive an
important role in City branding and
hopefully attracting cultural tourism
and also in circulating on social media
so you've got images such as this where
sort of if you look at Instagram and
search for Star architecture or
spectacular architecture you will see
loads of images or even let's say New
York using using uh using let's say
certain space or new builds in New York
and labeling it as best Instagram spots
and then you get these uh this
interesting uh let's say tourism
basically photograph themselves with the
building in the background as a candles
let's say
uh I've been there kind of attitudes but
it's quite obvious where sort of the the
spectacular Arctic plays a key role not
in relation to questions actual use but
largely in regression in relation to
questions of representation and how can
you actually uh how do how well do these
images look like on Instagram or other
websites
now this is empirically this is
interesting he's a new phenomena with
longer histories but empirically
interesting theoretically it raises
certain questions about how we should
look like how we should look at at city
development and how we should look at
how cities uh change over time this ties
then I would argue with a literature on
what is sometimes called geographies of
circulation where we really try to
understand City cultures as an effect of
circulation so not necessarily designed
locally but actually images traveling
between cities of course also traveling
of Architects and other experts but also
Concepts images plans best practices so
my Urban culture as such perhaps also
Urban policy as such becomes a kind of
practice of inter-inter referencing so
cities referencing each other or
buildings referencing each other to to
to to to to stake out a claim so to
speak
now all this leaves back in my view
although not always recognized as such
with the Innovative nervous studies do
classic cultural studies concerns with
the politics of representation but also
to an anthropological interest and
there's a very nice book an article also
by Ayana already from the late 1980s on
the social life of objects so how do
objects travel through space and Through
Time
okay
last section for today because this as I
said is it's well well throttling Theory
within Urban studies to really look at
sort of the visual in relation to to the
urban
but especially uh yeah the last 10 20
years I guess we see an increasing
interest also in other sciences and the
urban the example I briefly want to
discuss with you today as a closure for
the lecture uh isn't it is um research
and auditory Sonic cultures the
vocabulary tends to differ
um there's a lot of interesting work
being done on this still sometimes also
by practicing uh practicing artists
practicing musicians that also writes
such as for example Brandon LaBelle who
wrote quite a nice book on acoustic
territories sound culture and everyday
life so you see again everyday life
returning as a as a as vocabulary so in
chapter 3 for example which is the some
of the examples I use here where you
explicitly bills on micheliness of those
the practice of everyday life a very
develop the view on walking not an in a
visual way as actually the setode did
because he had a lot of discussions to
do about how you look in relation to
building how you position yourself in
relation to the city but a very develops
with you and walk through an auditory or
rhythmic perspectives and then he gives
all kinds of examples such as crosswalk
signals warning warning alarms or
personal audio so looking listening on
your smartphone to music while walking
through the city but also for example
sound art or marching bands or protests
and they're all sound plays and let's
say experiencing and and structuring uh
let's say city city life
he gives the example for example of
floriano jumano and fallante Sao Paulo I
think he actually mentions as Rio
dictionary but I think it's in Sao Paulo
um we walked around uh with with a big
speaker on us on his back uh which
basically
um where the voice is speaking out loud
don't don't something like don't pay
attention if I remember correctly so he
was walking around the streets in public
space don't pay attention don't pay
attention don't pay attention which
obviously the exact opposite will then
happen which is a pretty nice or neat uh
intervention I think in in public space
as a kind of art project
another example is okay is that that we
have active networks this is a much
longer history also of field recorders
people doing field recordings but
there's a very nice website for those
that are that are into this stuff uh
which uh it's called sound cities just
Google it you'll find it which has
connected let's say field records from
cities across the world where you can
actually play well this has been mapped
literally on the map of these cities and
where you can play Let's see sounds from
these cities or from these particular
locations in these cities uh and that's
that's an ever-growing database but
there's also active community of sound
recorders field recorders recording
sounds are cities and it's quite nice if
you have a bit of time to let's say to
go through some of the sounds and also
experience some of the let's say
differences and sounds uh between
between different cities
one example I want to just briefly play
and I hope this all works with uh with
sounds I'm just going to play it and
then you're gonna have to tell me if you
hear the sound so turn on do turn on the
sounds uh is a very nice piece I think
by Felix bloom a Mexican artist simaphor
was so normal from Mexico City 2015.
very
um basically manipulated the walking
signals uh of
um on the street in um
uh in Mexico City and when we replace
the sound of a pedestrian traffic light
with the sound uh with like let's say
the classic sound with the sound of a
donkey uh which according to him is a
nice way of of well paying attention to
well first of all making people think
differently look differently wait this
is something else than I expected so
it's a kind of intervention but also a
bit directing attention to an animal
which is largely disappeared from Mexico
City uh says this Urban space which uh
which uh was different let's say 30 40
50 years ago so I'm just gonna look if
this works and you're gonna have to tell
me just do it like this or something if
the sound is okay
do you hear sounds
okay perfect now please play
[Music]
foreign
okay so just one one small example which
I thought is a pretty pretty nice
um
nice intervention with a lot of humor uh
Felix Bloom also did quite he's done a
lot of work as a sound artist he also
did quite some interesting work and this
is a kind of early work you could argue
but where later on he actually worked in
collaboration with blind people uh to
actually and and use let's say sounds
and their experience of urban space in
order to sort of make make artistic uh
well it's artistic projects which is
also some interesting work to just check
his website if you're interested in this
kind of stuff
this example I'll move to the very end
which is a nice example by the way of
of sound and protests and there are many
examples of this following the 2011
Fukushima Fukushima nuclear accident in
Japan Japan saw actually a wide range of
public protests here's one example which
was a sound demo organized by a loose
association called shirota noiran
amateur revolt
and the organized a kind of sound demo
protest which is pretty neat if you like
noise which I do but since it's a 10
minute video I will
leave this for the very end and close my
sorry that one that will come in a
second
and move to my conclusions
before I do so are there any questions
on the um on the section on sensory
urbanism
and I know it's almost 8 PM so I know
it's late
yeah just just unmute yourself and start
talking because I don't see anyone
everyone in my screen okay I would just
like to share with with you and with
whom can be interested about the project
of um sound of tourist tourism
Lisbon he mapped the the sound of
tourism in the city and it's pretty
interesting
I didn't know it yet so I'll check it
out very cool yeah okay thanks
other comments suggestions
interventions
no
I will wrap up then with the conclusions
and then after the conclusions I will
move to the to the Tokyo video but
there's obviously no obligation to sit
through 12 minutes of noise so I'll just
leave it play for those that are
interested uh but I will conclude uh and
say bye after the after the conclusions
okay to wrap up this uh this relatively
intense session I think around the
different strands of research on on
Urban culture what I tried to get across
is that research and urban cultures is a
thriving and more perhaps more
importantly or very all equally
importantly and into a transdisciplinary
field of research it's increasingly
difficult to distinguish between
disciplines in research and urban
cultures which perhaps is a trend that
applies to all teams you could say but I
definitely think it applies more
strongly to research and urban culture
building on 1980s 1990s debate on the
cultural term uh post-modernism and
urban uh and the symbolic economy and
through interaction with Urban
anthropology and cultural studies
particularly through Notions such as
informal informality informal urbanism
everyday life what we see is that Urban
studies is really Diversified into
multiple strands of research dedicated
to cultural issues it's important to
make distinctions here because different
strands have different artists have
different communities of practice but I
would say there are three different
strands that that that are most
interesting but they pretty much do
cover it and they're not the only
strands but I do think they cover uh
let's say 80 of of the urban studies
research on Urban culture perhaps with
the exception of urban tourism and
cultural issues which I didn't discuss
in detail today the first one being the
Arts activism and urban engagement the
second cultural infrastructure the
informal urbanism and the third strand
around sensory urbanism where I give
very briefly two examples on visual
cultures and sounds
that's it from my site for today
um if there are no further questions
then I will move back to the uh to this
presentation sorry to this video
um I have one quick question
um are there any connections between
um Sansui urbanism and clubbing culture
for instance
um
limited limited I think it's in the
research is limited I think the clubbing
culture literature as far as I know it
is last year literature that builds on
the LA City Classic cultural studies
tradition
focusing on let's say youth culture
popular culture uh sociological
approaches by and large
however it's if you look at let's say
practitioners in clubbing culture
then I think there are stronger
connections especially those working in
let's say electronic music moving let's
say from a minimal techno orientation
who have increasingly moved into let's
say modern composition and or indeed
field work type Fields field recordings
type of work there you will see
um
artist who
um well who who sort of transcend the
boundaries who connect these things
because they then become you could say
sensory urbanists through their practice
but in the research I would say less so
they think they seem to be quite
separate well they are to a large extent
quite separate fields
but which doesn't mean that the
connection cannot be made so that may be
done your job yeah
well I'm thinking uh
I have one example in mind
um of Tbilisi in Georgia
where last year there were very big
protests I have to say I really don't
know the details about it but I know
there was also
uh some substantial mobilization from uh
clubs and from people from artists and
people from that scene um
and you saw some sort of a collaboration
between
yeah these these people from club
culture so to say and more political
movements and also using music in public
space as a form of protest yeah no that
that happens of course and I think in in
the Berlin example I used before I think
you also see these examples of public
protest and uh and music I mean the the
classic example of the love love parade
started out you could say as a political
movement even though I would argue it's
that it was heavily commodified soon
after or increasingly so
um but the sensory urbanism literature
perhaps relates more you could say to
the experimental sites and to the sound
not not even necessarily music and
that's a different kind of scene I would
argue and although there is overlap
obviously so yeah
yeah thank you any other comments
questions
perhaps just a very practical question
uh for me regarding the seminars that
will follow uh in the coming weeks and I
wonder how
um the presentations will will go
I asked because we were asked in the
past to record the video of our
presentation and I wondered if you
wanted the same or if we will give that
in person yes the rule would be would
remain the same I think that's how it's
the most communicated also so I would
actually need to look into the details
myself because I've been busy with with
the lectures so far but the idea would
still be that
the recordings are well are recorded in
advance and then we have and use and use
email it to me or you and and we
presented yes
thank you so much
sorry okay yeah okay
then I will move to the presentation but
it's 8 P.M so this is just when I say
the hardcore survivors who
want to stick stick around for a bit
longer
um I'm gonna say goodbye in any case I
will also look at it again so you can
still chat if you want to uh and then
thank you for your attention and I will
see well I think every one of you next
week during the during the seminars all
right so here we go
thank you
foreign
[Applause]
[Music]
thank you
foreign
[Music]
help me
what do you think here
[Music]
station
s
[Music]
foreign
thank you
oh yeah
oh my God
in Africa in Asia Latin America in
Europe to say that we stand with you in
solidarity
foreign
[Applause]
thank you
welcome guys
for me
[Applause]
foreign
[Music]
all right that's it have a great night
bye
thank you bye-bye