should be recording automatically but
well it is now thanks for thanks for
reminding me so double rationality the
rationality of the discipline uh which
is taken as uh some kind of
um Fields deriving from Natural Sciences
alluding to laws of physics which
apparently help to understand where
people go how they move around the city
um and the rationality of the of the
people themselves of the users of
passengers drivers who make rational
economic choices in terms of where they
go how they go
how does this apply to the city uh well
basically the city's approach as a clean
slate so it's social political spatial
complexity it's seen if it is seen it's
seen as an obstacle to these principles
of rational planning
um if it's not seen then basically well
this planning is applied as if on a
clean slate
which
in this particular slide maybe this is a
bit of an exaggeration these are plans
from the cocusier who was really very
back then it was called bold or
courageous in terms of proposing to
actually demolish all's uh neighborhoods
or whole cities to to give way to this
rational modern planning
um but a lot of these planning
principles have been applied and I'm
sure that you've been to maybe even
lived in cities where
um whole neighborhoods if not whole
cities have been designed according to
this principle of rationality speed
modernity that of course focused on or
framed the car the private vehicle as
the ultimate most rational most
liberating mode of of Mobility mode of
transport
we also arrived last time to this
growing reflection starting from the
1970s and then through the 1980s and
1990s on many different problems related
to car and automobility so there's wider
social uh phenomenon related to to
massification and commodification of of
private cars
so a lot of social issues have been
raised and primarily environmental
issues have been raised with regards to
automobility with regard with regard to
the car and to be frank I think in a lot
of Transport debates whether in Academia
or an activism or in policy in Brussels
I think is quite apparent in many other
Belgian cities too this is where we are
this is still very much the dominant
Paradigm in terms of how policy is Being
Framed and how research is being done
Harris are considered to be something
detrimental to the quality of urban
space to a living
be it because of its environmental
impacts the pollution noise accidents
that it causes uh it's a very dangerous
mode of transport
for those of course who are outside of
the car and Clash collide with it or
it's spatial Footprints all right so the
the spatial uh impact of the the
infrastructure the amount of square
meters that have to be devoted to this
particular amount of Transport in order
for it to uh to be able to uh to move
around the city so I'm thinking here
about all the urban motorways the
parking lots Junctions and all that that
has to be present in the city for the
car to uh to be a a valid uh useful of
of moving around
so this is what we did last time
uh
a bit of an well not an interlude but
what happened also uh throughout the
1970s and 80s is that in the global
North at least in so-called developed
countries such as Belgium but also
across the pond in North America cities
have uh entered into a post-foldist era
and I'm sure this has been covered a lot
by David and probably a little bit by
Nick and here I'm going to focus much
more on the transport related impact of
that shift of course it was not
something that happened over a day and
it's difficult to tell or to pinpoint
when did for this cities
you know conclude the existence and and
we move to prosperity and it's more of a
longer process that happened over over a
long period of time at least at least
years if not decades but what's very
important there is that if you go back
to these um curves and that are somewhat
similar to contratives waves of
different Innovation waves uh 1960s 70s
and 80s brought first The Innovation and
then the massification the spread of ICT
technology so different modes of
different instruments of
telecommunications and also a big
development of Aviation of air which was
used both I mean of course it existed
already in 1930s 40s and 50s but it's in
the 1970s that it really became a common
or more common than ever way of for
people to move around to travel of
course not within the city but between
cities between countries and also to
move Goods so this really propelled uh
or gave constituted a really big step in
terms of globalizing both traffic of
people as and and of goods of trade
and that's coincided with a general
shift from industrial to service economy
ongoing supervisation of not only
housing but also a number of other
economic functions that were
traditionally related to memory course
also going to do the suburbs which
created a polycentric
mosaic-like patterns of suburbanization
so the suburbs were no longer these
residential areas from which people
commuted to the city center but actually
a lot of jobs a lot of productive
activity and service economy would start
being located in in the suburbs
themselves
uh so creating all kinds of
constellations which for example could
be called the Suburban downtowns or Edge
cities that comes from the work of
famous geographer and Soldier uh
analyzing the development of Los Angeles
in the 1980s and the 1990s
the Paradigm of this could be seen I
mean or the symbol not a paradigm of
this transformation could be seen in the
particular space or a type of space of
an airport if back in the 1970s as you
can see in this image the airport would
be a very functional Place uh a place of
arrival a departure and a rather small
area would be devoted to the airport
this over of course a number of decades
has completely changed so you see that
development of one of the most important
efforts in the world's Hip Roll which is
the airport of Amsterdam
uh what's very important here is that
the airport it's no longer an addition
to the city but actually increasingly a
central space around which or in
relation to which the city develops so
what kind of a city a city what kind of
an Oakwood city has uh has a
repercussions in terms of what kind of
class of investors and productive
activities it can attract to have an
importance in airport Hub is
increasingly only well it's already a
well-established point of the agenda of
open marketing of Urban Development
um and airports are no longer just
airports I mean you can see here in the
slide that around sleepwell we've got a
number of other activities so a business
district office spaces uh residential
Hotel so it is uh sort of neighborhood
in itself that is built around the the
airport
um itself
this is important why is it why is it is
important
well there was a number of things at
stake here but the most important thing
here is that this change of typology of
different spaces in relation to these
different modes of travel so coming into
telecommunications Aviation means that
the travel contents are becoming more
and more complex
um the globalization of world economy
and the centrality of the city and this
global economy means that there is a
number of productive activities jobs
basically that happen 24 7. it's the
Paradigm of going to uh I mean of most
people going to work at eight o'clock
nine o'clock in the morning and then
going back in the afternoon of course
it's a lot of people still do that but
there is plenty of jobs that happen
overnight that require
transport infrastructure that is
provided in places and at times that
we're not needed there was no demand for
in the past
so in our
in us this
making of those Urban economy more
flexible uh and more precarious has
repercussions in terms of making
transport and Mobility also much more
flexible or the demand for much more
flexible way of moving which of course
means that it's way more complicated and
way more difficult to design Transport
Systems than before since people move if
we can put it in a very blunt way in in
much more complicated ways than ever
before at very different times in a
different stasis just to give you an
example I mean traditionally
reserventence of the airport of Brussels
will be considered of course as a very
important space that'll have to be
connected to the city primarily to
receive passengers there and from and
increasingly a random area of the city
and I think you covered that with David
White's uh in quite in detail there's a
whole Hub of business and productive
activity which of course attracts a lot
of middle class workers who would go to
that area daytime but then the
development of ongoing development of
the city sorry of the airport means that
there is
um high demand for workers in logistics
for example who have to arrive at the
airport at three o'clock in the morning
which raises questions in terms of
provision of public transport through
that area a lot of these people would
for example reside in working-class
neighborhoods of Brussels
so
um there is a question with a nighttime
public transport should be provided to
that area
um but then and get a current Paradigm
of public transport by Time by night
time in Brussels this mode of Transport
is mostly provided for leisure
activities so for people who go out
enjoy cultural activities or socializing
and then want to go back home at two
o'clock three o'clock in the night but
not for people who actually need to
reach their their jobs at that time of
the of the night in very let's say weird
or previously not so present areas such
as the the savitem area or other
localities around us that hack okay
so having said this uh so a quick
reminder of what we did last time and a
quick
uh cover of this shift from for this to
post four days in Paradigm of uh of
Urban Development and its repercussions
for for the cities uh and and transport
in them
here's what we are going to do today so
we will discuss uh perhaps have a little
discussion actually I will be trying to
ask you some questions and engage in
some exchange here
what is the sustainable Urban transport
and different sustainable perspectives
on imagining transport and developing it
and then we will engage in a progressive
deconstruction of that Paradigm and
analyze what we can identify as critical
approaches to transported Mobility that
built on a number of perspectives that
you already heard from David and bass
and Nick about
all right last week what you had to do
and many other things that an article
you had to do as students of Master
nerve and studies and geography is to
read a paper by David bannister on on
sustainable Mobility paradigm
um I wonder where they used to remember
anything from that paper this is not an
exam so don't worry if you remember
things that were not exactly you know
um I mean what you remember isn't
exactly carry clear maybe things a
little bit fuzzy but
does something ring a bell from that
from that piece
um if you if somebody asked you today
before this particular lecture what is
sustainable Urban transport what comes
to mind does anybody want to uh want to
share their thoughts on this with us
that's called awkward silence
foreign
does anybody remember what banister says
in this paper
that's all right
okay well
it's not how to put it it's not the most
um fascinating paper I've ever read but
for transport geography it's absolutely
fundamental so this is really something
that
you see being referred to for when was
it written 2011 right so nine years in
this is still a very very important
piece of writing that really defined
almost a whole field of research and
transport and Mobility
what's important here and this is
important when we keep thinking about
the last lecture in the neoclassical
Paradigm of uh of developing transport
is well could be summarized in a number
of points so if you think about this uh
image that I showed you from the Corpus
here and this modernist rational
approach to planning cities around
transport or
here the assumption is that we have to
ultimately break with this
monofunctional planning separation of
functions keeping residential areas on
the one side and productive activity
jobs offices industrial activity on the
other side and then Leisure somewhere in
between these three in the in between
these two here the idea is that we
really have to engage in planning cities
that are much more mixed which different
functions are
allocated much more closely to each
other why do we have to do that well
because this increases the possibility
of of engaging Less in mobility of
basically in moving less in the in the
city which has of course very good
implications or potentially good
implications in terms of the
environmental impact of transform
so the idea is that if we make cities
more mixed in terms of the functions and
on top of that more dense we might
arrive at the situation in which people
don't have to travel such far distances
or they don't have to travel that often
and potentially and that's the second
point we can also facilitate some kind
of a shift from the mode that we all
want to disappear I mean I'm thinking as
a sustainable Urban transport planner
now so the car towards public transport
Collective Mobility on the one hand and
on the other hand
so-called soft transport mode so walking
cycling to profoundly Challenge and
hopefully end the domination of cars in
in cities like
so this is I mean goes beyond the
critique of the car uh how do we maybe
not get rid of the car but how limited
how do we limit its presence well we
make cities more dense more mixed and we
make public transport and other
different modes of of moving around more
attractive
well of course there are important
cultural and social barriers to this so
there is some kind of social inertia and
you mentioned it in our discussion at
the end of the last lecture people are
used to driving the they of course have
been also told for a couple of decades
now that uh I mean buying a car is
something not only perfectly normal but
maybe in context such as Belgium or
Brussels a perfectly rational choice
and also well if we follow the
neoclassical line I mean people make
rational economic choices uh so it's
been simply quite profitable and and
economically reasonable to have a car so
to instigate some kind of a social
transformation we need to pay more
attention to how people make these
choices and this perspective starts
adding a number of psychological
analysis for example and factors to this
to this equation so it's not only an
economic uh choice and some kind of an
economic decision that people make when
they take a car or some other amount of
Transport but there's also
um
different social aspects psychological
aspects that impact and make an impact
on this and this means that sustainable
Urban transport Scholars planners
activists are much more attentive than
the neoclassical colleagues in terms of
how people engage in different
Lifestyles why do they practice certain
travel behaviors it is called which also
leads to a lot of studies on inclusion
in transport or exclusion from it on
accessibility two different transport
modes or accessibility through transport
to different Urban functions which
progressively over the you know 1990s
2000s and up to today questions this
Paradigm of of seems to question this
Paradigm of top-down planning and and
policy so this figure of some
neoclassical rational expert is not
necessarily
um well it's still there but it's not
the only god-like figure that makes
these like decisions in terms of you
know here we will build a Motorway and
he will build some residential uh
neighborhood etc etc
where is the city in this in this
Paradigm or in this perspective
well the city is
um
an outcome of the sustainable transport
Paradigm it's a sustainable transport in
the sustainable city is is an in it's an
integral component
um of what uh what Jacob's called good
City on what David bannister in the
article you had to read uh identifies as
Urban viability vibrancy Vitality there
was a lot of uh words about a lot of um
writing about uh the the attractiveness
of the city or its livability or its
resilience that's a bit more recent so
there's a lot of keywords which identify
uh a city as
um
ultimate benefactor of the shift towards
sustainable transport so there is talk
about maintaining economic performance
of the city since well we remember that
neoclassical Scholars have essentially
tried to theorize this relationship
between economic growth and development
of Transport so it's still there we move
away from the car but the cities still
continue to develop the economies
continue to thrive we achieve social
cohesion so presumably everybody is on
board there is no Losers of this process
it's all of course environmentally
friendly we arrive at Urban environments
which provide Better Health environments
or facilities well not facilities but
are basically more healthy for the for
the residents and all this in the spirit
of participation so everybody is on
board and and
this political process does not exclude
anybody well if you think about this uh
I mean I'm no my intention is not to be
ironic here I think that
um by the way the slide I mean the image
here is from uh this visualization of uh
in Brussels so the central uh
Avenue that crosses the Pentagon from
north to south and if you remember how
this this street looked like some years
ago
um this kind of vision is something that
we might all you know want to subscribe
to I mean who doesn't want to live in a
city that is all these things
economically performing socially
cohesive environmentally friendly I mean
it's a perfect City it sees
um the problem is well before we move to
the problem
um there are a few
I'm sure that this rings a bell and I'm
sure that you know a lot of different
practices which are trying to policies
practices that are trying to achieve
these things to make the city more
environmentally friendly in terms of its
transport economically performance
inclusive cohesive and whatnot
it's what examples you know so this is
maybe an easy question to answer
compared to the previous one
does anybody know any practices of
sustainable transport basically is it my
question
because you can see that the
construction of bike lanes for example
yes very much so I mean it's a
promoting a different mode of Transport
than the cars right one of the soft
modes cycling so we absolutely yes
what else
I see it enter
um I'm living uh
here next to it about one kilometer of
the Opera in antrop
and um
two years ago it was uh
for um
passengers
very difficult to cross the roads and
now
um they made a tunnel
and they made a huge space for um carbon
transport and and passengers so
you can see now and then
a big difference
um clear division from from what's
what's usual until the 90s so you mean
that there was less space of well of the
car infrastructure
by public transport
yeah
the the car was was still
um like they say it was the boss
um right presence of the of the car was
was very important we seen our shift
there
and this shift basically consists of
creating some infrastructure for
pedestrians and public transports to
somehow public schools now for a meeting
place uh for the Opera okay okay
to this
um can you hear me yeah I just just
right before the lecture I I read about
Paris with a more
um restrictive policy about banning
um your parking spots in cities in in
order to achieve the 50 minutes uh City
the so-called so-called Fatima City yeah
right so restricting restricting car
infrastructure or transforming it into
different type of infrastructure for
either either different modes or for
pedestrians so creating some Urban space
okay
what else maybe developing both rapid
transits for example in America
yeah does everybody or is this somebody
who doesn't know what bus Rapid Transit
is
it's a funny question to ask to a screen
but oh no don't tell me that it's
switched again I have to stop sharing
your screen but perhaps you want to
explain what bus Rapid Transit is
because I'm sure that there is somebody
who doesn't know
I can help in case
your definition is not perfect well what
it has
yeah yeah you know what I have as an
example is these lanes that the just for
bosses so they're developer a rapid Lane
that it will only go for buses so it's
supposed to work better around the city
yeah
yeah it's essentially creating separate
lanes for for buses but what's quite
specific about this or quite particular
is that it's
um kind of imitates or replaces an
underground system so a Metro system
which
is of course very expensive to build so
the idea is that instead of engaging in
all this digging and creating this very
costly and an invasive infrastructure
you can just create some separate lanes
for the buses and have an efficient
public transport system which is Metro
like
and that's I want to say common but uh
well a lot of cases first emerge in in
the global South right so in South
America and then in South Africa
um but there are also cases in in global
North in Western Europe
okay there is a lot of these different
policies and a lot of different
um
a lot of different uh practices and
ideas it seems so let's quickly go over
I mean let's let's try to put them
together into some kind of coherent uh
typology of different things that cities
can do in order to make this transport
more sustainable so the first thing is
to tackle the problem right so if the
problem is the car then how do we deal
with the car well we can either improve
the technology of the car and this means
um reducing emissions making it
contaminate the air a little bit less so
cleaning the engine technology
substituting for of petrol diesel
vehicles by electric vehicles or biogas
or whatnot uh creating the con I mean
changing the construction of cars so
that they cause less casualties in in
case of accidents right so this is
something that today we take for granted
that cars have these um crash zones and
crashes are being done safety tests but
this was virtually non-existent in the
1970s or 80s
so that's one thing so basically it's
trying to make the car a better vehicle
for the city
well here in the immediate problem is
that I mentioned that last time uh among
the type of vehicles that see a number
of sales go up most I mean most rapidly
in last two or three years are SUVs so
the sports utility vehicles which are
basically these massive jeep-like uh
cars which are extremely dangerous for
pedestrians and if you also turn to one
of the most important or marketized
inventors of Transport technology Elon
Musk I mean it's a guy who does electric
cars but also if you paid attention to
that I don't know if you know if you
notice that in the news I think it was
early this year or last year that he
produced this massive truck uh like
American style you know pickup truck
which has not been tested in terms of
its impact on pedestrians in case it
actually clashes with one but there is
on the one hand the industry tries to
reinvent the vehicles to make them more
safe and environmentally friendly on the
other hand there is still a push for
creating gigantic vehicles with simply
cannot achieve that with the size and
the you know its audience or the
audience is not simply looking for this
okay so that's the car another thing
that of course can be done is uh to
restrict the accessibility for the car
uh to the to the city as a whole or to
its different
um areas specific zones right so we can
for example impose these restrictive
pricing instruments such as congestion
charging or Powers which was stolen in
Dutch which was very recently announced
in Brussels but it existed in in several
other
Belgian cities in one form or another
for for quite a while now
um we can think of reducing physically
the space for the car so basically
making uh roads more narrow so so
cutting some Lanes reducing the number
of parking areas and then uh as it was
mentioned uh earlier replacing this
infrastructure is replacing the space
with other users so opening this space
to for example pedestrians or
non-motorized traffic creating these
so-called pedestrian zones or shared
spaces and here you have one from London
in this slide and also the famous
congestion charging scheme in London
which means that in a specific Central
area of London you pay 12 pounds to
enter every time you you do that right
okay
what other things can be done to tackle
a lot of Mobility well of course if we
want the presence of the car to go down
we need to propose some alternative to
the car our obvious alternative is
public transport and here sustainable
perspectives on transport basically uh
keep emphasizing the importance of
increasing the quality of public
transport of increasing the
accessibility of public transport
across the urban or Suburban space and
indeed fast Rapid Transit is one common
example of how this can be done actually
quite inexpensively also the
reinstallation of urban trumps and many
cities in the global North that got rid
of the tram uh to create space for the
car if you remember my slice from from
last time that's what partly happened in
Brussels in the 1970s it's a very common
way it was a very common phenomenon
common phenomenon sorry in France where
a lot of cities Trump's Trump network
was quite simply dismantled so here
since the 1990s 2000s we see The Return
of the Trump Urban funicular so creating
these cable cars plenty of other modes
basically of public transport and also
promoting the notion
of multi-modality right so creating
different options for users so that they
don't have to Simply choose between the
car and something else but there's
something else is a variety of different
options from which one can choose and
depending on where they go with whom
what they feel uh like like using in a
particular moment of time what
corresponds better to the behavior do
they to their lifestyle right if we if
the lifestyle and behavior is what we
pay attention to much more than before
um and then finally what's important in
this portfolio of different solutions or
tools if you will is reducing the need
to travel right so I mentioned already
that here the idea is that we make
cities more dense more mixed so perhaps
we don't have to travel so often and so
far
and in planning or in geography the idea
here is to progressively link Urban
Development with transport development
so the idea of Transit Oriental
transport oriented development
emerged within this Paradigm so for
example fostering some activities some
development around the development of
new Metro stations or Railway stations
or whole transport corridors a little
bit like what I showed you last time
with Copenhagen right the finger the
five finger plant which was one of the
first ideas of linking transport
development and Urban Development
um and many other things that's well
quite frankly I'm much more interested
in in sharing with you the critique of
all this than than this itself because
this is very easy to find and there's
plenty of different Publications on this
I mean basically if you follow any of
these uh websites which deal with or
well these are called magazines these
days that follow uh Urban policy City
lab the Atlantic fox or whatnot I'm sure
that you know more than I do I mean this
is what they say I mean this is what
they promote a lot right so the car is
the problem so anytime a big Northern
also in the global South uh this is
picked up a little bit but anytime any
important city does something in terms
of curbing automobility
um this is very often picked up by this
kind of media and hails as a radical
intervention as a radical step to to
reinvent Humanity to give cities back to
the people to make cities more
sustainable green attractive and etc etc
now I'm not saying that this is all bad
and that this is uh you know problematic
in itself but there is a number of
critical questions that answers critical
geographers really need to be asking
about these practices because they quite
simply
um well they are they are not really
taking full stock of the complexity of
cities that they're being applied in
for one
so
um well the first immediate problem is
that the word sustainability or the term
sustainability has already been picked
up by the industry the Paradigm that
sustainability in principle wanted to to
criticize and to have some critical
Cutting Edge over
so for instance the the oil industry and
the car industry both claim to be
extremely sustainable these days right
in terms of how they produce soil and in
terms of how they produce vehicles I
mentioned already this idea of
Reinventing the car so it's a more
sustainable mode of travel in in cities
but the deeper problem is that
and I will show that in a moment that
the kind of questions that sustainable
Urban paradigm
um asks about the city and the solutions
that it tries to bring are essentially I
mean they can only reveal some transport
reality to a point so it's very quick I
think that we can reach some kind of a
wall
um and this debate between let's say the
neoclassical engineers and economists
and the anti-car proponents of
sustainable vanities it's not a very
productive one
and very importantly for this course and
for you is I don't know Urban
geographers urban planners of the future
the relation between transport and the
urban in this debate is very it's very
weak so conceptually but also
empirically
um this kind of thinking about
transported Mobility simply does not
tell us a lot I think about the city
which is why we're here two nights
right so so let's deconstruct it and
explore some critical stuff about it
basically so
I wonder whether you can already pick up
some critique of this from Elena and her
colleague
I'll be starving with the readings today
does anybody remember something from the
reading for today
um I do
it's been a week since I read it
but uh
um I know that she uh has like
identified two main principles of
critique
which is first that the Alternatives
that are being proposed by um the
automobile industry and no specific
plans they are not very
like sufficient in reducing the uh out
to mobile impact
um in in certain cases you can you can
say if I uh say something wrong and then
secondly
um
well it's it's sort of a very exclusive
uh sometimes discussion I think but uh
yeah it's not very present anymore but I
would like to pose another question for
that paper it kind of upset me in a way
oh yeah
yeah if we're at it like uh I basically
I liked her way of like introducing her
thoughts and like structuring the paper
but I was a bit like put off just uh
methodologically uh in the way that she
uh links empirical evidence that she
produced herself to theory that is
oftentimes very theoretical and like
um based on uh very uh personal beliefs
and attitudes which I like also support
in a way but sometimes I found that did
make her arguments less striking and I
was just wondering because we are like
still in the beginning of all of our
like uh Urban critical research careers
uh how that is to be done
uh
if you have an answer to that
I don't know I mean I don't have an
answer to that question
um well I would agree with you that
maybe methodologically this is not the
strongest paper uh it's an analysis of
plans and it's not very clear exactly
what she's maybe done with this and
maybe it's true that her conviction is a
little bit stronger than her empirics in
this particular paper
um I picked it because it summarizes a
few things a little bit better than than
others but I really like what she what
she what she does even though the best
work that she's done is in French I
think which makes it not accessible to
everybody here
um
but yeah I think your first point in
terms of what's you know what's in the
article it's it's spot on it's also
there in the title I mean uh she may be
uh it's again she risks uh being maybe a
little bit uh engaging in some kind of
exaggeration right it's not every single
sustainable Urban transport policy that
leads to the processes that she
describes but there is a tendency for
these policies to create some
inequalities
and for the politicizing the debate
so um it's not exactly clear who these
policies are supposed to be for they are
these obvious a little bit again in this
kind of neoclassical uh Direction
rational tools of now dealing with uh
with the car is the problem right so in
fact the power relations in transport or
in transport policy have not really
changed is just that the focus has
shifted significantly and now
um this is what the planners are doing
as opposed to what they were doing in
the 1970s and 80s
um let's dive into this
whoops uh great so what are the and
that's my um individual of how to put it
my personal top five of the reasons why
sustainable Urban transport Paradigm is
not exactly the the you know doesn't
give you a complete view of the
relationship between transport and the
and the city and and also with some I
think quite practical theoretical
empirical uh recipes for how to get out
of this uh roadblock pan unintended so
the first issue with with a lot of the
riding on sustainability is that it's
still very much focused on technology
so there is a lot of attention given to
technological solutions where social and
political Innovations and some bottom up
political activity organization
engagement of people as political agents
not just the consumers and customers
that have to be now convinced to shift
from one mode to another from the car to
something else this is not so present
and uh well this comes from the from the
guru himself Elon Musk who is um despite
of course some obvious critique it was
his personality and and how he carries
himself in media he still is
um very much the hope for many in terms
of transitioning from carbon heavy modes
of Mobility to electric vehicles which
according to the industrial are the
thing of the future so according to Elon
Musk
um as he says I think public transport
is painful it sucks why do you want to
get on something with a lot of other
people that doesn't leave where you
wanted to leave doesn't start where you
want it to start doesn't air doesn't end
where you want it to end it's a pain in
the ass and so that's why people like
individualized transport that goes where
you want and when you want
so the idea idea is not to engage in
collectivizing transport for example and
making this a more common service or a
more common experience to break not only
the Paradigm of dependency on fossil
fuels and the car but the dependency on
individual transport making this
basically a less individual activity
which is a social political activity as
well no to the country here the idea is
to develop a better technology within
the Paranormal individual transport and
Elon Musk I mean he's doing a lot of
things but one of the other things in
Tesla and the produced production of
electric vehicles that he does is
um boring tunnels on the Los Angeles to
basically create some parallel Motorway
system if we can call it this way that
bypasses congestion so actually the
focus here while
um might apparently be on making trans
more sustainable it is essentially to
solve congestion which is an extremely
as I explained last time neoclastical
formulation of the problem
another issue and that's from Elena's
paper and but I think it's not from the
one that you had to read for today but
from another thing that I that I learned
from here is this focus on on
the individual as the not only well how
to put it not only is the source of a
number of Transport problems but also as
a as a solution to to address these
problems right so
the idea here is that essentially we can
convince people to change the habits to
change the lifestyle related to
transported mobility and in this way we
can solve a number of issues related to
to this uh to this field of of open
Planning of urban policies
um
which means that within the sustainable
Paradigm
um a lot of policy makers a lot of
Transport stakeholders would uh rather
than engage in the politics of Transport
they would engage on the pedagogy that's
related to it so it's suddenly the
challenge is to make sure that people
engage Less in behavior that is
identified as bad behavior for example
driving or living in the suburbs flying
around and switching to what is
considered to be good type of behavior
positive behavior so cycling around
walking living in a city center living
in these dense mixed urban areas that
don't require that you engage in
mobility and so much
and while this of course is not a
problem in itself I mean it's good to
think of why would people
um stick to particular ways of moving
what's very uh detrimental I think to
the debate and to ultimately solving
some issues related to transport
is
um putting these different ways of
moving and different behaviors related
to movement in a coyote where clearly
there is a moral component so this good
and bad behavior I think this is
something that can actually antagonize
people against one another rather than
try to think of Transport problems as
common societal problems thus issue
number one and issue number two is that
in this discussion about individual
behavior
um engagement with analyzing and then
ultimately addressing structural causes
behind behind transport and Mobility is
not so present so if we focus on on the
question why would people drive
um and why would people of for example
even specific ethnicity or gender or
class drive more than others
um it is very important to also
understand what is the structure uh
behind this what is the the general
policy that allows people to obtain
access to uh to a vehicle that allows
that are of car infrastructure which
very often and that's the case
definitely in Belgium it's often
absolutely free to use with no taxes to
to use motorways or with cheap parking
etc etc
so this perspective is
um in itself not a problem to look at
you know why people engage in particular
type of behavior and not other
um but it's very important to also
understand the structures behind this
what Elena also writes a lot about and
many others as well but as I said I'm
really quite convinced by by her writing
um
is the uneven geography that is being
produced by these different uh
Sustainable Solutions
somebody's asking a question in the chat
so let me read that so maybe there's
something in between for example
self-driving cars and apps like uber
um will be able to create smaller
vehicles that can be shared as public
transport so in a sense in between but
in between of
in between what
and between private uh I mean including
individual transport and Collective
transport you mean
Rudy do you want to explain whoever you
are
foreign
hello
Rudy are you with us
I hope you didn't just write the comment
and left
maybe the connection is not very good on
your end
um
well yeah I mean clearly in in recent
years there's been a rise of uh of
expectations towards this shared
Mobility modes right so so a number of
practices which allow you to get access
to seemingly collectivized transport
like uber I mean essentially you don't
own the vehicle but it's just a not even
a phone call but a tap on your phone
away
um
but there is a number of uh there's a
number of issues with this so there's a
question whether this actually replaces
uh individual transport
um so do people have less cars because
Uber is expanding in this city if we're
focusing on Uber in this instance
um there is also a lot of studies that
show that Uber actually adds to
congestion so there is the more Uber
develops in the city or it's
um counterparts or different other
competitive platforms left in China
there was a huge company called DD that
essentially does what Uber does
um so the more these companies develop
in your city the more the how do you
call it well the total number of
vehicles the the car stock increases
which means and that's a problem in a
lot of Chinese cities you basically have
more traffic jams so these cars are in
traffic all the time they keep looking
for customers they have to be mobile
um which means that you add to the
problem you try yourself which well then
you try to yourself again adding more to
these shared platforms
and also the big issue with Uber if we
are focusing on this for a moment is
that the working conditions of course
are quite quite terrible so the idea
there is that essentially there are
exceptions to this but in most cities
where Uber operates
um workers are not really workers
they're contractors
which means that they very often go in
debt to actually get the vehicle that
they're driving that they have to pay
back to Uber because it's offering also
leasing services this means that they
work very long hours unlike regular taxi
drivers that have to actually clock in
and out this is much more regulated in
terms of how they work for what amount
of time and also what knowledge of the
city they have I don't know how often
you've taken Uber in your life but it's
often the case that these drivers are
exploring the city alone I mean they
just learn as they as they drive which I
understand they might come from a very
difficult situation that this is the
only way for them to get access to a
more or less decent way of making money
but there's a question of safety there's
a question of Ethics in terms of
um inviting such a practice in in our
cities
so there are a lot of expectations for
these platforms and indeed there is a
question does this maybe sit between
public transport Collective transport
and individual transport but uh
um I would say that these hopes are
still not really fulfilled
um
okay that was a bit of the digression
let's go back to uneven geography of
sustainable transport
so what is the problem here
um more often than not the application
of the sustainable tools different
policies infrastructural measures to
deal with Mobility
uh especially quite exclusive what does
it mean well
on the one hand it often happens that a
lot of these measures are applied in a
specific area of the city and more often
than not this is the central Urban core
which has to be saved from the car in
which the the car has to limit its
presence which in no way contradicts uh
or prevents further maintenance at least
if not developing a further
infrastructure for the cars in more
peripheral areas so you can think of
cities in which in the city center
you've got
um restrictive parking regulations
you've got a lot of pedestrian areas
it's simply not easy to drive around
public transport is definitely a more
logical thing to to do to use to get
into but the further you go to the
suburbs the more
um
multi-lane streets or highways you see
or actual proper highways a lot of
parking lots all the infrastructure that
actually well belongs to the 1970s and
1980s
and that is I think a situation not only
in Belgium or and Brussels specifically
but
in a lot of these cities that are
supposedly
have achieved um a great level of of
policy in terms of dealing with with
Khan so Copenhagen Vienna a lot of
French cities that both these uh tram
renewal programs uh as long as you are
in the central part of the city this all
looks uh very coherent and very well
inverted Commerce good from a
sustainable transport perspective but
the farther you go from the city center
the more actually the more cars you see
the more it actually resembles the
problem that these policies try to try
to solve
another inequality is of the vertical
kind meaning that it often happens that
um
the investment in these kind of
sustainable tools comes at the cost of
putting the car infrastructure
underground so and you can think of any
case in which pedestrialization of of an
urban Avenue or Boulevard means that the
cars have to be put underground or
parking lots of the other highways
and this is often the the problem in in
the so-called car-free cities the cities
that are often picked up by
International media and and praised for
having addressed head-on the domination
of the cars and dealt with the problem
of automobility
um
a specific tool that's that I think we
can see this and even geography in ah
there's a question in the chat an
example for Rudy's question from Berlin
great
um let me go on with the congestion
charging while you're discussing Uber in
the chat uh this is perfectly allowed so
an example of this and even geography
can be found in in congestion charging
which is one of the let's say
um yeah one of the most uh classical
tools of of sustainable transport
Paradigm in terms of you know limiting
the presence of the cars the idea is
simple it came from Singapore in the
1970s it was developed as a very
neoclassical uh tool of planning
basically a problem with congestion and
the idea was to convince to encourage
drivers to use the car off-peak so to
minimize the the traffic the traffic
jams in morning and and afternoon or
evening peak hours
and progressively this tool or perhaps
with the shift of philosophy behind
transport from the neoclassical to
sustainable uh perspectives this tool
um was picked up by by the sustainable
narrative and now it not only allows to
solve congestion but actually it allows
to limit the presence of the car in the
city which of course supposedly makes a
positive impact on on the urban
environment
and this tool has been put in place in
in a number of cities in Europe
so you here see pictures from Oslo but
actually this exists in pretty much all
uh Norwegian cities and towns so a
system of tolling Gates
um in London which is probably the most
important or the most known case in
Europe in Milan but you also have
similar policies and instruments in
Stockholm in Sweden and then recently
also in Brussels announced with a lot of
pump and Circumstance this idea that now
it will cost the user the end user money
to enter with a car Mica to to the
Brussels capital region
so
while this gets a lot of attention and
and this policy is discussed as a very
uh as a very efficient uh tool in terms
of limiting the presence of the car in
cities
um there is questionable evidence I'm
not saying that this policy is uh is is
a bad policy or that it never works but
basically it's it's supposed to uh
um productive results in terms of
limiting the car are not exactly there
in the in the in the in the evidence so
the results are quite mixed on the one
hand we see that in in a number of
Cities traffic of course diminishes but
since it's The delimited Zone it's it's
quite particular so it's not the whole
agglomeration that actually
um has the access to the car limited we
see that the traffic often moves from of
course the The Zone in which the
condition charging the flight to the
outer areas in London for instance it's
quite clear that there is significantly
more traffic around that that zone it's
the same case in Madrid which uh which
um essentially followed a very similar
principle
there is also very questionable evidence
about what happens with the funds that
are being raised through these systems
so while very often these policies are
put in place with uh this Narrative of
saving the city from the car of making
some kind of societal transition to to
posca society in cities like Oslo or
London funds from these uh from these
schemes in in a way that's very clear in
London maybe a little bit less
transparent but at least part of these
fans goes to actually maintenance and
construction of car infrastructure you
know it's very it's a very common
practice to put these congestion
charging areas or
booths if you if you will to actually
subsidize the construction of of
specific uh transport infrastructure
Road tunnel or a bridge it's it's done
in a very transparent way so in a sense
it's basically asking the transport the
car user to
contribute a little bit more because of
course this contribution is already
there through tax system to the
construction uh to the financing of the
construction of Transport infrastructure
of cutting in car infrastructure and
finally the impact of these uh of these
schemes on overall quality of the city
not just on air quality in a specific
area is quite limited so
um
yeah I said it basically so despite the
The Narrative of of these practices
saving Urban environment it's not
exactly clear that this is this is the
most obvious thing to do to limit the
smog in the city especially when these
uh when these areas are quite uh
spatially Limited
the problems that immediately emerge
from from policies like congestion
charting is that well it leads to some
social segregation right so we expect
um that all people react to this uh to
this policy in a similar way right they
will reconsider whether they want to
drive or not whether they want to enter
into the Zone by car or not but in fact
of course those who do not pay for the
vehicle and in particular in Belgium
this is a policy that is very widespread
half of new vehicles sold in Belgium are
so-called company cars which are
received for free by employees from the
company as a way of giving them an
tax-free salary bonus basically so for
these people who do not pay for the
vehicle itself and often whose
consumption of the vehicle gas so or any
kind of fuel they put in the car
insurance this is all paid by the
company very often this very often
basically is included in the package so
the congestion charging is actually not
covered by the individual it's covered
by the structure that provides the
vehicle
um in in the first place
while of course those who do not have a
job who might be seeking one those who
are from lower working class background
who might also be doing very difficult
complicated irregular trips that require
entering and leaving in different times
of day because they need to go to a job
that that quite simply requires getting
by car and I'm going back here to this
example of somebody working in logistics
public transport between molenberg or
zavendam for example at three o'clock in
the morning being simply not there you
have to have a car to to reach this kind
of activity to to be able to access the
kind of urban function
and then ultimately well what it does to
uh to to Mobility is commodified so it's
an essentially neoliberal service you
pay as much as you use it's not a common
system anymore you the idea is that
everybody pays not according to the
means but according to the ultimately
um the price decided by the by the
market
so
um again not to say that this is about a
good idea but to say that there is quite
simply a lot of questions a lot of them
quite clearly related to to critical
geography that should be asked about
these these policies
it's already past seven so I suggest we
take at least five minute break before
we can continue so get a little bit of a
drink uh whatever it is that you are
you're sipping to make through this
lecture
um and I'll see you back in in four five
minutes all right
foreign
okay let's try to resume
I'm going to share my screen once again
all right
where are we
I suppose you hear me and you see me
um
great perfect so
continuing with uh the uneven geography
of sustainable transport measures
here you have a very simple or even a
map more of a scheme that shows a little
bit how this limitation
plays out in space so Oslo I don't know
if you've heard about that but also is
one of the most
um
marketized cities in terms of its
alleged fight against the car it's uh
leading some kind of a war against the
petrol-fueled vehicles and basically
there is this area in the city in which
um to which access is not only
restricted in terms of extra payment
right so there was actually several
layers of this congestion charging and
then the final one is this uh Ultra
inner city in which cars propelled by by
gas or fuel are not allowed is only
electric vehicles but then when you look
at the whole agglomeration of the city
it's quite clear that I mean this is a
very small area so we are actually
talking about quite specific zones of
the city which as I mentioned are
supposedly saved from the car and are
supposed to be made more pedestrian or
people friendly
same idea or same limitation can be can
be seen in Madrid which until recently
had also quite a restrictive uh
Mobility area this has changed with a
change of political majority does not
matter if it's this area still exists
although the rules have have changed to
some extent the idea is that Madrid
which was called in worldwide media as
an anti-car municipality a municipality
that takes some radical measures to to
limit the presence of the car in fact
well it does so but it does so within a
quite limited uh
designated area whereas you see that in
the in the general map there is a whole
car infrastructure around it and
multiple motorways both
around and from that Central Area so
there's a question with a automobility
is actually being
properly uh uh challenged or is this
more of an urban policy that focuses on
valorization of specific areas of the
city and here it's you don't have to be
a smart critical geographer to ask if
this is not part of some revolarization
strategies that try to increase rent and
profit to gentrify quite simply specific
areas of the city and the limitation of
car traffic being part of of that policy
to beautify the area to make it more
attractive to tourists to specific type
of investors
while limiting mobility of of this of
this kind
this we've covered and here we arrive to
the to the well to it to a case of of
such a policy limiting presence of the
calf the pier tonight in Brussels which
I'm quite sure uh all of you have uh
have already experienced and and see
so well this map you've seen quite a lot
before I'm sure Brussels with its um
Zone 30 so the the limitation of of
speed there and the petone marked in in
red uh at the moment of installation the
biggest pedestrian area in uh in Europe
I wonder whether you've got any
impressions of this place before I
um show you my take on on or share with
you my take on on what happened over
there
um I imagine you've been to lupiteria
but do you have any
uh any interesting thoughts about this
do you like this place do you think it's
not so great
um I don't know I don't I don't have a
very uh deep thought about it I don't
think but um
it's definitely nicer than it was uh I
mean like I lived in the center for like
five years ago or like no was it five
years ago like longer ago but like it
was really horrible like when you cycled
through like downtown it was really
awful because like the road was just
disgusting like you don't you didn't
really want to be there
um now I mean it's a bit
no I I don't have the feeling it's it's
very much
um
it's it's very true for what it is you
know like for for like
I don't know it doesn't really feel like
a downturn it feels a little bit
provincial
um but like at least it's like I'm
definitely happy with like that it's
much better than it used to be like
really
like it it's it's definitely an
improvement but it feels the Big City
Vibe a bit okay for those of you who who
didn't see it before it was changed into
a bit of scenario I pushed a slice so
you see in the top image uh how this
street could look like on a Friday
afternoon quite regularly so full of
cars for four lanes
um and then well the situation that's of
course pre-covered uh well I don't know
I probably right now if you took that
picture would be quite similar
um anybody else who has some some
impressions of how how this
transformation looked like
somebody who loves this somebody who
hates this
and for whatever reason
um I agree with him because it was a
place
when uh when I passed when I study in
Brussels where I pass with my
girlfriends
I don't want my girlfriend to let alone
on the other place
some years ago but one frustration I
guess from I I followed the dope process
and what I know was it was very
difficult for uh Transportation like
like MVB and steep
um public transport to pass because it's
the the lane was was cut
um yeah so
they wait uh wait for over two hours to
go to another place when set was five
minutes it was two hours
so you mean it affected other modes of
of of trying to not only the car but
also public transport yeah yeah the
victim was public transport and I guess
in in in Brussels it's very important to
when you have a Prestige project like
that you need to consider all of
Transport modes and not only pedestrians
press each project I think also is an
important uh
also like like an element to add maybe
is that it's terrible if you go by bike
it's really not made for bicycles like I
I tried cycling through it and I mean
right now it's not so busy and it's all
right but like on on on days when there
is I mean there's lots of tour tourists
of course lots of people use the the
area so then it's just really not nice
to cycle there yes I share these
Impressions I mean these are not only
Impressions and the fact is that and
this area was redeveloped but without
any bicycle policy in mind so there is
basically I'm not I'm the last person to
say that what was there before was great
but uh you can vaguely see it on the
right hand side of the top picture that
there is actually a bicycle lane not a
great one but there was one now it's
it's simply not there uh somebody's
writing something in the chat
why do they take down the larger trees
neutralization of bulovanos but I find
the Landscaping quite poor well so there
was a number of uh things at stake
um I mean let's cover that first
um
it was announced in January 2014 the
municipal authorities of the city of
Brussels so the uh Mill Brussels 1000
announced that they want to expand an
existing pedestrian zone so you already
had some streets especially it was
complex that were not open for the cars
and the context of that and that's quite
an important thing is that there was a
series of protests called under the
slogan of picnic the streets a movement
of uh some spontaneous Civil
Disobedience basically people would
occupy space that would normally be
taken by cars you see that in the the
picture normally a lot of cars so right
in front of books that will be basically
uh some kind of an action people would
just sit down and enjoy the Sun and and
manifest that they want uh allegedly the
space to be for people
taken away from the cars and this space
should be freed from the Cars to make
the city center for Brussels more
sustainable more attractive and more
livable
the project is launched in June 2015 so
that's when the street is closed and
there is an eight month test phase
without any infrastructural change so at
first to go a little bit to the question
of design there is no design change
basically industry is closed and there
is uh as as many people call it a sea of
asphalt I mean suddenly you can walk on
this on the street which
place a little bit of course on people's
imaginary that suddenly you realize how
how huge this infrastructure given to
the car is and and what what could
happen in place of this infrastructure
well
and then progressively after this
eight-month phase we see some kind of
infrastructural development so an actual
change of the build environment
the problem there is is that well there
was a quality of design that is being
put into question I'm not a designer or
landscaper but a lot of people have
criticized the way that this looks like
the immediate limitation is that right
underground we've got a canal uh towards
the end of division and we also have a
metro line of pre-metro line which runs
right under the the surface of the
street so it's not for example possible
apparently to put uh to put large trees
over there which uh already starts you
know making an impact in terms of how
the space is uh space is done
um well there were very high aspirations
when when plutonium was was uh was
announced it was not only supposed to be
a classical project or According to some
scholars in Brussels or even politicians
it was not a transport project or a
Mobility project it was an urban project
an urban renewal project which by
closing this uh Paris like Boulevard
because actually it is in its uh in its
architecture very much an inspiration of
Parisian boulevards the closing of it to
motorized traffic was supposedly a step
towards getting the city center or the
city as such out of decline to put um as
the mayor of Marissa meal of the of that
particular municipality said that
Brussels the Belgian and European
Capital would finally enjoy a truly
Dynamic pedestrian attractive and
friendly inner city like many other
International Metropolis
which is located in the northern part of
of the pitonier and that's the famous uh
square of famous I'm not sure but the
characteristic one with the Coca-Cola uh
signed that uh lights up it was compared
to Times Square so the idea was to make
this project
um allow Brussels to become an
international City to to create this
Prestige project as it was I think very
rightly said uh that would put brussels
on the international map it was not just
a question of you know getting rid of
some some correlated nuisances
and of course the amount of the plant
was announced there were a number of
critics so there were shopkeepers that
were upset claiming that they would lose
customers because people could not drive
into the shop residents a number of
Citizen organizations what were they the
the issues that they would mention I
mean the the the problems that they
would that they would note about the
project well they very much relate to
this uneven geography that I that I was
talking about so if you look at the the
the map of the of the pizza in red you
see these
um this at that time Europe's largest
pedestrian Zone I think now it's been
surpassed by Ghent and and other cities
um Brussels is certainly not the only
city in Europe or in the world that
engages in in these policies it is of
course the main Central axis is cut but
you see that you can actually drive
around the the city uh the city center
so you've got this area which is
pedestrian friendly if we can put it
this way where cars
um Mobility is extremely limited
um but in fact you can quite easily
drive into the Pentagon as we call it
and drive around on top of that what's
also very clear is that
um a particularity of Brussels which is
a very high presence of underground or
multi-story parking lots is largely
unquestioned so actually
this this day today there is about 19
000 parking spots within the Pentagon
within the stroke City Center of
Brussels the original plan of
pedestrianizing Boulevard
included the creation of additional 1
600 parking spots so the idea would be
that of course we give this space to The
Pedestrian and we we allow the space to
be to be somehow reclaimed from the car
but in fact the cost of this or the
price of this I don't know how to call
it is that we actually adds to the car
infrastructure so we definitely do not
want to make this less accessible as it
was called by by The Cars
and then as one of you mentioned there
was an immediate conflict with uh with
the public transport operator the most
important one in Brussels Steven who
basically saw uh day lines pushed out of
the zone so suddenly the buses that
would cross that area have to be
um have to have the have to have these
stops relocated which means that the
accessibility for people who rely on
public transport is
uh is somewhat reduced
right and then well that's some years
later I think that picture is from 2018
as far as I remember checking on Google
well there was a kind of a pushback
right so the cars that were at first
definitely not allowed on the pitonier
now in some circumstances in some
situations can actually enter so you can
actually see and it's taken directly
from Google I didn't have to go to the
pizza near and wait for a truck to enter
you actually see uh of course the
delivery vehicles but also public
transport you see over there in the back
of the of the picture I see there's a
bus making a turn and entering a petunia
and whenever I'm there with friends who
are not from Brussels I mean they are
they are really surprised to be on The
Pedestrian area with public transport
buses and trucks and taxi drivers and
other vehicles who in exceptional
circumstances actually can enter which
questions a little bit this I mean is
this a pedestrian area or is this a
pedestrian area but without uh really
getting rid of all the cars just some
cars
um the question of yeah
um making this a Prestige project and
putting Brussels on the map I mean there
is an argument there to be made and uh
and some local critical geographers have
made it myself included that this in
fact indeed is not a transport project
in the mobility project it's clearly a
project of rivalry valorizing this
particular part of the city it's quite
clear that as you go down southwards
towards the South Station
those of you who have uh who have been
there I'm sure I'm sure noticed it those
of you who haven't that's where we would
go on the Excursion that I hope we will
do in Spring you see that this is one of
the poorest neighborhoods in Brussels
one with very high youth unemployment
especially where there is a very
um
precarious tightly knit but very
vulnerable local economy and any kind of
change in in built environment puts this
economy on the on the huge pressure
especially when the narrative around
clearly uh includes this idea of
bringing big Brands tourism uh to The
Pedestrian area making this place of
festivities of consumption of continuous
Festival
um
so for example the alderman for comments
of the city of Brussels famously said
that the objective here is not to change
Mobility the objective is to recreate a
commercial Promenade new brands which
are not yet present in Brussels are
coming there is a real craze and you can
feel it
for the current Brussels 1000 mayor not
the one that had stepped down because of
some corruption Scandal
um the aim of the project is to keep or
bring the middle class to Brussels to
increase its tax base so suddenly the
idea is not just to or not at all to
actually get rid of the cars or or allow
pedestrians to enjoy the some kind of
newly created area it's a very Urban
project in a very kind of Twisted way so
the idea really is to create a new space
a new neighborhood perhaps of
consumption of leisure of 24 7 shopping
which also of course uses or engages
with the narrative for sustainability
and livability and is somewhat related
to mobility and transport but to a
limited extent
you see that there is almost only white
people there like so the the people that
you talked about that you see on the
lower slide
um like like the owners of the PC market
on the owners of like 0.50 like
basically all all people with the color
they they don't they don't feature in
the marketing of the of the city about
the project it's a very good point of
course that's a that's a very common
issue with these visualizations and
imagining of uh future everyone's Super
Why
um but like there's there I saw that
there's one black man on the right
but there's also no
um yeah I know people with disabilities
very few old people yeah so yes I mean
it's a it's not a very diverse image
it's a good point and also in no way
does it correspond to the actual reality
of of that neighborhood and the kind of
services absolutely no I mean yeah
um Well we I'm really need to speed it
up so um so we cover some important uh
stuff okay until we finish no no but
thank you it's a good comment there is
of course all issues related to
participation and and no actual change
of power in in the patronier but I think
the petone is a very good example of of
how these sustainable ideas can be
applied without changing at all
questions of who actually decides and
for whom uh transport policies are being
made
so very often a sustainable discourse
focuses when it imagines participation
of users of the of the beneficence of
the of the projects uh it basically
imagines that the the main idea is there
to build consensus to inform people of
the decisions that are rational that are
are good practices best practices in
terms of achieving sustainable Mobility
protecting the environment and whatnot
so as a Flemish actually scholar has
once wrote in in 2000 about the problems
of sustainable transport policies that's
the last bullet point these policies
include a harmonious and conflict
developing vocabulary that ignores and
silences the deeply contested ways
through which the transport system is
continuously shaped and transformed and
which inevitably results in a variety of
winning and losing interest groups
that's I think the case in many other
sustainable transport projects this idea
of winners and loses is swept under the
carpet so in in theory everybody
everybody gains but those who are
clearly upset are not heard are not
really listened to and often are mocked
so again we go back to this moral
geography of bad behavior and good
behavior of City shopkeepers who don't
understand that this is a project that
they will benefit from but car drivers
they want to access the City versus good
consuming middle class pedestrians or or
cyclists not so more not so much in the
case of application but scientists are
also part of the part of the vision
um
and in all this to make this point quite
short there is much more impact no not
impact much more Focus much more
emphasis on
um the success of these practices rather
than on the interaction with complex
social spatial phenomena that are there
in the city so there is much more focus
on on the transport part of Transport
project rather than or the urban part of
the purchase well we don't have a lot of
time to deal with okay what could be
done with with this hegemony of
neoclassical on the one hand that's last
week and sustainable on the other
um that's today perspectives on
transport but let's try
um so what would diverse critical
approaches to to transport and Mobility
be on the one hand
the new mobilities paradigm so that's
another reading for today if you manage
to read it uh that's great if not I
encourage you to to have a look because
that's an absolutely fundamental reading
for Mobility Scholars these days I mean
maybe sheller and John Aria are two very
important figures in in in this field of
geography or or any kind of discipline
that deals with mobility and transport
so here
we've got a bit of a shift of attention
shift of focus and
it's really putting um it's shifting
away from transport as a as an
infrastructural phenomenon for example
to a Mobility as a social and political
phenomenon that's expected Builds on on
diverse disciplines from sociology and
political studies to ethnography and
anthropology
and it really explores a lot of issues
that cultural studies Scholars for
example would deal with looking at in a
number of phenomena happening in cities
so different representations and
meanings of Mobility Sensations
experiencing experiences of Mobility so
everything that happens on this micro
level of what people what kind of
practices and Norms are being being
observable or being practiced in
Mobility related spaces in public
transport for example in these
pedestrian areas and what cultural codes
and Norms are related to automobility
uh the problem with this particular
approach is that well it looks very much
at the micro level and whenever it
engages with structural issues around
Mobility it runs the risk of being quite
descriptive so it mentions a number of
issues race class inequality but there
is not so much of a methodological depth
in terms of exploring these issues and
also it's a concept that is quite
Western in a sense that it developed in
the global North and then rather
specific areas of it and it only now
starts engaging with with situations
with empirical context in the global
stuff
another approach another Avenue for for
for doing critical research about
transformability is building on the
traditions of urban political economy of
Transport right so looking at the city
as a social and political construct
which by no means by in no way
is governed by some rational laws of
supply and demand like in the
neoclassical Paradigm or which does not
really look at people as consumers that
have to be convinced to to drop or to
disengage from
um unwelcome or bad type of behavior and
start engaging in good type of behavior
and but rather looking at people at as
at Urban inhabitants as political agents
who do not make just rational decisions
in terms of how they move but have
political potential to to shape the the
urban reality to change how transport
and Mobility is organized in the in the
locality in this city and when you look
at critical urban geography and a lot of
names that I'm sure you've already heard
or maybe even read
um from before
David Harvey Neil Smith Edward Soldier
they've all contributed to to
conceptualizing to exploring this Lane
between infrastructural development and
social spatial distribution of public
services so transport has has been there
to to um
to analyze the critical development of
the city but
absolutely foundational uh readings
there or the first steps towards
critically exploring the relationship
between the transport and the City come
from feminist geographers who would
arrive and that's the reading that you
also
um I think was a sign for today uh Susan
Hansen's work on the deconstructing this
apparent divide between the home and
work and
attaching and women with domestic uh
situations and apparently
imagining them as less mobile Less
Mobile beings while uh attaching this
this Mobility potential to to
predominantly male male subjects and
male situations
foreign
part of that is to understand
the homework relationship and homework
commute which I mentioned last week is
is absolutely the most uh well let's see
the foundational focus of Transport
geographers analyzing
um these Mobility patterns related to
the to the move from work to home and
the feminist geographers already in
1980s demonstrated that this uh this way
of looking at transport and also this
way of engaging Mobility is fundamental
for maintaining uh for maintaining
capitalism this is something that is the
Cornerstone of the of the capitalist
system in cities or outside of them
what emerges from this is understanding
transport and Mobility is not just uh an
infrastructural phenomenon or something
that has some environmental
repercussions and some social ones and
here I'm thinking about sustainable
approaches to Mobility but as
essentially a form of capital Mobility
is a as a potential that is unevenly
distributed as any form of capital
around or across Society across its
different spaces and across its its
classes which leads to understanding and
challenging different structures social
political economic that stand behind
what makes transport unsustainable in
the first place so it's really asking a
question why are people moving in
particular ways not because they are
used to a particular lifestyle because
they have some cultural norms but
understanding a political and economic
system that enables for instance the
domination of the car and trying to
address the system as a result rather
than looking at how people can become
convinced and or how situation in terms
of Mobility can be changed in specific
areas of the city it's looking at things
Much More Much More broadly in much more
structural ways
right so
and here I attached bibliography to the
end of this to this slide so you can
look at these different studies if you
if you're interested in transported
Mobility there is a line of of research
that is looked at the transported
Mobility as a way of reproducing
existing social political economic
interests regulatory Frameworks power
relations regulated by the market on the
one hand and by the state and very often
contested by from the bottom up
there is
a lot of research for some reason the
reason the references are not showing up
but if you're interested I'm more than
happy to send you those that something
strange with my slide here but there is
an ongoing work uh already going back to
the 1990s that shows how neoliberal
policies that affect Urban culture
provision of housing Urban environment
are also extremely present in provision
of transport and Mobility how in in a
natural transport is increasingly
commodified and for example congestion
charging that I mentioned today is part
of that it's turning and we could think
public space that's an urban Motorway or
an urban street is into a commodity that
has an additional price tag attached to
it which as we consume we have to
additionally pay for depending as I
mentioned not on our means but basically
on our on our demand
there is also a fundamental issue that
many geographers have dealt with that is
of Transport related inequality and
exclusion so basically trying to
understand to what extent transport
um enables movement of of some people
while restricting that of that of others
this we will Skip and of course uh well
it might seem very obvious today but if
you look at what was being done in in
geography in urban geography or
transport geography in the 80s and the
90s that was definitely not the case
there is now a rise of research which
looks at the questions of class and the
questions of race and the question of
gender is absolutely fundamental for
understanding uh Transport Systems in
cities and and Beyond them and one of
them is this
um well maybe not such a foundational
reading but still something that is is
very important and and and really
defined the agenda of of research into
transport for at least this decade uh of
course there's there's more recent stuff
that also has been written but I think
this is quite a nice uh introduction to
the question of gender and Mobility
um
and here we see that as with the
questions of race and the question with
class but this is something that uh was
already quite established in the field
already uh there is an Inseparable
relationship between gender and and
Mobility that on the one hand translated
mobility mean development or some kind
of opening of accessibility to different
opportunities breaking this supposed
Paradigm of uh the domestic female and
the work-related male but actually
Mobility is something that opens uh
opens this time and that gender on the
other hand affects travel reasons and
patents in terms of the complexity in
terms of the frequency and regularity
and in terms of why actually people
engage in in movement why do they
actually move around the city
and perhaps one critique that could be
made about the paper that I ask you to
to read for today is that well it
approaches women as a rather unified
category that can be uh uh maybe not
reduced but summarized into in in terms
of particular Mobility patterns that uh
half of humanity engages I think that's
a little bit uh risky always but what
clearly
um I think is interesting in this kind
of line of work as I said uh there is
there is a definite follow-up and and
work that explore these questions in
much more detail and and it's much more
fine tune to a sophisticated but we see
that
um without considering the agenda
component we we basically miss the fact
that uh in many urban contexts women
engage in a completely different way
with Mobility they conduct trips which
are much more complex regular because
they quite simply are related to uh
diverse care related activities they
would be much more inclined or perhaps
forced to
um to bring other people along to uh to
act as drivers for other passengers and
because they engage in quite simply more
activity these than than male
subjects in this way I'm simplifying
here of course a whole lot but this way
of approaching transport and Mobility
uncovers and not only differences in
terms of how people move but differences
in terms of power relations that are
there behind movement and transport
which in my humble opinion is maybe a
little bit there in sustainable
approaches to Mobility but it's quite
simply not pronounced enough or does not
really show us
um in full depth the the multi-level
structure of power relations that are
there behind behind transported and
Mobility
um now what's left I'm we are we are
running out of time so so I I don't
definitely don't want to talk about
everything but
what's also important to remember is
that well besides questions of Transport
workers because so far we've we've
basically talked mostly if not only
about passengers transport users people
who use transport
um there's a question of Transport labor
but also very importantly a lot of
research done on on transport and
Mobility as a vehicle for for some
contestation discontent and struggle and
I started these two sessions with uh
with Greta tunberg with protists in
Chile and other places and
year in year out sometimes sometimes
month and month out you see that
transport is used as a very important uh
subject for a lot of for very diverse
movements and social groups to expressly
discontent with whatever it is and
sometimes quite directly in capitalist
system and that's the case with G Le
Jean and who quite symbolically would
occupy roundabouts across rural or
Suburban France and sometimes
symbolically and that's in East
Jerusalem a Palestinian activists
attacking
light rails and kind of Tramway stations
as a symbol of Israeli colonization in
East Jerusalem
um sometimes these will be protest
against uh some kind of a surface level
policy like the increase of public
transport fares or policing and that's
the case in New York City or the
construction of of one of these
underground parkings related to Le
pitonier that would add to the number of
parking spots in the city while
supposedly actually opening the city for
the for the people
this we will have to skip
um the very last point that I want to
make today I mean I I still would like
to give us maybe 10 minutes for your
questions and maybe some comments uh if
you still have energy to to do that is
that and that's perhaps related a little
bit to this question of new
liberalization of transforms and
Mobility is that what we see uh is that
despite these different
um theoretical approaches and critical
questions that people critical
geographers are asking we see
um a process of standardization of
Transport policies so if you are a
transport engineer and transport
Economist today there is really this
tendency towards
unifying experiences of different cities
into a portfolio of best practices which
are then transferable from from one
locality to another there's a huge
business behind it and not only in terms
of think tanks uh and big consultancy
firms but a whole flurry of events which
you can learn from
experiences of others which you can
learn about what your city should be
doing
and
some Scholars have engaged with that
studying specifically the policy
mobility of of these best practices and
recipes in the field of urban transport
but what's perhaps quite important to be
to be added to this is that well
the story of of policy transfer is is
quite long I mean the the tradition of
deploying Western World Views
eurocentric Concepts and theories and
methods in a more or less unchanged way
in in some other geographical contexts
in Africa Asia Latin America
it's a very long story and the story is
has a name in its colonization or
coloniality
and this is something that really is
there to be done by by the future
generation of of
critical geographers or the transport
geographers or Urban geographers is that
of decolonizing this body of knowledge
which
um pretty much everything that I have
referred to uh in in these two sessions
comes very much
um from the global North that reflects
my own education that's something that I
think I still have to do myself is to
really start looking at the transport
reality and start defining
um formulating questions about this
reality in terms of Transit Mobility not
from our Global Northern perspective but
also that of the South and just
uh again it's a it's a just a simple
example of what this could mean in
practice
is looking at the question of
informality in transport which
traditionally uh that's a slide from one
of these classic reports uh Commissioned
I think either by un or the World Bank
on informal transport looks at
informality in transport as something
that means bad quality in terms of
safety of passengers speeding
environmental impact basically some old
rickety Vehicles which uh await to be
transformed into modern Western formal
public transport system the the kind of
we know from northern cities like
Brussels or or many others in Belgium
France or Germany or whatnot
um but and that's something that has
been done quite recently or is in
process
um is actually understanding our
experience of transport and mobility in
our formal environment is very much
something that can be informed by these
informal experiences of the Google South
an example well if you ever are at wbd
these days unfortunately this practice
is on hold because of you know what
there is a flowery maybe not but at
least a few informal transport practices
that you can find in the gardeni area
these informal taxis vans that bring
passengers informally somewhat illegally
from the South Station to um
Charlevoix airport so the Brussels South
Charlevoix airport and to Paris which ex
well exhibit a very strong similarity
with
many other informal practices that you
can find in cities across South Asia
Africa and Latin America
and then finally while these practices
of course attract whenever they do they
attract very negative attention of the
media of the police they are treated as
something that is a illegal and be
unfair to formal Regulators that pay
taxes and have to operate within the
legal framework of in this case the
Brussels capital region
there is and here we go back to the
beginning of the of the of the first
session a number of practices which are
proposed by the transport industry
transport of Mobility industry like Uber
or many other app-based practices which
are essentially informal practices which
try to operate in the in statuses of the
system and somewhat legal but also not
not to the full extent if you think for
example about what Uber does to its
workers or what is the spatial impact if
we can put the sway of these e-scooters
which uh operate in public space but
very often literally occupy the space
the paving and and whatnot without
necessarily making the system officially
legal or recognized
well here we pause our little right of
two sessions uh I apologize for this bit
of a fast-paced ending to the second
session but we just uh I realized that
we we ran out of time to discuss things
a little bit more detailed way but we
still have eight minutes for some
questions if you have them uh maybe some
points that you you have in your in your
in your head right now something that
you want to share this is the moment
and maybe I'll stop sharing my slides
do you have some questions some comments
well
it's perfectly fine if you don't of
course I mean it's quite late in the day
I understand it
and it's it's definitely a sub-optimal
experience to do that through through
Zoom world
any of these platforms
all right Vitali is
asking about transport labor and there's
also one more technical question
well quite simply the concept of
Transport labor looks at Labor Relations
and conditions in transport so it's
trying to
um
change the emphasis a little bit I mean
if you look at the literature on the
neoclassical or sustainable side
and the predominant focus of
I would really say 99 of the studies is
on the passenger on the on the driver or
the or the consumer and the question of
what working conditions shift to
sustainable transport involves for
example it's very rarely asked
and that I think can lead us into some
dead end
situations in which for example we we
really gave a lot of Hope and we built a
lot of expectations towards some
Mobility practices like uber like the
electric scooters or whatnot without
really understanding that um and that
comes from transport labor literature
that the main Innovation that Ubi brings
to the table perhaps is not uh
connecting drivers and users because
that existed before and I mean informal
transport without the app of course but
it exists in most uh cities in the world
in a global some Global Northern cities
being an exception rather than the rule
but the actual Innovation is degrading
transport degrading working relations to
uh end of the 19th century basically a
worker has very few rights so it does
not have the right to unionize to
collectively bargain and it's not even
recognized as a worker it's basically
some kind of free atom contractor
who
in spare Leisure Time engages in driving
people around the city which we all know
from now a whole body of work on Uber is
definitely not the case I mean these
people are full-time workers not just
hobbyists who try to make some spare
money on the on the side
um so yes
that's what transport labor is about
some technical questions let's address
those for the next discussion seminar is
it the same way of working with
PowerPoint and voice over
um well the way I understand you did it
in other discussion seminars is that you
basically recorded your presentation
which then either you sent to me I think
that's probably a better
solution and we basically listen to and
then we have a discussion which you
facilitate right as those who discuss
the paper
uh so it's not exactly voice over I mean
so you don't present the PowerPoint live
the idea is that you pre-recorded the
presentation with your fellow uh
students
and will the exam be online as well yes
the exam will be online and we are
meeting with basnick and David to
discuss exactly how this will be done
most likely we'll be in well obviously
since we will not be in your rooms it
will be an open book exam
so you will have access to the slides
and all that so but since we haven't
done that before it would be a classic
exam we are we are discussing how to do
this so that it's challenging enough for
you and also not too difficult
um
right so with the voice voice over
indeed
the Belgian Brussels government ever
taken any action to prevent informal
Transportation do you know how relaxed
they are towards this well actually I
researched these navit as they called
they'll go from midi to the Charlevoix
airport and
no the Russell's government is
definitely not happy about these these
uh informal taxis the situation there is
that these men and all of them are a
male
um uh official taxi drivers so they have
a taxi license but what they basically
do is that to make more money they offer
individual seats in in the events and
the taxis and that's precisely what's
illegal so you cannot as a taxi driver
in Brussels you cannot uh
basically stand there on the street and
try to approach potential passengers
offering them individual places in the
car it has to be the whole car that is
rented
well it's a bit ironic but uh what
happened a few years after this practice
uh got into the focus of I don't want to
say public debate but basically these
drivers started being harassed by police
and there was a legal procedure against
them uh flipko I don't know if that name
rings a bell it's a company that runs
the official pass from midi to Charlotte
Airport started exactly exactly that so
they basically now offer well now it's
suspended but they started offering a
van service which goes door to gate as
it's called and it picks individual
passengers and individual seats are
offered and for some reason this is
perfectly legal whereas the taxi drivers
are apparently yeah engaging in an
illegal activity
no uh just uh just as a rebound do you
know why flipko
um like implemented this but in a
non-competitive way what I mean is that
they're actually more expensive than the
not that they're like informal of it
because I think they they have a very
different customer Target so people who
would take an event that's also from my
own work they would be very often of
immigrant backgrounds so there's a lot
of people from Eastern Europe from
maghreb who are quite simply used to do
this mode of Transport for them this is
a very common thing to see
and use in the country of origin
and also they the drivers of the navette
would basically find the customers on
the spot itself so you walk towards the
bus I don't know if you've ever had that
experience but uh whenever I had to walk
to the bus
or flipko and they would try to approach
you and convince you to ride with them
whereas I think uh people who use the
internet who have access to a website
who can who know how to book a ride who
have a credit card to book a ride
that's uh yeah that's a different Target
group
um so maybe that's why flipko can offer
prices which are not exactly competitive
on the economic front
um
well but what it means that's the last
sentence about the navette is that uh
informality in this case it's some kind
of a front for in this case State
institutions to Define what's legal or
not I mean for them to decide that the
navage the informal drivers are informal
and therefore legal and I mean it's an
arbitrary decision to decide that this
is informal whereas Uber is formal
um or actually in the case of uber and
Brussels authorities the regional
authorities pretend that Uber does not
exist
so they don't chase it away but they
also don't promote it which is a perfect
playground for Uber they are they that's
exactly what they want
and they they are not interested in
being recognized as an official public
transport service for example because
that would mean having to comply with a
lot of regulations uh which they of
course not interested in complying with
in in your research about this do you
know if like uber uh drivers partner up
with the like informal Navid drivers to
actually try to convince clients to use
the informal Navid rather than the
flipko for example no I don't no no I in
this particular case they definitely not
I mean the Navid drivers as most likely
taxi drivers in Brussels they hate Uber
they really don't like that it exists
because it basically eats into the
market
um I'm not saying the taxi driver is
here you know some
angels and and uh most uh I don't know
uh
uh fun well not fun people to work with
or on but uh I mean
they they can also uh offer services
which are overpriced and and try to rip
off tourists and and or I don't know
people who come back home Intoxicated by
you know taking a very long route or
whatever with Uber of course the
advantage is that you know the price
before you get into the car more or less
but in this case no there's definitely
no collaboration I would say that there
is some conflict even
uh
uh you probably heard about that already
happened at least three times massive
strikes of taxi drivers against
uh some kind of effort towards
regularizing Uber by the Brussels
Brussels Capital Region authorities
any more questions comments
well it also goes without saying that
um at some point you will be picking uh
topics for your master thesis and you
are very welcome to pick some related to
transport and Mobility either supervised
by me or by other people there is some
more in the in our team and in different
departments as well but
um I don't know if I've succeeded
probably to some extent but not fully
but if this there was one thing that I
really wanted you to understand about
transported Mobility is that at least
from the critical geographical
perspective it's a really really diverse
field there's plenty of things to to do
um and there's plenty of interesting
things to do so I yeah I really look
forward to seeing your research topics
uh and hope that at least some of them
will be related to transported Mobility
and if you need some little push or some
encouragement we are always there to
help you with finding some interesting
literature for inspiration and whatnot
so
um I really really hope we meet in
person one day uh I hope it's not uh too
far in the future
I really hope that we can do an
Excursion uh even though it's on
transport it's interesting uh people say
so
voila I I really hope that we can do
that in March April May the latest so
until then uh I wish you all the best
with everything and with the exam
uh good luck don't get discouraged by
this online Paradigm it will be a way
soon I hope
so
we will be in touch with you about the
exam don't worry about it
enjoy see you later