[Music]
thank you
welcome everybody good evening
welcome to the second session
off Urban
social geography
uh thanks for being here uh despite the
live stream and the recording
I think it really makes sense to be here
um
so we can have a bit of an interactive
session
um
how did you arrive in Brussels first
week
everything going okay yeah
yeah okay you're Landing still a little
bit
yeah
um how did you find the stuff so long
for for those attending
did somebody attacks it's not so long
yeah
they don't live up to your expectations
more or less
yeah
did you find it weird that I started
with uh over 50 of the urban population
lives in cities that this was on the
first slide okay yeah we didn't have a
deal that she would put that on there
but
I can see your critical Minds
deconstructing that first slide so that
um
yeah we have our answers here ready okay
uh today we'll be talking about you
could say an important chunk of of
research into urban uh urban geography
um most about geographers yes
they haven't no last week that
yeah it didn't work
um
yeah you remember yes okay as well no
the system doesn't work I'm not sure why
um but I have a singing voice so I'll
try to project my ideas
um and if you don't hear it I can do it
if it's higher or louder
um but maybe we should be a little bit
quieter than that will help as well so
world cities Global cities one of the
big debates I think in urban geography
in urban studies more widely
uh it's also a very long-standing debate
uh going back to at least the 80s which
probably also explains why you had to
read old stuff uh that you may or may
not find outdated uh I hope it's not
outdated they're all texts but I think
they're still relevant in one way or
another and we'll also try to discuss
that a little bit now what's the
structure of today there's three main uh
Parts uh this lecture
first of all we're going to discuss
I I mean very generally the centrality
of cities and city regions in the global
economy and will take you through three
uh complementary views or views that
built on one another by John Friedman
Sasuke assassin and Alan Scott
secondly uh so that's kind of a
conceptual theoretical discussion
secondly we'll have more of a
methodological discussion which deals
with how uh given these Concepts how we
can actually measure and say something
empirical about world cities and Global
cities
and one of the main methodologies there
is the methodology by gork which is the
globalization of world cities research
Network which was founded somewhere in
the 1990s by Peter Taylor and has been
one of the main you could say empirical
methodological uh contributions to the
debate from that period
and then third of all as we'll learn
um there was some kind of a dominance
if you will in this area of cities and
globalization
um and there as a dominant voice there
is also quite a bit of uh friendly and
unfriendly critique criticism uh toward
um this particular framing of of global
City and world city formation and I
think going into these debates is
actually quite telling
um as to how we Define uh world and
Global cities uh where we think that
that criticism is Justified where it's
Perhaps Perhaps less just a fight where
it deals with other kind of issues and
I'll be talking about four of those
points of criticism one you could call
the both Colonial critique a social
constructivist critique people that talk
about State rescaling and the role of
the state and then finally
um some Brilliant Minds that had
something to say about financialization
okay and that may alter a reading of
what actually happens in world and
Global cities
but before we start
my question to you uh why are cities
Central in the global economy and what
would it mean to say that cities are
actually powerful economically powerful
take a minute uh talk to your neighbor
uh right time a few notes and think
about what your answer could be go ahead
[Music]
foreign
yes
[Music]
thank you guys
okay first ideas are the most creative
ones
uh yeah
so how are cities Central in the global
economy and why oh how can we see that
they're powerful
is he the burning hand
become those centers of
um markets and of multinational
companies and that's why it gets more
and more power sometimes even more than
the nation states that are updated
because they become the part of this
International network of those
pharmaceutical cities
and on the other hand it's like most of
the innovativeness most of the capital
um like mostly not Material these days
but also like social capital is placed
in those big cities and that's why like
you you kind of have this uh point of
migration of high professional stores
okay thank you so it's something that
these are the seats of corporate power
and perhaps the elite that buzz around
those corporations okay other ideas
yeah the back
[Music]
yeah
um
for example
yeah
okay so not just economic processes but
also the power of people and ideas
cultures diversity okay other ideas
yes I guess it helps out to that but we
we're talking about flows because this
is
true that all these flows come together
in large cities and then it becomes more
than it goes from this large city to
another large city and kind of
goes further than the national level
instead of going from the north city to
the the other parts of the country
because it moves between cities
and what is the the substance of these
flows it can be anything like for money
to knowledge to people
Commodities as well
okay other ideas yeah we were talking
about
um just like cities like city government
uh often have you know controlled daily
life budget and make cool side effects
you know a large number of people
quality
it's kind of the Benjamin Barber
argument what if Mayors ruled the world
there's a lot of in a lot of contexts
you could say the main economic centers
are also important political centers and
the national economy and National
politics and it seems to be also that
there's some kind of an extra
territorial supranational Authority
there as well okay thanks for your
answers I think there's other options to
talk about but
I think you already uh got to some of
the essential points what I'm going to
show you it's a bit of a a dated list of
figures but just to give a little bit of
of exhibits as to how important in
economic terms then and perhaps also
like the political terms
some world cities or world city regions
or Global city regions are this is a
list and this is research by a certain
man named lombrex from the early
Northeast and he compared the main you
could say leading metropolitan areas in
in Western Europe so it's by no means an
international comparison at a global
scale but it's comparing
um Delta Metropolis this is basically
Amsterdam rottenham the Hague Etc the
Flemish Diamond which is roughly
speaking against Antwerp Northern
uh Brussels uh which is kind of the
economic Heartland if you still remember
in Belgium
which is Western Germany kind of old
industrial area which is a a large
conversation with a lot of industrial uh
activity or at least it used to be
France this is basically greater Paris
and then greater London is greater
London okay so comparing these five
areas on a number of characteristics and
you'll also see the NX figures what he
kind of finds is that these region city
regions metropolitan areas are bunching
above their weight if you compare the
share in a national surface so the size
in terms of built-up structure depending
the complete territory
it's actually quite small
um when you compare that to figures in
population
these largely outweigh the share in
national territory and then when you
look at the share of these areas in GDP
which is kind of the value total value
of all economic transactions which is a
flawed measure in many ways but it's one
way of starting to compare National
economies we see that that these areas
actually punch above their weight so for
instance when you look at the Flemish
Diamond to take the Belgian example 30
of national service 52 of the population
lives there but 63 of all economic
activities uh actually take place there
um
more striking figures are even there for
uh for Paris and London only one and two
percent off uh of the territory uh about
we could say one-tenth to one one-fifth
of the population but in terms of
um of economic power especially for the
case of Paris it's it's way bigger than
you would anticipate okay so a large
um agglomeration and concentration of we
could say economic transactions that is
taking place
it also means that a lot of these places
tend to be richer
um than their Hinterlands okay so it's
kind of a runaway process it's something
with these activities that are taking
place there that generates more wealth
per capita so this is GDP per head so
you divide the value of economic
activities by the total population in uh
in that City so typically uh these
places are richer than
European average and also compared to
the rest of the economy in that sense
when you look at Brussels Brussels is
you could say the richest city uh in
Belgium
in principle richer than the rest of
Belgium but as as we discussed last week
there's a lot of this wealth actually
leaking to the periphery which is
actually in Flawless and bologna so it
doesn't really show when you look at at
figures from the Press of Capital Region
but the same would actually apply okay
um another way of looking at it is yeah
and this was kind of referred to by it's
a concentration also of ideas Innovation
people
um it's very difficult to measure that
one way of doing that is is looking at
patents right which is a kind of
certification legal certification that
something has been invented in one area
or another a coveted vaccine uh some
kind of a chip an algorithm whatever and
it has intellectual property on it so
and it can be commercialized in one way
or another but it's a very you could say
oh stock exposed kind of measurement of
of places and their their a measure of
innovation but it's a way to compare
different areas and what you see is that
uh here it's a bit more mixed
um if you for instance in in France you
see that uh that Paris is actually uh
outperforming the rest of of the country
this is far less the case in the UK but
it is the case in uh for instance the
Flemish dark okay so it's a bit more of
a but mixed picture but we see that in
general there's a tendency to locate you
could say Innovative processes as
evidence to battles okay there's a lot
of innovation that is not being measured
here no social Innovation for instance
it's really linked to Technologies uh
high-end services and these countries
okay
when you look at the the structure
of the labor markets uh you see that
typically metropolitan areas is also
show a higher share of Highly Educated
uh Highly Educated work okay so
substantially bigger
um say like
say in the Delta Metropolis it's 30
percent of uh Highly Educated people
compared to more or less 20 percent of
the rest of them in Netherlands and you
can have a look at the other cities to
see how it fares okay so a different
kind of Labor Market structure which
tells us something about the kinds of
activities that are probably taking
place there
uh and another indicator there is when
you look at the employment uh figures
across different kinds of sectors so
there's the in the three sector model
that's agriculture industry and services
and we see that well obviously uh
agriculture is very small but that's a
constant everywhere but that there's a
significant larger share in services in
these metropolitan areas than in the
rest of okay so it's there's these are
places that are not marked by industry
but by service economies
so these are just the number of exhibits
uh that tell you something about the
economic importance but it doesn't
really tell you why these places are
important it's just kind of a hint that
something is going on there and actually
you already mentioned quite a few ideas
of how we can theorize the centrality or
at least conceptualize the centrality
and Power in off cities in the global
economy one of the main text uh that is
in the reader for this week
was this world city hypothesis by by
John you've rolled Reddit
so you can just interrupt me if you want
to interject something
um but I just want to give you a number
of notes of my personal notes on on uh
what John Friedman was actually writing
about
so a bit of context to this uh to this
thesis or hypothesis it's a hypothesis
that
groups a number of observations from the
1980s tries to come up with a bit of a
research agenda that needs uh empirical
testing right but you need to understand
a bit more of this context of the 1980s
people of my age have to have the habit
of starting history in the 1980s because
it was the decade they were born if I
was 10 years older I was probably going
to refer the 1970s but as a toddler this
was my my context right so
um you have to remember that in the
1980s this was this emerging kind of
idea that we would experience the end of
the city right uh it was the rise of uh
information and communication technology
on a very Democratic large scale uh not
yet the internet but that was emerging
in the 1990s and being democratized
cheap mass transportation it became very
cheap to fly around the world
um shipping became something that was
very affordable
and what we kind of see is a complete
restructuring of the economy this kind
of reaching its high day in the 1980s it
was already going on in the 60s and 70s
but by the 1980s what became obvious is
that we we are in a new situation
which would call the new international
division of labor with new kinds of uh
geographies of production much more to
the the global east uh and far less
centered on the old industrial areas in
uh say European and America what we've
been discussing last week and we see uh
that this new centrality of cities need
theorizing if cities are not the places
where a lot of goods are produced and
hence where you get some kind of a trade
surplus when you start trading these
Commodities say textiles Etc with other
places in the world what is then the
kind of source of power that cities
actually hold okay
and what John Friedman comes up with is
say look to answer this question we have
to look at how cities are actually being
inserted and indeed an urban system that
is not only National but as Supra
National is actually a global Urban
system
you have to understand that in mostly in
the 1970s a lot of the tradition in
urban geography was looking at Urban
systems in a very nationalist way it was
methodological nationalism it was
looking at Argentina you have Buenos
Aires which was the Central City and
then you had a number of smaller towns
uh but there was a huge configuration
there uh and it left to some it left to
some blind spot as to what actually the
position of these cities were and
processes that went beyond National
economies and as these processes became
ever more prominent
it requested a huge uh you could say
conceptual Innovation uh that started to
emerge in the 1970s hence the importance
of Regents
um theorizing conceptualizing about
world city so a global Urban system
and the kind of main underlying
hypothesis sorry yes
so the last part what I was saying is
that you have processes of globalization
which means that the way that Urban
geographers were looking at Urban
systems became obsolete in one way or
another they were mostly linked to how
economies were functioning at the
national scale
uh looking into let's say where
productive activities were located how
commuter flows were organized how
Capital float etc etc
but as an increased share of the economy
became you could say International or
transnational
yes the first thing that needed to
happen was some kind of a conceptual
framework or apparatus that allowed to
understand centrality at a different
level
but differently instead of talking about
National Urban systems people started
talking about global Urban systems all
right
but looking at centralities okay so what
Freedom kind of uh started to to argue
also on the basis of his reading of
David Harvey in 1970s on Manuel castells
is that we can only understand what goes
on in cities if we relate that to the
position of these places in This Global
Urban system so it's the kind of their
function that they take in the global
economy or rather in This Global Urban
system that will help to explain what we
find in certain places
turned around on the other side of that
coin is that this Global Urban system or
this global economy can also be in part
explained through what is going on in
key Global cities or in this case world
cities to use the terminology so it's
the processes that emerge and are
steered and controlled from these places
that will have an impact on them larger
macro processes in the global economy
so that's kind of this dialectic global
system macro level Global Urban system
world cities and they're kind of
co-productive or co-constitutive right
so one of I mean one of the main
excerpts or key answer excerpts there
from this world city hypothesis which is
kind of very poignant is
um key cities throughout the world are
used by global Capital as basing points
in the spatial organization and
articulation of production and markets
the resulting linkages make it possible
to arrange a world world cities and into
a complex spatial hierarchy so it's
about appreciating how indeed capital
is and its actors
is kind of basing itself in cities as
they organize Global Production
and uh commercial activities okay so
that was kind of the main focus and if
we understand that we will start
explaining why certain places are
important and others less and why some
cities are dependent in this process and
why others are actually powerful
so yeah as I said it's a period of
geo-economic restructuring uh the loss
of a lot of functions uh that were
typically taking place in cities and I
mean John Friedman was was writing from
Los Angeles which was a very
production-centered uh town or city and
it was losing functions and what he
observed was still a huge concentration
of skyscrapers
and corporate headquarters but
production had long left
so this kind of conundrum was how do we
explain that how do we make sense
and indeed as I've been explaining you
had this emergence of the new
international division of labor
activities that were being offshored to
other parts of the globe and the
emergence of a new set of Enterprises
corporations multinational corporations
if you could say an American firm would
be globalizing or multinational
corporations where it was actually kind
of hard to still identify to what extent
they were still connected to some
territory yes
when you say that the production
activity has long left
what is the exactly these credential
activities I mean I this was the
question when I was reading the text
yeah I mean obviously it would depend on
the city that we're talking about uh but
think about uh what happened in cities
like Brussels I mean textile industry
um all kinds of of production facilities
for consumer goods that were initially
uh I mean think about washing machines
uh you know everything that you use in
the kitchen
um these were typically produced in the
post-war era in you could say the high
income industrialized countries
but because there was you could say
pressure on the profitability of these
activities because the wages were rather
High
these activities were offshore by
emotional multinational corporations and
one of the main motivations was the
search for for lower wages okay or you
could say less regulated labor markets
uh than than what was occurring in say
the traditional industrial areas yes
yes yeah I mean yeah indeed I mean and
this sometimes a little bit of confusion
there because people sometimes say okay
these industrial activities uh shifted
to the periphery so I think in the first
instance is the initial periphery of the
city I mean the whole year the suburbs
but I think even and it had something to
do with you could say more the urban
geographies the land Trends uh the
ground prices in cities because it's I
mean you need large surfaces and it's
easier to organize peripheries but then
at the later stage they would basically
uh I mean these activities were Cuts
because of investment in technology and
because you needed Less jobs
to make the same products and or there
were shifted to other places around the
globe okay so but this is kind of
I mean what what started to occur I mean
some people even in some Industries it
was already in the 1950s it's a kind of
this
and over a day
but it culminated if you will in the 70s
and then the early 80s which was a
period of crisis in a lot of cities
so yeah this new type of corporate actor
multinational corporations transnational
corporations uh and how they organize
Global production networks so a
production Network that used to be kind
of regionalized or nationalized in one
way or another
um relied on local suppliers ended up
being Global I mean if you have tried to
order a bike in the past one year you
know what it means to depend on Global
Supply chains or production networks
it's just
an intensely fine-tuned process if
anything goes wrong
I don't know a tanker blocking
um the Suez Canal or something
uh it's a precarious situation but
that's the kind of reality Global Supply
chains and it's a part of the economy
that's extremely dominated by these
multinational corporations just some
figures I mean there's a timeline there
1960s was about 66 billion what was kind
of uh foreign direct investment
sorry for the technical terms the terms
here but it means
um direct investment in setting up
um factories so you build a plant
somewhere else
so like uh Mercedes-Benz built a plant
in Korea or something I'm not sure if
they did
our Toyota builds a plant in in Texas
and it's kind of foreign direct
investment logic and it boomed basically
and you look at the figures of 2016
um I could update that I should probably
do that about a third of the global
economy is actually
um equivalent to these FDI figures yes
foreign direct investment
it's not too important but you just have
to understand that this is a measure of
transnational flows so it's a measure of
uh what part of the economy is
um not local but it's actually Global or
transnational
and it relates to uh the investment
activities by large corporations
to set up
Greenfield Investments out of this goal
so imagine a green field where you put a
new Factory or some such thing as
Brownfield Redevelopment which is an x x
site which is then a refurbish or one
way or another
okay so these are those kind of
activities so 90 of this global economy
uh of this FDI is concentrated in these
multinational corporations and slowly
getting to my point here this is also
why John Friedman was looking at
multinational corporations and their
geographies to identify and
conceptualize uh world cities so for
John Friedman Friedman it were the
cities where a lot of these headquarters
buy is an international corporations uh
we're located we're uh I mean those were
those cities that he identified as World
Series Okay so
since they're so important in the
globally okay
so as he says world cities are then uh
to be uh sites for command and control
and he really saw these corporate
headquarters as the places that controls
and command it in various ways either
through governance systems by decision
making by their internal structure uh
how Global Production was being
organized okay and it's kind of
methodological hypothesis was if we map
uh these headquarter geographies
we will actually be able to to map the
global Urban system and we'll also
understand the relation between
different kind of cities uh as to who
controls what and so it's a way to to
look at Power in This Global Urban
Network some places are more dominant
hold more command and control functions
than others okay so and then he came up
with this um
with this map or art program or whatever
you want to call it
um yeah it's certainly dated because
Soviet Union is still on there and it's
not gonna not part of this figure which
is also debatable maybe they were not uh
I mean you could say euro-american
corporate headquarters there but for
sure there were links uh even with
between the Soviet Union and capitalist
countries for sure but the whole point
is that what what Friedman actually does
here is Translate
uh the critical tradition of world
systems theory which is a way to explain
uneven development in the global economy
to an urban framework so identifies
three kind of areas globalization Arenas
if you will one centered on Asia one on
Northern America and one on Western
Europe and typically he kind of finds a
Power Balance where you you have
powerful cities with a lot of corporate
headquarters uh and you could say the
northern part of the hemisphere and more
you could say subordinate roles for
countries in the global South so when
you for instance look at Northern
America you have Los Angeles Chicago and
New York which are identified as core
cities with a lot of headquarters and
they're kind of
organizational networks threats to the
global periphery so there's connections
with Rio de Janeiro for instance Buenos
Aires and these are kind of
semi-peripheral cities who
also hold command and control functions
and headquarters that are oriented
towards these centers in the global
North could be that there are
subsidiaries of large corporations that
are organized their setup Etc so it's a
way to explain how power is distributed
in This Global Urban system and also
starts to explain why
perhaps some places benefit more from
this integration in the global Urban
system than others so it would probably
lead to an accumulation of wealth in
cities in the global North
to some extent also in the
semi-periphery think about Uria de
Janeiro but at the same time it would
also work as some kind of a funnel of uh
to siphon off a siphon actually of
surplus towards the global North
for instance uh a U.S corporation
producing stuff in Argentina
um in part there will be benefits
locally but at the same time there will
also be an extraction of surplus value
to the global North okay so it's also a
way to understand
unevenness in this global economy
I know it's a lot sometimes a lot of
economic terms but just to give you an
idea a restructured global economy and
the imaginary of a global Urban system
and cities taking a different role uh in
that on the basis of their command and
control functions which treatment
defines as headquarter functions
so that's world cities world cities
corporate headquarters command and
control I'm just giving you a number of
key Concepts there
a second way of theorizing it is and
that's why I also had the other texts I
could have given you the entire book the
global City but it would have taken you
uh a week probably or at least a few
days to actually read it you're still
invited to do so but it's a kind of a a
shorter uh kind of version of the
argument which kind of explains what
centrality is uh to Sasuke assassin okay
um but I'll give you a bit more context
by by referring also to her book the
global City so one of you could say what
is being argued to be one of the seminal
pieces talking about cities and
globalization it starts kind of from the
same route as Friedman I mean it had
been a very intense conversation in the
1980s about yeah what is going on with
cities they have shifting functions
they're faced with the industrialization
etc etc there's also a fiscal crisis of
the local state a lot of cities were in
trouble if you you saw the movie Taxi
Driver with the young Robert De Niro
he's uh he's driving around the Relic
New York in the city neighborhoods are
in trouble there's a lot of blight
um so cities were struggling to think
about what their functions could be and
what is going on especially in 1970s is
a complete restructuring of these Urban
economies so for assassin it's less only
about you could say new command and
Control Function about headquarters she
looks at the complete restructuring of
urban economies from you could say
manufacturing jobs to service economies
so we already saw that the majority of
economic activities in metropolitan
areas of our services but she
particularly focuses on on a particular
subset
of these Services which of course
Advanced producer services
so in the coming months you will
probably start to hate the notion of
advanced producer services or be
intrigued by it but it's a kind of I
mean you probably never heard about it
and neither did I before I ever read
about it but it tells it's it's kind of
um
trying to capture those very
sophisticated if you will Professional
Services that serve as inputs for other
firms so in in themselves they don't
really produce much
but still their input is very important
for other corporations
think about financial services
law management consultancy accounting
and auditing advertising etc etc so
these are not really producing things
that you can then buy and consume at
some point
this is actually very knowledge
intensive sometimes it's also called
knowledge intensive Business Services
which are kind of consumed as they are
produced so legal advice it's kind of
produced in in face-to-face meetings
think about a corporation that wants to
set up a shop or a plant or an
investment in China a European firm
probably you want to check a thing or
two with a large international law firm
that can give you a lot of experience as
to what the regulations are for I don't
know investment and ownership in China
um you would need
dedicated Financial Services how do you
finance uh your International expansion
you would need
um the advice of auditing firms
accounting firms because probably you
want to attract some further funding by
issuing I don't know stocks or bonds or
something like that so Financial
investors would want to look at at your
activities
[Music]
um
advertising yes how are you going to
sell your cookies cars Etc in China
um you need to know something about
about the local market or local markets
the sensitivities
um so yeah you may want to adapt your
practices there you may need the advice
of management Consultants because you
may say that you want to globalize but
how are you going to manage this process
what kind of responsibilities do you
give to your managers in China do they
have autonomy to take decisions
uh will you work with uh with the
central command structure how will you
think about the profit profitability of
your activities etc etc I mean it's not
a course in um in business studies here
but just imagine as a firm that you want
to globalize there's a lot of things
that enter into the picture and probably
uh these kinds of inputs that you need
are so specialized as it doesn't make
sense uh to start producing them
yourself okay so uh you just buy a very
very specialized inputs you get in touch
with lawyers Consultants Etc they would
fly in charge the hell out of you and
then
um run off and maybe their advice was
okay so a shift to the service economy
but with the globalization of production
and the globalization of markets and
financial markets we see that certain uh
service firms are becoming increasingly
important and these are these Advanced
producer Services Services
given to producing firms
um
and what she says is look instead of
looking at
um headquarters of Corporations we best
look not at the multinational
multinationals themselves but we we best
look at where these APS firms are
located
and it's not just that they have kind of
cold control over global Productions
networks as you could imagine corporate
headquarters where a CEO with a big
cigar takes a decision of uh flashing 10
000 jobs in in Belgium or something it's
a more dilute uh diluted form of control
which he talks about it's more about the
control capabilities it's uh the
assemblage or the you could say in the
entire mixture of these kind of service
economies that allows firms that use
these services to exert control of the
global scale so multinational
corporations Patel look at the long
story story short depends on yet another
set of players Advanced with user
services to actually be able to manage
Global Production
so that's kind of her reading not just
corporate headquarters but look at these
notes of advanced uh producers
and the second important element that
she links to that and we'll talk more
about that next week because it's a
slightly different topic is that this
these APS economies is high-end service
economies also is an important engine in
producing polarization
the other kind of process that produce
polarized uh cities but an important
driver according to sussland is
the higher remunerated salaries stuff in
these kind of
um
activities and this will have an effect
on the city so it produces an outcome
where you have high and low skilled
labor forces in APS or around APS and at
some point it could also even lead to
what she calls the peripheralization of
the core okay so there will be a drive
also to to boost informal labor markets
uh in parts of the local aircon okay but
we'll talk more about that uh next okay
so that's her idea about global cities
and in the end Global cities aside from
the production of specialized Services
needed by complex organizations for
running a spatially diverse dispersed
network of factories offices and service
outlets and the production of financial
Innovations and the making of markets
both Central to the internationalization
expansion of the financial industry so
for assassin it's both about and you're
free to refer to socials because it
rhymes with buttons as other students
have done so before and make movies
about
um so it's both about global production
networks but also the running of global
financial markets so it's not just the
production of goods themselves but also
connecting to the world of Finance to
get investments in these production
models okay so that's what Sasuke
assassin is talking about
and the the Paradox that she sees is
um is that as there's a kind of a
dispersion of activities at the same
time there's a growing need for
concentration okay the more dispersed
Global production networks the common
financial markets the more the need for
centralized control or control
capabilities over these markets so
that's kind of the Paradox of cities
despite uh the internet Etc or
virtualization of activities there's a
continued role
um for for face-to-face interaction
interpretation and limited set of cities
so why are APS located in a limited
number of cities
well she talks about different kinds of
part dependencies so it means that once
a situation establishes itself it's kind
of there's all kinds of cells
reinforcing mechanisms
so
if there's a concentration there's a
deep Market in services so if you go to
London for instance you're quite sure
that you will find everything
um if you have these kind of services uh
some kind of a labor market culture
where will emerge around that you'll
find a specialized labor there and yeah
in a lot of world and Global cities
think about New York uh or London some
kind of a yep culture young urban
professional culture has emerged within
these kinds of APs firms
um there's also a lot of synergies
between these firms and I'll tell you a
little bit more about that so also these
different ads firms work together as
they Service uh their clients
and what is even more striking is that
these APS firms in and of themselves
also become Global corporations so they
also set up International
networks either to follow their clients
or to be to remain credible as a global
as a global act okay so a number of
reasons why this kind of geography
reproduces itself and is increasingly
anchored in in a number in a limited
number of global cities
some empirics uh from a dear a colleague
from it will be much even clicking in uh
who did a kind of nice set of maps on
law firms in Brussels it's kind of
interesting to see that the
concentration in global cities you could
say when at the more abstract level also
translate into clusters at the
Metropolitan level and it tells us
something about you could say the more
micro sociologies and geographies of
these kind of Professional Services so
what you see is on the left hand side
law firms
um the big picture are foreign law firms
the smaller insect map is is Belgian
firms the number of commonalities
which is kind of the center of a very
rich neighborhoods or set of
neighborhoods in South Brussels is a
location of both uh I think Belgian
um Boutique law firms and also larger
Law Firm but one is foreign law firms
but what is special for the foreign law
firms they're very much concentrated
around the EU District okay so a lot of
activities either have something to do
with
uh deploy their clients that are located
there which is either directly the
European commission or
um or firms that's want to Lobby uh the
European commission and this is kind of
a process that we'll talk a bit more uh
when we do the
um the tour in Brussels in uh the end of
next week okay so micro geographies are
also uh produced microclusters produced
at the urban level the same as for
instance through in um in London has
some great work by
um cook at all not Captain Cook but
another cook so we cooked up this figure
um obviously what you see there is the
city of London which is also a very
particular uh jurisdiction in and of
itself it's it has some kind of an
exceptional rule that doesn't follow the
regulations of you could say the
continent in this case the UK in and of
itself the government in a very weird
way I never I can never recall how
exactly and I'm not even sure that
information is themselves but it's kind
of a self Corp I mean the self-regulated
self governed
um jurisdiction
on on the island
where corporations also have a large uh
say in okay so within the LA the limits
of the city of London uh you find
particular regulations there that's why
the stock exchange is located there and
all the financial institutions are
located around and then besides that the
specialized District the legal District
etc etc so this tendency of of seeking
proximity is also evidence yeah
firms also uh interact with one another
um so this is some work we did in
Brussels uh we took a corporate survey
uh aimed at uh APS professionals so we
we sent the survey around to it with a
league less expert ICT experts etc etc
bankers and they kind of listed how they
interacted with other APS firms either
in their daily practice for themselves
or as they uh were giving services to
their customers okay and what you find
is actually quite a bit of interaction
um with sector itself
uh and also particularly between sectors
and law and finance law accountancy and
law and against and financial services
so just imagine uh as a corporation what
often happens is that yeah when you
issue some kind of financial product
think about
um a share or something or you want to
go for a loan
then we need a financial institution we
need a law firm that needs to kind of uh
come up with a prospectus or check the
perspectives that is that is made by um
by financial institutions uh Auditors
and an accountant would have a look at
that so this is a kind of connected uh
thing to financial markets what we also
found is quite some interaction between
ICT and financial services this has
something to do with you could say the
digitization of finance that is
currently going on
um so quite a bit of interdependencies
between different sectors will also
explains why does the need for proximity
yes there's a question
that's a very good question
um what do I remember from these
percentages I think
um all right so I think the um yeah
that's it's standardized to the you
could say the largest link so we looked
at you could say the intensity of
interactions and we found that within
financial services this has the
strongest link so
it's it's a it's a relative scale so
that's the strongest link it's uh 100
and then you when you for instance look
at the relation between law and
financial services the strength of the
tie between law and finance is only half
of the kind of relations within Finance
itself
um it was measured in a different way
it's measured uh by frequency so uh on a
regular basis how much do you uh hire
advice uh in you could say law etc etc
um
but there's other ways of of measuring
that for sure okay so it's it's one way
of doing that so yes this kind of
um gravitational pull towards other
actors in This APS complex explains kind
of the reproduction of global cities
another one was indeed this
globalization of strategies of uh APS
firms themselves so they're both
clustered and they're globalized at the
same time uh Deloitte
um well I mean it's part of its uh of
its branding process HSBC it's the same
thing so it's playing on both being
Global and tapping into local knowledge
okay you may think about that what we
want but it's certainly a part of their
corporate strategy or the geographical
strategy
Etc
okay yes okay that's probably early days
but are you guys looking at all about
how
coveted forward
uh no I was taking care of my children
um no uh but I think that's a good point
I mean
uh I think for sure there has been a
tremendous impact on business travel
but it's also kind of a long discussion
as to what extent you need business
travel these are the video conferencing
and other kinds of things
um
so there's already quite a bit of
research in there there's also you could
say more ethnographic approaches uh that
are kind of questioning
uh the actual data relevance of having a
global network but differently are these
offices really being used or are they
mainly there to have an address and
populate websites uh and then you may
actually find that it's much more
concentrated within a number of global
cities despite having a very Global
Network and there could be other ways of
organizing yourself either having
temporary clusters or meetings or
conferences to make things work that
there's also and we'll read a bit about
that a practice of circumference of
people that are that are based in London
that are then two years based in
Singapore so there are other kind of
strategies
um but yeah the main kind of question
will indeed be
um
covet now the final proof that there's
an end to the city
I think that's hugely overblown and I
think that's quite a quite a bit of
reasons about the knowledge and density
of certain practices that explains why
face-to-face and direction will prevail
just as uh when you think about teaching
there's hopefully some added value to
face-to-face teaching over looking at a
screen
and it has something to do with the
interpretation of information and is
being shared about how grounding
processes work do we think the same
about certain Concepts Etc and if you
don't do this face to face you just miss
out on this micro uh feedback loops if
this would be online I wouldn't see
nodding or frowning so I would be in
trouble sometimes okay so I think yeah
it's clearly it's a very important
question
there will probably be a more strategic
use of these sites and will also be a
more selective use of face-to-face
interaction which were done ultimately
also input
um
input APS activities and their
geographies but it won't lead to a
dissolution I think personally uh I see
no no theoretical reasons why that
should be obsolete
but it's uh it's it's research that
could be done and I mean there's a whole
class of uh of people digital Nomads uh
these are more you could say
self-employed they don't depend on other
inputs uh in their production process
think about setting up a website or
something you can just go to Bali and do
that from there but even there you see
uh the emergence of temporary clusters
other digital Nomads that are in Bali to
discuss stuff
etc etc so I think even there there's a
social aspect to that and you get the
return of centrality even where you
don't expect it and it seems to be
something that is related to the fact
that we're talking about cognitive
culture capitalism and that's a
excellent bridge to what Aaron Scott is
talking about
in his notion of global city regions so
we talked about world cities corporate
headquarters sussing talks about global
cities you look into a wider complex of
these Advanced Services that sit around
corporations
and then uh Alan Scott who says well
you and your world in global cities how
do you explain something like this which
is a much larger conversation which is
urban to some extent which depends here
on San Francisco
in case you haven't noticed but how do
you make sense of this wider San
Francisco Bay area with a lot of we
could say centrality but it's not
necessarily connected to poor
metropolitan areas so what kind of Alan
Scott is talking about and says yes uh
very nice that we talk about this
classic
um world and Global cities when you when
you look for instance she was talking
about New York London Tokyo later on
Chicago
uh neat metropolitan areas but there's
other kind of structures uh
morphological structures polocentric
regions that do not necessarily fit the
definition uh that that
Sasuke assassin or John Friedman is
talking about and that also links a
little bit to what we discussed last
week
um how the city looks like or where the
urban is can actually spill over
metropolitan areas okay
so clearly places like uh like Silicon
Valley
um they're not dependent on the poor
urban area per se but they also kind of
um an example of the need for proximity
and high-end Advanced sectors right so
what Al Scott says is that yes
something is right
but the kind of wider uh process that is
going on is a process towards centrality
in knowledge intensive
activities and this pertains to ABS
firms that are located and you could say
the poor metropolitan areas but it also
applies to high-tech firms the gaffa's
platform corporations etc etc all these
kind of innovations that came out of
Silicon Valley for instance or when you
look at the Pearl River delta which is a
kind of much more Polo Centric uh
production area in in the southeast of
of China
um it's also a form of centrality uh
where you have some metropolitan areas
or Metropolitan courts but it also goes
beyond there so what what interests Alan
Scott is more yeah this driver of
centrality Beyond APS themselves and it
says look at the centrality uh that
Sasuke assassin finds is actually part
and parser of a wider uh shift towards
cognitive cultural capitalism right so
CCC
and it means that a lot of economic
activities crucially depends on on
knowledge inputs and types of knowledge
that are not generic not standardized
that are not easily appreciable at a
distance no you need interpretation
dialogue with clients dialogue with
other colleagues to make sense of what
is going on because it's a very complex
matter
you need to make sense of the situation
collectively and hence there's a drive
for proximity there okay and this
applies to an increased uh part of of
the economy which also means that it it
goes Way Beyond the first producer
surface so and the spatial form it takes
is is one of global city regions so you
have a more polymorphic quality
polycentric kind of structure
and his kind of meta geography if you
will is a world of global city regions
with this kind of interconnection
interconnected and Blazer role in these
uh Global production networks in global
markets yes
yes
and this we need this kind of connected
to this APS that are all this service is
connected to
um well the point by Scott is that uh
yes in APS and law firms Finance Etc
there's a clear need for proximity for
the reason that we've been discussing
but this also applies to other parts of
the economy think about high-tech
um think about education or whatever
and these are also prone to this
agglomeration Dynamics and that is
because
um increasingly the production process
is knowledge intensive just compared to
um you could say 50 years ago it would
have been a very standardized process
just make 1 000 cars per week
this is becoming increasingly customized
uh it's much more about prototyping it's
much more about
tailoring uh particular cars I mean I
don't know anything about cars but I'm
I'm stuck with cars
so it's it's much much more uh just in
time delivery it's much more tailored
rather than than mass production that
used to be the case uh in the 50s 60s
70s and this has shifted
roughly in the 1980s where it was more
about flexible production systems where
you could say the connection with
suppliers but also customers clients
became much more important so it's a
kind of broad scale
restructuring of the economy which also
explains why proximity matters not only
in these Advanced administers but more
broadly to bitcoin I don't understand
what drives
these companies together in Silicon
Valley for example
okay well I have a whole lecture on that
and economic and financial geography but
I mean in part part of the story as you
could say the Contemporary benefits of
economic agglomeration which has
something to do with yeah what economic
geographers call positive externalities
by being there you get certain benefits
that you wouldn't get if you're not
there
stepping into high-scaled labor uh High
skilled labor for instance Venture
Capital etc etc but there's a lot of uh
what people call Cloud dependencies as
well and when you look at the story of
Silicon Valley there used to be a lot of
government investment there
um I think U.S military and the
semiconductor business making chips and
those kind of things was hugely funded
by the federal government
in NASA DARPA and all kind of Ministry
of Defense
and a lot of these Innovations within
later on commercialized by private
players
who then use these Technologies to build
their own platforms and there's great
work by Mariana matsukata for instance
who uh who's a great Economist who says
well if you look at your iPad
almost every critical
uh element there piece of technology can
be related back to some kind of federal
investment uh etc etc so
which brings certain to an argument
about is it really private Innovation
that we're talking about or does it have
something to do with sustained
investment by public authorities in
these kind of Investments the same is is
true for big Pharma for instance it's
universities that come up with new
vaccines and these are then
commercialized by Pfizer Etc
um so it's very complex story and no
clear answers it's a field of its own uh
but what we need to do we need to
understand is that this proximity and
the centrality goes beyond cities
themselves
okay so it's it's much more prevailing
process
but still I mean the point being is that
at some point APS firms uh even in these
Global city regions they would still
have some kind of a role to play as
connectors think about Silicon Valley
firms
um that come up with new technologies or
that want to make make a profit out of
these new Innovations
they would have to be kind of certified
patented their intellectual property
would be protected as probably very
likely that would be uh San
francisco-based law firms that would
then specialize in okay uh yep
well I mean they're not you now this
kind of these are the debates I'm just
rehearsing the debate of the 1980s 90s
slowly getting to the Northeast and
we'll we'll move through that uh
throughout the lecture
um
uh but this mainly tries to capture what
went on uh in the 1980s and what what
was the starting point if you will of a
theorizing of world and Global cities
right now
there was a belt yeah
well uh well there there so the question
is as to what extent is the Rust Belt a
global City I don't think I mean it it
would uh Alan Scott would really see
that as a as a global City region
because it's it's mostly you could say
uh a remnant of an older process of
industrialization which was much more
focused on mass production so think
about uh factories in Pittsburgh Detroit
etc etc
the fort Factory
um and this was kind of in the history
of the of the US it was a kind of
process of industrialization that was
finalized but on its returns since since
the 60s 70s and then you had to switch
to the Sunbelt States uh a lot of
production especially in the car
industry was taken over by Japanese
Investments and a lot of states where
the labor rights were less protected so
mm-hmm
I mean the difference would be uh to
what it's and I mean it's just one
example but the question would be to
what extent do uh in this day and age uh
knowledge synthetic intensive production
activities or other activities takes
place in the Rust Belt I think to some
extent this is the case but it wouldn't
be an uh a leading example I don't want
to be exclusive I think it could be
visualized as such but it would be more
of an empirical question to what extent
is actually taking place
um whether it's just a morphology of old
Industrial Area like the rural area or
whether there's some kind of an
integrated region which you do see in
Silicon Valley because it's kind of all
organized about technology
um we could perhaps argue that it used
to be a global City region of yesteryear
uh but perhaps the globalization was
less less advanced
there and then uh or at least it would
be would be different
okay just to say there's different
conceptualization let's try to capture
functions but also the morphology of
these places and I think it's something
to reflect on uh and comparing uh where
you get okay
um
yeah I think in the interest of time I
will have to move on because I I'm using
a lot of words uh but I think it's
important that things are clear
um so second of all and I might speed up
a little bit I want to give you a
methodological example of how people
actually dealt with this conceptual
apparatus of world and Global cities in
global city regions
to measure these processes or
empirically study these processes
so this is the work by the globalization
and world cities research Network
um and it basically starts with
um with a number of questions I mean
uh when you look at some of these claims
I mean it's it's one thing to say yeah
we have to acknowledge world city
formation process of global City
formation process or to say that
inter-urban connections are really
important and actually when you start
diving into this
and you quickly run into into trouble
um and this is actually something that
that was kind of loaded already in the
90s uh so a very long time ago but I
want to give you the entire development
of the agenda
um that is actually quite quite few
insight into uh world city Network
formation so we had a number of case
studies in the 80s and 90s especially
with Sasuke assassin on a particular set
of cities along the New York et cetera
Etc there was all kinds of hypothesis
and claims about the insertion in a
global Urban system
but actually empirically there was very
little insight into this so what
connects cities how Central was cities
in these Urban systems
I was kind of uh very much an ad hoc
answer that you get to the extent that
uh John Randy short said there's even a
dirty little secret in world cities
research actually empirically there's
very little on the actual connections
being made between cities so we don't
really know a lot about this this is
something that's uh kind of a research
Gap to use neoliberals uh academic speak
um
that uh that the globalization and World
Series research network was checked onto
um and there was a number of ways of
trying to to deal with that
um
people try to work with secondary data
in the 1990s of starting 1990s thinking
about for instance yeah uh looking at at
the flows of airline passengers so our
cities connected
um by by Airlines
this for instance gave rise to these
kind of
type of research and this shows you
say the world city Network on the basis
of Airline flows
any idea whether this is a viable method
can we measure the centrality of cities
in the global economy by using Airline
flows
bill
foreign
yeah so some major airports are not
necessarily in global cities yeah other
ideas
I couldn't find any data okay other
kinds of sources to be used okay so the
flow of Bitcoins okay yeah I'm bit more
particularly with with this kind of data
on airline flows other ideas yes
traveling or
absolutely different kind of attitude
absolutely yeah other ideas
[Music]
that's exactly the same I mean it's
debatable I mean are you measuring
economic importance or are you measuring
command and control
yeah that was also the kind of yeah
there's a hub and spoke system people
write about papers flying where you
don't want to go uh so it doesn't really
connect I mean there's a lot of people
in Reykjavik but not necessarily to um
to do anything there yeah and the other
ideas
yeah yes yes yes absolutely yeah okay so
I mean it's uh I mean at First Sight you
kind of can do something because it's a
kind of intuitive picture here
especially when you look at the top of
the hierarchy uh so you find that New
York and London is actually there uh but
then you quite quickly go into all kinds
of anomalies yeah
these Hub airports that's that um uh are
kind of not necessarily relevant tourist
destinations which tell us something
about economic importance but not
necessarily about the importance in
terms of controlling the global economy
which is kind of a different kind of
process
um
yeah I was going to say something else
about that but it's yeah uh I forgot
about it
um yeah so we can also think about about
new data Collections and
um so we have Bitcoins is one way and I
want to pick your brain a little bit
more on that but before that I mean just
saying that
uh one of the big struggles in the 1990s
that researchers Urban researchers were
confronted with and this is still the
case today and you'll probably note that
in some of your courses is that a lot of
the statistics are collected at the
state level and not necessarily at the
urban level
and Peter Taylor uh by now Emeritus
Professor that founded the globalization
of world city research not to always
refer to this notion of Statistics it
connected to
statistics and indicators that were
collected by the national state to
measure the national economy etc etc and
at some point the centrality of cities
in economic process
has only Krypton uh slightly so we we
have sometimes at the national level
indicators about cities but then
inter-city connections and flows it's
very hard think about trade flows for
instance
it's between National economies but you
really have to assume that probably
the major metropolitan areas will be
more tight into this process than others
yes
um
sorry yeah
um yeah or like South American
interviews and a lot of resource
extraction happened in these places and
uh
no no but these yeah I mean it's always
a question and we'll return to that
about the the power of representation
this is the result of when you cut off
the list at some point so it's the most
connected places just in terms of
Passenger flows which is another reason
why it's not a parade example
yeah but you can turn it around and you
can focus on Africa uh African cities
and how they're connected in uh in
global global airline networks so you
could do some kind of if you will bottom
of analysis and it's actually something
that we did that we look at the
evolution of African cities and global
airline networks and it could tell you
give you a hint about how these places
are are internationalizing the
globalization Global globalizing through
their Airline networks but even then
could still be a very rough uh rough
figure and it would also as we found
capture other kinds of processes the
liberalization of the airline industry
in Africa rather than the increased
importance of someone
uh cities in the global Urban Network
so yeah just just to give you an idea of
what is the trouble when you start
looking for new kind of data you perhaps
can think a little bit about what other
kinds of summations uh you could use
and it was exactly kind of a conundrum
or thing that that people were were
chewing on in the 1990s and as it became
evident that some kind of new meta
geography uh was needed and I'm using
meta geography in a sense uh that it
refers to a social spatial structure if
you will that helps to make sense of the
world so it's a geography that explains
uh how processes work like the nation
states tells us something about to what
extent uh
identitarian politics is able to
territorialize I mean to to make it
difficult
whereas uh whereas perhaps
um the world city Network tries to
capture uh the integrated fashion of
economic processes and this is actually
what
uh what Manuel costells was writing
about in the 1990s when he was talking
about this space of float which you put
into opposition with the space of places
so he said well we have this traditional
view of the world as a mosaic of
territorial States
which are kind of yeah if you put them
together you get a world map but there's
another kind of geography that is out
there which is
discontinuous so it's it's kind of it's
not a continuous space these are kind of
islands if you will that are connected
to flows of goods people
um money knowledge etc etc so this is
kind of characterizing the space of
float and it's kind of it's a
socialization process this sociologist
so as a society emerging on that and it
was a kind of uh kind of visionary I but
I I he intended to be Visionary in a
sense that this would be the norm so we
would be become the network Society we
can wonder about that but what is kind
of still relevant I think is that
there's a tension between these spaces
of flows so these islands of connected
urban areas
uh which is to some degree detached from
a mosaic of city-states and there's all
kinds of oppositions between that if you
look at the election map in the UK not
the election map the referendum map
um and you look at the
leaf or remain
uh vote
it was clear that London uh wanted to
stay in which tells us something about
the importance of being remaining
connected to we could say other
Financial Centers on the European
continent the rest of Britain I mean
summarizing now
uh was was against that which shows that
there's a disconnect in the daily lives
of people uh to um to to the interest of
the city
um I'm not saying that uh the leaf uh
campaign actually connected to the real
needs of Brits but that's another kind
of discussion okay so this space is a
flows served as a kind of new method
geography which then was an impetus to
start collecting new data which
ultimately brings me to
um the god heuristic and I'll try to be
as brief as possible in the interest of
time it's also not something that you
need to
I don't know you don't you don't study
this by heart but it's a way uh to kind
of appreciate a certain methodology
um so just go to this website once at
least uh it's hosted by Loughborough
University in East England in the
Midlands
uh it's a very interesting source for
urban level
case studies uh studies on
connectivities between cities that you
can also use for other courses I'm
thinking of the course by bus for
instance so
um it's quite a quite an inventory of
nice case studies uh there so what's the
starting point of this you could say
project uh by globalization of World
Series research network was is let's
take APS firms as the clearest indicator
space species of this new space of flows
so there's a new space flows that
characterizes how the global economy and
Global Society works and as we read
castell's assassin it's very likely that
if we use these corporations we'll be
able to indicate a command and control
functions cities so the starting point
are the geographies of APs firms to tell
us something about world and Global
cities
the reason is as I explained earlier
these APS firms rnms and of themselves
International Players they are they have
a global City geography if you will so
it makes sense to start looking into
those
and the idea is that you can actually
build a model
on the basis of these APS geographies
and the model is based on
the co-presence the shared presence of
APs firms in multiple cities
summarize is one in one and whatever
it will make connection between these
two cities and we can assume that there
will be some kind of flow of probably
emails telephone calls ideas there will
be secondments people will travel
between these officers money will flow
between these officers etc etc so the
shared presence of APs firm in multiple
cities so one firm being located in
multiple cities so and there's three
steps with any model you need to specify
it then you can measure it it's filling
it with data and then hopefully
something comes out of this this model
okay
so yeah how does gork solve it so just
as a as a random example a number of
global or world cities New York London
Brussels Kuala Lumpur and Hamburg
and these are kind of
contain spaces with a number of firms in
there and these are our APS firms so
this is a model this thing cities and
they host APS firms so many firms are
actually the same okay so we have by now
uh transformed uh corporations such as
Audra Anderson Lesnar Von Clifford
chance the law firm Bruce Allen Hamilton
Lloyds as an insurance company so just
to give you some impressions
so how is it specified what does God do
it says well oh there's a firm here in
London or Brussels
how important is this firm actually okay
so you try to measure this in an
objective or at least standardized way
so that you make the same error every
time or that you write every time so you
say okay for this one office in Brussels
by Barclays or something or HSBC a bank
how important is it and we use a very
standard scale zero to five no offers ah
easy you give it a zero uh oh it's the
global headquarters then it's a five
okay and throughout the agent you see
but it would be I don't know KBC or
something like that large Belgium tank
okay and then there's a whole range in
between
a typical office would be two maybe a
regional headquarters and there's a lot
of those in Brussels that actually
control European activities uh would be
a three or a four
um so yeah this is kind of the idea
there's a hierarchy and office functions
and we can measure this in a
standardized way
nervous values
so imagine what the importance of of uh
the connection between uh two offices
would be so a very important office in
Brussels
a very important office in London would
probably generate more traffic in terms
of emails than phone calls which is then
again a proxy for you could say the
importance of the activities in global
command temperature okay so it's
basically calculating the Intercity
relation the R value there
by multiplying these service values so
very basic so you have a very important
one times a very important one gives you
a very strong relation between these two
places okay
it looks a bit like that you can imagine
the connection so
the thicker the line the more important
the connection between these kind of
offices uh and yeah
you can populate a complete Matrix with
that you could do that in Infinity until
you drop that or you don't have the
energy to look for more information on
office networks okay so but this is kind
of the basic model and it allows you to
do for instance this kind of thing so
there's three cities in this very short
list we drop Singapore and work and they
have these different kind of firms APS
firm a b c and d and we can could
imagine a bubble where you say okay and
firm a has a global office in New York
um a very important office uh or a
regular office in Singapore and a
regular officer
and it would be a bit different for b c
and d okay
so just one example out of thin air
what you can then do is start to measure
uh the connectivity of cities
thus far we've been talking about
first
and what the importance of the city is a
referral you can also think about what
is now the strength of a city's
connection based on the on the presence
of firms so what you do is you basically
summarize all these different ties
between cities for one uh for one city
okay sounds a bit complex but it really
isn't so what you would do is think
about the connection between different
cities on the basis of the corporate
Network so think about five times two
plus five times two would be the
connectivity generated by first theorem
doesn't be four times two New York would
be five times one uh in addition to that
and two times five and in some you would
get a figure of 48 that's purely a
relevant example but it would give you
the highest connectivity in uh in this
model right and then for the other kind
of cities we could do a similar exercise
for instance
it wouldn't be generating connectivities
for firm A and D because there's no
presence for these terms so you could
generate some connectivity or a and for
C it can also summarize that and what
you could also do is Express this as a
proportion of the most connected City in
this tiny example of New York and you
would get to say well entrance is four
tenths connected as well as New York so
New York is is our leading we're all
sitting here then we have Singapore and
then enter okay so a very very small
example to tell you how to structure
okay service values thinking about
connections between cities and then
summarizing these connections that gives
us an overall view of the productivity
of a city in the world uh sitting okay
so we have specified the model and then
you can start measuring it and filling
it with data
um and how has gork done this well the
specification obviously refers to the
aps firms and um and it's kind of nice
is that this measurement has occurred
several times since I think 2000 but
every time in the same way so kind of
definitions of uh of categories of this
kind of APs sectors has remained the
same there has been numerous kind of
reiterations of these measures so five
sectors are are connected to substance
interpretation currency advertising
Financial Services traditional insurance
law and management consultancy
basically what God does is the leading
firms 175 verbs based on Forbes and
other kinds of corporate corporate lists
uh that tells something about turnover
the size of these phrase etc etc uh are
kind of selected
and then what is also done is is yeah
you could do this with an infinite
number of cities well not infinite but a
very large list of cities but uh to
avoid a bit of I don't know it's not
bias but to
together manageable data set you could
say the largest cities or what we know
from certain countries as economically
important cities are selected in this
list so it's not a purely inductive
exercise it's kind of an informed
decision to include some uh cities and
other colors so a lot of firms a lot of
cities and then on the basis of
information uh that we that we can find
on corporate websites we make a decision
as to how important offices are
and then you can basically start uh
filling an entire Matrix so just an
example uh to to share a bit of how this
works I mean if you think about just
look at the website can be quite tough
but you can actually although a lot of
these websites find very detailed
information coming at the address level
of uh of these offices and a lot of
these corporations are very proud that
they're located in the meeting world
cities kind of a branding so quite often
you can find that yes
uh yes
to avoid defenestration that's a very
good idea
I think yeah I'm not sure whether it's
going to take away all the noise that
that's what you're aiming at
um so yeah so it's um
it's a freely accessible source of
information
but obviously
um it's also a bit of guesswork it needs
to come up with some kind of
interpretive guide to to reach
uh these websites and to make decisions
as to how you will uh give attachive
value to these stories okay just one uh
for example and then you can build this
kind of matrices
so all the firms in a lot of countries a
lot of cities and then you can start
applying that problem okay so it's an
approximation of the importance of
cities in these corporate networks uh
and it has delivered a kind of sustained
analysis or modeling of these
interactions uh on that basis
and then maybe you already have seen
this kind of maps so a lot of uh world
city Network research and start to look
uh into the actual geography that we
produced so this is some research uh
from a while ago
um it just shows the the absolute levels
of connectivity so the global network
connectivity and the darker practices
are the most connected places and then
uh the lower
um the lighter colors so it gives you an
idea take a good look at this map
what you learn from that or where you
find striking
anything striking here
does it confirm what you thought
you learn new things
yeah
no
yes I am I'm pretty sure
this is the world mapping there are lots
of human things
so why are there so many Europeans to be
selected like you said like if you're
kind of making the largest cities
in Europe we don't have the largest
number of populations so I I don't think
no so but it's it's a list uh so this
there's a number of criteria I mean
population is one but it's also in in
certain countries I mean uh is also
looking forward to basically with known
economic importance so in Belgium uh it
would also include Francisco
uh which is absolutely another two
million uh inhabitant cities so but we
know it has important board activities
just to be clear these are not 525
cities within selection I think it's 123
so it's focusing on the most connected
cities uh which as a result
apparently gives
a geography that is skewed towards
it's a North America Western Europe and
then has a bit of presence elsewhere
yep
it seems like this
is
like that like there's like a whole lot
of economic relationships that are
Global that that business like that is
absolutely a good case relationship
um you know which like on an individual
level are probably not put the money but
like yeah
I I agree 300 so the question is I mean
does this represent citizen
globalization or does it represent the
location strategies of APs firms and to
what extent is this the same so it's
it's the question is to what extent you
go along and they claim that ABS firms
are an indicated species of commandment
control
I think to some extent this is the case
but there's clearly other processes but
I think and that's something that will
return to later on uh
we have to I think another key
distinguish between say more economic
geography readings whereas there's also
more urban studies critiques some people
would say that you're not capturing
globalization here
and there's other process we should look
at yes that's true but it doesn't
discredit one particular reading or one
particular focus on the process as long
as we're clear about what it is it
measures and what it is that it doesn't
but if I complete the example that
remittances I'll return to that in a
second is is
um it's very appropriate so this we have
to be careful that we that we
we're not switching to some kind of
Imperial uh
act here uh to try to claim that one
process dominate something but if we're
specific we can say something
same here it's uh the same period That's
a kind of comparison uh between two
periods in time if we I mean there was a
data collection and allows analysis in
2000 and then just before the crisis uh
in 2008 I mean the previous crisis I
mean I'm getting old
um so comparing uh the structure of the
world city Network which is effectively
on the aggregate level
um the structure of corporate strategies
and their geographies and I mean it's
kind of interesting to see that even
before uh the euro-american or North
Atlantic financial crisis there was
already a shift going on in terms of
strategic importance of cities in the
East and I mean both in Eastern Europe
and uh the global east so I'm talking
about uh Chinese cities for instance so
if for instance we're interested in in
secular shifts within the structure of
the world economy it shows that it's
also reflected in the corporate
geographies of these APS firms
which
knowing that they're important inputs
for Global corporations tells us
something about the relevance of these
cities and how Capital circulates on the
global scale so it tells us something
that everything and that's also and
that's also why Rob uses heuristic and
that there's some modestly connected to
that heuristic is a kind of a starting
point it's a searching device
when you say oh what the hell is going
on in
let's say Miami
it's dark red what could be the process
going on how does it explain that how do
you explain that it's one of the worst
uh performers if you will and lost so
much connectivity where it's a very
important Transit Hub between Latin
America and a North America
is why is it losing its functions uh is
it because Latin America is becoming
less important or uh for North American
Capital uh what could be going on there
I mean you can think about numerous
other examples uh there and it should be
I think and that's how I personally use
it the starting point for analysis and a
different set to a different set of
methods you could do a case study
follow the thing follow your nose and
try to problematize these kind of
filings but it's a way to refer to refer
back to that and it gives you and that's
I think the added value some kind of
standardized overview
there's a lot of things that's further
that we can say about that
um
I really need to press on uh because
it's taking a bit more time than
expected are you still okay to proceed I
promise that we won't take 25 minutes
but maybe 20 minutes
if I'm lucky
is that okay or you want a break
otherwise it's going to take
yes you can
um yeah is there a collective need for a
restroom break
is that a yes hand okay
uh yeah two minutes because we really
because
we can't take too much time so
if you project that in 20 minutes your
bladder will break uh go now
thank you
[Music]
um
thank you
very much
what I know about uh
the World by itself yeah
[Music]
um
thank you
foreign
[Music]
um
everybody
's prices
[Music]
all right thank you
we can see
uh please take your suits
okay okay
[Music]
so yeah just one thing that you should
appreciate by now a long tradition of
Rural and Global cities research then
this kind of empirically informative but
at some point and especially the early
2000s there was a danger that or at
least this research agenda was was
interpreted as you could say dominant or
hegemonic even uh within Urban studies
or citizen globalization and as such it
also raised quite a bit of criticism
um and I think it's debatable to what
extent this is just quite at some points
it certainly is for the points I think
I'm personally but I'm also kind of
involved in these debates a bit more in
the wild well just take you through them
uh and I hope to do so within the next
uh 20 minutes
right uh I think we could say I still
think that the heuristic can be powerful
to the map and spatially analyze Global
Connections but uh clearly something can
be said that I'll just skip that and cut
the business one of the most important
uh could be a more most trenching
critiques was launched at the beginning
of the Northeast by a famous
um scholar Jennifer Robinson
um a South African uh working from
London
uh wrote a book uh ordinary cities or
whatever uh papers was
um world cities or a world of cities
where she kind of
um or was a bit frustrated with with
this dominance of world cities uh
research in the debate about citizen
globalization and it says she says well
it's quite a different thing to talk
about world cities or to be interested
in a globalization of cities more widely
right and that's good reasons for this
difference or the kind of the lack of of
what role in global cities research was
doing then in addressing cities in
globalization since and we've seen the
maps a lot of the cities around the
globe and especially in the global South
are basically dropped off
the physical literal map right so we
find that there's a lot of connectivity
in European Western European North
American Asian cities but there's
actually very little to be told about
African cities they're basically not
represented police
so it's an issue of representation there
in her view
uh but it also deals with
um with how we conceptualize uh world
and Globe cities and in her argument
um we've focused too much on a limited
number of economic processes whereas all
the kind of connections remain unsteady
and one of the examples that was already
given was yeah you can look at
remittances and you would get a
completely different view perhaps
on these Urban Networks
so when her kind of claim is that
by doing so by these say geographical
conceptual biases World Series research
has ignored role in position of numerous
ordinary cities in the global economy
and there's a tendency
to uh you could say offer a eurocentric
global City Theory and then projecting
that in other areas of the world so a
post-colonial critique
it's concerned with people say power
relations in the production
of theories and Concepts and how these
Concepts and theories are reproducing
uh existing inequalities and there's
these are also geographical so it's a
social spatial and evenness at the
global scale
we keep on kind of reiterating the
dominance of certain kinds of activities
come up with certain kind of maps
measuring things in a certain way in the
end we're part of the process and part
of the problem if you will
I think there's certainly an argument
had to be made there
um I think representation is problematic
in my own research that was also kind of
the starting point of why I was
interested in looking into uh Islamic
Finance as a way to understand Middle
Eastern
uh World City information processes not
to a traditional lens of the classic APS
firms but to look at okay to what extent
or local norms and ethics religious and
other regarding Finance
um giving rice to a global sector and
that's in and of its own that could then
also start allow us to unpack
inter-urban connections that was kind of
what I did in my uh my own work on
Islamic Finance so I I certainly am
extremely sensitive uh to this outcome
but at the same time we also have to uh
be clear that that part of this
criticism perhaps also out of place I
think uh Jennifer Robinson really starts
from an urban studies critique and she
wants to understand
um you could say globalization and its
plurality not just economic but
otherwise and even within economic
processes why diversity whereas for gork
I think the purpose is how can we
understand the reproduction of uneven
development on a global scale at least
in the freedomanian tradition where it
was about
how can we explain it indeed the fact
that that there's still under
development in Andre the Frank's terms
in in the global South does it have
something to do with the supporting the
position of these cities and macro
processes macro macro capitalist process
so is it something with
the extraction of value organized
through these corporate networks and
supported by its APS firms that actually
explains why these cities are not on the
map so is this a result
uh is this not a neglect on this place
it's the fact that these places are not
represented means they're either
bypassed by these core protectors or
that they potentially are are
subordinating in this process
which could then be a question of is
this really the case
uh can we look into this processor so
sometimes a bit of a confusion I think
uh between kind of a deliberate choice
not to include certain places whereas
some of these maps are actually to be
taken as as a result of a critical
analysis
I do agree that in a number of you could
say analysis that are more technical in
nature uh in terms of the world city
Network this kind of critical Edge was
sometimes lost and there's a kind of a
mission drift towards mapping networks
whereas the connection to process of
uneven development was less clear that's
a bit of my personal
uh crusade to um to make the connection
uh to the Critical Agenda again so this
but certainly
um Jennifer Robertson points us to to be
very clear about what it is that we are
measuring through this kind of goal
analysis and what we're not so it's
about placing them these kind of methods
in a wider uh you could say firmament of
of methods uh two to work with that
now it does also connect to what kind of
practice uh we which we wish to endorse
within the tradition of urban studies
in the sense that uh and this is kind of
our
um or my personal
disappointment with a lot of research
that has followed the work by Jennifer
Robinson from the South but there's a
lot of tendency with weird rich Jennifer
or Jenny uh and a very reductionist
representation of her legitimate claims
claims and we we actually wrote a paper
about this with the egregious title uh
kind of straw man speak uh where we kind
of deal with
um with distilling what is kind of
Justified criticism and where we think
it's a bit too much and what we
particularly regrets is that some of
this criticism has led to
disengaged or polemic pluralism where
it's a kind of rejection certain agendas
to do something else without taking
stock about of the knowledge that is
produced there so what we try to then
propose is some kind of a middle ground
is a more engaged form of urban studies
debate which also means that you can say
yes
like analysis analysis or relatively
research in general
we need to put it in its place but it
doesn't mean that we can try to work
with this Concepts to make sense of
places
beyond the short list of world cities
could be that I'm babbling and I'm
defending on explaining myself in
different kind of ways in unnecessary
ways but let me try to make it more
clear uh you can say ah Beirut Manila we
don't need a world city Concepts it's uh
well the world city is a euro-american
invention can't do anything with that
uh it could be something that you could
say uh they say yeah we need the concept
of the middle eastern city of the Asian
City because everything is particular
and then we need to build that theory uh
and then it's so unique and particular
that you you can't do anything
so
people disagree and say look
there's no one-on-one projection of
world city formation as a process on a
city like Beirut for instance or Manila
uh but we'll have to work with the
concept to see to an extent it does
explain something of what we find and
what extent it doesn't and perhaps we
need to enhance or tailor uh diversify
the concepts
and in the process we potentially may
even learn something about the place
that we we study but at least we still
remain in a position that we can speak
back to the original debate which is I
think the point of urban studies that
were not Lost in Translation but try to
connect to some kind of organized or
overarching debate even if you're
studying in very diverse places
now yeah I won't say too much about
these two cases because it's also part
of our discussion seminar but just to
point down the kind of contrasting cases
uh so in one paper we looked at Beirut
um which is kind of an interesting place
I mean we call it a city more by X path
uh we're also the formation processes so
what you see is a built environment uh
with skyscrapers
um they obviously took a hit and are
taking a serious hit uh currently uh
with the the entire term of the country
isn't
um but on the first side you would say
okay there's actually when you start
looking at APS activities it's actually
very little going on there there's a lot
of very little Regional headquarters
there's very little International firms
but when you then start looking into yes
remittance flows or and and the diaspora
you find that almost one-fifth of
Lebanese economy is made of out of these
remittances and a lot of it braces back
to ABS professionals that are located in
the Gulf so it's our it's our McKinsey
trained pedigree Consultants McKinsey
Liberty that is then advising the Saudis
or people in Dubai the Elites in Dubai
that earn their money there uh send back
their money and buy a hugely overpriced
apartment in the city center of Beirut
at the real estate market which is then
kept artificially booming by almost free
credits from the Central Bank of Lebanon
which is also the personal property of
the living families of
um of Lebanon so it's kind of connected
um now in any case uh it shows you that
if you follow your nose in a sense there
still are some characteristics of world
city formation especially in the role of
high skilled labor but it's a kind of
it's it's an impressive Regional
capacity building
Regional uh circuits of value that are
kind of connected back to the city
yeah
um so it's function as a kind of a
capital city to the region rather than
as a kind of server service deliveries
if you look at Manila it's kind of the
opposite you'd say wow a lot of
activities there a lot of APs firms
they're all there but then you when you
start looking into these activities and
there's something that Rihanna gleibert
has done
it's basically part of the largest one
of the largest Outsourcing sectors of
Tendencies uh that you find so a lot of
back office activities for Global Banks
and other kind of service providers but
it's not really command and control or
not at least not what we think of it
and it may also work through and what it
can explain in terms of the segmentation
of the labor market but because it would
not be high-end managers that are then
gentrifying neighborhoods
but it may give rise through a middle
class or something so it may result in
other kinds of Labor Market structures
but at least we can still refer back to
world cities and start comparing to what
is going on
so this is an example of an income
passing approach to try to encompass
diversity in your research design and
try to make sense of it okay so that's
how we solve it I won't say anything
more because I want to leave something
for the debating session
second uh point of criticism is uh
social constructivist critique
um again a bit the same in the sense
that representation matters and this is
the great work by Dory Massey uh who was
a uh trying to say nice economic
geographer from the UK
um
thought about spatial divisions of labor
was one of the leading voices and and a
lot of progressive debates uh in
geography
um and she also wrote a book
world city in 2007 uh where she kind of
engaged with with this agenda
and
um what she basically says in this book
is
um yeah
um
world cities are not just a given an
economic geographical reality based on
as we set the clustering of these abs
firms their labor markets Etc
but they are but they're also a product
of uh discourses representation
etc etc so they're mediated by political
interests
um Elites others and other actors that
project certain discourses about world
and Global cities and these also have
ultimately uh performative effects so
they they produce or co-produce certain
realities okay so that's kind of
knowledge Theory so the world
is also to some extent shaped by how you
represent this and then you can can be
an Ardent very strong believer of that
and say okay the world is almost
exclusively reducible to how we
represented whereas others would work
more in the kind of materials fragrance
okay not everything is shaped by words
right so
something to think about at what extent
Rapid Station actually matters now
during uh explains this for London
and she says yes it's a globalized
financial center but the way we perceive
it and the way the city reproduces
itself is the outcome of a decade-long
battle of representation which was led
by dominant Financial Elites politicians
not often uh not seldomly connected to
all boys networks that have been
projecting the world city status of
London and this has become some kind of
a hegemonic
unquestioned uh neoliberal growth
strategy okay it has been part of that
neoliberal strategy since uh the 80s and
the kind of ideas that what is good for
the financial industry is good for the
city what's good for the city is good
for London not good for London it's good
for the southeast of England
what is good for the Saudis is good for
the UK and uh dear Europeans with good
what is good for the UK is also good for
Europe so please deregulate Finance
so it's a rhetorical strategy she calls
uh the passport Toto where the park is
there to represent the whole so it's the
interests of the city of London which
are projected to be the interests of the
UK citizen and again as brexit has shown
this has been quite uh radically uh
rejected again
um
whether legitimately or not
um so yeah there's this neoliberal
growth strategy and it also was
connected to a legitimate legitimized
certain material decisions in the sense
that
if you look at this course is about does
hydro need a new uh Runway because of
capacity issues yes London cannot uh
keep up with its Global City status or
it cannot grow it its connection to new
Emerging Markets if it doesn't have an
extra Runway so please neighbors
go away or
needle your ears
um but we absolutely need this and
Global City discourse is there to
justify that but also when you look at
the Restriction of the UK economy and
70s and 80s I mean closing the mines etc
etc and this has produced very uneven
outcomes in the UK a lot of cities in
the north and hope mining areas
industrial areas saw a decline and at
that point what would have been
interesting is low interest rates or
that could boost investment to
restructure these peripheral economies
that didn't happen at that point there
was an inflation there was high interest
rates which made
but simply money very expensive
and which made that it was very hard to
seek investment in these areas and
obviously this was in the interest of
the southeast which generated an influx
into Financial Services Etc which then
further grew a global City London so
it's a particular political agenda that
is behind there that has produced there
another final point that we us as
academics or academics to be are not
neutral bystanders and her claim is that
especially when you start looking at
these world city rankings
um that Gog is claimed to produce this
is part of the problem it's kind of
fueling the self-fulfilling prophecy is
giving people in the city of London
the instruments and the exhibits to say
look uh we're still the leading City but
Dubai is closing please come on we need
further investment uh in the city or we
need the regulation or something like
that
um so that's kind of for also attention
critique and sense that yes
um world cities research is performative
in that sense
so yeah uh just a few uh slides there
and I'll return to that I mean the
pictures that we have of representations
that we have of London
um are the Blitzen Glam quite often and
it's typically the city but then how
cities kept the city of Lomas kept
working or the wise much important area
remains often undiscussed but that's
something that we'll talk about next
week
um
yeah and this is kind of uh Battle of
representation is ongoing this is a bit
of a dated figure it's still with uh uh
with Theresa May there who I was going
for a global Britain agenda uh and again
you see that yeah
um
uh this kind of City Elite is trying to
push it in the the whole campaign in a
certain way uh threatening to leave
um rapidly in the city of London which
would then impact you could say the
global City status of of that City okay
so it's kind of still the same
repertoire that is being used uh at
times when when brexit was was still uh
unfinished business
it's probably not still not unfinished
business but voila now I think uh and
then I really almost had to close
performativity is a very important
criticism that's something that we
should be very reflexive about it
basically means
the insights that you produce kind of
figures that you produce the maps that
you produce to what extent do they shape
and impact reality to an extent are they
picked up what is the responsibility of
a researcher to keep ownership over his
or her results
do we have an impact of that and it's
something that that is also very
important to reflect on in relation to
world cities and Global cities
and there I think my personal stance is
that we should probably not exaggerate
the influence of world and Global cities
research in the sense that it's only
part of a much wider phenomenon of of
City rankings etc etc and actually when
you start looking at it it's often the
ABS firms themselves that come up with
all kinds of rankings another much more
picked up in popular debates by
politicians that want to gain uh
a world in global City status rather
than referring to go in and of itself I
mean it would be a pleasure to actually
know that people read academic papers
but I think it's actually quite quite
limited so yes we need to be reflexive
about that but at the same time it could
maybe a little bit overblown and
rankings are produced uh probably by
other facts
um I'm sorry to run through this another
point is
[Music]
um
and a criticism a criticism that deals
with uh to what extent
uh world and Global cities takes into
account you could say political economy
um processes or the politics of global
City formation and I think that connects
uh to the work of
um of Doreen Massey
um and it's a kind of an agenda that was
pushed by new Brenner especially at the
high at the end of the 1990s
and he says well it's not just economic
geographies it's not just agglomerations
cluster etc etc uh what we need to
account for is the restructuring of the
economy
and what he says a rescaling of the
nation state
so the way uh capitalism is being
governed is not exclusively at the
national scale but something is
happening with that at the same time
it's becoming supranational so you get
all kinds of international organizations
IMF oecd etc etc in Europe we have
European Union that starts to
increasingly govern uh the economy and
at the same time there's a kind of
devolution growth and the importance of
regions of cities as governance layers
and some kind of kind of a hollowing out
of the national level so in the words of
of you know Brenner it talks about
globalization as the undoing of the
state whether as the re-specialization
or re-territorialization of the state
where it attaches itself to new spatial
layers and it calls these new state
spaces uh to which you have new kinds of
all kinds of new state projects growth
projects so
to summarize that seems a bit complex
but there's a shift in in how National
economies are being managed in terms of
spatial scales it's also happening in a
much more entrepreneurial way and I'll
say more that about that next week
but the point is that this these are
politically negotiated processes
and you can have a look at at this
overview slide uh to the kind of
detailed uh process that are going on
there but just to give one example they
also kind of gave last week Brussels is
kind of in this
straight jacket of the Brussels Capital
Region whereas it doesn't
um
refer to the spatial scale of the actual
metropolitan area or the economic weight
of
of the city
whereas in other context you see the
formation of
um of the larger metropolitan areas as
governance structures where Global City
from the foot is now trying to put a
high in life
it's a kind of more Global City region
organization which has its own
governance structure etc etc so there is
easier to appreciated than that emerges
when you compare that to Brussels so
it's it's a rescaling process and you
see that in a lot of European contexts
not seldomly also kind of pushed for by
the European Union who likes to see
the Europe of regions it's kind of this
idea that you need larger entities
um
city regions or regions to to kind of uh
take control over upscale economic
processes
so yeah a sensitivity to how the states
spatially reorganized itself to an
extent there's new governance layers to
manage also these economic processes
that was kind of also added to the
debate and then finally very final
slides is and it's kind of a critique or
a criticism
buy
um where people working in the realm of
financialization
I'll say much more about that if you
take the economic and financial
geography course it's
it's all about financialization but just
the point of the fact that
um
criticism deals with what it is that is
going on in world cities so it doesn't
really uh criticize the relevance of
command and control practices in world
and Global cities but it says that
perhaps the nature of these activities
has transformed over the past 20 or 30
years
so financialization what does it mean it
means that an increasing part of uh
economic processes or value-based
processes or profits generating process
not occurring you could say in
productive activities but is somehow
connected to financial circuits so
financial investments is by owning
Financial assets rather than actually
producing something uh that uh that
people get rich and it also explains a
runaway inequalities between those who
have large uh huge amounts of wealth and
others who who rely on their labor but
we'll say something about that next week
so financialization also means that
there's a lot of pressure on
corporations
two generate returns for financial
investors so it's not just about
competing with other capitalists too to
be the most efficient car producer of
cookie manufacturers it's also to do so
to generate as much shareholder value
compared to your to your competitors
it's one I mean this kind of called
corporate financialization it's the
restructuring of Corporations so that
the shareholder value is actually being
created
so
perhaps world cities are still about
seamless service for globalization so
the management of Global Production
processes networks but this other side
financial markets perhaps needs to be
taken much more seriously and these abs
firms may be more and borrowed and
Loyals and process of financialization
rather than productivist logics
um
so yeah just uh wait
um so yeah and I think
um this is what I say here World Series
may become like obligatory passage
points for other reasons than the ones
that have been assumed uh already and
that's why uh in one paper we talk about
an augmented world city uh hypothesis
it's not just about generating value
from productive activities but it's also
about extracting value to rent
extraction practices from those global
production networks and you can see that
for instance when when you see how
corporations attract funding uh you need
a whole uh amalgamation of of connected
ABS firms to issue in this case a Euro
law which is some kind of an offshore uh
investment instrument and this is a um a
firm a real estate Corporation
Northern Germany and it's kind of face
all these people to issue debt on a
global scale so to finance Its Real
Estate projects in Germany so world
cities are mobilized to attract funding
and to optimize that in a particular way
the same thing happens when you look at
the other side of the equation when
value has been produced the point is
that you
limit the taxes that you have to pay on
your Surplus value otherwise
shareholders won't be pleased and you're
competing with other firms to pay as
much shareholder value as possible and
this is a classic example by Google who
is using a double dutch Irish sandwich
to um
yeah to make sure that it's it's
minimizes its its uh its its taxes right
so
it puts I mean I studied the details and
I actually don't know them by heart but
places some intellectual property in
Ireland and that fermented through the
Netherlands goes back to Ireland and
then it passes through the Caribbean
um uh to optimize that circuit and this
is also something that firms like
Deloitte and law firms are also engaged
so it's the optimization of these kind
of financial structures uh amidst
financialization is also a very
important function of world cities so in
the end
I think to summarize the picture it's
about
um you could say representation you
could think about
um world cities as kind of Mount Everest
agglomerations of wealth that is being
generated and then will then spill over
across the territory but you can also
think about uh how's it called in
English the Marian deaths 11 kilometers
deep uh where a value that is being
produced elsewhere is being extracted to
and is basically uh putting a drain on
the global economy and if you look at
what happened during the financial
crisis
each of the financial sector created a
lot of surplus if you will generate a
lot of profits then came the crisis and
it I mean I think in Europe it was the
figure of 700 billion uh that the
financial sector was kind of bailed out
and it was even more in the U.S
it's huge figures of saving these kind
of activities where in general they're
actually putting a next drain on the
global economy
so we really have to think about world
cities in a critical way
what do they contribute or what are the
actors in world cities what do they
contribute and what what kind of things
effects are or more
problematic I'm very sorry to take a
little bit more of your time but that
was kind of four ways of being critical
about world and Global cities
there's no time for Q a now but next
week we'll continue and maybe we can
start with uh with some questions next
week week if you would have them
and uh we'll talk with the flip side of
the coin
about the flip side of the Chrome is
just polarization so what does it mean
world and Global City formation for
these very places
and these are the two texts that you're
warmly invited to read
thank you
[Music]