thank you
oh my God
um
thank you
services
welcome everyone
good evening this certainly is my
favorite time of the day to teach teach
a course at 5 PM after every start at 8
A.M so anyways uh welcome to Urban
social geography or urban geography
depending on your exact type of
enrollment I am boss van Hur for those
who don't know me yet and I'll be your
let's say your lecturer for today's
session and next week's session
um for some reason because I was I had
started a web stream on panopto but for
some reason I was I'm receiving emails
from Individual students asking for
permission to gain access to the panopto
webstream I gave everyone
access access until a minute ago now
I'll stop so because I have to teach at
some point
um so if you receive let's say messages
from your fellow students who cannot
attend the reason is that they arrived
after five past five and I need to get
started but if all goes well the
recording will be recorded and uploaded
it went wrong in the previous lecture
today because I've been up to technical
difficulties but hopefully we'll manage
to day I might close the window at some
point but it might help to get some
oxygen in here so feel free to also open
windows at the end if you prefer
um welcome so two sessions
um as with some other course we run
especially the big introductory Master
Level courses
um Urban social geography urban
geography is a thematic course so it
tries to give you an insight into
different let's say teams around let's
say concerning let's say different takes
on Urban Geography I would personally
prefer to call this course Urban Theory
yeah because I think we do more than
just geography but the basic idea is to
give different conceptual analytical
perspectives on how to how to study or
how we can study Europe
my role
in this in this course and I guess also
in my own research specialty is I'm the
cultural guy so I I tend to focus on
more cultural issues uh so I'll be
talking you through
both today and next week Monday July say
cultural approaches to studying the
urban
um today's session oops here we are
today's session is really you see a
historical overview
um in the sense that I want to go
through some discussions which you might
know uh or either let's say in generic
terms or relatively specifically around
let's see how let's say uh thinking
about let's say cultural approach
towards the urban has been informed
let's say historically speaking so I'm
going to go through a number of let's
say historical steps mainly focusing on
let's say the impact that sort of the
thinking about the post-modern Assad
this seems like old hats seems like old
information it's it's certainly a debate
that is not used with this kind of
terminology except maybe unless a
journalistic media but certainly not
academically asking speaks in the last
10 years I wouldn't say that people's
modern has been the main Obsession for
for let's say for research but I would
argue that much of what has been
discussed from the 1980s onwards more or
less around the postmodern as already is
still being let's say dealt with
although using a different vocabulary
yeah this is what you will often see is
that the terminology terminologies might
change but if you open adapt in more
historical lands you will see the summit
even though the terminologies have
changed then let's see the underlying on
uh let's say content or the substance
that's behind terminology as we made the
same over many many years so not
everything is new even though you use a
new terminology so today is a more
historical session you can see on
historical historic sized approach
next week it's I mean rather generically
called Urban cultures but there I want
to sort of give you a number of
perspectives let's say on or let's say
what could temporary approaches towards
studying uh the urban from a cultural
perspective
um I will not give a definition of
culture I mean I'm not I mean so it does
that's it's a lost it's a lost task it's
not going to work I'm also not going to
give a definition let's say media
Scholars are not going to give a
definition on what media is still they
do interesting research but please keep
in mind that one of my aims here is also
to if you decide to adopt a cultural
approach please be very clear and
specify and unpacking and
operationalizing your use of terminology
because it can mean so many different
things yeah so you have to be quite
specific and hopefully my lessons will
help with bits to give you let's say an
insight into the different layers or
different let's say let's say lines of
research that exist and that all use the
terminology around around culture so
that's what I'm going to try let's say
to bring across uh today
so this is basically the structure of
today's session let's see how far we get
it's always unpredictable with slides
and then mood of the day and questions
of students Etc
but first I want to start with a very
let's see setting the scene focusing on
the cultural turn the humanities and the
social sciences I assume most of you
will more or less know what the cultural
Authority Humanity social sciences is so
we'll not discuss this in depth yeah
there are many many books written on
this again it's a debate I think that is
more or less
not finished but it has been let's say
many of the debates we've had when
discussing the cultural term Humanity
social sciences have now and we've been
internalized in everyday research so in
that sense it has become well
naturalized in in in very literal sense
so that's the first part very much
setting to see second part I want to
talk to you about post-modernism and the
city there I will mainly focus on the
work of Frederick Jameson not because I
think that he's the only one who has
written on postmodernism in the city
he's not even an urban scholar per se he
actually comes from literary studies and
philosophy but his work is thinking
about this has been very influential
especially because it has been picked up
by Urban Scholars at a later stage
among which the Los Angeles School of
urbanism which is the third section the
third part of today's lecture because
they really have worked you could say
with this with this idea of the
postmodern and the city and have
proposed new ways of studying this city
as we will see not everything that you
have proposed uh was as new as they have
claimed but still that it has been quite
a foundational moment for for the study
of the urban for urban studies at large
to close sorry now not too close then
there's a fourth section which adopts
was it continues partially underwater
School of urbanism did but really sort
of broadens and broadens the debate and
has perhaps been more influential also
and this is literature that's usually
summarized or with terminologies around
Urban Landscapes or the symbolic economy
yeah these are terms that you see
popping up especially from the mid 90s
90s early 2000s onwards and that is
still very influential in in our
thinking on on the city and culture
today
um very last part I will discuss this
today or I'll pick this up tomorrow uh
it's what I call meeting halfway uh
Urban anthropology cultural studies and
the spatial turn my entry point in
discussing the urban that's in and the
cultural culture is trulicity spatial
and geography as a discipline whatever
discipline it might be but let's say
parallel debates going on and what we've
seen from the May 1980s 1990s onwards is
that let's say some of the concerns that
are geography or economic geography or
Human Geography at large has had really
started influencing other debates at the
same time as human geographies started
engaging more or let's say actively more
assertively with other disciplines there
are many many disciplines that could be
that could be let's say
mentioned here but for me some of the
more influential ones are anthropology
Urban anthropology and cultural studies
yeah so where geography start engaging
more with questions around and let's see
questions traditionally uh discussed in
anthropology or in cultural studies
cultural studies then topology also
started engaging more with less of the
spatial concerns of geography so this is
something that I will close to this
lecture it or open next week lecture and
now I'm going to close the window
because
hear the difference
is one reminder I have a habit of
talking fast so if I talk too fast just
raise your hands yeah this is I have the
very strange habit of talking faster in
English than I do in Dutch which would
be my mother tongue
um don't ask me why if you ask me to
speak German I'll still slow down but
that wouldn't help for let's say General
comprehension in this class I think okay
first part cultural turn or cultural
turns
um
the slides are all uploaded so in that
sense you don't have to sort of type
like crazy just try to focus on the main
uh the main elements and try to go the
flow of the argument and trying to
develop
some of you will notice some of you will
not it really depends a bit I think on
your on your educational background yeah
I would assume that those were the
social sciences especially Humanity
backgrounds will be more familiar with
this debate than those let's say coming
from an engineering background but it
much depends a bit on the specificities
also which countries you have studied
so some take-home messages what is the
cultural term the cultural terms it's
part of a wider shift since I would
argue the late 1970s at least since this
period that it was phrased as such in
research practices in Humanities and
social sciences yeah so there are
various interrelated claims so that's
why I talk about cultural turns in a way
because it's not that easy to identify
one single shift in research practices
one is empirical and that simply argues
well simply argues culture is becoming
increasingly important in advanced
societies Advanced societies being a
code word for Western Europe and North
America basically yeah so
knowledge-based sites Advanced societies
post-industrial societies whatever term
you prefer so this is the first claim
being made as to why there is and or
should be a cultural term yeah culture
is simply becoming more important
um and you've opened the question what
Dan is culture about let's just assume
that it refers to the arts film media
whatever right so adult should become
more important
this relates to a second's plane which
is theoretical
we need better theories to grasp better
cultural dimensions of the social yeah
referring usually to symbols effects
meaning making practices yeah
the one that doesn't necessarily relate
to the second principle you could have
no change let's say an empirical
phenomena but simply saying well but you
really understand these old phenomena
better we need theories that capture
this the culturals let's say dimensions
of this phenomena better yeah but
obviously when we talk about the
cultural turn often this comes together
we say Okay culture is becoming more
important empirically and in order to
really understand this better we also
need other theories because the theories
we have don't really capture this quite
well you know so that's the tech
influence the third Point again of
course related with methodological
if this is the case or also respective
of this we need new methods to better
interpret different empirical data and
or to interpret data differently yeah so
either the old data in a different way
or to interpret it better or to
interpret data differently so it's a
time to interpret new data uh that we
need different methods for this yeah
maybe the simplest example in the
current setting would be if you look at
the rise of social media and let's say
data data skills for example and let's
say the last 10 years it's obviously a
new methods have also Arisen in order to
be able to investigate these phenomena
so there's a Classics as a
straightforward example of how a new
phenomena has emerged as a society-wide
and we're not always able to capture it
with the same methods that we had before
so you might need different skills
different methods yeah I mean again
question mark not saying this is the
case but this is let's say the argument
is put forward because obviously with
let's see existing methods you can still
do quite quite a lot or maybe they're
tweaking them so that's um important key
in mind so that's the clay but it also
means you have to be let's say
self-reflex appear because a lot of this
involves let's see claims about the
cultural turn does things better yeah
but then of course you always have to
ask yourself okay but better compared to
what right there's often a kind of
simplification of disciplinary histories
because that we say let's say within
urban geography it's a Well we need to
cultural turn because we need more
qualitative matters before all these old
guys just did quantitative methods yeah
it's just the data crunching this is not
what we need we need to do new matters
and there's like yeah if you look
superficially at that history that might
be the case but if you look more closely
you will see all kinds of different
strands in let's say the 100 or more
than 100 Years of urban studies research
that actually come very close to some of
the claims here made here yeah so that's
the ethnographic research for example
took place before but it's the same so
it really leads to a simplification of
often that's a disciplinary histories
and you need to be quite quite careful
the same arguments around let's say the
industrial and the post-industrial the
post-industrial is not completely new no
but it tends to actually foreground
different trends that might have existed
at a previous phase also but in a last
not in a sense of dominance so this is
important to keep in mind
yes
I don't hear anything sorry
what's your question
I'm afraid because I don't see it
I can have a go on this one but
only I don't have the problem with not
speaking loud enough but I'll see let me
see
yeah the building is awful is
building works also yeah
see I don't hear anything what you're
saying
check
if you're going to dream this morning
last year has all worked quite well but
everything slowly everything is falling
apart give it one year
because there's also not much I can
actually do here
it's all on that but you won't hear me
will you
yeah
and it's awesome I'm afraid this is not
working
thank you
no sorry I could do about it all right
I'll try to speak a bit louder and a bit
slower but there's nothing I can do
about the building usually buildings are
installing five yeah I mean what the
hell anyways
um
so these are some of the main shifts
that you should understand as being part
of let's say the cultural term the
cultural Turks yes just to give you some
quick examples of let's say uh offers
the foundational books that that might
act as a reference reference of let's
say exemplifying the cultural turn
this is getting better yeah so
exemplifying the cultural turn
yes
I'm wondering how people look on this at
panopto they don't understand anything
of this so anyways
um
Frederick Jameson coming from literary
cultural Theory who I will discuss in
some detail precisely because some of
his elements uh some of his arguments
are let's say really foundational thing
for much of urban studies in this
particular strand of research but you
see it also political science and
historical sociology stage formation
after the cultural turn uh really
looking at you could say meaning making
practices State imaginary some terms
that maybe now have become quiet
let's see natural really uh to to think
about what the state is but perhaps from
let's say an earlier institutional point
of view we're not so much the case yeah
so
and as you see many of these claims were
made or cultural and economy after the
cultural turn yeah
foreign
but it really doesn't help for the
Acoustics right
so looking at organizations much more
from a cultural perspective that is not
just about the organization and let's
say a functional manner but also about
again meeting making practices ways of
Behaving uh within organizations
um anthropology and history history
sociology Etc you could name many many
of these books but they all at that
point in time and it was all around late
1980s throughout the 1990s that these
kinds of claims were made most
forcefully in in academic literature
now to Frederick Jameson every year wait
it sounds a bit harsh but every year I
have to check online if he's not that
yet because he was born in 1934-4 but I
don't think he's that active anymore but
he would think he was pretty active
until five to ten years ago which in
itself uh is quite achievement he has
published an enormous amount of books
and articles
uh is a professor or Emeritus professor
of comparative literature at Duke
University and has become I'll put I
just put some passwords here has become
very famous for Marxist literary
cultural theory for debates obviously on
around modernity and post-modernity and
also for the relation to culture and
political economy so if these buzzwords
should already give a bit of an
explanation let's ask them how he
interprets culture because he has a
strong you see Marxist but in a very
let's see open manner but especially
this is important so he always looks at
the relation of culture to political
economy which is basically a code word
for capitalism yeah so this is I would
say I would say his main concern in his
writings at least on on culture and
postmodernism
now there's a phrase that has become
well this is also his article originally
published in 1984.
which he died which he titled
post-modernism as the cultural logic of
late capitalism yeah so this is really
let's say a phrase that has become very
famous also you see it referred to
um on a regular basis now there are a
number of elements I don't know who has
wrapped to the article I'm not going to
ask I'm not even going to ask who has
actually managed to finish the article
because it's not a simple article I am
very well aware of this
um it is worth it I mean have a drink
sit down late evening and you'll maybe
understand it better uh
who knows
um but it really is uh I'm I'm trying to
give you also let's say some
foundational original literatures not
just about secondary literature artists
writing about other artists but this is
the is a is an article related to book
that is let's say it's referenced all
the time so it really helps to go back
to the original uh to get a sense of
what is arguing now I picked to do your
homework I picked some as a key quotes
from from this article which in a way
give a good summary of what this claim
is about and which shaped I think some
of the urban research later on
first he says of course modernism is not
a style but it acts or it is a cultural
dominant yeah
so it's not just a lifestyle question no
it's actually something that has become
dominant in our contemporary culture
second
and directly related aesthetic
production today and this is of course
where let's see it's Marxist on as the
political economy sympathies show a
static production today has become
integrated into commodity production uh
generally yeah so it's really difficult
he argues to distinguish aesthetic
production and production of the Arts
symbolic entities from Commodities yeah
so it basically becomes one two sides of
the same coin that's basically what
she's arguing yeah I think if you start
thinking empirically it's quite easy to
come up with concrete example of
anything oh yeah that makes a lot of
sense yeah a work of art let's see a
painting is at the same time let's say
aesthetic production yeah it's about
symbolic and meaning making practices
yes about interpretation but it's also
sells on the Art Market yeah and it's
not to do with speculation so it's both
you know
that historic elements
I'll skip this because it's interesting
but there's a very let's say 1980
sentiment where sort of globalization
and Americanization was very much seen
as one of the same thing or
globalization was seen as you could see
an extension uh of an earlier history of
Americanization yeah
and then he talks about it this again
becomes very important I said well
basically he looks at postmodernism as
the third stage of capital capitalism uh
referring to Alice Mandel was a market
scholar actually at this University many
many years ago
um which would then be a uses different
terminologies for it he refers to
post-industrial capitalism because the
base capitalism to multinational
capitalism or to Consumer capitalism
yeah so you could argue this all here is
the politically political economy policy
political economy side of postmodernism
yeah so post-modernism accompanies this
phase of capitalism yeah that also means
according to to Jameson it only makes
sense to talk about postmodernism from
let's say the mid 1970s onwards there is
no such thing in this way of reasoning
as post-modernism in the 1920s just
doesn't make any sense yeah because it's
so much tied to a particular face or
particular stage of capitalism
one reason why this article has become
quite famous and it's a bit more
difficult to understand now I think is
because he does quite an extensive re uh
reading and interpretation of one
particular hotel which is the
bonaventura hotel
um in Los Angeles
so uh designed by John Portman built in
the mid-1970s and one of the largest
hotels in La and to my knowledge uh it's
it still is
so just some pictures
this this hotel for him it's a bit hard
to imagine now but it's if you look
represents you could say the culmination
of post-modernism as the late logic as
the elastic logic of of late capitalism
so what does he argue here you will see
that some of these elephants return in
later debates without reference to the
hotel or the specificity of his his
argument it aspires to be a total space
a complete world and an attempt to not
be a part of the city yeah so it tends
to be a world on its own yeah
to not be a part of the sea so it has a
reflective glass skin which repels the
city
outside and achieves The Peculiar and
placeless dissociation of the
bonaventura from its neighborhood yeah
just keep this in mind somebody's else
because they will return later yeah but
it is separate from the city so it's
quite a quite easy to imagine later and
I'll give some examples also if you
think of let's say gated community style
things right things that are let's say
within the city but cities are highly
unequal so you have different elements
let's say separate even though they're
formally speaking part of the sea this
is what he's arguing at that this is
what we see in the Bonaventure Hotel and
then this becomes a bit more difficult
to imagine now because it really is I
think an experience of that time I think
we're now so used to these kinds of
architectures and these kinds of
buildings but here according to him this
becomes impossible to navigate they have
postmodern hyperspace I'll skip that is
impossible to navigate yeah it's just
too confusing in any way you can no
longer situate yourself as a subject
within this world but you're just very a
very fragmented human being that was a
kind of let's say a typical let's say
literary Trope of 1980s post-modernism I
think this has probably become us
Central to the debate most likely
because we have so we have become so
used to behaving like this in the world
again I want to discuss these in detail
I'll skip the first this one might be
important to remember here because again
this shows up and later discussions
especially when we think about
discussions around cultural heritage
yeah his stories isn't a thesis history
a random cannibalization of all the
styles of the past and this idea that
especially post-modern architecture just
use different elements for different
eras and combined us into a new building
yeah so it didn't produce let's say
formally speaking something new but it
was more of Rico large a combination of
all kinds of existing let's say
architectural Styles yeah so a random
categorization of the cells of the past
the past as a reference finds itself
gradually bracketed leaving us nothing
with nothing but text yeah
so this is also again something that
pops up in later discussions uh on okay
what what do let's say
um
what what does let's say culture
actually produce and there's this idea
that the postmodern that it well we've
actually reached a post-modern phase but
there's no linear trajectory if there
ever was let's say between history and
future it's just a recycling of the past
yeah
okay
now that's Jameson
does that make a bit more sense than
when you read the text
yeah
okay
um
now I mentioned Jameson
um not because I like my old almost dead
white man but um but because he really
has been inspirational I think for many
let's say researchers that came after
from different different perspectives
also yeah the Los Angeles School of
urbanism is one of La cities
um let's see cluster or a cluster of
activity that came together from the mid
1980s onwards and we should also refer
to James in order to build on it in a
more you could say social scientific
Urban research type type of manner
what does the Los Angeles School of
urbanism argue and I'll deconstruct this
idea that it is a career in school but
that is sad to argue
first of all following Jameson literally
following Jameson it looks at the
post-modern condition as a radically new
Urban condition yeah so this is what
they call post-modern urbanism yeah main
characteristics and again be aware of
let's say the simplification of
disciplinary histories because it does
it does have especially in this let's
say
foundational text or a text that try to
let's say really put let's say the LA
School of urbanism on the map through a
number of key Publications it did have a
tendency to then say okay but everything
that came before in a way it was
it's old hat we don't want that we need
something new so yeah very very strong
sense of simplification for some of the
main characteristics self self-defined
Beyond Chicago school what we see now is
not you could say eccentric City but no
it's about Urban fragmentation yeah
it understands LA and Southern
California as privileged cases so the
priority case for doing research but
also as a prototypical case in the sense
that they understood LA and Southern
California as the future of other cities
across the world yeah look at what we
see happening in LA and this region this
is what we will see happening in cities
across the world yeah so it's kind of
three figures let's see future Urban
developments yeah
it paid a lot of attention to
restructuring which was like say the
generic word focusing mostly on
post-forwardism flexible accumulation
the the Redevelopment of firms so I
won't go into this because I think
you're all aware by now of let's say
let's say uh yeah post fordism basically
yeah
um and there's a nice quote from Mike
Davis a writer analytical writer
uh belonging more or less to the same
scene in a way where we talked about the
LA School of urbanless saying well
they're basically politically economists
with their spacesuits on not quite sure
to fully understand what he means it but
it looks really it sounds really nice as
a as a quote
so it gives you a sense it's politically
economy but it's a bit off it's
something else right it's a bit
speculative
foreign
it's important again to be aware of
simplification of disciplinary histories
and it also applies to the LA school as
such yeah so it was all it was soon seen
as a coherent school but it was also
soon critiqued by others and even by
those within working within this domain
or that was let's say label as being
part of the LA School of urbanism saying
well actually there's not one single
claim being made by the LA School of
urbanism but actually there's more
diversity within this supposed school so
there is a diversity within coherence
perhaps so I would argue there are a
number of different lines of research
which in itself have older histories
longer histories but it really came
together at this point in time and I
think it still shapes to some extent uh
to quite a substantial extent here
current research that we are doing today
yeah so one important traps which has
become even the most
famous one is more
political economy economic geography I
guess really looks at postpartism
flexible accumulation industrial
organization Regional development so
really about the transformation of firms
how firms relate to each other how they
connect yeah and what this means for
regional development yeah
let's see the key artist there to
mention of perhaps Alan Scott Susan
Christopherson Michael stalker most of
you will have heard of these names at
least yeah
however there are also other lines of
work one thing I mean this problem is to
some extent most related to First a
political economy of place because if
you look at let's say Regional
development the transformation of
companies there's also an element there
okay what does this mean actually for
let's say local place conditions it has
to do with Place identity but it also
has to do with branding elements it has
to do with let's say local patriotism or
it has to do with local labor markets
Etc yeah
this that leads to distance strength I
mean they're all related obviously
someone like Jennifer wolf having worked
on homelessness unskilled work local
labor markets a classic argument in this
literature is that the transformation of
of the region as a result of let's say
the transformation of its political
economy leads to more polarized labor
markets so we have let's say simplified
put in a simplified sense we have let's
see high earners and we have let's say a
very let's see if if not unskilled and
then it gets very low paid and
precariously employed workers on the
bottom so it leads to a more polarized
labor market there's also you think that
has been picked up later by someone like
Sasuke assassin working on global cities
yeah so that's important and this wraps
less I mean less famous but but let's
emerge now I think more Force for the
last 10 years is work around
environmental justice yeah the
transformation of the region has also
had effects on the environment at large
the planning issues but also uh ecology
issues more narrowly put and this has
already received some attention there
yes
I'll give I'll give some examples I
think later on but basically it's about
Urban fragmentation if I would have to
put it in a bus word so this idea that I
mean especially me for those that
attended my lecture on the European sea
there's this idea that it's a compact
City it's a coherent city is
historically grown and amazing world of
actually
it's a post-modern city it's almost
inverse right it just it's like a
chessboard where whatever you could put
about rationality not a good example
because you know it's a very clear rules
there but when you just like a game
board where you could put wherever you
want and this is how then the city
develops yeah so and this is what and so
this relates to Urban fragmentation and
the other one sprawled I would say say
those would be two issues where they
argue okay this is actually
foreshadowing why the urban developments
and they're not completely wrong of
course I would simply I would just argue
that maybe La was not the first and in
parallel at least we saw we see many
other cities where this was also the
case especially uh in the global South
um but this is I mean that's only a
critique that has been raised towards
the LA school also because it's only
only at a later stage I think that it
started looking outside of North America
it was a strong American bias maybe
Western Europe and only later that it
started expanding and then of course
somebody's theories no longer hold or
somebody claims in any case yeah yeah
okay
so there's a lot of diversity if you
look at it at the same time it must be
said
cumulatively between the mid 1980s and
the mid and the late 1990s various key
Publications were published that put La
really on the map of urban studies yeah
so and this really really helps I think
to to retrospectively look at this as a
kind of coherent La School of urbanism
yeah that's ranging from a 1986 special
issue in society of space which is one
of the few journals specifically
dedicated to LA to books like the city
Los Angeles and urban theory in the mid
1990s or rethinking LA
or Studies by Alan J Scott on
technopolis there are many many of these
key books that really appear to the key
references in the field of urban studies
that are still let's say dealt with or
referred to uh today yeah
well for example Mike Mike Davis as I
said what an academic person but his
famous book city of quartz which again
is continuously referenced in many
different uh parts of the urban studies
world and uh and Beyond
this one is perhaps already a partial
answer to your question because this
shows a bit in extreme I would say how
some of these artists looked at at city
development I mean I'm saying in extreme
because this is really an article that
tries to codify some of the claims that
were made in a more subtle manner than
many other orders
um
and by doing said he also radicalized
some of these claims not necessarily in
a in a helpful manner I think but it
helps to keep in mind
so they said they argue that the spatial
manifestation so uh the honest dear and
flusty so I forgot their names
they argue that the spatial
manifestation of post-modern urbanism
was a kind of key no capitalism Yeah so
basically it's apparently a board game I
wasn't aware of that but basically a
very fragmented form of an urban
structure in which the quote
urbanization is occurring on a
quasi-random field of opportunities Yeah
so basically there's no longer this idea
that you have a city center and then it
emerges outwards or there are particular
structures related to planning Etc no it
just it's pretty random yeah
and this is also all of course also the
end of theory because if you make this
kind of claim that does not really much
you can you can do anymore so it's also
highly let's say simplified so I would
certainly not encourage you to
understand this as the core business of
the LA School of urbanism this is almost
more a parody of the of this debate
nevertheless some of the lesser the
items literally speaking they put on the
map of Keto capitalism
still resonate with us today because for
example we have here at no verb which
you could say there's a lot of which is
still going on on let's say ethnic
communities the relation between ethnic
groups and let's say localities within
cities neighborhoods we have Team marks
parks sorry it's a lot of
commodification of public space we have
created communities with obviously plays
well we have Street Warfare So that
obviously there's violence in the city
which is a classic team in urban
research spectacle again which relates
to let's be commodification of space
command and Patrol centers which is
let's say the classic team Awards like
Sasuke assassin this idea that Global
cities are with where the action happens
when it comes to post-political and
economic rule so all these different
elements do
uh well we're identified by them and
have played an important role in later
research on this city
yeah I give some examples already here I
don't need to go through this again
so much my summary uh of the LA School
of earliest I already hint that the fact
that
this was not without its critique and
some of this critique was quite
legitimate because one of let's say my
hobby was is to really warn against the
simplification of disciplinary histories
there's a lot of academic laziness
involved you want to make a claim that
you do something relevant and
interesting and by doing that you say
about that what came before was actually
not that interesting but you actually
simplify that history yeah so if you're
intellectually I think very honest you
have to be very careful with these kinds
of strategies you have to be much more
or less honest and open and respectful
also of what came before and maybe
moderate your own claims to towards new
illness this is not what the LA school
did or let's say let's see some artists
within this field
so critics were also abundant and all
very early on raised let's say made
let's say problems had the issues they
had with let's say the claims of noon is
put forward by other school Earnest one
being what's really new here yeah
you might claim that this is work done
that hasn't received enough attention
but actually there's already a lot of
existing work on diversity restructuring
consumption and commodification or in
urban poverty yeah especially Urban
poverty has been foundational to riding
on the urban since the mid-19th century
yeah so there's actually an
industrialization basically so what's
really new here
that's the first legitimate criticism
second one it is
the LA school it really sort of reduced
The Chicago School
do a kind of Burgess concentric zone
model the idea that everything that was
written in the 1930s which is post-hoc
sometimes labeled as The Chicago School
was about the concentric zone model this
idea that as a central central air
business district and had people move
outwards depending on let's say history
and and capital also yeah there's much
more internal of our or there was much
more internal variety within the Chicago
school so it does not justify this kind
of simplification yeah so many things
the TLA school is now doing actually was
already happening in The Chicago School
so let's say the American claim there's
of course also a struggle you could say
within us American Academia saying well
we've had Chicago now we move to LA this
is where the action is happening and
then many other Arts were saying well
maybe not quite yeah so that's important
to keep in mind
a third one this perhaps for me the
most the most interesting or the most
relevant critique is there is truly I
think a kind of ethnographic void in a
lot of literature and post-modern
urbanism what do I mean by this it
really relies on a kind of deep text
reading of the city this is the most
let's see extreme example
this is how we see the city I mean if
there is anything more top-down than
this I mean it's hard to imagine right
it really is like okay let's hear this
is how we see the city but it has no way
at no stage do you see any engagement
well with what people on the ground
actually think about the city they live
in or work in yeah so it's a very sort
of top-down Matrix oriented reading of
the city so which is labeled as an
ethnographic void which I think is the
most forceful to your team yeah it has a
marginalized agency and interpretation
of Ordinary People yeah and there's no
so there's also no post-modernism From
Below you could you could imagine a kind
of let's say fragmented urbanism and
then brick collage a combination of
elements by people making making do
making a living in a city and combining
different elements but none of that is
part of this discussion okay so it's a
Much More Much Too dubbed down too too
detached reading
last critique and they said it relates a
bit to this idea that La pre-figures
wider Urban developments they're saying
well la is actually not that radically
different on two levels uh first within
La existing Urban theories before the LA
School of urbanism are still relevant to
explain what happens in la la is not a
complete free let's say board with
quasi-random uh let's say activities
taking place no you can use all the
theories around let's say agglomeration
for example in order to understand LA or
in this wider region so that's one thing
the other side is that the empirical
phenomena we see in LA are also visible
elsewhere and not just as a prefiguring
not something that comes after the other
school urbanists talked about La no but
actually something that was already
before maybe some cities were even
earlier and the other thing is also to
some extent where especially research is
working in the global Styles uh really
connected to right say okay there's much
happening elsewhere which is perhaps
more interesting also and certainly
shows let's say that La is not that
special after all
okay
wow went fast yeah
get off the screen
questions
well I mean I would
I would situate that a bit I would say
certain strands within geography this
was at least what what you're saying but
if you look at much of this literature
especially worked by people like Alexis
and Christopherson they're all working
in a kind of realist vein right in the
sense of it's pretty straightforward
Empirical research right there's a world
out there we're going to study it some
of the examples you mentioned might have
happened but I would say that was more
or less a visible or more Central to the
debate in literary studies it may be
cultural studies to some extent and less
so in geography
so um I don't think it was necessarily A
in when it came to the LA School of
urban is the necessary much reflection
actually on the epistemological the
methodological Dimension and it was more
an observation of new empirical facts on
the ground which necessitated new
theories according to them so I think
it's more on that level but obviously I
mean as I said at the very end there is
no such thing as one cultural turn and
also no such thing as one force
modernism so I think that's uh and if
you look at the way a term such as the
postmodern has been um let's say discuss
within different disciplines you see
quite radical differences between what
is actually understood by the postmodern
in the first place and there are
interesting books written on this also
but yeah that yeah
okay other questions on these first
three was it two more substantial parts
nope
um how are we doing time wise yeah let's
give it a few more minutes and then
we'll see
um am I talking too fast or is it
okay-ish I think the fact that I have to
speak very loud automatically slows me
down right so that helps in a way so I
might just start screaming in my
lectures and then I'll I'll slow down my
Tempo yeah
foreign
so we've got cultural term we've got
postmodern let's say jamesonian
approaches a sort of Vision on the
postmodern
this indirectly or directly influence a
lot of La school urbanism work yeah I
think it was not just Jameson but there
are many many that see similarities
there and there's a related strand which
now I want to discuss with you which I
would call as the urban Landscapes and
symbolic economy mostly because this is
the terminology that was
that I mean the different strands of
research but there's a lot of research
around these this kind of teams which
supposedly refer to actual facts on the
ground so don't see it as something
completely different from let's say the
other school of urban is more let's say
developing in parallel perhaps also a
different inspiration it's coming a bit
more I would argue from black City
Cultural studies tradition which also
emerged in the 1980s yeah but obviously
their interactions also so just uh to
know as a clear cut categories here
if you look at what I now describe as
let's say one body of literature because
for me it makes sense to describe this
as a relatively coherent body of
literature there are a number of key
guiding assumptions arguments shaping
this kind of literature one very similar
to Jameson flexible accumulation
post-forwardism and post-modernism are
two sides of the same coin so this is
your Marx's argument right so there's a
political economy and the culture as you
can see that let's see the other side of
this political economy but it's it's
it's it's impossible to extract it just
belongs very closely together
and Innovation perhaps that this
literature introduced is it's according
to the much of this literature says well
we see the rise of postmodernism also
hanging together with the rise of a new
middle class yeah and this very much
hangs together again with just a rise of
post-fortism post-industrialism because
it Latin new you could say work
opportunities new fields of work new
labor markets which demand that you
could say uh a uh a a a type of worker a
type of population that was overall
Highly Educated that was knowledge
oriented yeah so this is the kind of
debate around higher education
knowledge-based capitalism and this was
very much seen as it's higher educated
and this is what they should understood
to be the rise of a new middle class
yeah it's not your classic middle class
which perhaps massive more fixed but and
this is the introduction that was done
here say okay this rise of the numeral
class
is accompanied by a device or an
interest and new you could say aesthetic
sensibility sensitivities interests
preferences yeah this idea that there's
a new kind of Aesthetics emerging with
this new group of people yeah which they
labeled and commodity Aesthetics in a
way that because was highly driven or
widely related to let's say lifestyle
preferences yeah
I'm interested come up with a good
example I'm interested I work for let's
say a
not I can't come up with a good example
I try to come up with a better example
here
I'll give examples in a minute yes it
doesn't really matter
um
[Music]
no because the kinds of examples I was
thinking about are mostly around let's
say Urban Street culture for example
which is very much related to particular
let's say the lifestyles that really
lead to let's say how you identify with
particular Lifestyles and these
lifestyles are closely connected to the
buying and showing of particular
Commodities yeah shoes clothes
artworks that you affiliate that you
associate with if you're a bit higher up
Etc
so let's say the second part third one
is that culture was key or is key to
Urban Redevelopment this has remained I
think very influential I'm doing work on
this still but there's also his work
that was already let's say put forward
and started being done in the late 1980s
work being done on real estate on
artists on on representations of urban
space yeah if you think now of work
being done on the impact of of
gentrification yeah on on City spaces
how artists play a role in both let's
say boosting gentrification but also
being kicked out of gentrifying areas
That's a classic argument which Harris
you can already made in the early you
know in the mid 1980s so not much has
changed you could say in that in that
respect
and the fourth role I think this is
something that was relatively new
perhaps also picked up more on the
European side of the discussion and
which was not really at all really
picked up by the by the alley School of
urbanism is an important role of the
state yeah staying investing in cultural
landmarks but also really developing all
kinds of cultural economic policies yeah
so this is what more or less it would
have to give let's say a nutshell
definition or a listing of key elements
what the symbolic economy literature is
more or less about
few examples
one interesting article that Paul Knox
the rest of those Urban landscape early
1990s where we argued very much along
jamesonian lines there's widespread
agreements that the emergence of
post-modern architecture culture and
philosophy in Western Society has
proceeded in tandling with the emergence
of globalized more flexible forms of
capitalist Enterprise
or second part of that quote
post-modernism as the cultural closing
of advanced capitalism you know so this
is basically Jameson all over again this
idea two sides of the same goal I
register a question here because I mean
I would question if there was really
that kind of widespread agreement yes
there was widespread agreement on this
claim within Marx's political economy
and yes marxian political economy became
let's say especially within geography
that's a pretty not dominant But Central
to the debate I would say in the 1980s
and 1990s or especially in the early
1990s and this is part of that kind of
explanatory logic yeah I personally I
mean I mean see much to agree with and
these kinds of claims but I don't think
actually that that let's say cultural
expressions are always that easily the
other side of the same coin of the of
let's say the capitalist political
economy yeah so if there's more
complexity there that is easily let's
say simplified
um so this is important to keep in mind
unless of course you fully agree with
this argument which is which is possible
foreign
so the point about the rise of a new
Miller Glass again in the same article
knocks offers a quite a useful summary I
find
yeah it makes a couple of claims which
is not specific to Knox but I think
specific or or representative let's say
this wider literature
first he says well and this is the shift
to post industrialism the emergence of
new class fractions under Advanced
capitalism yeah so we see dominant
classes but actually they change over
time but so the structurally speaking
let's say this hierarchy remains but
different class fractions might emerge
to become dominant this is what not
under Advanced capitalism you see the
emergence of new class fractions or the
new middle class under Advanced
capitalism
that's the economic arguments the
cultural argument would be this was also
a generational reaction against
modernist Aesthetics
let's see the children growing up in the
1960s rebelled against their modernist
parents and thus started proporting
different ways of Behaving different
ways of cultural preferences yeah
it's not wrong it's highly simplified
but it's not it's not wrong of course so
that's you could say the socio-cultural
uh
related to this this related to that
let's say this move away this critique
of of modernism you really referred more
to the kind of lifestyle orientation but
you can look at positively art becomes
part of everyday life yeah this is
something that does not use something
that is separate from us no it becomes
even more radical but you can also look
at it more critically or it just becomes
another commodity it's just a question
of lifestyle of showing your identity
showing off your identity yeah so
there's a lifestyle orientation
self-realization expression and I need
free responsibility cultural politics
true sort of culture you position
yourself as a citizen in many ways
for Local Economic explanation as
already into that is this kind of
commodity Aesthetics a kind of Niche
oriented consumption with emphasis on
tastes and Aesthetics and hence an
increased role for design also someone
like Paul Knox and later work he
specifically focus on Urban Design or
design the design sector as a central
sector in advanced capitalism yeah and
we can also we can all understand how
this works I mean I think we're all
parts in a way of this group right so I
wear disclosing but not that close even
though it's exactly the same as just a
slightly different color right I wear
these shoes but not these shoes or I
want wooden floors or not these kinds of
floors in my house depending on which
phased in your life your life you are
right it's pretty Niche but still we
have very strong opinions about this
yeah don't start talking to me about
music I have very strong opinions about
music but if I look at it for more
distance uh obviously I have to admit
that it's pretty Niche yeah so now I
sort of
um
let's see I uh let's say establish
distinctions between what is good bad or
better or or not as good yeah it's
pretty specific yeah so I think this is
important this is really about this
Niche oriented consumption that has
increased I think rapidly over the last
30 years I think this is not something
that we saw to such an extent
if you would go to the 1980s for example
in the early 1980s
cultured Urban Redevelopment so another
strand I would say that is really part
of this kind of debate
um even earlier indeed I forgot that
it's this early
one of the earliest probably the first
book actually by Sharon zukin it's
called love living
I guess most of you would also know
Sharon zukin who has done a lot of work
in culture in the city
and law of living was already published
in 1982. I think she was early for her
time so it's not uh you could say not
that typical but it was really a
foundational book I think and it really
shapes still many of the debates that
we're having today around the role of
artists in particular in urban settings
yeah
so around love living which was New York
oriented and there were lofts in New
York but there are lofts in New York
which of course does not apply to every
city but structurally speaking you can
see similar processes at least in larger
cities I would say
what did she argue okay we have let's
say abandoned moths anti-locks and we
see a reoccupancy of abandoned
structures by artists so early 1980s
we're talking about here also New York
at the height you could say of its
crisis and let's say at the deep end of
this development yeah but there's the
first thing a reoccupancy of abandoned
structures by ours this is Then followed
by a new middle class yeah so the
artists move in first it's still
roughing Rowdy but then the new Miller
class it moves in and it gets a bit more
a bit more let's see clean a bit more
fancy which she calls a reconquest of
the inner city
leading to a kind of Loft lifestyle they
have people living in
let's see dwellings that do not
represent your classical at certainly at
that point in time Suburban let's say
one Family household so you have to come
up with a new architectural style a new
way of imagining how to live in these
laws yeah
his size and also become an increasing
terrain of conflict between competing
users both between Alton advances if the
inhabitants if they were still there
artists and a new middle class yeah
where artists use Lofts also as a
production infrastructure to produce art
the new middle class by and large used
these laws as residential infrastructure
yeah and you work somewhere else yeah
and then culture is also in a very early
on especially even from the early 1980s
owners in New York was used to develop
and profit from him from an emergent
real estate market so real estate
intermediaries very early on realize
that ah these artists moving in suddenly
this area becomes interesting becomes
visible at the very least and thus we
can actually use this we can exploit
this this is something we can build on
yeah we can start identifying this we
can start selling this for a profit yeah
now this was early 1980s I mean if and
if I tell you this story it's pretty
clear I would think being you all being
Urban Scholars that this Rings this
resonates let's put it at those terms
resonates with discussions you see on an
everyday level and most of the cities
that you're familiar with yeah this idea
that ah that us identifying areas this
is like a Proto a proto-definition of
gentrification or cultural
gentrification yeah so when I think if I
think of an area such as I know in
Russell such as sanjul to some extent
this logic is followed yeah and I mean
I'm not familiar with too many cities
but I see similar things happening in
Berlin or so and you still see it
happening and saw it happening and then
many other cities where this is the case
for this has been a major strand of
research for quite a long time already
and it has been refined Etc but it still
shapes shapes the discussion
so ultimately of course there's also and
again this has also received research
attention but also means that artists
have become both drivers and victims of
Urban Development yeah it is a similar
article from that time ourselves
which shows our artists were well really
the earlier let's say the the movers to
move into a certain area and to start
developing the area true Building
Development to a lot of development or
other types of uh Building Development
but then when the the the area the
neighborhood had reached a certain stage
of development and real estate prices
odds then again we're in a sense moved
out because they couldn't no longer
afford uh to live there except those
perhaps that were smart enough to buy at
an early stage but this was rarely uh
the case but then they had so they were
both drivers and victims of urban change
and this again hasn't changed that much
over the last 30 years except that
perhaps this phenomenon has globalized
and it has become a much more strategic
uh government uh well much more let's
say forceful government strategy so this
is in a way mainstream Urban Development
by now
okay looking at the time let's take a
quick break uh and then I'll continue
with the second part or let's see the
the last third of the lecture
thank you
episode
foreign
[Music]
is
sues
a few things
foreign
yes
um
foreign
thank you
again
you know
thank you
very much
information
because
there is
relationships
um
tonight
thank you
very much
foreign
[Music]
thank you
yes
eternity
foreign
[Music]
all right let's continue
that's my first announcements
foreign
everything
yeah okay let's go
um so we're still in the symbolic
economy part
um and I'm discussing different strands
or what I mean this is lesson identified
by me so what I consider to be a
relatively clear and body of leadership
within this body of literature there are
a number of different strands of let's
say research attention yeah so before
and I just finished the part on let's
say cultural Redevelopment
now in last part within that section I
would argue really focuses on
representation of urban space now please
understand every strength that I discuss
I can only do so much in a two-hour
lecture minus the breaks But please
understand every strand as potential
let's say lives of Investigation for
yourself for a paper for your
Massachusetts whatever right just I'm
trying to let's say hopefully give some
inspiration as to what possible teams
possible topics are that you might want
to engage with in more detail so this
isn't also for me a bit I want to see us
as my role in in especially for those
here in their first semester of their
first year Masters what I see as my role
just giving a few let's say 400 few
ideas about what could potentially be
interesting to do more research about
yeah so one element here is
representation of urban space this is
probably a relatively straightforward
exercise where a lot of attention
recently and especially also outside of
urban studies in marketing it's
cruciatingly boring but still that's not
a discussion but we should investigated
the role of media and marketing in
putting cities on the map yeah yeah I
mean I should say Nuance there's a lot
of boring research being done in this
field there's also some interesting
research being done in this field but
some of this very very instrumental yeah
so there's this research that focuses on
Urban images what kind of images do we
have in mind when we think about cities
how we can really sort of change these
images also contested images yeah and we
all will have let's say City images in
our mind when you're not going to do the
quiz now whatever would ask you to sort
of I wouldn't mention the city I would
ask you to to to mention the image the
first image that pops up in your ads
then it's quite clear there will be a
large element of consensus I think
within the audience yeah Paris Eiffel
Tower I mean something like that right
so the couple of uh cliches
this has become increasingly important
and debates also around Urban tourism
especially European cities have always
been key sites for tourism yeah so
there's The Grand Tour there's sort of
let's say the upper middle classes
Aristocrats between let's say European
Elites who have let's say traveled to
and around Europe two different European
cities but this has become let's say
massified over the last 60 70 years
early after World War II yeah and it
just really that's it to like to its own
development around Urban tourism
explicitly of course let's see the whole
discussion about America yeah Airbnb
would also fit in here yeah this has
increased they also been picked up where
you could say it was to some extent
firm driven that's the entrepreneur
driven this has increasingly been picked
up by most local and National States as
important development strategies for the
local
government
and the focus on tourism as an important
driver for your economy it's a highly
volatile economy of course and this is
something we now see with covert well in
a very clear sense suddenly everything
falls flat and therefore that's for
locally conscious rely heavily on
tourism that's obviously is is quite a
disaster
um if we're economically speaking of
course socially speaking that's another
discussion that is a nice book also
that's why I just mentioned it here I'm
not going to discuss it
but in any detail by mayor Greenback
in a new upside branding New York how a
Sydney in crisis was sold to the world
which traces a bit let's say The
Branding of New York from the 1980s
onwards our city at let's say at the
bottom ends uh being confronted without
migration actually tried to reinvent
itself through its images in order to
become let's say more attractive again
open question of course if The Branding
has played the most important role in
the city becoming more attractive but
certainly it has played a role in this
okay
last part in the role of the states uh
very briefly
um again this is debate that has been
picked up both in urban studies as well
as outside of urban studies from a
cultural perspective especially in
literature specifically on cultural
policies which is a dedicated field of
research on its own
um
which I would say you see a couple of
things we see strategies aimed at really
developing cultural Industries I have
myself done research on on this whole
debate around cultural Industries which
is very much about Local Economic
Development this idea that you actually
attract artists cultural workers to your
city in in order to sort of develop your
local economies much research attention
has gone into this since the 1990s but
especially 2000s yeah there's also
research around large-scale events World
fairs art exhibitions again this has a
much much longer history it transcends
also Urban studies as a discipline
because if you look at let's say a
discipline such as art history that has
done excellent work on let's say
Arts exhibitions and World fairs from
the mid-19th century onwards yeah so
yeah we're always let's say events to
attract a global or this European
audience to your city but again this has
become increasingly kind of economic
strategy so you want to attract the
Olympic Games you want to attract a
biannual or you want to have a
Etc yeah there's also been increasing
critiqued because often there's a lot of
investment going into this but what
actually is that's it it delivers then
it turns out to be quite Limited
and more broadly I think there's
literature again from the 1980s all the
word squash related to work by zukin on
the Arts and the urban growth machine as
it was called in the 1980s certainly
which really focuses on let's say Arts
networks Elite networks and arts
institute Arts institutions as local
attractors for invert investment and
Urban Development yeah so there's a
classic example if you look at
sorry the museum built in the gubernet
museum in Bilbao that's an always
mentioned case when it comes to uh you
place a museum in a relatively run down
City I'm simplifying here and this
should really boost the local economy
and to some extent it did again with
many issues attached to it but it's not
completely false yeah so there this is
work that has received a lot of
attention also
here one more recent example uh not sure
if the city needed you could say this uh
it was certainly not a round run-down
City in a sense does anyone know this
example
so it's the M plus Museum in Hong Kong
actually which actually was just open I
think two one or two weeks ago two weeks
ago designed by star Architects Herzog
in the Miron uh and a well a uh a
typical UKC example of a city that is
both
aimed at attracting and perhaps
improving you would say the cultural
image of Hong Kong but attracting uh
let's say tourism to the city but also
as a kind of
uh let's see
advertisement for the city and to some
extent in a very little sense because
the the main building side you say is
one big LCD screen at the same time next
to being a museum so you could actually
sort of literally see how this is a kind
of commodity aesthetic right so very
very literal manner
but also for example big commercial
artifacts such as the Art Basel who
develop let's say
um well which is now staging I'm not
quite sure what the current state is
because also covertly messed up a lot
but what it was is a stage annual art
fairs in Basel in Miami and in Hong Kong
um not only do these events attract
wealthy Visitors by and large yeah they
also spend there in these cities so
again it becomes a kind of local
development machine yeah more recently
Art Basel also started a so-called Art
Basel cities initiative where I try to
have events in different cities which in
this case Buenos Aires is one example
which supposedly should benefit the Art
Basel because it can globalize more but
also other cities across the world who
do not have the annual art fairs can
supposedly benefit from let's see the
name and reputation of the art barsing
and we see these kinds of initiatives
emerging quite forcefully over the last
especially over the last 10-15 years
okay
last section for today and I'm actually
doing quite well on time so um I also
won't discuss this uh unless not every
every bullet point on the slide
but just as a kind of wrapping wrapping
up
to reposition let's say my my debate
which was let's say mostly oriented
within urban geography but to reposition
it again within a broader debate on the
spatial term yeah so much of what I
discussed was launching a geographical
concern or geographical concerns but the
spatial turn more broadly frames that
kind of debate foreign
so just to wrap up in the late 20th
century urban geography was heavily
influenced by the cultural term this I
discussed yeah so I related the based on
post-modernism and globalization yeah
this has had to in effect let's say the
epistemological methodological effects
was that there was an increased interest
in ethnography everyday life imaginaries
representations or in short culture yeah
so this is really what I think has
shaped much of urban geography over the
last uh well 30 years
across the social science and this is
how I opened my lecture of today this uh
cultural turn intertwined with an
increased interest in spatial
configurations so let's say urban
geography is already into that became
more interested in cultural questions
the cultural disciplines which I would
say is cultural studies and and
anthropology
became more interested in spatial
questions yeah
so there were a number of reasons for
this one is and I addressed this in some
other lectures
one is a kind of really post 1989
obsession with globalization
on one level one superficial level
globalization is or is is the end of
spatial questions because everything is
global yeah but it actually intensified
this concern with spatial questions
because it soon became clear of course
that it was a process that actually had
spatial effects the other spatial
process there was a stretching of social
relations taking place which could be
and and needed to be understood in a
spatial manner yeah connecting a to B uh
as a spatial effect and it leads to
different let's say spatial
configuration
uh social sciences Humanities sorry yeah
in order to be able to fit everything on
an already too crowded slide I had to
sort of
across the social sciences and
Humanities yeah so the creating interest
in spatial crash and spatial questions
and this of course is where the
geography starts becoming let's say an
inspirational discipline for other
disciplines this is exactly what happens
in the 1990s especially
hence an increased interaction between
our job to Urban methropology and
cultural studies which are already
hinted at
um
I'm only going to go quickly through
this but uh the the slides are slightly
more detailed
um
because I added these slides because not
let's say
the elements I discussed in the previous
slides the previous one hour and 20
minutes or so
um cover I would say most of what is
relevant concern the culture in urban
geography over the last 30 40 years
which is already quite a challenge to
fit that into a two-hour lecture but it
really misses also some elements so I
mean I propose let's say quietly let's
say in a way a linear trajectory of how
previous discussions influence current
discussions and that had an effect on
this but in parallel of course there
were also discussions and I just want to
briefly hint at it because there's again
these are all of us that have become
more or less important but they can't
really necessarily Trace back to some of
the elements to let's say Friday Jameson
for example
so there are two
core teams perhaps that have also really
shaped
um
interdisciplinary Urban studies over the
last couple of years and that in a way
have emerged more more forcefully from
disciplines outside of geography but
it's definitely let's say informing
Urban studies at large which for me is a
very interdisciplinary discipline uh
up to this day two elements one
informality second everyday life
informality for those that have studied
ethnography and topology they will they
will become have been well will be quite
familiar with this term
um
is historically and I'll give some
examples there a religion has looked
specifically on coming from also
Economic Development perspectives or
developmentalists perspectives to some
extent focusing on labor markets
precarious work migration legality
political governance and conversations
I'll unpacked this in a minute
everyday life partially overlapping but
partially coming from uh whereas this
tends to become simplifying you from
from anthropology everyday life tends to
come
but I would say is cultural studies as a
discipline that emerged in the 1980s
focusing very much on agency community
community building resistance off on
local level of Lifestyle driven
consumption identity media and
representation yeah so and precisely
these terms those that read the
newspaper provides there's this
obsession with some of these terms as
that they want to critique and that
emerge I think most falsely from
cultural studies obviously the the
critics have never read cultural studies
but that's another discussion
uh let me see
now in formality I mentioning this here
because this has become a special last
10 years Urban studies I mean there's so
much research taking place now on on
informality and the urban uh but it's
important to keep in mind that this was
already a classic team within Urban
anthropology and development economics
especially from the early 1970s onwards
an article always references the one by
Keith Hart in formal income
opportunities in urban employment in
Ghana and the title itself already makes
pretty clear what uh well where he
stands and what the topic is right it is
really about local labor markets it's
about Local Economic Development yeah
but what did Keith Hart and many others
with him argue there is a lot of and I
think it's something that maybe julvin
Hammond is lecture for European cities
in an organizing World also picked up on
what is registered to be part of the
economy is only part of what is what
what we should consider as economic
activities yeah so we have formal
economic practices businesses that pay
taxes and that are registered as
businesses but there's a lot of
employment Beyond these forward economic
practices so beyond governments Beyond
firms Beyond factories Beyond
large-scale Commerce yeah so this is
where the distinction between informal
and formal comes from yeah
so this is important to keep in mind
this of course gets slippery because in
some literature
this and this comes together right then
you say well actually the informal is
illegitimate and the formal is the
legitimate but that is only partial or
partially true I mean we can have a
discussion about what's legitimate
unless for example say we'll we'll all
agree that someone taking care at all of
their children because the constitutes
work but we I think we also all agree
that this is not illegitimate
well far from it right so whereas drug
trafficking uh is probably informal
because it's not registered as such but
many would also consider it illegitimate
again we can have a discussion on this
if that makes sense that distinction
yeah
now this is how to constantly merged and
this is interesting because this is one
of the not few cars but one of the key
Concepts that have really traveled from
the global South to Global North yeah so
this is where work that emerged most
forcefully in research on the global
South yeah and this is terminology
that's really sort of it traveled
it doesn't happen too often you could
say
so I mean in terms such as post-modern
urbanism in a way is the opposite
example
apparently
I'll just check in just one sec
now in urban anthropology if you look at
informality
it leads to a lot of research on
opportunities but also precarious uh
precarities created by unregulated
economic activities so there's a strong
interest in gender Dimensions so people
women working on markets working at home
so this is really about let's say what
what the bread and butter of a lot of
urban anthropology
as well as transnational Dimensions
particularly this Dimension I think has
been picked up most most clearly in
let's say the more cultural work uh in
urban studies so for example many Street
vendors also being transnational
migrants hearing a picture of LA rambla
and Barcelona so illegal migrants doing
working on the in the city
and it raises questions of economic
survival most obviously but also
questions of of the governors of these
markets of of the political identity of
these actors or the cultural social
identity of these actors and with a
nervous studies is a particular this
strand of research which has really led
to a boom I think of research and
informal uh on informal urbanism yeah
I'll pick up some of these elements in
my lecture uh next week
now that's very brief I mean I could
have two three lectures for sure on
informality as a concept as a practice
and how it's picked up in different
strands of research just as a kind of
stepping stone please understand this as
a stepping stone to let's say the more
contemporary research that I will
discuss next week the second strand of
research which hasn't been much part of
let's see the poorest Modern urbanism
Trend the symbolic economy trance is the
literature on everyday life I myself
have been partially trained in cultural
studies and everyday life was a concept
that popped up that this was like
regularly used all the time from the
late 1980s 1990s onwards it was really
used as a key as a key uh well topic
what does the term basically entail in
most cases because ultimately it's also
not more than a buzzword there's a lot
of theory behind it yeah but ultimately
it entails a key concern with Lyft
experiences of people and the meanings
constructed by subjects in their own
world so classic cultural concerns if
you wish yeah
so most of this leisure in in in
cultural studies on everyday life tends
to also position people as active agents
rather than as passive consumers or
passive recipients of political power so
this automatically leads to this kind of
debate on strategies versus tactics and
so the resistance people can have on the
ground in relation to see the structures
they are confronted they are well they
are confronted with
um
I'll skip this part because there's also
another part in anthropology which also
addresses this
um
and this also makes I think the everyday
a truly transdisciplinary concept I mean
again there are not too many Concepts
that are truly transdisciplinary I try
to understand Urban studies as a
discipline that is much broader than
specific disciplinary debates because
it's just very boring to stick to one
discipline yeah but the everyday has
really emerged from the 1970s 1980s and
as a truly transdisciplinary concept so
again similar to the postmodern I think
a question that was raised at the back
there is no such thing as one postmodern
if you look at different disciplines the
way they understand the postmodern it's
quite substantially different and
sometimes even contradictory the same
applies to the everyday yeah but one
discipline or one other says about D
every day might not overlap to a great
degree with what another author writes
about you every day so you really have
to look at disciplinary specifics in
order to understand it nevertheless
there are it is it has emerged as a as a
term as a concept it really connects
cultural Theory with philosophy with
Marxist is an ethnography with
post-structuralism with sociology and
with Aesthetics yeah so the many
interesting let's see entry points also
for you so for a study specifically next
to an unavoidable
uh the everyday who sees the everyday as
a side of utopian possibility but also
colonized by the commodity form so
that's commodity Aesthetics once again
you'll I can only urge you I mean of
course I'm not really fair is great we
all like him Etc but there's also a lot
of interesting work that has been done
by other artists which is perhaps
at least as relevant let's put it in
those terms uh then then I'll really
forever so please no no no no no more
papers on the right to the city I've
read enough of those that's
for example Stuart Hall and Tony
Jefferson classic British cultural
studies uh some of you might be familiar
with this over their work our special
Stuart Hall I mean if not do read this
work because it's pretty well it's very
very good
we're really looked looked at let's say
subcultures every day as a symbolic
opposition to a dominant order
I'll just mention some keywords that top
up here but this is terminology I think
which has become
internalized and much of her thinking
about Urban cultures resistance style
social practices subcultures growth
codes Urban use identity yeah
terminology that was not
used for the first time by Stuart Hall
and others but they really theorized it
and they really did something new with
it yeah
one caveat of forces especially early
cultural studies work it was highly
blind to gender the gender Dynamics yeah
this was I mean the picture shows that
it was used subculture was very much
around male use subconscious yeah this
has partially been addressed by by
artists such as Angeline like Robbie uh
who's actually my my first PhD
supervisor and feminist cultural studies
but certainly let's say it kind of
um underlying Trend in the early
cultural studies tradition that it was
pretty blind to to gender issues or also
partially intersectional other
intersection issues
from quite a different angle but again
it made an amazing book if I didn't book
you could easily read it it's very well
written the practice of Everyday Life by
Michel de Certo
um
translation obviously I think the French
is uh maybe 10 years older already the
original
um more poetic but maybe focused on
tactics tactics versus strategies uh so
the idea being that strategies are top
down and people on the street they sort
of engage with this and develop tactics
in order to avoid
State strategies mostly government
strategies so tactics are situated
tactics as
as
resisting uh let's say broader
structures this again is very much
shaped I'm not saying that everything is
good about it because it's too
dichotomous but it's a very
influential book that has really shaped
much of the debate that form so next
week I'll talk a bit more about let's
say from the everyday to cultural work
and activism a bit more about DIY
urbanism where some of the DIY urbanism
literature for example implicitly or
explicitly refers to the type of stuff
that is adored it already in 1980s
okay
just to conclude
um
as I mentioned the cultural tournament
is to be understood as part of a wider
shift in analytical sensibilities in the
social sciences yeah
I mean at the very beginning I said okay
there's the empirical theoretical and
the methodological these are three takes
on how we are how at that point we
started looking differently at the world
yeah
so urban geography itself as one strand
of debate within this broader cultural
turn uh was and is I would argue heavily
influenced by a Marxist or at least
political economic interpretation of
post-modernism as the cultural
expression of late capitalism yeah
you can also phrase it differently
there's very little subtle Nuance
cultural readings of let's say symbolic
objects such as the Arts in urban
geography for that mostly you have to
move outside of geography because it
does not have this history of taking
subtly about let's say cultural
expressions yeah which doesn't mean it's
not good but it's limited in that
respect the work and symbol of economy
in a way Builds on this but it has
shifted the tension a bit more to
questions of representation uh to urban
lifestyles and cultural production yeah
so the post-modern urbanism school was
wasn't interested that much in artists
producing actual pieces of work actual
art that was most interested in
consumption yeah so the commodity a
study said yeah you buy something with
which you identify as a lifestyle
question
and this is the last part that I discuss
we see an increasing or we saw an
increasing more in a sort of meeting in
a halfway between urban geography
cultural studies and anthropology as
part of a broader spatial term so this
is the funniest thing the interesting
thing is that this cultural turn often
also until the spatial turn yeah it came
it must emerge together in many ways
last point that I discuss is the
research and informality in everyday
life and related concerns as enormously
contributed to a development of a truly
interdisciplinary transdisciplinary form
of cultural Urban studies I think these
are some of the some you see this
happening in in the social science in
the United States at large is that
certain Concepts just resonate with
research is coming from very different
traditions and they become let's say
bridging Concepts that bring together
very different ways of thinking very
different histories of writing and this
is where uh most of them well the most
exciting stuff happens I would argue
okay next week uh this is what I will
try to discuss
um so today my main claim is history
matters so the history of urban studies
that I just discussed shapes also
current research debates on Urban
cultures and the four strands I will try
to discuss with you next week uh
certainly so it is more but I do think
that this is a pretty exhaustive at the
same time are one on the Arts activism
and urban engagement
this wants to add the second one
specifically focusing on cultural
infrastructures and informal urbanism
probably a bit more on the cultural
infrastructure site in the informal side
a third one on Urban tourism and
consumption cultures
and a fourth one
which links most closely to the
methodological concerns perhaps it also
is empirical at the same time
focusing on sensory urbanism so
different kinds of let's say engaging
with the urban beyond the visual and and
text uh again there's only so much I can
do in the two hours that I have next
week but hopefully this gives you a
pretty good overview of what
um cultures of urban research and urban
cultures can be about okay I'll leave it
there and I'm very fast for today any
questions
no everyone happy to go home at quarter
to seven on a Monday evening then I will
see you next week if I don't see you
before