[Music]
um
okay welcome everybody to the third
session Urban social geography
this week's topic is polarization growth
in global cities uh now at just a few
housekeeping announcements I think in
the meantime everybody has seen
schedules regarding discussion seminars
I think there's still some minor issues
here and there trying to get that sorted
as soon as possible but make sure next
week there will be a discussion similar
for each and every one of you so please
attend and if you're there to present
um stick to the guidelines which just
try to stick in 10 minutes of
presentation because it will be a tight
exercise in any case
try to practice a little bit at home so
that you stay within those 10 minutes as
much as possible
um and then we'll have a nice discussion
also be advised that we start with
excursions this Friday and we start in
Brussels for those uh Urban and urban
studies who are joining the global City
Brussels Excursion and as a reminder we
meet at 10
at the North Station Brussels North
and we meet at plus Simon Bolivar which
is the main square at the site of the
World Trade Center looking towards the
canal so Simon Bolivar and you'll see if
you're early either me wearing a very
special hat uh perhaps and some roses
and then if you're later you'll see a
whole bunch of people so you can't
really miss us in any case we'll be down
the stairs and somewhere on the Square
there's a few benches there we will
probably end around five at latest in
European quarter
uh and yeah uh you can bring lunch uh
but you can also buy lunch somewhere
there will be time over uh at lunch time
to actually uh buy things wherever you
want okay so that's not necessary I have
no idea what whether it will be this the
police check the weather forecast and
just accordingly and as I've learned a
pencil works better than a pen it's kind
of weatherproof although I hope it's not
a tornado that it's going to hit
Brussels okay
um right
so last week we've been talking about
you could say uh how to understand the
role of cities in the global economy the
whole discussion about command and
control functions to what extent uh
Power in This Global Urban system
relates to either headquarters and the
more classic world cities definition or
rather it refers to you could say this
amalgamation or complex of advanced
producer Services
um who collectively produce control
capabilities over global production
networks Global Financial markets we
also discussed plenty of uh critiques
different forms of critique on those
paradigms
what we'll try to do today is turn The
Coin around and
kind of in the spirit of uh John
Friedman's work back to the 80s if you
will
is also try to reflect on what extent
the insertion in these Global Urban
systems these powerful roles in the
global economy also affects the internal
structure of City so it's kind of this
macro micro link
last week we went from oh my gosh the
economy is globalizing uh what does this
tell us about uh the changing role of
cities in that global economy now having
established that centrality in the
global economy now we wonder to an
extent there are effects or implications
of that insertion on the social
structure of cities okay so it's kind of
the the flip side of last week's talk
so just to get started a little bit some
maps
uh was there a question
yes
I understand yes it was a bit packed so
let's try to have a break somewhere at
the um yeah at six something or five
past six yeah sure no problem
um yeah so Maps uh I I will yes
Apartments
the live stream isn't working
okay
or rather not okay
it is recording
[Music]
yeah
as you can see there's a red button
there and I think
the audio is supposed to work
zero viewers okay that gives us a hint
um let's see
the wrong link okay let's see
um
yeah
all right let me just put this online
ah
um
[Music]
it looks awfully the same
doesn't it
[Music]
thank you
there's already one viewer
so that means it works three yeah I
think we're there
is it okay
yeah
all right then
okay let me just try to start again I
start with some Maps always nice as
Urban geographers here's a maps from
Australia that I will talk a little bit
more about in a second from the
opportunity Atlas in the US basically
shows you
um the median household income of
residents over a certain period so this
is Chicago the darker I mean the the
Bluer the Richer if you will the higher
the income and the more the US is read
it's it's lowering so kind of see is
very much kind of concentrated wealth in
the city center apparently of Chicago
and then you can say the peripheries and
this kind of other Rings uh of Chicago
with lower incomes and then going back
further from the from the center
Richter neighborhoods
um kind of the opposite picture here in
uh Detroit I'll show some examples from
the US because there's this great
material on that
um here we see a very large
concentration of say poverty or low
lower incomes in the city center or if
it's actually the city of Detroit which
interestingly ends at this kind of Road
here which is 80 mile roads which you
may know if you still know who Eminem is
he's been talking about this
um
I think he was born and raised somewhere
over there it acts as a kind of a city
limit uh you could say the inner city
neighborhood and also uh it's also kind
of a fiscal limit
um
uh at this at this point and we see that
actually it's it's a quite strong social
spatial divide between poorer
neighborhoods in the city center and
then richer suburbs you may know that
Detroit has gone into default a few
years ago so it's kind of uh a weird
situation because it it is a rich
agglomeration if you will but uh the
city itself which kind of ends at the
Eight Mile Road uh is quite poor so
there's a lot of people commuting into
the city that are quite rich but the
fiscal base of the city itself is kind
of it's kind of limited okay so quite a
a large rupture there in space
other examples are
Los Angeles a lot of inner city uh
poverty and very rich uh suburbs if you
will we all know Beverly Hills uh and
and those kind of
um areas
um this is Miami just another example
where we start contrasts at the
neighborhood level uh between say north
um Miami and South Miami and also quite
a start difference between
um let's say Miami Beach and the kind of
where the tourist areas are
and the continent if you will or what is
kind of interesting in the case of Miami
is that actually uh from a
climatological environmental perspective
it's actually quite safe to live onshore
and these are kind of the poorer
neighborhoods with kind of uh increased
strength of floods and those kind of
things we see some kind of a movement
back onshore also by richer people some
people call this climate related
gentrification we start seeing an
appreciation of real estate values on
Shore so it kind of shows that that
environmental impacts all so
kind of start impacting social spatial
divisions another example
um
of New Orleans as you may know
from more than a decade ago it was hit
by a a large hurricane and also had a
very differentiated effect in racialized
and ethnic terms a lot of people were
were hit were left without help a lot of
people residing in these poor
neighborhoods often also had a different
kind of ethnic background
um
so again quite a bit of Divisions there
um San Francisco
um
looks pretty well gentrified uh also
kind of very common sensical I mean you
look at at real estate prices in The
Wider San Francisco Bay area and it's
obviously also related to this kind of
happiness or Global city regeness
regionalism that is that is uh going on
there but just still a few pockets of of
urban property for instance uh Chinatown
there to the north perhaps also the
mission which is a kind of a another
neighborhood yes
always the classification numbers
because it seems to know that the
distribution like that we had income
levels isn't kind of doesn't typically
normalized for the specific uh if you
know anything about that uh no I think
it's uh if you look at the scale it's
the same everywhere right so uh so you
can compare across cities as well and
it's a good point it could mean that we
kind of lose some of the Nuance in
certain places
but what you gain is comparability
across across cities but I can say a bit
more about that in a second
New York uh a city that will be talking
more about uh very kind of Rich Lower
Manhattan if you go to the north I feel
a bit like a weatherman here I'm going
to the north it's uh
it's as we know
um a bit more cloudy no I mean it's a
it's a an area with with lower incomes
uh the Bronx an interesting areas also
here
um Brooklyn
which we'll be talking about a bit later
uh which kind of follows the income uh
characteristics of of Manhattan there's
kind of still Lower East and we have
like a Little Italy and those kind of
places who are still you could say uh
giving some shelter to people that are
not crazy Rich
um but you could say a lot of
concentrated 12 in the center then or
what kind of area with with the poorer
population and then you could say uh the
rich kind of suburbs Begin Again
now the point is not necessarily today
to talk about spatial structures uh
you'll talk way more uh about that with
uh with Nick
and she'll discuss segregation patterns
and those kind of things what I want to
focus on is mostly you could say the
reality of it's a division uh income
divisions class divisions in cities so
where do you do these uh examples come
from this is a I think you'll find at
the great website uh it's it's called
the opportunity Atlas
and what I've actually it intends to do
and it also connects to the work uh that
of Nick or that the things that Nick
will talk about it tries to trace you
could say neighborhood effects and the
idea is that the neighborhood that you
raise them
we'll have a substantial role in your
future life chances
and they're they basically uh but you
can read more about about it on this
webpage they basically tracked uh the
evolution of people with a kind of Life
development or careers of people uh
linking it back to their original
neighborhood so to the places they were
born in so they could say okay people
that were born in the Bronx
16 years later
what is the kind of chance they become
incarcerated
what is their income level
etc etc so it's kind of in a way
uh trying to measure some form of
spatial privilege
by having a result or being born in
certain neighborhoods that will have
actually an effect uh which is in some
way you could say reducible to the uh to
the amenities that you have to the
social context that you have but perhaps
there's also even more than that maybe
it's some kind of an isolated spatial
effect beyond that so that's kind of The
Wider context of uh this Atlas And I
think yeah it's I would have hoped that
we had this for Europe it's a great
resource and you can you can browse a
bit do that but what I just want to
focus on today is the fact or use as
exhibits are these
um uh these income maps to illustrate
that
polarization in terms of income is a
day-to-day reality in a lot of U.S
metropolises had we had the data and
Europe we would also find uh quite star
contracts perhaps a little bit less but
still uh it would also be there so what
we can discuss then today I think is to
what extent class divisions
are reproduced in and through space and
actually try to understand why such
divisions occur in cities in the first
place now that's a very big debate
obviously what we'll try to do is try to
link that
to the debate we had last week and try
to link to what extents Global and world
city functions add to
existing polarization because
we cannot reduce it to an effect of
having headquarters or something
but perhaps entering uh the discussion
through globalized urbanization we could
actually start unpacking some of these
things so class divisions are about
the fact that we see social spatial
structures on the basis of social
groupings of
uh income profession occupational
structure and those facts so looking
through income levels and occupation we
find a social especially diverse
structure
now I use class here in a very let's say
uh analytical naive way because if you
use class
in many cases authors would also refer
to some form of identity formation
linked to that
that's not what I do here
it's more of uh much more mundane
looking at income levels
to look at the changing structure of the
city there's big debates to what extent
there is still such thing as class
identity
has something to do with existence of
subcultures depolitization etc etc
that's not really the point here it
would be an interesting debate it's more
about can we see objective objectifiable
divisions there in in society based upon
income and occupation okay just to clear
that a little bit
all right
um
so polarization
um it has been on the agenda has been
one of the main uh source of impetus or
or starting point for the world and
Global cities debate and again going
back to John Friedman and sort of wolf
in 1982
it's it's what kind of initiated their
interests there so just allow me to
recite with its towers of Steel and
glass with sensible shopping malls The
Citadel is the city's most vulnerable
symbol it's smooth surfaces suggest a
sleek and personality of money power
its interior spaces are ample elegant
and plush
and a properly secluded space is the
transnational Elites have built their
residences and playgrounds
country clubs and Bridal paths and
private beaches the overcrowded ghettos
exist in the far Shadows of the Citadel
where it is further divided into racial
and ethnic enclaves
some areas are Shanty towns none are
well provided with public services
garbages that does not get collected
only the police in the squad cars are
visible in evidence in many places
ghetto residents are allowed outside
their zones only during working hours
their appearance in the Citadel after
dark creates a small panic so it's kind
of a very dystopian image
you could say it's exaggerated it's kind
of
um not exactly empowering it's also very
black white but it's there's something
with this opposition that they that they
try to work with there's some kind of uh
growing divide in cities that is going
to become a social problem and that's
also what you also read in the world
city hypothesis of John Friedman
um
it's at some point it will become
everybody's problem and probably
probably also the problem of the elite
now again this kind of description tries
to capture a particular reality last
week I think I mentioned uh Robert De
Niro and Taxi Driver
uh perhaps
um uh John Friedman thought more talking
about contemporary La uh which is kind
of marked by The Citadel form uh to your
left uh if you've ever been to La I mean
a lot of Elites or people that are
walking around here never touch ground
they hover around they never go on
ground floor but it's kind of probably
dropped by a taxi in one of the hotels
and then they go at the first floor
level uh or second floor level in the US
from one building to another so it's not
only kind of uh horizontally segregated
there's also some kind of vertical
segregation there so that's kind of this
flow of people is not mixed with
um with bosses by
um then a bit further just kind of two
three four hundred meters is Bull Street
La uh not to be confused with Wall
Street in New York and this is kind of
where a completely different kind of
neighborhoods start so as you remember
this map from La
um in general you could say a very poor
uh in the city uh neighborhood
but kind of imprinted but by a number of
hotels
uh which kind of breathe post-modern uh
feelings and sentiments uh but then very
close to that immediately you're kind of
struck with with rapid kind of decline
um some people would call this a zone of
transition and we'll be talking with
Nick about the burgers uh model of of
cities there's a kind of a place that is
in change it's kind of changing
functions uh it's also a place where a
lot of uh migrants arrive
there's a lot of informal economy etc
etc and there's also kind of an idea
even in contemporary La that these
places The Citadel if you will these
hotels are also places that should not
be frequented by people that have
nothing to do there and just yeah as I
walk by I I think it was at the doorstep
of some of a plaza of Bank of America
something that I that I I took it um
yeah Bank Tower at Fifth Street
and it's kind of regulating social space
there and yeah you can't really read it
now but maybe you should read it at home
there's kind of very ambiguous language
being used so any activities that are uh
how's it phrase again that makes
annoyance or Muses that are
already annoying people or could annoy
people are actually not allowed there so
it's a very you could say uh ambiguous
fake description which gives for
instance social security guards the
Liberty to actually yeah remove people
from public space people that are
homeless and there's a there's a huge
homelessness
issue in L.A people are being displaced
even if they put offense in in downtown
uh there's a lot of panhandling selling
stuff and those kind of things and that
is kind of policed away so it's not it's
to be removed from from that public
space is because it doesn't fit the kind
of perhaps expectations of people that
that frequent these um
more like Citadel structures okay so we
could say it's still uh it could be an
extreme example but still very much
relevant today 30 or 40 years after uh
John Friedman was I was talking about
and this this is let's say one of the
the leading metropolis and economic
terms uh of the world
um so if it's happening here we could
imagine it's also happening elsewhere
okay
now what I would try to do now is look a
little bit into
exhibits about this archetypical case if
you will New York City
um
to show you a bit more how polarization
patterns have evolved over uh the past
decades
and I mean it's a Greek drama you know
already what is happening and the the
answer is polarization has increased so
income this disparities between
different kind of income groups in
society has increased and why New York
well I mean it's wonderful to say it's
has been one of the of the city's world
cities that have has received a lot of
attention uh it's still one of the main
uh Financial Centers of the world uh
it's kind of an extreme case if you will
if you try to research the impact of of
uh these kind of activities on the urban
fabric so
um I'm referring here to a very nice uh
study by the fiscal policy Institute
it's a bit dated
um but I still love it
um I'm actually hoping that it will do
the exercise again quite soon the
previous one uh report was just before
the crisis this one is kind of
diagnosing what went on just after the
crisis and I hope they have some kind of
I don't know uh mid-covets kind of
reports sometime soon but I mostly look
in these studies at the evolution of
income distribution and they use all
kind of weird terms such as desiles
quintiles quartiles which refers to the
place of an income group in the entire
population so a quintile is actually a
fifth of the entire distribution so top
quintile would be the top uh 20 of
earners and their average income the
bottom quintile would be
um the average of of the lowest 20 of
incomes right so these are relative
terms that show the position
with a certain income
what you would they position you would
take in this distribution okay and it's
usually focusing on income uh which is
income out of Labor
um in one way or another okay so this is
just one
um comparison and what they also do is
and they try to compare New York City
quite often uh sometimes they don't have
data on on New York City itself and then
they use New York state but try to be as
specific as possible
um and then they also try to compare to
the United States that's a question
yeah
uh I think I mean large really
polarization but the point is indeed and
that's kind of something that we get to
later
is that uh the question is if you
obviously more most easily start looking
at income because this kind of data are
easiest to find the next question is
what's the underlying occupational
structure so what produces that reality
uh and that's something that will pick
up uh on later and it's obviously
connected uh quite often kind of if you
think about the shift towards high-end
service jobs
would generate higher incomes
um
but the connection is not always there
is always highly contextual the same
kind of
um
occupations in different contexts may
give a very different income level and
that can be for a lot of reasons
so yeah but here we're talking about
income polarization uh to be sure
because it's it's it's the most obvious
Here and Now
so yeah as I said they try to compare
um city of New York but sometimes they
use New York State Etc so what you see
is here the median family income so this
kind of
people that are just in the middle of
this distribution this has been
declining over the past I think
um
uh 10 I mean in this case it's kind of
three to four years uh after uh the
creative session right so you see that
2008 2009 2010 2011.
um you find a steep Decline and it's
actually more more pronounced in uh the
city of New York so the city of New York
on average the median income was already
much lower than compared to New York
state which is kind of more refers to
the broader agglomeration mostly but
then also the rest of the state and it
was also significantly lower at the
United States so in general there's a
decline in median income uh in the city
of New York
at the same time what we see at the
other kind of sides of the picture is
the share of uh income total income
going to the top one percent and here is
again a comparison between
us and uh red then the state of New York
in green and then New York City kind of
smallest scale in uh blue which is on
top line so it's kind of interesting to
see and this data goes back to the 1980s
um they all share very similar patterns
here at the beginning the share of
income going to the top one percent
that's just reminds yourself one percent
of the entire distribution the top one
percent against the 99 remember
um was about 12 to 30 in the 1980s this
has exploded right so it has grown uh
across all scales
to something modest off you could say uh
22 in the US so one percent owns 22 of
all income just reflect on that
um and then in New York we see that
almost 45 most almost half of all income
is owned by the top one percent okay so
we all know Jeff Bezos and others uh but
this is kind of way more systematic yes
yeah
but the previous one yeah that's true I
mean this is just a figure
and it's one of these progress of liquid
possessions
yeah that's true that's right I mean
this is kind of you could say
uh the median income has decreased
everywhere uh it does seem to you do
seem to find here I would say that it it
decreases more in New York City compared
to others uh it's it's less you would
have to look at percentages there for
New York state or us but I think it's
it's kind of um going from 59 to 54.
yeah that's a very significant decline
but it's not one-on-one uh comparable no
you're right so this goes back way more
in time
um but the main point being here is that
a very small percentage is actually
running away with a lot of the income
and again indeed you see that here's
connection to what you were asking there
was a decline in general also for these
top one percent uh uh with the global
financial crisis but you also see that
it's kind of very quick rebound of these
highest incomes right so they they kind
of take a hit and that has something to
do probably with their fact that they're
exposed to so much parts of the economy
but then they rebounds uh quite soon
okay uh another kind of graph uh here
comparing New York state to the US so
unfortunately not at the at the city
level but yeah you get an idea here it's
comparing the top five percent in terms
of income and total income with
um
which you could say the bottom green
time so the the 20 uh lowest incomes and
then the middle group right so from 40
to 60 in the distribution so what you
find is that
um
over the years
um and this is comparing the late 70s so
you could say the mid 2000s so I mean
it's a dated analysis but that's uh the
furthest that they that they could go in
this analysis in uh the 1970s the ratio
between the top five percent and the
lowest incomes was 7.4 so people in the
top five earned 7.4 times more than
people with the lowest incomes in the
lowest quintile
um by the mid-2000s it had become 17.3
times right so take the income of the
lowest
um uh income households times 17.3 right
so tremendous tremendously growing
difference and it's also when you
compare it to the right growing much
faster uh than what you see in U.S in
general
and it still also pertains to the
relation between the top five percent
and but you could say the middle income
group or the middle class even there is
kind of these disparities have doubled
and they have have increased more uh
when you compare it to the US so it went
from 2.9 to 5.3 compared to uh 4.7
um when compared to yes okay so
massively increasing that difference so
it means that there's a growing
concentration of income and a very small
group
another exhibit showing this is uh
comparing the growth in income between
different groups so the bottom quintile
again lowest incomes actually lost a
share in total income
um when you compare the late 90s to the
mid-2000s
there was some growth for middle-income
groups and it was a very large group
that growth 18 to 19 in the income of
the life is good okay so the trends are
kind of clear it was a slow hiccup uh
with the global financial crisis but as
a kind of a secular Trend where a very
small percentage of the population yet
one percent or five percent is gaining
more and more uh share in the total uh
distribution I think
one way of of looking at that is why
that could be and we'll talk about
General patterns also more towards the
end of uh of today's uh session
is looking at what happens
um in evolutions of productivity so with
kind of with one hour of work what kind
of value do you produce how much cookies
do you cut or how much cards do you make
or how much
um you could say transactions Financial
transactions can you uh can you conclude
um versus the income from those
activities so what you see is that from
2001 until uh 2011 here there's actually
a 14 increase in productivity so for the
same hour of work you produce 14 more
wealth if you will
but when you look at the income levels
um from labor annual average real wage
so these are the the salaries that
people get
it has increased a little bit but it has
by no means kept base wet the Rises and
productivity left okay so it's kind of
it's running away
so there's an increase of about what is
it here two three four percent
um as we go across those uh 10 years
okay so that means that something else
is probably happening with the Weld and
value that's being created
and we talked a little bit about
financialization last week it means that
it's if it's not going to labor it's
probably going to the factor of capital
which means shareholders or uh you could
say well remunerated employees such as
CEOs managers who actually take uh a
growing piece off the cake
yeah this is New York
um
we'll get to more global patterns more
towards the end as a kind of an Outlook
exercise
but it's a trend that is that is
occurring across uh across countries
right and there's you probably know the
work of Thomas picketing it may have
rung a bell already uh he and his group
of we could say economic historians
have looked at systematically at income
data and income distribution data uh and
a more long-term perspective and they
yeah they can't compare all countries
because their data sources are limited
but they compare a number of key
European countries uh us UK Australia
etc etc so yeah these are unfortunately
um
patterns we see everywhere but in some
contexts they're more extreme than
elsewhere and US UK and we'll get to
that at some point are the most extreme
cases here
so yeah run away
um productivity but not necessarily more
remuneration
on the other side is and this is I think
a very telling graph is
to what extent uh can you make a living
a decent living if you work full time
on the minimum wage
right this was the analysis and I go
back again to the 1980s is it right
um
yeah or even earlier and you see that
during a substantial period of time if
you worked at the minimum wage
you were well above the poverty line
right so you had like 120 percent uh so
you could live if you will decently and
you wouldn't live in poverty
and this has completely melted away so
uh became uh very bad in the kind of
1990s but even well into today you see
that even if you work uh full time at
this wage you still fall below uh the
poverty line okay so it's kind of
something institutionally is wrong there
and the fiscal policy Institute has been
one of the main I would say Advocates
also for an increase in minimum wages
uh and yeah and a lot of metropolitan
areas also for instance in in London
there's also kind of uh demand for
London living wage uh which sometimes
should be higher uh than in the rest of
the country because the standard of
living it's just more expensive in these
large metropolitan areas okay so a very
dire picture a lot of people at the very
bottom are not only you could you could
say losing out in terms of income levels
it's also still it's not sufficient to
actually make a living uh when you're at
that site of the income distribution
so just to give you a bit of a picture
from this arguably extreme case of the
the sincerity of the situation
uh and yeah you can find this report
online pulling apart uh New York
um and I would recommend that you have a
look at that but I think the conclusion
is that we see uh in growing income
polarization in the state of New York
more narrowly in New York City
and it's becoming more dramatic than the
US average
okay over to you for another one to two
minutes group thing and I would like to
ask you why it is according to you that
specifically world and Global cities are
becoming so polarized okay and then
we'll take the question straight after
that go ahead
[Music]
thank you
again
[Music]
today
okay
thank you
I miss you too
[Music]
thank you
okay let's hear it this is what you came
up with
you
[Music]
what did you come up with
yeah
a little areas
so let's speak for four people
so there's a comment about the cost of
living
okay but it's more you could say more a
symptom if you will I mean it's kind of
the price of real estate housing
um daily consumption etc etc
you could say it affects everybody
to a similar degree unless we
acknowledge that there's even more
differences I mean that's that the cost
of living for the rich would be also
very high but maybe they can afford it
it's not really an explanation of why we
see polarization I think yep I think a
lot of governments buy into the tripod
and so we see large companies which
already have a lot of capital getting
more subsidies from the government
getting
um
place in say special economic zones
where electricity land live around a lot
of things are subsidized uh
they're they're drinking well providing
um
employment however that said employment
the salary is not distributed so you
have the larger companies getting larger
what do you mean with trickle-down
Logics yes so I mean the the rhetoric of
that is of course that if you have a
large company
it provides employment and the ideal
scenario is to be more people with more
money except what often happens is that
the top one percent offset company will
probably get larger income and the
income distribution is quite skewed
so yeah this this important critique I
think that's also what for instance
Doreen Massey was talking about I mean
and throughout her career fighting this
kind of trickle-down Economics principle
and she talks about
because of global cityization
which is actually producing inequalities
which are not it's not just let's wait
for a bit more Global City formation and
it will be eased away
what he actually says no uh this
polarization is an outcome of global
City formation uh it's because you have
certain activities that we will have
this is not something it's something
permanent and not something that will go
away a bit more trickle-down economics
so because economics something with
the fact that you create multipliers
that money circulates to the territory
we can create jobs will then fuel growth
etc etc but little is said about the
income levels of these people uh what
kind of jobs are created what kind of
working circumstance Etc right
okay other ideas
um
capitalism just how do I make the most
money as fast as possible and the more
you try to do that and practically
intuition as possible the more exciting
social problems but you know it just it
like self-destructure the same sounds
so there's deliberate corporate
strategies but perhaps they can also be
more viable and some live touch
regulations compared to other places
yeah yeah
the
formulations
so yeah that's true there's a lot of
local policy that works towards creating
some kind of a business climate
of national policies that are
restructuring the detection of Labor etc
etc yeah
I mean I also think that the cities are
trying to struggle to attract global
companies and that at the end global
companies They Don't Really enrich City
budgets with the taxes because they
either evade it either the city trying
to once again attract those local
companies trying to subsidize them in
terms of substitute but then
like taxes is something to support the
lower weight of the more like insecure
parts of the population and then like
they uh like a low-income workers they
don't get the support of the city
okay let's
there was a lot of answers from there so
spatial redistribution yeah
Taxation and also creating social
policies so this is something in one of
the tasks he just mentions it's very
briefly about the uh develop
developmental State something like this
like this uh this process has changed in
things that have a more active role and
I think it's going to be something that
also shapes this polarization absolutely
yeah foreign
but you know there's a maybe a
concentration of people who derived a
larger portion of their income from
financialization
foreign
because I mean we also have to
distinguish between uh say processes
that work across the entire territory
they say okay what holds for countries
and what is so specific about some
places that they seem to be more
polarized than the rest of the country
okay yeah
minimum
thank you
easily removed
[Music]
awesome yeah uh at the end at the back
sorry sorry
um
yeah I was thinking about following the
responsibility for social reproduction
has been privatized and put on to the
individuals so especially in places like
the US where there's continual crises
it's extremely hard for the working
classes
of course with responsibilities
and then also like a privatization of
of column is going to do
and different quality
can you say a bit more about social
reproduction because it's a very
analytical term or kind of almost
theoretical term what do you mean with
that
um just like things like
um everything from Healthcare to taking
care of children
um yeah you know feeding your family
having them enough money for utilities
and things like that
right so and when it comes to the system
the worker itself needs to be produced
in a social way uh it's not a good time
making the worker I mean physically but
also educating the worker feeding uh I
mean kind of educating and socializing
them into a particular uh working
culture yeah
um
I guess ideas Rich the richest
before I feel like places where that is
more accepted like in the UK there's
like hot dogs like reality TV for
example like
um big brother like benefit the street
it like kind of created the idea that
the poor are just like messy people who
kind of think about their property
oh yeah
I I would agree but I think then the
question is to what extent would it play
out more in an urban context than say in
I don't know rural Britain maybe because
it's poverty is is less present there
although I would like to see a map of
that but yeah I think the power of new
liberal ideas is clearly going to but
okay one final idea
[Music]
um
so it has something to do with them
perhaps with um existing solidarity
networks it would extends there's still
solidarity between people uh and what
extent the urban environment still
supports that
you've covered quite a bit of ground I I
don't have it in my slides all of that
but I think it shows what you can do
collectively in trying to um try to pick
up this puzzle so so thank you for that
what I just want to do is is take you to
a number of slides because I think try
to gather a number of elements and then
work towards this polarization thesis
however fullable it is uh we'll try to
try to get there and then we'll take a
short break
so yeah uh conceptualization
uh have been written about this uh I
I've been mostly referring to the global
City but there's plenty of other kind of
scholarship on that uh as you can see in
this picture it has been one of the main
kind of
um
um you could say theorized conceptualize
uh problems of contemporary cities and
something with yeah what you do with
this uh with these dualities
um John monkov and Manuel constells
talked about dual City Susan Feinstein
wrote by divided cities Peter Marcus
another great scholar talk about quarter
cities
uh Buddhists talked about fragmented
cities Etc so it's kind of has been one
of the main debates in urban social
geography but it seems that uh all these
kind of uh things necessarily or or most
emblematically start to connect
um to cities rather than wider uh wider
territories and
um and and a lot of people start to look
for
um particular answers as I said last
week I tend to go back to the 80s
because it's kind of my my natural
cohort
um but quite often people go back to the
60s the 70s and this kind of wider
restructuration of of cities and wider
economies and we could say uh the North
Atlantic sphere so it's
I mean there's a lot of things have been
written there's a rich scholarship but
arguments it's kind of biased if you
will to say the crisis of cities or the
the crisis cities have underwent
in Western Europe Northern America okay
so there's plenty of stuff that needs to
be written uh on on the histories and
these historical trajectories uh of say
Chinese cities uh African cities etc etc
um
but it's not something that uh that I
can now cover uh today okay but
um
it's yeah kind of the general narrative
that you find in these different uh kind
of analysis is that the economic
restructuring kind of started uh in the
1960s 70s when
there's a culmination of the crisis of
what they call North Atlantic fortism
and as I I think explained last week or
two weeks ago
um there was this system of regulating
capitalism where there was a deal say
between the workers and capital that
increased productivity would uh
um that the fruits of that and the
surface of that would be shared with
workers okay this is kind of Ford going
back to to Henry Ford uh he he paid his
workers a little bit more
um so they would be more productive but
they could actually in fact also buy the
cars that they were producing uh at the
at the hellish speed okay so that was
kind of the Wilder model uh we saw the
emergence of the middle classes in the
immediate post-war era everybody could
could buy uh consumer goods because of
rising productivity levels uh it was the
invention of free time to actually spend
your money and consume it and so I can
actually go to shop Shops and and buy
stuff at some point this model kind of
started to crumble there were problems
with
um with productivity it couldn't keep up
with Rising uh wages
and kind of them at the macro level the
solution was
a relocation of production uh and you
could say the start point of
globalization the new international
division of labor the effect was that
there was de-industrialization and you
could say the core of the world economy
is high income industrialized places so
again we're talking about Northern
America Western Europe mostly
and it's set in motion the process of uh
structural and employment
which was
felt throughout countries and
territories but was very very Urban uh
in many contexts there was a lot of
productive activities within cities
um and as these active moved away became
obsolete what happened is that you could
say Urban poverty and unemployment
became very much Urban phenomena so
cities lost their functions productive
functions
but they had to deal with a lot of
things say the costs of unemployment etc
etc so we have a decline in tax base and
in many contexts what you see is a shift
towards
austerity so there's less income
so this budget cuts etc etc so the whole
idea and the immediate post-war era was
a strong Indian state so you had mass
production Mass consumption but also
with states that was inspired by John
men and he said okay if there's an issue
with uh with consumption
well the the government itself will be
the first investor will make sure that
um that the economy keeps on going that
kind of changed in the spirit as well
the state was seen as something that had
to roll back its activities stop
interfering uh with all kinds of uh
market-based processes and so this kind
of the starting point of uh the
neoliberal ideology
uh whereas the state was still kind of
setting the rules of Market uh Market
systems
it stopped indeed providing for instance
a whole range of public goods that that
were mentioned in many countries okay so
most of I mean accentuated this took
place in the US and the UK you could say
the new liberal heartlands or the
leading examples of that with uh that
Margaret Thatcher Ronald Reagan
but it started to creep in an effect it
became some kind of a mobile policy that
was also in practice being implemented
in other contexts
sometimes to a lesser extent in a more
variegated way etc etc and the whole
research agenda by Francis Jamie pack a
very nice uh and one of the leading
scorers in in urban geography
is about that so what is neoliberalism
what is neoliberalization is it the same
everywhere how variegated is it how does
it connect itself to different kind of
contexts that's that's the whole thing
so we see those ideas spreading a lot
across a lot of these say Western
European North American states
um and in in one way or another it leads
to some kind of to a self-fulfilling
prophecy because as the state Retreats
from certain areas
it deregulates very often
um a lot of these uh these markets which
hands more power to large corporations
and we already talked about uh
multinational corporations uh last week
and we see a rising concentration of
power of industrial and financial
conglomerations etc etc and indeed in
the process where also the state is kind
of rescaled where a lot of
responsibilities are kind of pushed to
the local level you get some kind of a
self-fulfilling Mantra of competing
cities to attract Global capital okay so
that's kind of the situation where a lot
of policy makers you could say in the
80s end of the
1980s were kind of facing uh a kind of
zero-sum game where there's only so much
production for instance to take place so
Amazon will uh will have its Center
either here or it will go across the
border and what can we do about that
well
David Harvey is one of the the the main
uh scholars in this area he says well
what we see that a lot of our policy
makers are trying to do is they try to
become entrepreneurial right so whereas
they were managing
the territories and trying to think
about
um the spatial structures of welfare uh
amenities and to distribute growth
across the territory you kind of get the
flip side a much more competitive idea
about growth and a new kind of role for
people that were previously managing
territories to become some kind of
entrepreneurs right
and David Harvey talks about this in his
famous piece and I think uh people and
miss and four cities also discussed this
with um with Matthew uh from uh he
describes the shift from Urban
managerialism to Urban
entrepreneurialism where you get a
different kind of mindset with policy
now
okay so this is kind of the Mantra is a
bit structuralist but it's kind of the
reasoning of how you could say macro
phenomena at some point lead to a very
particular Urban reality
um and what David Harvey then does and
this is a kind of a short excurse that I
want to take you through what it does it
says okay in this competitive
circumstances
we see that policy makers start to adopt
a number of strategies and a number of
entrepreneurial strategies and I'll take
you through them
be advised and sometimes it kind of
interesting to see that people think
there's kind of some kind of a recipe by
David Harvey say if your cities in
trouble please consider applying this
strategy this is not what David Harvey
does he kind of observes and analyzes
this phenomena he's not prescribing some
kind of entrepreneurial strategies that
then should be implemented by policy
makers just to be clear which reminds me
of an anecdote David Harvey I think once
gave a lecture in New York and he I
think he's famous for his analysis or
reading of of thus Capital
by Michael Marx volume one has very nice
videos on that he has a companion to
Capital
uh and also gave a lecture about that
somewhere in New York and apparently
there were also some investment bankers
in the room and after the lecture his
investment bank has walked up to him and
said well Mr Harvey I think you have a
very good understanding of how Finance
Capital Works would it be possible
possible to hire you as a consultant
[Music]
um I think he declined but yeah just to
be very clear I mean it's
um it's an analysis that he provides
it's not a recipe that it thinks that
should be installed okay all right
um
so yeah I mean the first kind of thing
that is under pressure if you will is
these productive activities or what it
sees is that
um some policy makers still manage to
kind of keep productive activities in
their territories and I mean that still
there will be some public and private
Investments and you could say the
physical and social base
um uh of course physical and social
infrastructure so think about knowledge
networks educational facilities uh try
to build Venture Capital sometimes the
state becomes some kind of venture
capitalist itself uh but indeed as has
been described also try to work on all
the things that are too costly uh
um reduce excessive labor costs for
instance
um tax breaks etc etc and that quite
often kind of leading the idea is that
the city regions should become yeah
silicon valleys uh that that should be
the ambition that they should seek to
attract Capital people
um sometimes this kind of set to attract
the creative class to refer to Richard
Florida but it's kind of this idea that
yes a high-tech productive city is still
mad imaginable and we have to create the
right business environment to get there
okay so images of clusters and there's a
lot of cluster policy but it used to be
I think in a lot of cities
it's also the reason why you had
dedicated districts Edge cities uh
linked to healthcare or biotech
etc etc so that's kind of one strategy
that is still imaginable for cities
the second element entrepreneurial
strategy is to compete for consumption
yeah so people have money to spend
there's a spatial division of
consumption what you want is that people
spend their dollars Euros uh rupees in
your country and your city and not in
the neighboring City okay
and obviously with globalization this
this kind of changes you see the
emergence of global tourism flows etc
etc so there's a kind of battle if you
will to attract tourists retirees
there's a whole economy behind Elderly
Homes uh because well these are people
who have pensions still and they provide
a safe stream of income
um
and you could say local consumption
activities
now there's a contradiction in
capitalism there because with the crisis
of fordism uh we see a decline in
purchasing power the factor labor is
typically less powerful
um so yeah there's there's less less
money to spend people don't really see
uh an increase in their in their uh real
wages as we've seen in the picture uh on
New York but this goes back to the 1970s
for instance when you see pictures of
the US
there has been hardly any increase in
real wages despite huge productivity
growth okay
um so this conundrum in many cases being
resolved by
reverting to uh to credit basically
um
so instead of kind of buying it from the
salary that you have
there's an increase to say
financialization of the economy in the
sense that a lot of households become
dependent on credits mostly through
banks to obtain housing but increasingly
also all other kinds of consumption
Goods Goods washing machines cars etc
etc
so this is kind of one way of solving
that that contradiction
um it's also uh trying to attract High
income jobs uh because yeah they have a
lot of money to spend uh and what form
does it take well in many cases uh it
will have some impact on the social
spatial structure uh it could be either
state-led gentrification it could be
market-based gentrification
um in many cases what you will see is
that cities will try to uh become more
attractive one way or another by using
Heritage uh architecture and these are
things that that you will also talk with
with boss about cities are kind of
transformed into these kind of urban
spectacles that are
collectively adding more value to the
goods that are consumed there so if you
walk around from the spectacular
neighborhood you might be inclined to
spend a bit more yes
yes
very also really increase the work of
the city like the one in
library and before that the seat was
very
popular and everyone was not really an
attraction and part of it
was very interesting yeah yeah yeah no
but it's it's kind of these these
examples of of landmark buildings uh
they're they're quite often they're used
in large scale reconversion number one
is is I think maybe you refer to Bilbao
all right that's Northern Spain yeah so
there was an old Industrial Area uh and
I think it's in the 1990s already
spectacular urbanism in the sense that
spectacular architecture usually there's
some kind of a mobile class of what they
call start attacks uh who are kind of
foreign
who connect to these Global circuits and
starts producing these kind of
spectacular architectural forms that
then send the message to the world which
can be then uh kind of linked to City
branding or city marketing strategies
Etc so the city in and of itself can be
consumed but also plays a role in
fueling consumption practices within
okay so that's kind of if you're
interested uh to hire David Hardy for
that he can advise you how to do that
and then the third third one is what he
says he said there's still
an element of the previous system there
but it's kind of transformed so and you
could say foreign
to kind of stimulate growth it was still
capitalist growth for sure across the
territory somewhat evenly
um so yeah there's you could say General
taxation there's a fund and it can be
invested across the territory and lower
level governments can still try to
attract some of that funding but it
becomes increasingly you could say
marketized as well quite often you'll be
competing with other cities and other
regions to start to attract these kinds
of redistributed funds
um just a number of examples in the U.S
it's it's about where our military and
defense Investments being made that's
the story of Silicon Valley in Europe
there's a lot of competition between
regions
um
for for instance a regional development
funds which work on both competitiveness
of of regions but also cohesion so it's
not kind of
100 evil or something like that but it's
a mechanism uh to yeah to redistribute
um these kind of Investments across the
territory but increase you could say the
capacity of these places for growth and
at the same time also work towards
providing amenities
uh Child Care etc etc people that are
joining me on Friday I'll say a little
bit more about that in relation to
Brussels the canalso for instance is one
of these zones of actions uh for the
European uh Regional development effect
when you look for instance people that
know Flanders a little bit
um you have stops feeling spray actin
urban renewal projects
it's kind of led by Flanders
um
and it's it's basically giving money to
uh to cities to reconvert Inner City
neighborhoods okay and quite often you
have to apply uh either you say okay I'm
going to hand in a concept note so you
get some some funding to develop your
idea and then perhaps if you're
successful later on you can attract uh
funding by uh by the Flemish government
but thus far you see that it's mostly uh
the Central City Central stadium so the
main agglomerations that have the main
capacity also to apply uh for these
funds so
it's not that all small cities can
actually uh benefit from that okay there
was a question
um
specifically is redistration Surplus
like looking at both electric economies
like governments are just financing that
they're all running down so they're all
running
deficits yeah deficits so I mean it is
that's an interesting like just looking
at it like Surplus but really it's like
making choices about where we're going
yeah yeah who's going to pay for the
future yeah but that's yeah okay so
there's a question okay uh governments
don't have money how can you be talking
about Surplus I think what I'm talking
about is the service that is being
created uh in the economy which is not
necessarily the same as the government
budget
uh which is under conditions of what I
would call permanent austerity is is
kept small and then the only thing that
you can do is is yeah say okay we're
going to become more efficient and
that's a a mantra that you hear often or
basically have very small cuts across
the board so I think uh it used to be
you could say more
um in the previous especially to for the
70s or something like that it's the
allocation problem was smaller because
the fiscal base was was larger there was
more economic growth which could be more
easily taxed without you could say
hurting corporations or people or
workers it's only at the point uh where
um you could say and yeah there was a
kind of stagnation of profits that it
became very hard for governments
um
yeah to how would I put this to um to
maintain fiscal levels
without eating into the profits of of
the corporations that were still there
so it's kind of a
yeah it became a very awkward situation
uh so they they rather kind of cut back
on on expenditures running to increase
um for instance corporate tax rates so
that could have been one way of dealing
with that thinking about uh
um raising productivity levels in
another way by investing in technology
etc etc and that has happened to some
extent but it hasn't been the answer uh
across the board I think the main
I would say Trend was to
keep a check on on the on the wages of
people so yeah that's when I when I talk
about Surplus is kind of more what kind
of wealth is created within the
capitalist system
rather than more in accountancy terms
what's the does the government run a
surplus or a benefit or or a deficit
um yeah just to be be clear there
um but yeah despite the fact that even
if there's the smaller budgets available
and so the allocation mechanism has
changed it has become less kind of
an element of how would I put this
managing
kind of growth across the territory it
has become more of a of a competition
really and you see for instance these
urban renewal projects as long as
there's a competition
to attract These funds to your city
um and that's yeah then you see that it
leads to some kind of uh Winner Takes a
doll phenomenon I mean Flemish
government is reflexive about that so
it's not extreme that it's all to one
city but still there's a tendency that
some cities benefit a bit more from that
than others that's
that's always dependence
um yeah
um I'm taking a lot of time then the the
next uh kind of final one and then we
kind of end the excurs and go back
um to the discussion about command and
control and world cities the kind of
final strategy is to make sure that in
the international division of labor in
these Global production networks and
Global Financial networks that you hold
these functions of command and control
and you can say there's a specific kind
of entrepreneurialism well you're invest
in physical connectivity digital
connectivity uh nowadays uh that you
invest in you could say supply side
economics I heard that a little bit uh
so state of the Arts uh districts
that are there to attract International
corporations and
development Central Business districts
that what I mean with that
also invest in educating the labor force
uh thinking about installing business
schools for instance in Frankfurt one of
the uh the leading Financial Center in
um in Germany
um due to University it has its business
school financed by Deutsche Bank right
so and there's lectures uh by people
working at Deutsche Bank
educating the new generation of critical
uh social scientists okay
um so this kind of a dynamic that's
particularly attaching itself to world
cities and the kind of idea is that if
you attract these Global functions it
will indeed set in motion some kind of a
trickle-down effect
it will inflate property prices because
they will as we have learned with Brad
Christophers they will become a part of
international portfolios
etc etc so that's kind of the strategy
that is set there
okay let's have a quick break uh five
minutes and then we actually get to the
polarization thesis which is taking a
lot of time today
a little bit yeah
thank you
okay
[Music]
uh yeah
um can I do the screen you can send me
an email
or maybe what I can do is just but I
want to avoid that kind of um
or you can just shout and say who is
bueno no no no no
[Music]
okay yeah I think they have that same
problem as far because I don't know who
is presenting with me this weekend I
don't have any ways
thank you ma'am yeah yeah yeah but
normally you can see it uh on canvas
yeah
okay and it's probably because
the people in the other group
uh I'll add email addresses
[Music]
this is
foreign
[Music]
okay
um
[Music]
[Laughter]
um
because
it wasn't something yeah
[Music]
foreign
okay let's reconvene
let's get started again
okay
so we have this brief excurs learning
about different entrepreneurial
strategies and I think what I wanted to
show is that
thank you there's there's a wide
restructuring of the economy and we can
place growing Global City formation
within that as one particular strategy
okay
or one particular process that is
explicitly relevant for world cities
now going back a little bit more to the
discussion about how does this connect
to polarization
well as we found there's this and it's
mostly Friedman and wolf Friedman and
system
uh the starting point was this
observation of a change in the economic
base generally a decline and well-paid
manufacturing jobs which is some kind of
an exodus because of globalization of
production
and at the same time a restructuring of
the economy uh towards services
as we've seen 80 percent of cities is
service based but it's both at the high
end and at the low end both formal
Services service markets and informal
service
so what kind of polarization thesis says
well there's something particular about
these commands and control functions
uh
fuels this polarization process please
take a seat
okay
[Music]
please do a refill
so there's something particular about
these APS and headquarters economies
that will set a motion polarization
process okay
so at one point there's you could say
competition within the APN APS complex
itself which will lead to
an idea of Outsourcing getting rid of
some kind of non-core activities
quite often this leads to low-key kind
of activities that are all and a lot of
contexts also linked to some form of
informal economy
and a lot of kind of Migrant labor that
takes care of routine service charts
think about cleaning functions think
about
um well the Xerox machine and those kind
of things clerical work etc etc
next to that what you also see is that
with these high-end functions or these
command and control functions
it comes with uh the influx of
wealth salaries people that have a lot
of spending power that have their own
desire for certain forms of of housing
quite often the sets in motion bursts of
gentrification so the displacement of
initial populations
um and it's also at the level of
consumption Goods of of leisure
activities that this leads to a
transformation okay so if you host these
activities well basically the managers
the CEOs people in Business Services
Advanced producer Services well they
have the whole Ecology of cultural
amenities and hurricane Etc uh so
there's this also creates some kind of
demand for
um low-income jobs to cater quite
literally to these uh Elites there is
something particular about world cities
which makes that there will be a even
more augmented process of polarization
compared to non-world cities or
um
or wider territories okay and the end
result the ideas is that you get with
you get a a different structure or
income distribution in the sense that
there's a lot of growth of jobs at the
very top there's a growth of jobs at the
at the bottom of the income distribution
and in general because of a decline in
well-paid well remunerated stable
manufacturing jobs there's a kind of a
decrease of middle income groups and you
end up with an hour class okay so
something like that okay
um that when this kind of figure shows
how that works
it's a bit hard to decipher here but
there's the growth of M which is kind of
uh managerial class so CEOs of
international corporations link to that
is p these are kind of the producer
services or the advanced business
services that we've been talking about
and then below that see these are all
kinds of clarable tasks okay
menu tasks and kind of taking care of
administrations
Etc in the current day and age these
activities are also kind of being
globalized and offshores and of
themselves the 1980s there these back
office Works still took place in global
cities okay
so at the same time you see a growth you
could say an informal markets or
informal parts of the economy
um
and these are often also based on
um on migrantly okay
um
for instance what we have here I mean
all these kind of amenities that we were
talking about hurricane
letter activities is kind of supported
by that uh there's in informal
production facilities that are
re-emerging in cities and then yeah
consumption rules and other kinds of
things that are also kind of emerging
there in connection to
um the rise of this APS complex and
Global Corporation so in general what
you need to remember is you have an
exodus of these high-wage manufacturing
jobs that's what kind of is the main the
restructuring and the kind of influx of
workers
um often from uh from a global scale of
foreign migrant workers that quite often
end up in uh in informal labor markets
and note that I still have this one if
you don't mind how
big okay so a general restructure of
this labor market and importantly and
what sets
um women Global cities apart from you
could say the rest of the territory or
small cities is that this labor market
becomes globalized
and it speaks because I have both sides
of uh this hourglass it works at the at
the top level we have the uh the high
paid
um migrants and it works also at the
lower end of the income distribution
and quite interestingly
uh sometimes quite cynically there's
um also different terminologies for that
so people at the high end uh it doesn't
really matter uh or they're kind of not
seen as immigrants but these are expats
quite often for instance in Belgium they
enjoy quite interesting text regimes
with the discussion as to whether it
would be a nice idea to actually tax
expats in Belgium
um so these are kind of seen as people
that
um
that bring in a lot of expertise a lot
of value that make a city very
competitive uh in this global war for
talent whereas uh people that are more
at in the lower paid jobs are seen as as
immigrants right uh or foreigners etc
etc Okay so
there's a lot of terms of being used
there that are
take part of a very performative and
normalizing
um and normalizing the situation so the
way we talk about these divisions
matters I think
um
so what we see is
um uh also
growth of of low-skilled
or these skilled uh migrant workers
um so are the people that have little
qualification in a country of origin and
and come to a world of global City
or people that have qualifications
but
for some reason because they cross the
border have lost proof of that okay so a
lot of contacts even if you eradicated
in one or one in the other direction
uh you have to kind of be accredited for
that right so you have to uh your
diploma needs to be certified to be able
to access the labor market in one way or
another
this in and of itself is quite an
interesting process uh but it means that
a lot of people especially in informal
uh relative informal migration
may not be in the position to actually
do that so they may have all kinds of
skills but they can't formally use them
okay so this is a kind of process of
descaling that is that is going on now
what it creates especially in a place
where you have a lot of immigration and
that's that's typically World in global
cities it just creates a very large pool
of people that have a very poor
um
uh you could say that are that are not
really empowered that that don't have a
bargain power to negotiate a better
wages
um and if they don't do it well somebody
else will and that's kind of the the
notion of a reserve Army of Labor
a lot of people that are in flux debt
will basically take any job
and you see in that case you see the
emergence of what people call 3D jobs
dirty demanding and dangerous or dirty
dangerous and difficult uh a lot of
Migrant labor in Roman Global cities
ends up in uh these kind of segments
and these are typically jobs that people
um that kind of the natives if you will
are unwilling to do
and I mean for instance if you look at
the whole debate about the fella Fallout
of brexit
and it had been driven tremendously by
anti-immigrant they are stealing our
jobs sentiment uh and now they're the
economy is kind of crippled
by uh not having access to fuel because
there's no truck drivers to actually uh
or migrant truck drives to actually
bring the fuel to to pump stations gas
stations so you can refill your car so
it's kind of
uh history with the Vengeance there
um and it kind of shows The crucial
dependence of our economy a lot of
cities
in that migrant labor and a lot of
essential services that is absolutely
undervalued in societal terms
um
yeah and then
what what is actually uh quite
interesting to see and that's also work
by Sasuke assassin when she was still
married hence group
um that yeah
a lot of these activities are informal
are connected to floating populations
people that are residing temporarily in
cities
um that may be transmigrants uh move on
one way or another
and yeah they they form the context of
you could say potential exploitation
it's not necessarily happening but it's
kind of a context where people that want
to take advantage
um Can more easily do that okay
um it can be
sometimes for very good reasons to say
Okay I want to help somebody
and I'll let you clean my house or take
care of the children and I'll pay you
the minimum wage or something like that
[Music]
right that could be the position of a
middle-class family uh in in a global
City but at the same time there's this
structural discrimination of these
groups in society they may be well
suited to take other jobs at Society but
yeah they're kind of forced into them so
it's kind of in combination with a large
group of people that are looking for
jobs
um the informal character allows a lot
of
um informal uh potential forms of of
exploitation and this is what substance
calls the peripheralization at the core
so what she says is that typically we
think about exploitation as a relation
between say the global North or the
global South well actually it's taking
place it re-enters the global North so
in world and Global cities you can also
find this
um these exploitative relations because
the global South is actually
living
in world and Global cities whereas the
relation
remains exported okay so
peripheralization of the Court just in
figures to to illustrate this is to
referred a little bit to the research on
this so there's a whole strand of
research looking into urban belief
Networks
some kind of interesting work by uh
William Carroll looking at Interlocking
directorates it's it's one way of
measuring
um you could say the connections between
cities
um
by looking at the the overlaps between
the board of directors of Corporation so
one one member of the board sitting on
different boards so for instance
uh 40 spunk Belgium and BNB buddy bar uh
Paris or something like that and we see
actually in this picture there's quite a
strong connection between Brussels and
Paris but it shows that
yeah uh as we we live in a kind of
global economy as for the corporate
world has globalized there's also you
could say the social structure there
behind that of a traveling Global Elite
with a lot of power decision making
power that is connecting this kind of
place okay so if you're board of
directors of uh and the board of
directors of 10 or 15 corporations well
you will be
you say traveling around in first class
uh between these places
uh and and go from Citadel to Citadel if
you will okay
um I also did a little bit of research
into how this looks and Islamic markets
and I found actually quite similar
things the geographies look different
um but um what out of that is how
governance structures work in Islamic
Banks and there you find that next to
the typical board of directors you also
have a Sharia board and these these
boards basically review to what extent
the activities of banks are
in line with the Sharia okay so are they
um hello or are they not considered uh
Allah
uh yeah it's it's very similar to what I
found in uh on the previous figure in
the sense that it's also very
concentrated uh uh social geography so
it's very concentrated in a very limited
set of Scholars
um some of them sit on the board 50
different corporations
um which creates all kinds of
interesting things as to to what extent
is this so credible that they will
review uh the Sharia compliant character
or other things going on
uh you see there's a connection with New
York
um well at some point golden Sachs uh
also was planning to to go into Islamic
markets and there was a whole
controversy uh as to what extents
um their financial products
was actually
um reviewed by by Sharia scholas or
whether this was some kind of reviews
etc etc there was a huge Flashback by
um
scores by this entire community and uh
in the end it didn't materialize but
just to show you that there's different
ways of approaching these Urban lead
networks but it's it's the existence of
those kind of structures that allows us
to understand yeah what kind of
activities take place at that level and
how do you can affect uh say income
structures because they they're
extremely well remunerated and will
reside in different kind of places
now at the other end what I was talking
about is this these new forms of
industrial
um
exploitation uh in these sweatshops
so yeah what are these kind of
sweatshops you may have heard of that
it's kind of the Renaissance of very old
forms of exploitation or industrial
organization you may have heard about in
the middle age Middle Ages you had to
put it out system where people in the
household and were in the countryside
were actually producing uh at the piece
by piece salary uh textiles for uh for
capitalists and cities
um it's kind of reinvented in the 20th
and 21st century and so flat shops are
these small units usually underground uh
or in secluded spaces often in the
textile industry
uh that works through all these kind of
sub subcontracting uh deals so you never
quite know who is really hiring people
so there's different kind of layers of
of governance there uh a lot of people
yeah are indeed paid by the piece or
have daily or weekly contracts uh which
yeah it's extremely precarious as you
may understand
um and yeah we see that it's kind of
re-emerging and it was say the 19th
century
um it took place in a lot of
industrializing cities
it's went away and for instance in the
U.S you see that because there was all
kind of yeah the trade unions
um initiatives
uh regulations were adapted for instance
in relation to the to the New Deal
um just before uh the Second World War
which made this practically impossible
so it was in a context where you had far
less migrant labor but actually possible
to regulate those markets
but that's kind of returned to the 1990s
this kind of all of a sudden is back at
these are very old data but in the 1990s
uh calculated I think between four
thousand five hundred and four thousand
five hundred of seven thousand textile
companies there and then in New York
were actually sweatshops okay so when
you think about world city formation
it's not just
um these Glitz and Glam offices with
bankers at the same time it's very old
forms of exploitation that are made
possible by a complete
absence of any labor rights uh
protection
so yeah uh the places in Chinatown of
the lower lower east and yeah is this
kind of situations are still occurring
there okay
now then to turn a little bit to
um I would say criticism or critiques of
the polarization pieces because it seems
to be a very kind of elegant thesis
right as the the restructuring of the
economy at the same time there's a
globalization it leads to attraction of
headquarters and APS functions and this
kind of adds to a wider process of
income and rational polarization which
then may also lead to social spatial
polarization okay because people with
different kind of income groups may not
necessarily live in the same place quite
on the contrary if they have very
different Lifestyles they may want to
live something else
same time also the empirical base is
mostly linked to a limited set of of
cases New York London Tokyo so
especially in the 1990s when
this became a major debate the question
is is Susan right uh or is something
wrong to put it in the words of Chris
Hamlet who is also one of one of you say
the main counter voices in this debate
so for instance according to to hamnet
yeah he's very critical of this term
polarization as we also briefly
discussed before
he says well it's an all-purpose General
signifier
and in the end yeah it doesn't really
explain much and we don't
necessarily neatly describe what is
going on in particular world cities
so what it says is that next to
polarization
this other process is thinking thinkable
right we can think about
proletarianization so that's the
emergence of say
an exploited underclass if you will to
use that term in society as the main
Trend or it could also be
professionalization which somehow refers
to social Mobility
um the rise of middle income jobs etc
etc so instead of assuming that world
and Global City formation necessarily
produces polarization it's actually a
research question empirical question
what is going on uh in cities Okay so
rather than just saying okay uh this is
a piece or or a given fact it may be a
hypothesis to see to what extent we see
evidence of polarization or where do we
see other things happening and one way
of doing that is also taking more into
account the occupational structure and
the spatial structure of cities
so to tell a bit more about this
occupational structure uh what it talks
about Chris hamnet and this is kind of
an interesting evolution in the 1990s uh
he mostly looked at the case of London
uh and he says well
what we find in New York
are not necessarily necessarily find
that in the case of London there's
actually very little polarization what I
find is professionalization okay
so yes there's a growth of high income
jobs
but it's not necessarily linked to an
explosion of jobs at the bottom so it's
it's not really an hourglass at the same
time we also see evidence of a growth in
Middle income jobs
and a lot of people
can make can move up you could say the
occupational structure can be trained uh
it can get a training
um and are professionalizing
um so yeah he doesn't find the pattern
of of what what was assumed to be the
the two expected pattern of New York at
the same time he says well it could be
related to the fact that migration is
there and then far less the case
um it's also uncomparable to uh what you
find in New York so you had migration
obviously uh to London but it was less
globalized it was mostly linked you
could say too
the remnants of Empire but it wasn't of
the scale of what you found in New York
and so he says yeah there's also a much
more generous welfare state
when you compare it to what you had in
New York so
no this is okay let's not exaggerate we
don't really fight polarization other
pathways are actually thinkable
um and then
what we actually uh kind of find them in
such context is that
um
it might be something that's kind of
more intersects with
um
you could say uh process of privilege
that intersects with gender roles in uh
and society and this benefit so it's
it's less uh the whole discussion about
yes does this APS complex that that
start to transform the entire labor
market now it's actually wider
dimensions of of uh gender and ethnicity
which is in society that will explain
what we find in labor markets so for
instance Joy by Susan uh Feinstein
and colleagues they they look at uh the
exclusion uh by female labor in high-end
jobs or for instance the work by uh by
John Wills
um no John May and colleagues I forgot
what the first name of the co-water is
is to say okay look we have to look much
more at ethnicity to understand what is
going on because
um for instance one third of of London's
Filipino population is actually in
Health and Social care Brazilians are in
cleaning services uh
sick are are hired as as security guards
algerians are running
um the Metro System etc etc okay so
these kind of more General processes
will tell us much more about what is
going on
what we find is that when you start
looking at more recent work at London
is that yeah this whole argument that
that longness somehow excluded or
protected from processes of polarization
doesn't really seem to hold yeah there's
a question
uh
yeah like a shadow economy or something
yeah I think that's one of the reasons
uh that's a very good point and I think
that's one of the differences between
for instance the work of John May and
colleagues and the conclusions by Chris
Hamner who is focusing on formal
occupational structures
so indeed that's the first point
methodological question is there's
basically a result of the data that is
being used
and actually what you find is that uh in
the article that was in the reader which
is a way more recent one he also admits
that process of polarization are going
on in London okay so it's kind of um he
has seen the light Chris Hamlet and
that's kind of yeah just referring to
this paper is kind of I find a very
interesting paper because it really
targets uh migrant groups here in the
sense that they look at at remuneration
and the kind of jobs that are being done
by people that typically are not part of
visual statistics
um
and yeah it's kind of it's kind of hard
to draw conclusions from that and say
okay uh for instance if you look at this
picture yeah this kind of showing the
the division across different kind of uh
rage groups so they they yeah collected
responses by over 300
uh uh people in informal markets
um
yeah you find that only nine percent
actually uh earns the living wage right
so it's it's
it really shows that there's an overlay
between the migrant labor and poor
working conditions but at the same time
it doesn't give you an overview of the
entire structure of the labor market so
it's kind of a yeah it can't draw
systemic conclusions from that but if
you for instance compare it to this kind
of picture which is not about income but
there's about
uh job quality so it's a very rough
marker of you could say yeah where in
the say social hierarchy or occupational
hierarchy are we at
there you see that there's actually a
growth at uh in the kind of the the
shooting jobs if you will
um a stagnation will be prime of normal
decent jobs and a large growth at the at
the top okay so and these kind of
indicators that that they would
occupational structure it's counter
evidence towards professionalization so
I think what happens here is that
when Chris Hammond was writing his his
argument against Susan in the 1990s it
may have still been true
it may be have been biased by looking at
formal statistics not capturing what was
going on at the bottom because it was
basically part of the informal economy
but then even with that
as time has passed the picture uh even
in the formal Market would would no
longer look as he would have described
it so it's kind of a process of of
restructuring that has um that has only
been initiated later I think compared to
to report
okay but in any case I think
um it's also not necessarily the points
uh to say okay assassin is right or uh
or Hamlet is wrong point is that we have
to
identify different process that can
actually take place at the same time so
you can imagine ant polarization and
professionalization at the same time
it's not because you see polarization
that some
segments of the population actually
undergo social Mobility uh in fact it
could actually be quite an interesting
question in the context of
polarization who is still able to
improve oneself on the labor market and
who is who is not so it's kind I think
that for me was kind of the gist of of
the article uh by Chris Hamlet's uh
there
okay let me move on because uh again
running out of time
um so yeah looking more closely at the
occupational structure I I can't
possibly go beyond that but it gives you
a hint of what to look for the second
element is spatial structure right so a
very important critique Prince by Susan
Feinstein is uh to what extent are the
result of polarization is also a
statistical artifact and there's a lot
of focus on on cities
but we at the same time we know that
middle classes have been suburbanizing
or are still suburbanizing so maybe this
whole disappearance of middle-income
jobs from cities and the fact that you
end up with a very polarized labor
market it could be some kind of an
artifact
um so yeah I think that's something to
to take into account that's also why
it's interesting to compare you could
say differences between what we did in
New York State versus New York City I
think you can't say that there's no
General Trend in kind of a decline of
middle income jobs for instance in the
case of of the US
um but it's perhaps less accentuated
than if you only look at at a very neat
uh City Center okay so there's always an
a possibility that wealth is
suburbanized and would give you a
different question so
scale matters space matters in the sense
that you have to be aware that you need
to kind of map the appropriate
metropolitan area to to understand the
entire structure of the labor market
okay
no yeah and everything can go many ways
and sense that you also have to be
sensitive to what extents
um
uh you could say these higher incomes
will drive gentrification there has been
a whole process of moving out of cities
uh but there's also been a return to the
city when you take a city like Brussels
I think I would say it's around a few
thousand there has been a return of
middle incomes and a lot of places
really leading world cities has been
returned of the super rich
uh setting in motion motion process of
what Loretta Lee Schools super
gentrification in just one example of
that is and I refer to that on the map
uh Brooklyn
used to be you could say uh a nice uh
suburb uh off of New York just across uh
the river which was still affordable and
you could deliver these Brown stones but
what she described is
how actually the the top uh earners in
New York are increasing we're
increasingly buying in uh in these
property markets so we see that almost
half of
um of all Brooklyn was owned by the top
10 okay and that in that period you see
a tremendous growth in or inflation of
property values in that period so you
really have to look at the detailed
level uh within a city how uh you can
say these higher incomes
yeah what kind of spatial process they
set in motion and sometimes at least a
gentrification of inner city
neighborhoods it may be more peripheral
processes etc etc so there's no Unified
spatial structure there it's just a
question if we have a restructure of the
economy
where does it spatially attaches itself
okay
another example is for instance Brussels
where we find that let's say voltage
information and process often
europeanization of the economy and all
kind of functions that are linked to
that how it has kind of reinforced
existing social spatial divides and this
is worked by uh now admitted to a
professor from KU live and discussed a
lot
uh who looked at
um at the evolution of you could say
migrants populations and expat
populations sorry for that divide again
but it's it's being used in reality
um in in Brussels and what you see is
that
um
uh you could say typically the
population with with a lower income
um the Moroccan population has has grown
in the western partner western part of
the city
and the poor Crescent which is kind of
the leading imaginary there also with
policy makers uh whereas you could say
europeanization has attracted a lot of
expats uh mostly Americans and other
kind of um
people from the European Union mostly
settled in the Southeastern part of
um of Brussels and what Chris castellope
explains is that in this geography it's
kind of reproducing earlier rounds of
division in Brussels
um it's kind of no coincidence that
people with a Moroccan uh ethnicity end
up in the Northwest it has something to
do with the wider process of of Migrant
labor guest Labor uh from the 1950s and
60s
I can say a lot about that but the
bottom line is Belgian government
actually uh went to Morocco but also
Turkey Greece Italy to
um to really
you could say brand Belgium as the place
to work
um a lot of of Migrant Services broader
families they were seen as temporary
guest workers and the empties people
decided yes we were going to build a
family here
uh and he actually well uh worked in all
kinds of productive activities in
Brussels
who with the crisis of the 1960s 70s
uh ended so the the you could say
globalization of production also had a
huge impact on these kind of jobs so a
lot of these migrant workers
were faced with structural unemployment
and were kind of locked in into these
situations uh and yeah never really got
out of there okay so there's there's
still
um
uh provides unemployment rates
um and what we find is that with the
restructuring of the economy just at the
time when new kind of jobs were being
created there were the jobs that were
not really matching the the profile of
these guest workers so there was a lot
of of service work
um and yeah I mean it required training
which was not necessarily offered to
make that transition within one
generation so
that's why you kind of see this this
kind of pattern uh reproduce so the
argument by Chris gas float is that we
should really uh look also into
um
looking at the continuities uh in these
spatial structures you for instance also
find that
um in in contemporary Elite geographies
and kind of continuing a little bit the
work by Chris Castle but then focusing
on say the the upper stratum if you will
uh we looked at cultural patronage
activities which is basically
a method to identify people with a lot
of money or that think about themselves
as being distinct by consuming high-end
cultural activity so we basically went
to uh La moner
um
uh what is it again uh Elizabeth
so you have all kinds of highbrow
cultural activities uh in Brussels
taking place we also went to Bazaar we
tried to identify who is actually on the
big friend list uh who is sponsoring
these uh high-end cultural institutions
I mean these fees are not kind of super
spectacular I think sometimes we find
it's kind of you become a big fan of
bizarre I think it was 12 500 euros per
year so it's not kind of Jeff Jeff Bezos
but at the same time it's not something
that you could spend on a normal salary
so you that was kind of used as a as a
kind of Criterion to kind of find a
group that that has both you could say
cultural capital uh and also economic
what we found then is that and that was
actually quite interesting that the two
these kind of methods you could actually
identify where these people live and we
actually I mean boss and I uh took our
pipes and went taken pictures uh I could
actually uh at the plot level identify
where where Elites were living
do you find kind of interesting
clusterings there
and it's all very much concentrated in
and actually in a city neighborhood so
most of the kind of Roads led to uh to
this kind of area around
and those kind of areas so we identified
that our Elites are very Urban if you
will and the other place was kind of
more uh Suburban but still within the
Russell's Capital Region with spookular
which is more like villain neighborhood
um
uh so it's kind of a distinct uh way of
life but it's kind of interesting that
the the major we could say segregation
process that you find in terms of gated
communities those kind of things this is
not something that you
easily find in Brussels these things
exist in Brussels but it's not
yeah it's not the Sao Paulo or Rio de
Janeiro or this kind of thing so it's
really
um Happening by micro mechanisms at the
Block Level that is kind of segregation
is is going on
no just those were just a few examples
to take into account uh histories of
spatial structure that may matter
now drawing into a close I think what I
want to say is that yeah how to explain
um we could say inequality polarization
etc etc I think we've learned that
polarization it's just one way of one
outcome of this process is we need some
kind of an analytical or explanatory
model for that
Hannah and I want to draw on birds and
mustard here and I find it's still quite
interesting because they they're working
kind of three ways they said look
there's at the macro level a level of
global change the economy in general is
restructuring it could be financializing
this uh new international division of
labor etc etc so that's happening at the
macro level there's also at the
individual level
due to personal characteristics choices
Etc
patterns habits cultures you may uh have
different kind of Labor Market
opportunities
um there's a lot of noise there it's
hard to study
um in a systematic way but we need to
acknowledge that but what is kind of
interesting is how the micro and the
micro kind of connected by this medium
level level of analysis
because it's kind of the interface
between Global process and local process
so we can think about how ethnicity
gender and those kind of things will
structure access to the labor market and
positionality in the labor market as
that labor market is being restructured
we have to acknowledge National
differences
um we talked about yeah the rise of
neoliberalization
it hasn't materialized in the same way
or at the same time in different kind of
spaces there's large differences still
between more you could say
Social Democratic
or at least
light versions of social democracy
um Princeton Continental Europe compared
to the UK or the US
so
in Continental Europe in many places
there's still quite a solid social
security system uh minimum wages etc etc
and we kind of identify these are kind
of crucial elements in explaining uh
oh my God promo federalization is
getting late so if you have these kind
of security measures in place it will
immediately kind of prevent at least
informal markets uh that you have a an
explosion at the bottom
um so yeah that's that's something to
take into account and also clearly even
within National context you need to look
at the functions and that's connecting
back today with Harvey uh cities have
different kind of functions and that
will also shape its trajectory if you
look at city like Detroit or Charlotte
War it's not so likely that these places
will now become leading Global
commandment control centers okay
um because they don't simply don't have
that uh that economic trajectory so
that's something this positionality in
global economic systems has also been
taken into account concluding then I
think yeah the future how would it look
like
um this kind of freewheeling here but
it's it's kind of lightly and you can
see in the you know kind of current
developments uh in cities also amid
covet is that it's very likely that
these growing inequalities are only
going to increase
according to me you see that austerity
has been temporarily kind of uh forced
there's a lot of intervention linked to
covet there's again a discourse of a
strong state
but as you saw that you immediately send
a lot of official documents that it had
to be temporary and now you see a return
to a kind of discourse that there will
be again budget cuts need to be made et
cetera etc for instance in Flanders we
are preparing the digi from the digi
jump so our education needs to go
digital
but at the same time we have to have a
budget cut of 100 million euro
so
okay how do you marry those two I mean
for sure there's ways to become more
efficient but at the same time it's not
really credible okay
uh so nothing really has changed I think
in this micro narrative uh of austerity
so that's that's kind of continuing
and uh you could say the flexibilization
of the labor market it's still also
progressing okay
uh it will be different in different
kind of contexts but it's it's it's not
really going away uh migration as you
know
um and this is linked obviously to to
wider issues such as uh uh Global change
will simply be more people that will
have to rely on migration to still make
a living
uh which also means in a lot of cities
if you don't work on Social Security
minimum wage etc etc you will don't you
won't do anything about the uh the whole
discussion about the reserve Army of
Labor so these conditions for
exploitation
will remain in place
so that's kind of working at the at the
bottom end if you will
at the same time at the top end uh and
it's kind of returning a little bit to
the whole discussion about income
distribution at the very start
we see that there's some kind of Return
of the Gilded Age has
um Thomas picketti calls it so a period
in the in the 20th century where in the
19th century sorry uh where a lot of
um you could say personal protectories
were kind of shape there where you where
you already come from so it's a form of
patrimonial capitalism where it matters
more uh who your parents are than what
you do in terms of uh I choose this
profession or that profession I work
with choose to work hard etc etc
and that means that
um
an increasing uh part of of of wealth
is not based on on income but it's based
on other sources of return on assets so
you see that a lot of
a lot of groups that when you talk about
the one percent of the zero point one
percent their income is not
the remuneration of labor but holding
shares uh bonds etc etc
um so this kind of kind of explains why
people that depends on an income from
labor if there's no real wage increases
well you lose out on people that are
basically representing Capital that are
shareholders and that kind of runs away
and this kind of the research by by
picture looking at to the share of the
0.1 so not the one percent but the 0.1
percent
uh in the United States Britain Canada
and Australia
we're back in in the U.S at
um the 0.1 owning seven percent of
income right so 0.1 owns seven percent
of all income in in the US
so it's just just try to imagine what
that means so and it's it's and every
time you see uh economic growth and if
it's not automatic automatically
translated into an increase in wages
which is obviously a whole bargaining
process you see that the return on
Capital increases and but it runs away
from real income
um and I think that will be the main
discussion I think in the post-war era
what you had for instance the US is
extremely progressive taxation the
higher incomes were was taxation up to
70 it was considered normal
what you see now in in multiple
presidencies for instance in the US and
that has been relaxed there are now
counter Tendencies I would say corporate
taxation there's a whole debate about
that to what extent uh we need to kind
of increase that or standardize that it
is a kind of multi-level chess game
uh which will be hard to realize but at
least some things are going on that so I
think yeah at the top end I think I mean
if all goes normal there's no social
upheaval I think the strength will just
continue and the question is to what
extent to when is this socially feasible
to keep things together or will it
really pull apart and political and
other kind of terms when you think about
cities and then as the final point it
means that this function of cities is
becoming uh transformed as well and
maybe this links a little bit to what
Brett Christopher was talking about last
week is that cities become
basically safety deposit boxes for those
people that rely on wealth uh you can
think about absent renterism in London
there's all kinds of neighborhoods that
are owned for instance by people from uh
the Arab Persian Gulf that don't live in
London but just yeah and they don't even
bother to rent out parts of
Knightsbridge or Chelsea because they
don't care because they're the value of
these properties just increases so much
that
it's irrelevant whether you rent it out
another example is shell companies in
Manhattan the Time Warner Center
on average 30 million per Apartments I
think 80 percent of this case is bought
by shell companies which is basically
trusts within a trust within the trust
or whatever so it's somewhere in the
Cayman Islands or Bermuda trust that
boys these uh properties but you never
really know who's behind these shell
companies so it's a way to uh for which
individuals and corporations to buy into
the same profit property
to maintain the value of those assets to
store their wealth in places
and yeah to end on the final point it
means that the function of cities is
being transformed as
yeah as holders of value
uh primarily and according to Sasuke
assassin and the death I conclude
there's a real danger that a process of
deurbanization
is taking place in these leading world
and Global cities and the case of
abstinent terrorism is a good one
there's absolutely no life nobody is
living there it's a kind of pure
financial asset or it's an empty Tower
block where nobody lives
uh and it seems to be a very big
contradiction because when you think
about
bustling bustling world and Global
cities with a lot of innovation and
diversity etc etc
these are empty shells
there to store the value and the wealth
of a very very very very very very rich
people and I think it's a huge issue
that we should reflect on
okay thank you
[Music]
thank you uh I hope it was not too
depressing
um or maybe it that it is depressing and
that we do something about it
um