thank you
all right
welcome everybody
to
urban geography Urban social geography I
had to work a little bit to make the
live stream work I hope it does work
does anybody mind if I take off my mask
is that okay
if anybody's uncomfortable just let me
know
but I rely on my facial expressions
for Content uh how do you say that to
transfer content if you will
um so hi I'm David uh I'll be your
lecturer
and welcome to the course
um I'm very glad that we can
teach and have this uh in real life in
person
um I'll tell you more about
um the kind of hybrid character because
we'll also be recording the sessions and
live streaming this session
so I think the pandemic pandemic
conditions are still ongoing to allow if
you would doubt about any infection Etc
to follow the course remotely
uh I think this can be more evident I
think for the for the regular lectures
like we have today
um there's also a number of discussion
seminars there it will be a bit less
evident uh and there's also excursions
for some in there yeah I mean uh I can't
stream an Excursion uh but for the
lectures it will be an alternative and
you also have a recording at the end
um of the lecture series and this could
be an interesting instrument to study
um so yeah that's also how students have
used it last year
okay so what are the objectives of the
entire course urban geography or Urban
social geography well just summed up
there
I won't go too to deep into this uh just
here and now but just that you know what
you're signing up for uh for the people
that are still uh shopping around I
would say
um the objective of the course is to
give an introduction to key theoretical
debates in urban studies more
specifically uh focusing on spatial and
geographical dimensions hence it's not
um introduction to Urban studies but
introduction to Urban Geography
and and this is kind of uh kind of
signaling what we find important as
lecturers
to adopt a theoretically pluralist
approach toward Urban studies
you'll see that and I'll get to that in
a second that we work with different
teachers lectures we all have their own
backgrounds and they may be slightly
different some people work more on a
political economy perspective others
start from adopting a perspective from
diversity ethnicity yet others are
interested in
uh issues of culture then the broad
sense and others work in a kind of
Mobility framework and we'll try to
bring those things together in one
course but what is kind of uniting the
course that I think a spatial social
spatial understanding of contemporary
cities okay so that's what you're
signing up for if you hate cities this
is the moment to leave the room
um I Told You So So This Is The Old Mill
panel
um that we present you my sincerest
apologies
um but I think that hopefully diversity
across the curriculum is a bit better
than within this course but
um we're selecting from the people that
that can teach so please accept my
apologies for that but still we hope
that we can inform you from a range of
perspectives uh also including I would
say feminist perspectives and they will
pop up here and there
especially when we start talking about
issues of culture and issues of mobility
and transmit but you see those
Dimensions returning so who is part of
the teaching team well that's next few
months he's an expert in issues of
segregation and living in diversity both
from her
he is an expert you could say in
Creative Industries cultural geographies
of the cities of the city boytech
goblovsky
he wrote a PhD on fairfree public
transportation and he's an expert in
urban studies slash transportation
geographies and recently is really
pushing for kind of the colonial
agenda in transport geographies and
finally there's me
um I Won't Say I'm an expert in anything
I'm an expert in coordinating this
course by now uh and I come from a
background of world and Global cities so
what happens to cities amid
globalization uh how should we study
that analyze that well on the main
debates
and personally I've been looking a lot
into the geographies of Islamic Finance
as a way to understand I would say
Middle Eastern processes of urbanization
but that was my PhD currently I'm more
working in teams around Financial
geographies more widely thinking about
what typifies Global cities as command
and control centers all kind of things
that I'll be killing you with in the
next few sessions so I won't say
anything more about that so that's the
teaching team
and so this plural voices to some extent
and also there's also a plural audience
um so I was already referring to groups
of students uh by pointing to that this
is the urban social geography course but
also it's also the urban geography
Course and there are slight differences
between both courses but especially for
uh the lectures that makes complete
sense
um to to bring you together in a room so
we have the master in urban studies they
will be a master please raise your hands
and voices
okay thanks for the hands
uh this for citizens
yeah so that's even more exotic these
people travel around Europe in the next
two years
uh then we have our own exotic species
uh from The Bachelor of geography uh
maybe raise your hand
welcome and we also have
um urbanists in the room
um so please show me where you are these
people also combine this with with an
actual job uh so that's also why we
teach at night to accommodate that and
these are people that have quite a bit
of professional expertise so I would say
this is already a global Urban map here
uh confined in this room
um I would say enjoy this mix and try to
pick each other's brains as much as
possible I think just by comparing Urban
experiences
Supreme casual conversation you can
already learn quite a bit I would say
so similarities
um
all students have lectures and
discussion seminars this discussion
seminar for capacity reasons will be
split but I'll tell you more about that
for urban social geographers so that's
what mass and urban studies and for
Citizens we're kind of new to Belgium
uh we also offer kinds of excursions and
I'll say more about that as well and
these are mandatory fun
so how does the course look like uh
there's nine lectures
which we will try to make as interactive
as possible but there will be a degree
of me and US telling you stuff the
discussion seminars will be way more uh
flipped if you will where the content is
prepared by by you and then we discuss
this in the classroom so it's a bit of a
give and take there
we organized the
um the lectures in modules so you could
say there's four modules one organized
by me which deals with a general
introduction as you'll note today and
then we'll delve into theories
of world and Global cities looking at
what explains their Genesis what their
characteristics are uh why it matters
and what kind of the main processes are
that characterize Urban Societies in
world and Global cities and one of the
main debates there is
to what extent are these places
polarized
either in terms of ethnicity income
levels professional levels Etc
with depth Sensitivity I would say to
uneven is within cities uh I'll pass on
the word to an experiments
we'll focus more on processes of urban
segregation we're looking at the spatial
processes behind that
and one of the main debates I would say
in uh issues of diversity and ethnicity
is to what extent there are neighborhood
effects
is the fact that you live within a
certain neighborhood affecting your
future trajectories life chances Etc so
that's one of the main debates there and
there's pros and cons there's Arguments
for and against the existence of
neighborhood effects
um then we passed on to uh boss from
Hood who will be talking about uh you
could say the cultural approach
uh thinking about different cultures of
urban research and then so this deals
with various methods and mostly with you
could say uh an older cultural turn uh
within geography in the social sciences
more widely which was took place after
the second world war and then more
recently in the 80s and 90s okay the
real cultural turn where was all about
um a turn towards more qualitative
research methods other sources uh that
that could be studied and that could
serve the study herbis Urban societies
and then this is also mobilized in the
study of urban cultures where it's about
creative Industries the lives of artists
Etc which is a big element in a lot of
I'd say discourses on the creative city
as you may know the work of Richard
Florida it was all hype I would say 20
years ago that all cities should be
geared toward becoming creative in one
way or another so hence also large focus
on the literature on issues of arts and
culture as it is connected to the issues
of Urban Development
and the final part is with vojtek
blovsky
looking into through the lens of of
transport and mobility and what we can
learn about cities and he will be
talking about different kinds of agendas
that's typify I would say
transport studies all the way from
neoclassical views that connected to
Urban growth development to
sustainability issues which is a
paradigm in an office Zone and then
he'll be yeah drawing on his own
research looking more into what he calls
critical perspectives on Urban transport
where it's all about yeah who actually
benefits from the current Transportation
regime what are issues of inequality who
makes uh decisions about in Transport
Systems Etc so
I think by the end you should have a
kind of a 360 degree overview of uh of
debates in urban geography obviously
um we don't know everything far from
that so it's a selection of debates
um we could generate another curriculum
based with other forms of expertise but
it's also an exercise in trying to
um critically triangulate different
perspectives on the city through
different kind of tips which come with
their own methodologies Etc so that's uh
the setup of the course
and these take place here uh you just
about fit in this room so I'm extremely
happy and pleased and will take place on
Mondays between five and seven
um let's see what the quality of the
streaming is uh I if I would open
panopto which is my program I could
expect a stream of comments about that
but so I'll evaluate that but the the
idea is that everything is streamed as
well people that can't make it because
of yeah conflicts with work
um or well they might have time but
can't reach VB because it's immediately
uh after uh the working day I mean I
would understand that you would
um yeah follow remotely
um and sessions will also be recorded
on the other hand it's a kind of strict
recommendation to try to be here as much
as possible because I mean one of the
insights from the corona crisis yeah
when you watch remotely sometimes it's
hard to maintain discipline I also
recognize that with all kinds of zoomy
things and zoom
um I don't know seminars
so having a habit of coming to vud
coming to class I think it's also a way
to stay connected not only to the course
content but also to one another so
you could uh fall back on this but I
would not recommend uh a full digital
semester uh in any case so but it's it's
there and it will be your resource if
all goes well uh at the very end
so yeah we're here
a bit more on the discussion seminar so
yes please there was a question
foreign
yeah it's to have some slack uh in this
room we'll aim for two hours but we
already started like five minutes late
today
um so don't uh be upset if we take until
10 past seven but the idea is that it
would be two hours
um yeah depends a bit on what happens
yes
Excuse me
yes I'll post them online after each
session
um
yeah and if you go to the canvas page
and I guess some of you are not yet
uh be able to access uh come with us but
that should be resorted quite soon
you'll see at the starting page and I
made all kinds of modules there's a kind
of an outline module and there's a
module per session
where you'll see
um the required readings some additional
readings outposts a link to
um no I won't do it there I'll post a
link to the recordings any announcements
there will be session slides linked to
um to each of these modules so I mean I
think it's neatly organized so you
should find your way there basically all
content will be provided online for
people that cannot access
um canvas yet
please find somebody who has access and
try to share I would say the course
outline
um so please be aware that some of you
don't have access yet I think by next
week it should be okay
so yeah let's see
so yeah next to the lectures
um there's discussion seminars where we
basically use the reader
um to advance our insights into these
discussions around urban geography and
we take the various modules so four
modules and we organize that in one
block where we'll have a discussion
which is basically prepared by uo and
different kind of smaller presentations
and then we have a collective discussion
about
uh it's also in the outline so it's a
different kind of series of discussion
seminars because you can't have a debate
with 200 people in the room
uh so it's more like a classroom format
uh one for the master in urban studies
one track for four cities and then uh
also one for geographers and urbanists
and one go
um for mus and for cities it won't be on
Mondays it's on different times uh
during the week it's in uh your time
schedule
please check uh if you've already
identified where the time schedule is
also when the room information is
um and try to notice down in your agenda
because there will be an assignment
later that a small one but I would say
an important one okay please note that
down in your return
um also note that the lectures at some
point will have three lectures now but
then we will Skip One Week
uh before we go to the next module then
two classes then we Skip One Week etc
etc and it is because on certain Mondays
after module will have a discussion
seminar with geographers and urbanists
because it's we can't expect work
students to be here during the day
um so we will take these Mondays and
also please take notes for uh
myths and four cities that you don't
have to show up for I would say four
sessions uh on Mondays I mean you're
welcome to join uh but there will be no
lectures there will be discussion
seminars for another group okay just so
you know it could be a week also to
prepare a little bit more uh for the
discussion seminar that you you may have
yourself
okay I'll say more about the assignment
link to that in a second then Urban
social geography excursions uh there's a
lot of administration here apparently
um
we offer four excursions but because of
the size of the group this is for Miss
and for cities uh we'll have to
um yeah force you to make a short Choice
um so there's four excursions one uh led
by me here in Brussels which deal with
Brussels as a global City uh next few
months takes you to Antwerp to deal with
issues of Social and ethnic segregation
Minds that this is a bike trip so maybe
some of you are less comfortable with uh
biking just taken to this into account
others may be extremely experienced and
fight the rates uh too slow and also
don't want to join
um then there's an Excursion to show
everyone Again by Nick
and then wojtek will take you on
Excursion in Brussels around the team of
everyday Mobility
um so for excursions you have to choose
two
um this is also something that I I um
mentioned in this uh Google Sheets or
spreadsheets
um please try to go for one Brussels
Excursion and one other Excursion
because we want to kind of give
everybody the opportunity to go beyond
Brussels otherwise your remain stuck in
the Brussels bubble uh so there's please
select either Antwerp I would say or
either Charlotte yes the hunter bike
trip is actually like right here by
people from Russell's pointer no okay
you go by train and then
I don't think it's even the entire day
but at some point you'll go to the
locked Bowl which is kind of a
social housing product project from I
think the 60s if I'm not mistaken uh and
to reach that you'll go by by bike
um
yeah some people feel less comfortable
doing that uh
you could also say we have uh one month
to get trained uh so in any case it
could be an opportunity but take this
into account uh yes it was a question
and bring our own way no no no no no no
no no no no yeah well there's a bike
rental yeah Nick has arranged bikes are
there any other questions about this
uh not yet no uh but typically I mean
this would be communicated they start in
the early morning and the end at the end
of the day
um
yeah so it's a full day
see
okay
so please uh go to this um spreadsheet
and fill out your preferences
all right
okay I hope this uh the skills it
and fill out your preferences uh as soon
as possible and no later than next week
okay so there's limited capacity for
each of these
um excursions
so please uh take care of it
all right a bit more about the course
materials
um as you will see on canvas there's a
reader with what I call required reading
so I expect everybody
reach this at least once and preferably
in advance of advance of each lecture
it's a kind of way to keep track of of
the discussion
and there will also be additional
readings and these additional readings
will kind of be the resource that we
will use in the discussion seminars
[Music]
um
yeah the rest I've said already
um session slides and recordings
available after each session
and then this is weird and then
um yeah you'll have access via compost a
bit more about evaluation and great
distribution
so this assignment in the discussion
seminar
um is
um a critical summary and it accounts
for one-fifth of your total grade so
it's a kind of uh
a way to to be remunerated if you will
for your efforts during the semester but
the whole idea is that we digest our way
through
the literature and through the reader
that we do this in a collective way
um so what is the assignment
um all students have to read the
required readings but then
um
I have no idea what to do actually
uh let me just check this is off
[Music]
yeah no idea
okay let's let's just try to continue
um
so part two you'll be invited to
critically summarize one additional
reading so it could be a paper on Beirut
for instance when we're talking about
global cities
and
um
yeah I'll announce the schedule uh for
that you'll have 10 minutes of
presentation
and what you're asked to do is that you
focus on a core quote or uh passage or
excerpt from the text that you kind of
use this as an introduction to the text
that you tell us all about the main
argument of the authors
that you connect this to The Wider
debate to the literature that we've been
discussing yeah we've been talking about
world and Global cities yeah what how do
you connect that to this particular
study that we're reading about and then
toward the end you want to give some
kind of a critical critical reflection
so you can also start with the critical
reflection and weave that through the
entire presentation but you should end
with a number of discussion questions uh
which we can use to kick start the
debate so 10 minutes you give kind of a
crash course summary of what the paper
is about why it matters what we learn
from it and how we connect that to to
the discussions that we already have
so that's the critical summary a bit
more on that second I'm sorry
yes okay yeah because otherwise it will
be an endless stream of presentations
it's something that you can do with two
um so yeah it's a and and both of you
should uh take the floor at some point
yeah so the idea is that it's a bit of a
balanced exercise and also try to make
this an integrated exercise not somebody
one person saying okay this is the
argument but then the other person not
knowing the argument but having come up
with with the neural questions so to
give a stupid example that's not the
idea so it really try to discuss the
text together and come to some kind of a
shared understanding there and already
debating this amongst the two of you
would already be something worthwhile I
think
yeah
yeah the largest part of the evaluation
is a written exam
and this is basically
um a way to test you could say your
knowledge of urban of the urban theories
and Concepts that we've been discussing
throughout the semester throughout the
different modules
there's no uh particular focus on
memorizing things by heart but it's
about
mobilizing your knowledge to study
empirical examples cases Etc
and I think we'll give examples of that
throughout the course
for instance when you think about
[Music]
um
culture as an as a
say Urban Development strategy you may
get a question about okay there's a new
soundtrack
next to the Brussels Canal Zone to what
extent is this a a case of cultural and
regeneration
discuss and then you would would have to
interpret the case on that base so it's
not just about reproduction that's about
applying what you've learned critically
reflecting on the different concepts Etc
and you'll use the readings the slides
the recordings personal notes from
seminars and lectures and yeah those who
went on a disc on an Excursion can also
always refer to
um to the filters to actually get a bit
of more inspiration
so that's uh the setup of the great
distribution
um and yeah a bit more still about this
critical summary
um just a number of questions that you
could use as a source of information
inspiration or a template
so what is the key message from the
paper why is it important what is the
key argument uh what have you learned
and really try to be as nuanced as
possible can you compare the argument
being made with other perspectives or a
perspective from the required readings
or anything
foreign
important
yeah this is getting a bit weird now
yeah I have no idea
when I move I have the impression
um
okay let's try uh to continue
[Music]
yeah okay
I wonder what would happen if I would
push the out button but then I think
maybe
you know it might be singles or
something
yeah okay
do you really think that would be the
case yeah
yeah interference but everybody switch
off their phones is that an option it's
like 100 phones being switched off is
that possible to try yeah
but I don't really find it I think it's
necessary
yeah
but yeah
I think that's the most I can do
actually
maybe yeah let's try okay maybe we'll
have to live with it or I can sort it
out later
um
what happens if I
go this one
foreign
[Music]
excuse me
unknowingly
okay I'm not a genius this is clear by
now
um
all right uh and um yeah final point
that I already set this uh try something
um the debate that's that's what uh what
it's all about in the end okay
no you have to do this one
one so what I'll do as soon as I have
the full overviews who had actually
taking this course but make a schedule
uh and then you'll have to present once
yeah with somebody else
um
campus or
um it's not on canvas it's a different
kind of Google Sheets but you can click
the link in the in the slides that I
just uh showed so yeah
um
for those who don't have access to
converse uh maybe ask somebody who has
to share this link or just ask somebody
to to sign you up uh via this link
um okay
is that clear
there's a whole lot of administration
sorry for that uh but that's how it goes
I guess so I hope everything is clear
yes please
yeah but I'll make the the distribution
oh yeah because otherwise if we do this
bottom up then
it will be very very difficult uh so
I'll yeah but all texts are interesting
I would say
um
so so that's the idea but uh it might
take a while because I think for for
most and four cities it's quite clear so
that could go fast maybe for geographers
and uh stat it could last a little bit
longer because sometimes it's unclear
who is actually in the course but for
most unfortunately I think this can go
actually quite fast and then you can
also plan a little bit uh work in the
semester
um okay
together
all right
so uh let's turn to some content then
uh and let's start our trip
what we'll be discussing in Earth today
is basically what we'll do is we'll
deconstruct uh the title course
um and ask four questions
what is the Urban
what is the city
what is geography
and what does it mean when I say I'm
critical
arguably critical is not in the title
but it could have been right
it may seem consensible but I think
asking these very blue sky questions
perhaps uh could get us closer to an
understanding what urban geography is
about so you can also start already
start thinking a little bit about
what we would mean with the term the
urban and uh the city
maybe as I take you to a number of
exhibits you can draw some inspiration
for that and you can make a list and
then in a few minutes you'll be invited
to write a very short one minute paper
it doesn't have to be Pros where you
collect a little bit of ideas on what
those two terms could be okay
probably and one of the reasons why some
of you have studied uh or selected the
master in urban studies for four cities
is because you have been seduced by a
discourse or a frame of we live in the
urban age processes occur increasingly
in cities therefore we need to
understand cities if we want to make
sense of our futures or something like
that and this would be some kind of a
framework or repertoire
um that the world uh that United Nations
sorry calls a framework of the urban age
and it's a kind of frame that says well
we've long been a you could say rural
global population or a rural species but
at some point and someday in 2005 we
became an urban species and ever since
uh basically world population growth
will be Urban growth so increasingly we
are undergoing as a global Society a
process of urbanization where more and
more people
become Urban so this kind of Mantra of
the urban age has been around since
about 2007 so immediately after this
historical Urban transition
and it has been repeated as a kind of a
motivation for increased attention at
the cities so and there's something
behind that obviously because there is
indeed a transition to the urban and
this observable here empirically roughly
in the 1950s about 70 percent of of the
population global population lived in
rural areas and only 30 percent in urban
areas it was 50 50 apparently around
2005 and now it's reversed uh or it's
going to be reversed by 2050 expectation
is that 70 of the global population will
live in cities okay
so that's kind of the framework of the
urban age that is very much kind of uh
projected by the United Nations by all
kinds of uh world uh World reports and
that is kind of taken over by both
critical and more uncritical uh voices
in the debate
McKinsey would also use this to argue
for more consultancy into uh urban
government or something
but it's just as much Mike Davis when he
talks about uh cities of slums he'll use
this as a critical framework to refer to
make his kind of his work important
so what is behind this is an assumed
process or an identifiable process of
globalized urbanization so the process
by which
the urban condition if you will is
becoming a global phenomenon
and urbanization used to be something
that was not Global at all and if you
look at a few maps by Michael patrolling
uh who has a great handbook uh on on
cities
you see that it was very much say a
Western European or Northern American
Affair so UK
was extremely urbanized European
continents
also quite and the us as well apparently
Alaska was also extremely urbanized
the rest of the world was on the map but
not really on the map of urbanization uh
it didn't occurred there
fast forward to the 1950s you see that
this process is spreading uh especially
you could say throughout the European
continents throughout the Commonwealth
you see Australia and Canada popping up
also I could say more
developmentalists say to Latin America
uh USSR
and uh to a very very limited extent uh
Africa and then especially the market
not so much in Asia as you can see
we're moving forward 1990s
we see that this process is both
extending geographically and I uh
intensified so a lot of countries or
quite a few countries in Europe have now
an urbanization rate apparently between
80 and 100 percent which is kind of the
ratio between population that lives in
cities on the total population so
between 80 and 100 of people live in
cities according to these definitions
again note Australia uh it's a
tremendously urbanized uh continent if
you will obviously this is a projection
of the ratio on the entire territory
okay so uh almost all Australians live
in cities but that doesn't mean that the
entirety of Australia is a city okay
Maps could lie to some extent okay so we
may be exaggerating some things when we
think about uh
I don't know the use of Natural
Resources or environmental impact uh
that's that's something that we could
think about
um what is also important is kind of a
different kind of figure is that there's
some kind of a decoupling between
processes of
one of a better word uh economic growth
or what some people call uh more
problematically development
and urbanization when you go back to say
the history of urbanization in the 19th
century it was a pro a process that was
intimately linked to industrialization
economic growth but also obviously as we
know uneven development within Western
European cities
there was a lot of economic development
in the UK cities like Manchester uh
because there was a boom of the textile
industry it led to economic growth but
it also led to huge uh Urban
inequalities but in any case at the
aggregate level you could say at the
level of the country or the city there
was an economic Improvement
and that connected to the growth of
these cities
what you find in you could say the last
20 years and this has something to do
with all kinds of neoliberal policies
that work at the global scale especially
when you talk about Asia and
Africa you could say
um uh the Strategic adjustment plans
that have been rolled out there by uh
organizations such as the international
monetary fund and its sister or brother
the World Bank which has basic basically
opened up the borders of these conflict
countries to foreign investment as this
would uh Kickstart growth okay
in reality one could argue that this has
produced produced a dependent form of
growth or you could say an exploitative
relation between the global periphery
and the global core okay but at the same
time has initiated and this is kind of
the argument by Mike Davis an implosion
of the countryside rural living in these
places
um became untenable because a lot of uh
it's a subsidized activities or
state-controlled activities were rolled
back for instance in agriculture this
led to huge deprivation on the
countryside and in varying degrees a
search to go for the battle better life
than in a lot of African majoriences
Okay so
if we thought that it could be a sign of
Economic Development we could say in the
19th century and even if we take up with
a pinch of salt that's still not
possible to say in uh when you talk
about urbanization rates for instance in
in Africa or parts of Asia okay
now uh so and if you look at the rates
of urbanization we're talking about
seven to eight percent in some uh
sub-Saharan African countries whereas if
you look at the older industrial areas
or urbanized areas it's somewhere
between one and two percent still growth
so we're doubling I would say in 36
years uh if it's two percent uh but far
far less
um
so yes globalized urbanization that also
shows when you look at the hit list of
largest cities
um it was very much uh euro-american if
you will
uh the industrial heart heartlands some
exceptions Shanghai for instance uh
Japan
1950s but then it starts to really
diversify and become actually a matter
of not Euro America but Asia Latin
America Etc and a number of leading
cities in terms of population
in the 1950s now well down the list to
take New York for instance others okay
so this is kind of the thesis that
urbanization is now a globalized
phenomenon there's still different kind
of patterns behind that just you can
look into this at home because it may be
a bit small to actually read here
um
some places when you look at Europe uh
we're talking about 80 urbanization
still in Africa despite its uh large
urbanization rate
still foremost a rural Society so even
this despite a kind of a global
transition toward globalized
urbanization that's quite a bit of
regional differences that we need to
take into account
and that brings me to the next slide
this famous image that I stole it from
Neil Brenner uh uh where Batman beats
the crap out of Robin because he begins
to talk about
um this urban urban age again I think
it's a moment to really uh question
critically what is meant by the urban
agent to what extent we should really
believe and go along in this Urban age
frame and and a very nice paper I
haven't put it in the reader because
there's already quite a bit of of things
in there
is a paper by a new Brenner and
Christian Smith from 2014.
and they really deconstruct uh this
narrative and they point to two elements
one is
the notion or the idea uh or the
observation that we're living in the
urban age could be a statistical
artifact so it's a matter of how we
measure things
and there's actually quite a bit of
Divergence over time but also across
countries as to how a city is actually
measured
in some contexts
um
there's a city
um something counts as a city as of 1
000 inhabitants in other countries it
would be ten thousand and it would have
a tremendous impact on how we calculate
the urbanization
okay so this is more fundamentally uh
what they argue is that there's a huge
nationalist bias in how the urban is
defined I'm not saying that there's 200
definitions but for instance when you
look at at the work the work of
um
of organizations like the United Nations
they have been struggling to set a
standard definition of what the urban is
there's still quite a bit of diversity
and when you look at the work of urban
geographers for the past 50 or 60 years
this is a kind of a recurring issue
right so what they say is that yes there
are real empirical caps in our knowledge
here of of of the rate of urbanization
uh and therefore it's almost meaningless
to say as in some day in 2005 we became
more urban are we by now our Urban
species so it's kind of yes there's a
broad trajectory uh toward urbanization
but there's a very large bandwidth that
that we should consider and in fact it
could be more interesting to look at
different kind of urbanization
trajectories because it's it's dealing
with all kinds of different processes
that need to be studied as historically
unfolding rologists then being captured
in a figure of 75 for this so it's more
of an invitation to start looking at
things so this also connects to the
second argument
is that the urban as it is being
measured by a process of urbanization is
somewhat of a chaotic abstraction it
means that
um
different kind of things that are not
necessarily related are packed together
to define a certain process
and and this is something that for
instance a new Brenner and Chris
Christian Smith have also worked on
later as they discussed the notion of
planetary urbanization I invite you to
look into that debate their argument is
that the urban in fact as a condition as
a way of life or as a system of
production or exploitation does not
neatly overlay actual morphologies of
cities
so the urban uh may have nothing to do
with a concentrated uh blob of people in
space or with sitting within a
particular jurisdiction it could be
connected to suburbs etc etc so and what
they kind of are concerned with is when
you talk about rates of urbanization is
that you classify or categorize quite
diverse uh ways of of living into one
category of the urban uh and an even
more problematic so hence we don't
really learn anything about it and what
is even more problematic is that the
rule is defined as the non-urban
and is thereby
yeah not studied at all as kind of a
left behind place that only exists in
opposition to what really counts which
is then the way forward which is urban
living so that's kind of their arguments
just to kick start a little bit you're
thinking uh on this
since we now have uh I would say 60
seconds for a one minute paper Okay so
please think a little bit you can talk
to your neighbor
um in any direction about what the urban
is what a city is and what the
differences between the two right
thank you
[Music]
very much
those were 120 seconds
right here
okay
[Applause]
for almost three minutes for the one
week paper
please
what is a city what's the urban and
what's the difference
okay
so what's the difference then what do
you say
why is the urban a place
oh maybe not
because there are quite density of many
layers and cities
okay and why do you think it's the
reverse I think elements of the oven can
exist everywhere I don't think elements
of the city exist everyone so the city
defined as a dense place is kind of
identifiable in space whereas the urban
could yeah connect to everywhere
potentially okay
other ideas
or inequality or like in an infield
environment this is something you can
touch
so one is about you could say concrete
lumps of material yeah
about Urban societies yeah
other ideas yeah
yeah I think that connects a little bit
to what what we say processes and then
maybe outcomes products of urbanization
okay now other ideas
Etc
and that wouldn't be captured by the
notion of a city
if not cities can be
places of extreme exclusivity okay
um of dedicated to a very specific class
so a lot not all cities have
same the Notions of having public
transport that is Affordable for
everyone but I would say that if you're
talking about the urban you're already
thinking of it in terms of how do we
organize this mass group of people okay
and how do we get order into
um
so it's about the club projects
particular values perhaps behind
policies to organize cities we are
building on the process idea that was
mentioned earlier
okay
any other ideas still
yeah I think maybe for a city I think of
it having
focus of like
being people and maybe that also nothing
on to sort of like a governance
structure versus for urban I maybe think
more about
what is the like level of density and
the living situation and people okay
okay or like a descriptor versus like a
um
thing that everybody is like linked to
or participating in yeah yeah yeah okay
yeah there was a hand still behind
somewhere yeah at the back
um
[Music]
yeah so it's an administrative unit
which elected officials Etc that
accounts within the boundaries of a
certain space and not beyond that
perhaps
all right so inductively you make my
made my next slide's completely
redundant uh so yeah one of the ideas
and importantly to say I mean with
Brandon Schmidt it's kind of a
sensitivity that the urban and cities
are not necessarily the same
I think
the point is not to say or to Define
clearly what
a city is or the urban is but you offer
different kind of perspectives
um different kind of lenses
on on the question and by offering
different kind of perspectives
are emerging from different kind of
questions we may actually learn more
about the process of urbanization so it
is not kind of one ruling explanation
but there's many ways of looking at it
okay
um but I think yeah we'll get to
something more so one idea is that it's
about
a concentration of people it's also also
about the concentration of stuff
lump of material the built environment
yeah so it's something with density
something also a lot of I think
urbanists would recognize so it's the
built environment built up space that
clearly gives morphological uh signs
that at some point we have arrived in
the city be it high rises
a lot of of congestion uh that would be
markers of characteristics of so that's
kind of not necessarily Urban but it's a
kind of a marker of what is a city
then fetching a little bit more into
you could say the overlays between what
is urban
and how it's the borders cities
um cities are sometimes defined as uh
the opposite of the non-city as I was
saying uh as the opposite of the rural
and then a number of planning contexts
I'm thinking about for instance the
Netherlands it will actually be if you
look at the satellite image it will be
identifiable where one urban area ends
then there's Countryside and then
something else starts
but
yeah in many contexts especially in the
Flemish one for instance this is a
reality where you won't get really far
it's kind of you're not sure where the
where the city ends you you end up with
some kind of um
large boulevards that connect to yeah
villages in in the middle of nowhere
there's a lot of built up uh stuff along
these uh schustees Etc
um and there's a lot of activities
actually taking place outside of the
core areas of urban agglomerations
there's suburbs uh there's actually an
intensification of activities in suburbs
um
so yeah
um what does it still mean to talk about
the city as being opposed to the
non-city the rural it generates all
kinds of fuzzy categories so purely
morphologically you may end up
um being in trouble now okay yes
[Music]
that's for me
the city is something that is
that's perpetually becoming something
um
energy where we can experiment with our
identities and
yeah yeah I agree uh we haven't covered
this yet so maybe we're we're talking
about about this so it's
yeah the urban or a city uh is the place
of an urban life but perhaps the urban
also selections Beyond uh the city
itself so Urban living could also be
taking place in the suburbs but it's
some kind of an idea that within
um
Within These spaces uh a different kind
of society and a different kind of
behavior uh Norms values can take place
um so it's a distinctive way of life but
still it could be
um a very different kind of energy that
we may be talking about or a different
kind of bones that actually uh ties
people together
so just compare slum living with Loft
living it's a very distinct way of urban
living but they've been Mo both be
characterized as something else than
ruralism okay so
um and there's this big debate I would
say in urban sociology between what is
now distinct about the urban way of life
as some kind of an assumption that you
move from Community uh to society and
communities think about rural
communities where you have all kinds of
uh personal relations with neighbors
it's a small villages and this gets
formalized anonymized as soon as you get
to cities because distances become
larger because there's all kinds of
institutional roles there's a division
of labor that we'll get to in a second
and it becomes more abstract you take a
certain function within society which is
less mediated my social relations that
was kind of the argument uh by a lot of
sociologists also in the 19th century
that tried to capture the process of
urbanization so it's a distinctive way
of life it's not just buildings and
humps and of material it's it's it's
more than that
another way of looking at it and with
internet uh by you here at front it's
also about economic relations that tie
together people um think about flows of
energy flows of of work flows of ideas
uh flows of data
um that's uh that connects the
inhabitants of a certain place and it
would be more uh agglomerated in some
places than others but they wouldn't be
necessarily confined to you could say
the core of metropolitan areas
so the city is also the place where
divisions of labor emerge and there's
this famous picture by Adam Smith's
needle Factory or pin Factory uh where
uh cities are kind of a microcosm of an
uh a workshop where different kind of
tasks that used to be integrated in uh
in pin making are kind of cut up and
collectively places uh produce a certain
economic product okay so there's inputs
needed by different kind of suppliers
different kind of specialized workers do
end up with a product okay so
historically that has been a way where
Urban Elites could emerge that could
also kind of manage this process that
could also absorb part of the Surplus
that was being generated by a more
efficient uh efficient division of labor
standardization of work for instance and
it was also you could say in a more
critical framework the place where
uneven development and urban
inequalities actually have their Origins
okay so it produced more efficiency it
increased the urban Surplus if you will
but not everybody benefited so a complex
division of labor the idea that there
are a collaboration Effects by being in
a certain place
economic agents for instance will
benefit from from their presence because
they have specialized inputs Etc that's
kind of the realm of urban economics
Urban economic geographies that try to
capture that process
enough is obviously when you talk about
uh divisions of labor about these
energies that go around these also
structure
um Urban spaces and you could say Urban
class relations in a particular way
so
you could apply some kind of a
regulationist perspective here thinking
about
um
we could say different eras of uh of of
cities
as being engaged in particular
production processes pre-capitalist
cities for instance at the top left then
the typical newly industrializing cities
uh top right then going bottom left to
for the cities and then you could say
contemporary cities that are kind of
both exploded and imploded at the same
time with Rising densities at the edges
and also a re-intensification of build
up areas in the in the very core and the
return of activities there so a regular
a regular regulations perspective is
also kind of what Dory Massey will be
talking about she was a famous economic
geographers economic geographer from
1980s and she was also one of the main
critical voices and trying to understand
how particular forms of capitalism leave
their imprint on society in general and
on Urban Societies in particular she was
interested in regions but it also can be
applied
um to cities so yeah you had a really uh
a very hierarchical Society in general I
mean there's a huge generalization here
in medieval cities where the core was an
elite realm uh with some domestic
servants then there was a kind of a
layer of the lower classes and then
basically the outcasts with the number
of ethnic communities this I mean
there's a huge generalization but it's
kind of a guiding model uh that is it's
it's set to hold when you think about
industrializing cities it was kind of
thing and this is uh Chicago for sure
and we'll be talking with Nick more
about Chicago as it became a model of of
the industrial city in the early 20th
century uh a lot of industrial activity
in the commercial
um Heart of the City and then radiating
out uh in terms of you could say classes
working men's houses and then further on
more Elite cities people neighborhoods
people that could actually afford to
commute to the city center
then after the second world war if you
look at the bottom left it's a kind of
the poorest city where capitalism was
regulated in a particular way where the
Surplus that was being created by
capitalist production think about all
these factories mass production was
being shared by the working class so
this is kind of the typical American
dream it typifies American cities but it
depends also to provide European cities
where we had a massive round of
suburbanization uh the good life where
you could live far removed from
um from where you worked
compute by car and it was a way to kind
of spatially redistribute the surface
that was being generated in cities okay
that's a kind of a Harvard David
harveying interpretation of
suburbanization is not just a lifestyle
it's also a spatial form of how
capitalism uh of in that period worked
okay
and then kind of finally
um this kind of growth at the periphery
we see a kind of an outward movement you
can say the urbanization of Suburbia all
kinds of knowledge identity activities
that are starting to take place at the
edges a lot of City centers that are
losing functions this kind of historical
process in the 70s and 80s a lot of
derelict areas Brownfield areas which
are then in the subsequent decades
increasingly becoming the places where
you have waves of gentrification a
return of capital uh to City centers etc
etc
all this and I'm trying to hugely
summarize and generalize here because
it's a kind of Ideal typical approach
um diversity that is increasing in a lot
of cities new pockets of exclusiveness
and exclusion on the other hand so
cities also becoming increasingly
polarized Etc so the urban is is
different depending on the period you're
talking about it could be characterized
differently depending on where you are
and in what period you're talking about
[Music]
bottom left and right
yeah you could say that I mean
um in some handbooks it would be called
the Ford City this one and this would be
the post for this city which is kind of
exopolis there's not one and
identifiable Horror in the metropolitan
area
um whereas this was still very much in
relation before but it captures the
difference you could call it modernity
um yes but that's more referred to you
could say a discussion of planning
approaches uh modernist planning for
instance where it was okay we're going
to organize the city in zones here is
residential function here we have
industrial function but but you're right
in that sense especially in the Forest
City it was uh at the larger scale
managed like that and it was also where
a lot of urbanists come to reaction uh
was launched against uh later on
um
think about the figure of Jane Jacobs
who basically said well with Mother's
Fleming this hand there's a top-down
approach doesn't have anything to do
with with urban life in us and of its
own so we have to take stock of that to
start thinking about a different way of
planning so
modernism would be a marker I would say
of uh again yeah of urban Society but
also about planning Traditions uh that
have produced before this city
and then another way and this wasn't
really mentioned is yeah the urban or
the city is also kind of a projector of
symbolic power
um
it sends a message to the world and this
is becoming uh I mean goes back to the
20 the 12th and the 13th century where
uh the evil cities and Flanders had the
highest wanted to have the highest
building or some jiminiano in the 14th
century and Northern Italy
um
had something to do with corporate power
Merchant power but also showing the
Liberties of cities vis-a-vis uh
territorial states which were then still
feudal states in the Middle Ages
you see that this is becoming much more
globalized and that's the content of
these messages is also very diverse you
have the CCTV building in Beijing which
is some kind of a representation of if
it's authoritarian power of the Chinese
Central State over China but also extra
territorially as the World Trade Center
and
yeah we I don't think we need to
deconstruct that and I mean there's a
lot of images
um
I mean about acclaimed imperialism by
the US which was fasted in the
commercial uh interests or the
commercial power of the superpower of
the US
um which then also became uh a symbol of
uh of Oppression if you will and made it
a a target for uh for attacks
um as we all know so it's it's a highly
contested uh or arbitrary symbol there
and often it's also kind of used in
speculative
developments you could say uh Khalifa in
the Middle East and Dubai
um it's kind of part of a wider process
of say
ing Supply sites economics where it's
really about building capacity building
state-of-the-art infrastructure with the
idea that it will attract business and
others will in the end
drive drive growth to buy an Emirates
without oil or where oil has run out
through the 60s has had this
diversification strategy and it has been
to some extent a kind of self-fulfilling
prophecy uh so yeah it's kind of a token
of importance of centrality that is
being proclaimed there it also is a
token of other things a huge
exploitation of temporary labor for
instance but it is typically the Dark
Side of these kind of uh buildings that
is less uh discussed so it's part of
spectacular urbanism makes us wonder
what what is behind uh this image so
yeah symbolic power has also kind of
projected uh by certain kind of cities
um and then maybe a final definition is
indeed yeah the administrative
definition
um it has is a certain yeah
um jurisdiction within a country it's
the way where all kinds of management
processes are administered but the
population is serviced but how the
public sector organizes itself and what
is kind of interesting is that there's a
lot of kind of
um historical and accuracy
um yeah aberrations almost uh when you
take for instance the example of of
medicine uh in West Flanders I put an
arrow there for those who don't know uh
Belgium that well it has about 1 000
population in 2019 but it counts as a
city yeah so it's kind of a historical
artifact
um
it used to be a very important
um trading center for broadcloth if
you've ever been to Bruges that was was
kind of the main
um main kind of produce that was kind of
uh traded there Bridges was 40 000 k at
that time so a fifth of the size of
world City bridges in I think the 13th
century so what is a very small
community now was there there and then
an important city and somehow Mason has
kept its City rights and would still
count as a city in un uh in U.N language
okay so just to show that we should
probably be very wary about
about these classifications because they
can be uh quite misleading okay
for the number of people living there or
um that's a good question I didn't know
it by heart that it would be a
combination of of
of many things it would be indeed uh
size of the population I think
um yeah more more morphological
um character characteristics typically
it would be
um
continuous built up areas
uh
um and then included in that
some definition of a percentage of
people commuting to the poor City so
areas that are still dependent uh on the
core City because they're part of an
integrated labor market so I don't know
it by heart but there's kind of the the
agglomeration and then the bond here
which is gives a kind of an another
territory of that so and then
um that's basically what they call
functional urban areas that the kind of
definition that is that people would use
yeah and I think maybe there's also
something app to the part in becoming
school because I know what they're made
for example my appointment is my city it
never got similar rights okay so maybe
they just never requested anyways and
maybe they didn't did they did Wells
back in yeah
yeah I think that that could indeed I I
don't know the ins and outs of that but
I think indeed that could be a to be
part of the process as well yeah
[Music]
yeah they try to come up with some kind
of a standardization on the criteria
that I was mentioning so it's a yeah how
many people live there
morphological continuity and then you
could say economic relations
but especially when the um with the
population threshold there's a huge
fabrication some countries it would be 1
000 and others it would be ten thousands
um I think they do because Belgium does
so um so that's kind of the irony yeah
and that gets lost in when you look at
the urbanization rates of 200 plus
countries you can't look into that but
the point by by Brendan Schmidt is that
even if you solve that and come to a
standardized definition you're still not
out of the woods because it's it could
still
create all kinds of chaotic uh
conceptions because the urban is not the
same as the city okay so that was kind
of uh was the point okay so I hope yeah
there's a number of perspectives here
um
there's not one size fits all answer to
what the urban and the city is but
there's different ways of of approaching
the theme okay
now
um
one definition that we could still use
and there's also one that is used in the
handbook is kind of very generically at
the abstract level it's obviously
urbanization is the process of becoming
Urban
and it refers at the abstract level to
demographic process where increasingly
people
live in that and more more and more
density
it has something to do with the
globalization of uh
uh of urban uh influence be it economic
political cultural yeah it's kind of
these places that matter
and obviously this this Frame of the
urban age is mobilized there
and it's a call for
starting to look into how cities are
connected to the wider process of Urban
Development
and this is also connecting back to this
notion of planetary urbanization
by Brenner and Schmidt in a sense what
they argue is that while cities may not
populate the entire Earth they're
actually
quite delineated still if you produce a
map
you can't say that the entire uh global
map is urban uh maybe a lot of people
live in cities but still it wouldn't be
a totality
whereas the urban as a process as a way
of living as a system of capitalist
production would be almost a totality
and in planetary urbanization captures
actually the fact that even when you go
as far as as possible from the urban
context from cities
it would still lead back to these cities
one way or another so the exploitation
of seabeds in the North Atlantic it's
absolutely absolutely not uh has not the
characteristics of cities but it's
part of a uh of exploitation processes
that are commanded through uh through
cities so it's a an example of what they
call extensive urbanization whereas
intensive urbanization in their mind
would be the morphology of cities so
it's a kind of sociological imaginary of
urbanization As It All Leads back to
cities one way or another whereas a more
geographical imagination would start
with well we can still remunerate
certain places as being more dense as
being more urban than one another
whereas we also have to see the
connections with other things so
that's just one more approach of looking
at it
we've been talking a little bit about
urbanism because it's always a bit of
confusion difference between
urbanization which we've been talking
about and urbanism
um you have urbanists here it's it's not
just about observing and analyzing
breasts is also
um designing cities and shaping cities
in a particular way so urbanism is
is uh Dimitri uh uh as the craft of
actually designing cities to a certain
end but it also connects to uh and
that's perhaps also what you were
talking about at some point gaining an
urban attitude there's something of an
energy of that particular society and
cities refers to a particular
psychological or sociological feeling uh
that gives a particular meaning to a
space and I already talked about the
opposition between the ideal type of a
community where this kind of warm social
ties kicking things together versus a
society where it's more abstract formal
roles that are impersonal uh I think
when you look at cities and the
representations and the way the urban
space is consumed you find a lot of that
uh you could say societal
um anonymity uh or that kind of detached
element in those images and
when you look at yeah especially in the
19th century
I mean when people start to capture
process of modernity of urban modernity
and with this idea of the figure of the
fla nerve which was at the same time it
was usually a he a Dandy a rich person
that was both connected to cities
because of his wealth and he had to show
himself off but at the same time he was
also a spectator a walker by Passion who
consumed Urban space from in a very
Anonymous and detached way and
especially in the 19th century I mean we
have this Gallery here close to the
ground Plus
in Brussels it was a kind of urban space
was designed for this Anonymous
consumption was was all about Collective
spectacular consumption and in many ways
Urban Design
especially when we start to Rebrand our
city centers
goes back to these forms of of urban
consumption if you think about these
renderings of uh on Spock Boulevard or
if you look at renderings of how uh
Philippine campus will look like in 10
years it has this kind of spectacular
element always to it that's that
protects a particular kind of urban
attitude that is there to consume Urban
space to work
so Urban Design it's about
um
they're really giving shape to Urban
spaces but also capturing how people
interact with psychologically and
sociologically with the built
environment especially within urbanism
for for instance environmental
psychology and that is a a very
important team
planning is
a future oriented activity in which acts
as various types engaged so that they
can govern how development will take
place so
um obviously
economic process societal process don't
just unfold in and of themselves it's a
kind of uh process of being mediated by
a particular planning cultures I mean we
talked about zoning before it's about
giving a place to certain activities
making choices of where things should be
developed and it's actually quite a
power Laden process because development
in one place could mean non-development
in another place where do jobs where are
jobs being creative where do they not
and how do certain planning procedures
start to to tackle uh process of uneven
development or under development within
the city and especially in a city like
Brussels
one of the main you could say folki off
of urban planning
um in the regional plan has been the
Canal Zone it was kind of a prioritary
space which needed to be redeveloped in
one way it's a well we'll be looking
into the social geography of this place
uh and and throughout the course but
also as we go on excursions it's an
ethnically diverse typically lower
income neighborhood with a lot of
unemployment and it's also very much a
zone of transitions a lot of things
happening there Redevelopment and
planning is not neutral there
um there has been a large focus on this
area both in terms of trying to achieve
industrial Redevelopment because there
was a lot of unemployment kind of a
rollout of a zone of economic expansion
that was installed there
at the same time also the ambition to
achieve mixity to increase the mixing of
residential and and
um and and workings okay
and what is kind of interesting there in
in Brussels is that there was a very big
contradiction between the ambition to
attract uh businesses to this area and
create jobs and the ambition of mixer
team because mix City worked as a kind
of an incentive for all of residential
developers to start building
um yeah high-end or
I would say regionally unaffordable uh
Apartments house etc etc so
the idea of let's mix stuff is actually
making
um The Return of jobs to this area
very difficult it leads to forms of
industrial gentrification
and it's also leading to some kind of an
affordability crisis because the types
of houses that are being produced there
has nothing to do with what the local
residents would actually need okay so
that's housing production but it's not
tailored to the demand if you will
so yes uh planning plays a role
um and it's all but a neutral process
now what is geography
you have one minute to discuss this and
geographers I'm looking at you to
explain what geography is
because I can't
please discuss what is geography
foreign
[Music]
yes
you have an idea already
it's not as I have to explain not the
parts or branch of geology
and receptions that's typically what I'm
meeting up okay but um what's your idea
about this
mm-hmm
and they were
maybe total topology or
the terrains like that or the nearby
services
so
where a particular location is
okay so it's about location it's about
the impact of you could say the terrain
on activities and those kind of things
oh yeah okay thank you
um
particular like areas on sale
like
geology for example okay
geography is the study of space I mean I
can be applied to anything so it doesn't
matter what you're studying if you want
to be looking at a scale then that's
okay
that gives us tremendous power as
geographers thank you for that
thank you for that any other ideas yeah
so dialectics between humans and the
environment okay
other ideas yeah
foreign
[Music]
like to say for example sometimes it to
faculty
you think so special approach
that's very interesting yeah and your
idea is still
okay I think I think there's all I would
say correct in a way but it shows that
there's different different answers to
this question and the answer to this
question has been different throughout
the history of geography uh I would say
in the 19th century it was indeed about
creating detailed information on
resources topography and those kind of
things because geography was installed
in an imperial program of exploiting the
colonies but throughout the decades uh
the main purpose or less on depth of
geography has shifted
or there's different kind of parallel
interpretations of what the purpose of
geography should be
I start with a number of
definitions where else do we go the real
Royal geographical Society this is this
kind of the heart of Empire if you will
um one of the first geographical
Societies in the kind of part of the
British Empire as it's a kind of ruled
disease and it gives us some idea of
what geography could be so it's
the understanding of Social and physical
processes within the context plays
recognizing the great differences in
cultures political systems economies
Landscapes and environments across the
world and exploring things between them
so it's about the the world as a mosaic
it's about geographical difference
sensitivity to contexts
and also thinking relationally so how
does something that happens in Brussels
connects to Kinshasa for instance so
it's about connections between places
but these are not I mean I'm not saying
these are ideal definitions
by far not but we can be inspired and
fix certain things from
American Association of geographers used
to be the association of American
geographers by the way but they changed
their name to reflect more diverse
audience uh in the community
you want to understand the world's final
start with the River City a mountain a
village a road and follow it to the ends
of the Earth geography asked the big
questions where how why what if as you
were saying and gives you the
perspective to answer them with advanced
technology and the solid knowledge of
the world in which we all live okay so
follow your nose Trace connections uh
and indeed ask these big questions where
perhaps in other disciplines
um there's less space to do so okay
by the way if you go to the original you
could say literal Greek transcription is
Earth description
um but that doesn't tell you that much
right it's a standard definition would
be to describe uh human activity at the
interface of uh and with with the Earth
or something like that so it somehow
goes back to a very descriptive idea of
what geography should be uh not
necessarily producing any analytical
knowledge or explanatory knowledge okay
so I tend to not to like that definition
too much but
in original Greek it's what it means
okay
now to further a little bit there and I
think I mean this going a little bit
more
um towards my own expectation as well
just another quote
uh take from the handbook While most
social science disciplines can be
roughly defined by what they study the
economy culture society and so on
geography is defined by how we stand so
that was what you were saying
and so the World by our approach
geographers study the economy Society
politics and culture too but a
geographical perspective is one that
emphasizes space it is approached to any
of these subjects so it's not just that
we can claim uh like political
scientists or like economists this kind
of thematic field it's really our you
could say theoretical and analytical
working with the notion of space space
as something that explains what human
activity as it interacts with its
environment that really
identifies so sets us apart as
geographers from us yeah just the
questions the how is this definition
that any difference from you know
sociology as a whole
but because there would be far less
attention to space
I would say
that's so childhood sociology isn't that
space it's also defined how human
interactions go
like that the whole point is
how space defines house I wouldn't think
so I think sociologists would would
start with particular yeah
um histories perhaps look at the
relations organizational forms uh
perhaps identity those kind of processes
but I think and they perhaps they may
describe variety
uh across different contexts in one way
or another but perhaps they would not
use geography to explain uh
those differences so for instance I mean
I mean what could I think of as an
example I mean when you when you try to
understand urban life
uh being sensitive to how you're
inserted uh in a Global Network of uh of
cities could be
um could be one way to appreciate your
own positionality so if you're a citizen
of a city like in Shasta which is an
exploitative or subordinate relation to
other cities in the world it may give
you a hint of why your living conditions
are that bad whereas sociologists May
perhaps start explaining that from local
cultures uh local societal
characteristics political systems Etc a
geographer would for instance try to put
that in perspective and say look there's
an overarching system
a world system of sorts maybe we can
talk about this next week that allows to
explain uh that a little bit better
okay I don't but I think yeah and that
connects a little bit to the to the next
uh thing and the sociological
imagination and these are the words uh I
mean this is what what David Harvey
writes and social justice in the city
it enables the possessor to understand
the larger historical scene in terms of
its meaning for inner life and external
career a variety of individuals so the
sociological imagination enables us to
grasp history history and biography and
the relation between the two in society
so it's about think about issues like
class and how knowledge is produced uh
what kind of questions that you ask that
are predefined for not predefined by
shaped by our by your own class identity
for instance or epic identity to
acknowledge that would be one thing but
Harvey says the spatial imagination
enables the individual to recognize the
role of space and place in some
biography so like for instance somebody
from South Africa who starts teaching
in in London
in
as a geographer
how with this personal trajectory uh
lead to some kind of a focus on issues
of what is modernity what is
non-modernity what is development what
is under development and those kind of
things so how for instance on a career
as a scholar from the global South going
to the global North might shape the
questions that are being asked
next to just issues of class ethnicity
and other elements that may shape
positionality
I could use the example of Jennifer
Robinson for instance who fits this
exercise and she came up with the idea
of ordinary cities somehow debunking the
whole idea that would be extraordinary
world cities and then the rest okay so
just saying that in your personal
biographies
your spatial trajectory and your spatial
relations with other places may also
have an impact on the kind of questions
uh that you're they're asking I'm not
saying that uh sociologists are blind
but they they just ask different kind of
questions
okay
now for me I mean these are difficult
theoretical discussions it's also not an
epistemological
epistemology class but I think it's safe
to say that as as human geographers
we're interested in uh the interactions
between space and Society how spaces
shape societies and individuals and vice
versa how individuals and societies
space shape their environments and this
is kind of what
at soja a famous uh American geographer
calls an association dialectic
um and it's and then you translate that
to cities it's how Urban societies make
the places they live in and at the same
time how Urban space morphologically or
otherwise has again back an influence on
urban life as as groups and individuals
think about segregation which shows a
segregated social structure
it's something social but it also will
Define the kind of interactions that you
have with others in urban space and they
have an impact on what kind of
encounters you have in the city may have
an impact on
how privileged you are
um to what extent you know other social
groups and Society Etc so space one
example that killing to the work of Nick
later on
that shows that space has in itself some
kind of an autonomous form of
uh explanation I'm very uh defensive as
a geographer as you can see because as
all geographers I have an identity
crisis
um but that's kind of a very productive
one I would say because this kind of
typifies the history of post-war history
of geography and maybe other geographers
will will recognize that
um yeah so the social spatial dialectic
perhaps this is as a synthesis what we
can land on how society's people make
spaces and how it works back to them and
thinking about
the autonomous power of space and
explaining stuff
as an example if I can can I
yes
four ways and I mean you mentioned it
already it's thinking about different
concepts of space territory scale
networks plays are for common ways of
thinking about space
and they point to different kind of
spatial processes and again it's not
that one is better than the other to
understand what is happening but as I
will try to show by the example Brussels
kind of seeking tension between these
different concepts that get us gets us a
little bit closer to understanding for
instance in this case the conundrum that
Brussels supposed so one way of looking
at the city of Brussels is a territorial
one it has a particular jurisdiction
it's the Brussels Capital Region which
emerged as a region somewhere in the
1990s next to Flanders and malonia
and it has certain competences it has a
government a parliament we can do stuff
besides stuff on its territory
but not on culture because that's uh
something that is being decided by
flowers and the francophone Community
but other than that there's kind of
sovereignty uh on that level uh as what
can be designed so it's a very strict
kind of banded space if you walk 10
meters outside those boundaries in
principle uh the Brussels government
can't say anything about you
um and on the other hand it's also can
erect all kinds of barriers if Flanders
wants to add another Lane to the Ring
Road across Brussels because it is very
centered on on car Mobility
well there's ways of blocking that
because
um there's certain stretches of the Ring
Road where Brussels can say no let's not
do that here and in the end you end up
still with the bottlenecks okay so this
is territorial power to some extent uh
which has also been used uh by the
Brussels government saying everything
is 50 kilometers an hour max When you
entered the depart territory uh so yeah
um take it or leave it
so with territorial view of what
Brussels could be a second one it would
be a more scalar View
and scale
to
different processes work on different
scales some of them are really micro
teaching is a micro process taking place
in the at the scale here of the
classroom
whereas you could say commuting is
something that takes place at a far
larger scale as we go home it's a
process That's radically goes beyond the
boundaries of of this class okay it's
the same when you look at economic
activities
um as you if you look at the
Metropolitan Area morphologically
Brussels is actually much larger than
the Brussels Capital Region so if we
were to Define Brussels as a scale of
where Urban activities take place
you could end up halfway to Flanders or
halfway to Bologna okay so it radically
deep borders
um the territory that is the Brussels
capital region
in contrast to other contexts
um there has not been a very uh
successful process of we could say City
regionalization where there was some
kind of
governance expansion to manage the
Metropolitan uh process and a lot of
context we see that new governance
structures have been erected think about
London for instance
uh it hugely exceeds uh the original
Heartland of London but includes more
and more of its peripheries because
these places are connected to
um to the urban area okay this is not
what happened in Brussels and this has
something to do with the fact that
there's a very communitarian uh
sensitive issue okay because it deals
with all kinds of issues of
redistribution of uh of income Etc we
have to keep in mind that about 60 of
Belgian GDP is generated in Brussels uh
but it's not being governed into in its
totality by the Brussels government
in fact and that brings us to the third
one it's a network perspective
there's all kinds of micro networks in
this case this is the commuting map of
Belgium that makes that the Surplus that
is being generated by all these
activities and Brussels I think about
headquarter functions European functions
that apparently account for a quarter of
the Brussels economy it actually leaks
to the periphery so it leaks beyond the
borders of this territory of the
Brussels Capital Region a lot of people
including myself work in Brussels but
um basically pay taxes outside of
Brussels so I live in against this
beautiful other city
in Belgium and I yeah I get texts and
Flanders uh I spent a lot of money well
not so much because I work too much I
could spend a lot of money in Ghent
um but it basically is some kind of
physical leakage from uh from territory
right
and uh this is a problem with Brussels
we also could talk about uh eurocrats
who are not taxed at all but work in
Brussels so we can wonder about the
multiplier economic multiplier that's
being created by all these activities in
Brussels and that means that yeah
there's a lot of a large visiting class
about 400 000 commuters come to Brussels
every uh every day well pre-corona let's
see if it's still the case
uh but they use a city they spend uh
time on on the infrastructure but not
necessarily paying for that
and now it's very details of other kinds
of ways of arranging that as solidarity
than between the regions of flounders
for instance space
um a number of buildings every year to
Brussels as a sign of solidarity where
you can also frame it as just paying the
bill for being on the Metro in Brussels
using it every day and so this kind of a
discussion there
and it also is framed in very
identitarian communitarian terms
and this is kind of when you use a
concept like place
um
gets you a bit closer to this process of
how people attach meanings to some place
so Brussels and how it's represented in
Belgian Media or Flemish media I invite
you to uh buy a Flemish newspaper and
run it through Google to see how
Brussels is being represented as a
particular frame
um which has been augmented uh or
centralized even further as we had the
terrorist attacks in 2016
um where even Mr former president Trump
describe to normal and big as a hellhole
and was very nicely taken over by
Flemish media because it kind of
resonates with the idea of yeah
unsafe
image of Brussels
um
dirty image of Brussels
and yeah so it kind of resonates there
and what you see is especially is that
yeah this is also you could say
reenacted in the in the entire covet
crisis where again it's the same frame
of yeah Brussels can't manage look at
vaccination rates it doesn't get its
population under control they're messing
up again if we were independent and
flounders
yeah that we could be have all kinds of
other covet regulations etc etc would be
free already so it's kind of this Frame
of attaching certain meanings uh to
certain places so if you just go to
lidocack or you could also like they'll
be it's a big sign but flaming and
Thursday so it's
it's
yeah I would say somewhere here
so it's really dependent on um
on Brussels in terms of commuting but
what you see is that with the kind of
um return
of higher end residential functions the
city uh to the city of Brussels that is
actually a lot of displacement going on
and a lot of people that used to live in
what they call the residual housing
market still affordable housing in
Brussels it's actually being pushed out
and is increasingly
commuting to Brussels from further and
further away so in a sense you could say
um Brussels is spilling over all the way
to leader character and what you see is
that there is a very strong opposition
by uh identitarian parties a local mayor
which has really tried to
form a kind of a Bridgehead if you will
towards all that is foreign
uh to this process of urbanization there
and we can think about it uh what what
we want but it's certainly something
that is that is explaining a lot of the
tensions between Brussels and it's it's
growing Hinterland
so four takes of the Brussels to four
different kind of spatial
uh approaches and I think combining them
tells us a bit more about what on Earth
Brussels as a city is
um okay
um
is there still time do you still have
time for one minute of thinking about
what being critical means
I think in eight minutes we can stop so
one minute
of thinking of what is critical not in a
sense your condition is critical but
what is critical Urban studies or
critical urban geography for you what
does that mean
um
the countryside
[Music]
being critical
what does that mean
the ideas
are the absolute on the students
yeah so yeah questioning what you hear
what you see okay okay
making sure
all right
people who are the person yeah
so it connects a bit to what you were
saying uh fact-checking certain
statements
uh see where your ideas come from yeah
just being aware of your own biases like
confirmation bias sharing thinking about
something it's a huge help with being
critical as well cherry picking what is
that can you explain that traffic is the
selective picking of your sources
uh while you have Ida and you only code
source that also save others that also
represent the idea it's regarding all
the other end yeah so you go back from
the results to uh to the data selection
yeah yeah so being reflexive about your
own ideas yes exactly
required
mm-hmm
in the words
caring caring
uh and and okay and and caring how how
exactly that's an interesting term
s
and then
it will be like analyzing extracting and
like practice
and and what should we care about
um
true that's yeah any particular process
yeah uh I think it implies being
politically having an approach that is
politically engaged and also maybe
building upon his answer
listening to different actors and
especially the marginalized and not the
the what do you call them
official sources of knowledge okay
interesting yeah
it can also be accepting that there is
no classes
but like everything in the context and
okay
yeah I have to hold myself not a good
discussion but it's an interesting point
I think it's about being critical about
what effect is personally I would say be
sensitive how to how effect is produced
to use blue laptop in the sense that if
you put men in white jackets it would
give certain people them more power to
actually produce a fact whereas other
voices marginal voices will not be in
that position yeah
um
like a field level it involves like
taking care of the implications of the
way you're conceptualizing things are in
terms of economic and social impacts of
that and then
re-evaluating the theory sort of
Frameworks that you're using based on
what you're finding on that yeah
interesting so it's again being
reflexive about your own positionality
trying to tease out to what extents uh
your positionality shapes the questions
you ask
um and then try to address that one way
or another it's not easy yeah
um
foreign
label process
where some voices sound louder than
others
it reproduces stuff like that it also
has geographical uh implications because
it's not just some people I mean it
overlays with spatial structures I think
about it Global diploma Global cells
okay thanks a lot I mean uh exactly I
mean I have not so much to add to that
you can take the definition of of Jonas
at all and I think it captures some of
the things that were being said uh think
about New Concepts that reveal something
that we didn't know yet it's kind of
obvious but still
um think about being politically engaged
yes something that matters uh one way or
another but be reflexive about the fact
that some things might really matter
being picked up but not necessarily be
uh you could say very Progressive I mean
in a fascist Society there's all kinds
of knowledge on segregation to be
produced that is very useful and it
could be extremely politically engaged
in that but not necessarily uh
thinking about you could say
marginalized forces there
third Point indeed taking seriously the
experiences lies practicing words of
ordinary Urban residents
or marginalized social groups to think
about really okay we have this hegemonic
representation
what would happen if we would ask
different people if we start in a
different positionality etc etc
obviously you have your positionality as
a researcher on yourself
and it may be sometimes very hard for
instance as a man to study feminist
perspectives it may also be not
recognized as being a rightful person to
studying these kind of aspects so I
think it's a it's it's a kind of a a
negotiation process there and then again
or think about
um women that that focus on
the eliteness of investment banking in
the city think about work of Linda
McDowell for instance and how how it's a
difficult process for women to actually
enter these spaces have access but once
they get access they ask very different
questions and they'll actually lead to
quite uh revolutionary insights
an alternative formulation and that's
why I was a little bit hesitant with uh
there are no facts I don't agree I think
there are
um effects facts in a sense that there
are factual realities and a new series
kind of um kind of Middle Ground between
you could say
um truth as being something that's being
constructed
but you always have to construct it on
the basis of some kind of empirical
factual reality uh so not a radical
deconstruction or post-structuralist
thinking uh there's always a way of
saying this is I don't know the entire
truth but this is probably a little bit
more true than something else
and yeah you can write the citation uh
read the citation sorry
what he says is that the ultimate goal
is to reduce uh
illusion in society in and of itself so
if you have shark
periodical analytical categories and
Concepts you can work with that and you
will see things perhaps in a different
light and take away as
false beliefs and Illusions in society
and it also means that it's a kind of a
placeless and Timeless definition in the
sense that this could be the mission for
instance of critical Urban studies or
critical urban geography and what is
critical and what is a false belief and
what is an illusion may change over time
so it's kind of it keeps holding the
definition but it may have to be updated
in terms of how it works and exactly so
some rules of thumb
um
there's no universal theory of any
anything and I think we'll uh we'll show
that uh we have to be sensitive to the
fact that every theory has its
birthmarks
what were the questions uh that really
gave rise to formulating a research
question to a theory in a particular way
well we'll have to take a look at the
context about historically and spatially
uh to understand uh what that was so
think about The Chicago School that
you'll be talking about with Nick
it's it was assumed to be Universal
model there's actually a model of a city
that captures rapid urbanization in the
early 20th century in Northern America
and then the question to an extent that
actually explains something in different
locations in different times
we're not going to reject that but we
have to mobilize that concept and see
how far we get
so we have to be reflexive about these
bird marks so yeah even the concept of
class is something that is a western
Inception if you will
to what extent does it allow to actually
capture for instance Indian Society
so we need to kind of provincialize
theory and say okay it originated at
some point and now we can meaningfully
think about how we can speak across
context so think about
um
a global city has a concept that emerged
say mostly in in Northern America
Western Europe what extent does it allow
to capture what is going on in Singapore
for instance so to play uh while being
reflexive about these Concepts uh with
the application across
and engages pluralism that's kind of I
mean might be for engaged pluralism it
means that there are different kind of
theoretical stances different kind of
questions being asked entering from
different kind of teams and I think it's
not just about
acknowledging that but it's actually
engaging with this kind of descent
opinions and try to look for a
conversation and
maybe we can talk a little bit more
about that next week or in the next
sessions
as Urban Studies have grown and kind of
become ever more Global as the
urbanization has also globalized there's
always a risk that has some
um work that we become lost in in
comparison to use the words of Jamie
pack that we lose our points of
reference they actually be able to to
have some kind of coherent Urban studies
project or at least speak to one another
so I think there's a danger with a
Global Research agenda with so many
contextual differences how do we still
make sense of urban processes in
Singapore versus uh versus Brussels how
do you prepare
now I won't bore you now to death with
the next few slides too much but I just
want to say
um that what geography was and what kind
of critical questions were asked has
changed tremendously uh throughout time
much of geography originally was
really about human interaction with the
environment
um
say environmental determinism where it
was really believed yes it's really the
physical environment that will shape
human activities
Regional geography was also a very big
tradition especially before the second
world war where it was really about this
description of human activities in their
physical media there's still some
tradition there but what really happened
after the second world war boasts were
area especially since the 70s it was a
period of let's say great social and
political and economic upheaval is a
huge branching out of
um of geography so that's quite a
plurality of traditions there and they
take us quite far from the the origins
of geography was was really about
settlements if you will and then in the
pre-World War era was about okay show
East Anglia and where are the
settlements or describe me the structure
of a city after the second world war
especially in the 80s it was a kind of a
nomothetic move and the kind of we have
to formalize this and you have for
instance Boulder Crystal who came with a
quite a neat model to explain why at
certain locations you had certain
settlements of a certain size or for
instance he owns a much more such
formalizing the idea okay if there's
certain activities within a city at a
certain space it must have something to
do with the kind of value that is being
generated by those activities and the
fact that some activities outfit others
on a certain location so these are kind
of foundational approaches and I'm going
very fast here I know but it's just to
take note of that this led to a much
more plural uh discussion as of the 70s
and I I can't really do justice to all
these different Traditions here but what
you could say more radical and critical
voices uh share in one tradition you
could say yes questions of social
justice uh distribution they work in a
materialist setting so what people have
and how does class for instance income
Etc plus how does that explain divisions
in the city
nice names such as David Harvey uh Neil
Smith
those were kind of a period with a lot
of change we have social mobility of the
working class in 1970s
um feminist geographies uh that also
emerged at this point
um questioning male-dominated views
um on society
Etc so thinking about placing geography
relating it to process of of
um of capitalism
the other big strands you could say
um
there's more you could say a humanist
humanistic geography that thinks about
urban lifestyles Urban behaviors Urban
cultures which less kind of relates
itself to uh to capitalism uh in a sense
but really starts with okay what kind of
forces haven't we heard in the city how
are cities being experienced can we
think about the power of representation
how different spaces are being
represented what the power of discourses
is it's not just about material
circumstances also how we think about
certain places that will explain what
takes place
and also a shift towards more insane
qualitative methods
um that kind of simplifies the cultural
turn uh more widely okay
and this is not at the end of a
conversation I would say and that's kind
of the abundance of further studies
uh more widely and Robin particular that
all these different approaches exist
next to one another but you have to kind
of be aware that they work in different
kind of traditions and then we'll
formulate questions in a particular way
and I think you will see returning here
and there throughout the course somebody
who works perhaps a little bit more in
that framework or starts to refer to
that tradition and it's something to be
aware of I can't do justice to the
history of geography in three slides
that would be over the top but it's
something to think about
okay I'll end there sorry for taking a
little bit longer by next week please
try to get over these two texts
um or share it with your colleagues and
the world city hypothesis by John
Friedman and ALDI and uh somewhat less
old but still already investigated uh
text by saskia
mixed with muscles
all right
thank you very much
um and see you next week
[Music]