foreign
[Music]
I see some people with a laptop would
you mind to check whether the webcast is
working put your link on the link of the
link of the live stream
um I think it should be
it should be working I think
[Music]
um
because I think that uh some of you
might know me
and many others might not know me
I am experiments and I will teach this
class and the next one in urban
geography Urban social geography
and I consider myself to be an urban
social person that's a good a good kid I
think
and most of my research has dealt with
migration
newcomers in the city
segregation whiteness
and I've done a PhD with case studies in
kilometers and in South Africa about 70
years in Cape Town to study how white
middle class people moved to the city
and what kind of people they get to meet
uh in in the city
Etc
um so I've done some work on the
geographies of encounter the geographies
of migration
um and this year I have decided to work
less at the University and to spend more
time with my kids and more time on my
bike I like to cycle
um and so it means that I have reduced
my workload at the University and I
still have a 50 teaching assignment
um I teach social geography in the first
year Bachelor of geography I teach some
classes in urban geography I also take
the students on a field trip to Estonia
and this will be the geographers this
year and I've also done that for the
master in urban studies students and
two years ago was the last time I think
we did that
and I'm teaching a course on the city
and migration that's a title at the
University of Louisville so I have quite
some teaching assignments also
supervising some Master's thesis to PhD
thesis so that's what I'm what I'm doing
um I have written here in my presenters
notes who am I and I'm another white
male mid-aged middle class man
that you that you get to see here I
think this issue of positionality is
also an important one especially in the
kind of issues that I will discuss when
it comes to diversity when it comes to
migration what are my experiences in the
city
and so I think that's also something
important to point at and something that
we could discuss
um also
further in the semester like whether
this is something important or or not to
but there will be not so much time for
discussion today and there will be time
for discussion in the seminars and that
will come soon and there will also be
time for discussion on the field trips
I'm going to run through two field trips
for the students this is for the four
cities and the master of urban studies
students so not for all the other ones
and but we have one Excursion to Antwerp
and one Excursion to Shell next week
that I'm going to run and so I wanted to
share some practicalities and I don't
like the fact that I am somehow bound to
my laptop but this is for the live
stream and so it's I hope that it's that
it's uh is working now
um
but so first of all next week Tuesday I
think 40 of you have signed up to go to
Antwerp is that correct who will join me
to Antwerp
yeah
um I will hand out some
Excursion guides and printed them in
color by accident I don't know how happy
the department will be about that if you
get these paper copies in in full colors
so you can take one if you join me yeah
don't take one if you don't join me
because then I will not have enough
copies for everyone
and what is important and that's
something else that I want to hand out
I'm living in Antwerp and so I will meet
you in uh enter a railway station
um
to be in my wallet
who is joining to enter and is familiar
with this
Rail Pass OR Go pass
no one
yeah some people
um so I will give this uh to you and I
would like you for all the people that
join we need one line okay so it says
um this isn't French you can also fill
it in in Dutch or in English the day
Tuesday the date in the Belgian system
with day month year then the place for
American beef that will be Brussels and
then enter
yeah and you need lines for everyone
it's a bit complicated as
um you have tickets for those under 26
and other tickets for those over 26 a
bit more expensive
so I will give them to you
thank you
so good
so it's important that you meet on time
20 to 8 next week Tuesday we are leaving
rather early
um with a train that will have as a
destination
which is a small station to the north of
Antwerp but it's important that you get
off at Antwerpen Central
yeah so the group will meet 740 you take
you make sure that you get on the train
Elena and Louisa will make sure together
with all of you that you have a line for
each student you get on the train and it
will be platform five I guess if you're
late you pay for your own tickets and so
use let's use that as an incentive I
will not reimburse anyone who leaves
late you should travel with the group
and then you all arrive at the same time
according to the schedule at 8 35 and I
will meet you on the platform
yeah so that's what we do we will go
cycling I hope that everyone was aware
of that
it will it is November it will be cold
it will be wet so make sure that you
bring some gloves and some rain gear
because it might um it might be called
bring the Excursion guides especially
now that it has been printed in full
color because you will use that quite a
bit
and we are going to discuss basically
the topics of the this class and next
class so we will discuss segregation and
social mix in the field in Android
we will get to cycle about 25 kilometers
that's quite a bit
um but it has worked out every year
nicely so I trust that it will be the
same
um wear a mouth mask on the train
yeah I don't know what the regulations
will say how how we need to get around
in Antwerp we are quite a big group I
might split you up a couple of times
um bring a lunch or buy one in
Enterprises also I will give you an hour
to to have a lunch but we will be in
quite a fancy part of time so it might
be more complicated to find a cheap
place there but not impossible
yeah so
you will complete these rail passes and
go passes and then you will when you
arrive in anthrope you will give these
two to me
next week Friday I will take you to um
or some of you who will join me to
Charlotte
okay so a similar amount of people and
we will meet in the Brussels railway
station Central so that's important 10
minutes later but still quite early at
10 to 8. in order to be on the train at
seven past eight
yeah again the same system that say I
will be responsible for the rail passes
and the go passes if you're late you
will need to get in touch with a fellow
student to know where we are I'm not
going to wait for you at the train
station in but also you need to pay your
own ticket yeah
um we're going to hike first through the
city but we will also climb some of
these uh at least one Ash Heap in French
so this is a small mountain of yeah
like leftovers from the coal mining it
is quite steep it can be wet so you
should also have some good shoes that
allow you to to do that
bring a pen and paper and I will bring
you a similar kind of Excursion guide
probably in black and white
um for the shadow Excursion
and you can again bring a lunch or buy
one in Charlotte
do we have any practical questions about
these trips
that's a good question
um I think in Shelby I will end around
five meaning you can get back to
Brussels around six but I have a habit
to anti or to give you the possibility
either to get on a train back to
Brussels but I also suggest you to walk
back to Charlotte train station
and but if you want you can be back in
Brussels at six
um from Antwerp we will end at six the
very latest because that's the moment
when I need to give back the bikes to
the bike rental agency and so that means
that you should be able to be back in
Brussels at seven
some other practical questions
no and I'm looking yeah
no you will get a helmet you will get a
look
um if you're very eager to take your own
bike to Anthem it's you can do that on
the train and it's a bit of a hassle but
you will get a nice rental bike you will
get a helmet if you want and you will
get
um a lock for the bike as well
foreign
so I will see you next week I will see
40 of you next week Tuesday in uh in
Antwerp Central Railway Station
um I'm looking forward to that
so these are the practicalities about
the excursions I'm glad that I was able
to share that personally rather than
just another message in the canvas
um today you're not in session one
you're in session four you had an
introductory class you had two classes
on road City formation and polarization
in world global cities and basically
today we will continue a bit on the
theme of class three and I will we will
discuss segregation we will discuss
patterns of segregation and we will just
discuss causes of segregation and next
week I will discuss effects or
Consequences of sick yeah so these are
two classes that fit very well together
and there is a clear theme for each of
them patterns causes of segregation
today affects consequences of
segregation next week
I assume that all of you have read these
two texts
and have you maybe we can I can also
have a look who who has read these two
texts
you can be proud about it who has not
been able to read these two texts you
can also be proud about that okay so I
see that more people have not read it
not read them rather than read them
um for the discussion seminar I think
it's important that we have
like a shared knowledge and these two
texts for this week and the two texts
for next week will be the shared
knowledge together with what is being
shared in the class so I hope that all
of you will be able to read these two
texts and the two for next week by the
time we have the discussions
um
okay
today
I have basically three topics I will
discuss first these classical models of
urban form in the text by pachone which
was a textbook chapter there was a
reference to Burgess I'm going to talk
about Hoyt I'm going to talk about
Harrison Allman some classical models of
urban form that have been generated by
Chicago School Scholars in the beginning
of the 20th century
then secondly I'm going to discuss
patterns of segregation meaning that we
will discuss like how to measure
segregation and
how you can look at segregation from
different angles and then at the end of
the class I will discuss some causes of
segregation why is it that people lit
that poor and rich people live in
different neighborhoods of the city why
is it that you can find white people in
one part of town and people of like
African origin in another part of town
Etc
so this is the topic list for today and
I'm going to start with this classic
Land Use model by Burgess
so those of you who have read the
textbook chapter by pachome have been
reading about the burgers he was writing
from Chicago
1925. I think that's important I will
do the live stream like this I think
that might also still work is everyone
able to hear me at the back here yeah
okay so that's that's going around the
world so what was Burgers doing he was
trying to understand
how cities
were looking like and what kind of
groups groups of people you could find
in different parts of the city
they were stating that basically you had
five
concentric rings
in the Heart of the City there was the
loop
um the loop I will I will discuss that
later it's a term from Chicago basically
the central business district
yeah around that you have the zone of
transition that's how you found it then
around in the third zone of working
working methods the residential Zone
suburban and another uh residential Zone
with reaching out the commuters so five
rings around the city
and why was it that you have these five
rings well
because different functions in the city
in different groups of people were able
to pay different rents
so the theory was that in the center of
the city the central business district
you found
for example the headquarters of an
office
because they were able to pay the higher
rents that you had so close to the city
center
and further away from the city
was the theory you would find for
example
Suburban plots
um what's very intense because these
people were able to spend to pay less
rents
for their part of
so this is really Theory
um was basically underlying this model
of concentric things
yeah this term model can be a little bit
confusing
and because it could give you the
impression that this is an ideal type
like this is how it sit all through yeah
but Burgers was trying to do but
basically to
simplify reality and to understand how
cities were not necessarily how they
opened it how our cities and we try to
simplify it and that's how a simplified
version of Chicago of a western City
looks like
I told you already written in 1925
yeah that's very important why because
we are at a moment in time this is the
population of Chicago from 1840 to 2014
we are at a moment in time 1925 when
this population of Chicago has been
growing through an exponential growth
for many many years
yeah and that also explains why
Burgess was making a model of the growth
of the system
yeah it's not a model of any City it's
the model of a growing city and he tries
to understand how this growth of a City
Works
both in terms of a growing population
but also
a city that is characterized by an
expanding area that is built the
environment
is growing and so it's a level of the
growth of the city
and writing from Chicago in 1925 well
this is a very particular growing city
this is a city of immigration where a
lot of immigrants
are from all over the world but from
Europe in particularly initially arrived
and where they settle
and where you see that in
1900 you had less than 2 million people
and uh you need to go only 10 15 years
later to find another amazing into added
to the population and so this is a fast
growing City
um both in terms of population and in
terms of the area that is built up
that's also expanding that's also true
um it's also a city that is
characterized by heterogeneous
population so what you see here is the
result of a survey
going from house to house knocking on
people's door and then checking whether
there is someone English speaking in
White Irish in green German in purple
Dutch in dark purple Russian in red Etc
and so you see that the city was
characterized by a heterogeneous organic
all these people coming from different
countries of origin arriving in Chicago
at that time okay so it's a particular
City that Burgers is writing from and
I'm saying that because I want to argue
that this theory that Virgos made up and
which he thought was Universal for
growing cities was in in fact
a theory that was mostly applicable to
Chicago itself yeah and so here you see
a couple of assumptions which are also
mentioned
uh in the in the text that you've read
or that you're going to read
the assumptions and principles that were
underlying this theory of the model of
um the growing city of the growth so you
see that the assumption is that there is
this cultural and social approach
of the population
you could also think of other cities
yeah in countries which are less smart
by this kind of diversity
and the second assumption is that there
is a commercial industrial base to the
economy of the city
could you think of other
basis to the economy of the city
that kind of other places could you have
rather than commercial that's true
tourism yeah if you go to a city that is
marked by two resistance for example
each
distribute could be of any importance
please
yeah while in a commercial industrial
city it's a meteorological But Central
Business districts the center office
during the city is dominated by a
touristic cities well then you would get
different
I know also saw other characters
based yeah then you would hit the
Heritage I could also Imagine like
cities that draw a lot of pilgrims a
religious basis to the city of Temple or
a church would be Central places Etc so
you can think of other kinds of cities
yeah and then the the idea of burgers
would be that this model of urban growth
private ownership of property economic
competition for space you can imagine
other cities
in the Soviet Union for example plan the
economy different kind of systems
um for expanding area and population of
the city many cities in in Europe are
nowadays marked by shrinkage
yeah in Eastern Germany for example
um Genova in Italy city that has been
marked by shrinkage for a very long time
Detroit
a city in North America
that has gone through a similar
fifth essential transport is equally
easy easy rapid and key in every
direction within the city
it's hard to imagine how that would ever
be possible because you will always have
transport infrastructure that will allow
you to move from one end of the city
much more quickly to another end than to
another part of the city
okay number five the city center is the
main Center for employment and therefore
most credible
people also think to many other kinds of
city where for example the airport is an
important top and you have a big
um big development around this Airport
so these things are more attractive
because of differences in terrain I told
you I did my PhD on Cape Town you've got
the Atlantic Ocean you've got Table
Mountain you can imagine that these
differences in terrain are very
important to understand how this city is
owned
you have no concentrations of heavy
industry
yeah and you have no historic survival
of an earlier land use pattern in any
District
there is no Heritage do you have a 19th
century housing or a medieval argument
City yeah and so
um verbis himself already acknowledged
that it hardly needs to be added and I'm
quoting this that neither Chicago nor
any other City fits perfectly into this
ideal ski
complications in Chicago are introduced
by the lakefront the lake in Chicago
so there is a difference
the Chicago River another difference in
Korea railroad lines which mean that
which major transport is not equally
easy rapidly cheap in every direction
and historical factors in the location
of industry and which might mean that
you have concentrations of heavy
industry in some parts
um Etc
and so you see the acknowledgment that
well I'm trying to
formulate a universal model of urban
growth but well underlying my theory are
a lot of assumptions and principles
which mean that basically I'm writing
uh
I'm writing up a model of a specific
City in Chicago and basically my model
was composed for Chicago doesn't even
hold for Chicago itself because there
are many complicated factors okay
um I will I will discuss this further in
a bit like and we
in in urban studies we have been going
through a moment where we
um I started to realize well many of our
theories are provincial when we write
about gentrification and we make a
theory of gentrification then if we make
a case on Brussels then we write a very
Western kind of perspective
gentrification so it's necessary to
de-provincialize our theories I find it
interesting that already 100 years ago
there was this awareness that well me
burgers I'm writing from Chicago and
this is important to to understand
um
so how did this model look like I will
run through this Central Central most
Central concentric ring is the group you
have a wider group
and if you've ever been to Chicago
you've got this Metro lines that all
converge in the city and where basically
this whole Metro is making a loop and
then taking back the line from where
it's going so you have this elevated
metal track
but in a loop in the shape of a loop and
so that's why the essential business
that speak of Chicago is called
so this is the place where you have
shopping
uh where you have offices or you have
headquarters of companies where you
expect to find theaters
um Etc because these are the functions
that are able to pay the highest rent
the highest price for the central
voltage why do they want to be in the
central location well these are all
functions that need to draw
um office workers Shoppers theater goers
from all corners of the city and so for
them it is important to be in the
central location that is easy to reach
from everywhere in this and so they want
to be in
the loop
and Chicago 1925 a picture the video of
ID busy streets the first skyscrapers of
the world in the city earlier than New
York and so you have basically the first
city where you have this
um how to say that like this classical
uh Central Business districts from a
North American Town Syria it's all
skyscrapers
so Zone one the Central Business this
around this you have
The Zone in transition the zone of Truth
basically what you find there is factors
why do these factories want to be
located there they also rely on labor
that needs to come in by a trend by
Metro
Etc so they also want to be in a central
location that allows them to bring in
workers from all corners but they are
not able to pay these high prices for
lands but these functions on the
previous slides were able to offer them
and some of you find a second ring in
which you have these factors
not only factories you also find
neighborhoods there
yeah who wants to live close to these
factories nobody this is very polluted
this is very dirty these are very bad
living circumstances so who ends up here
the first generation of immigrants from
different countries of origin yeah and
as soon as these people are able to
perform a move to a better part of town
then they will do so
they have to do some of these names that
you find on these pictures
little hell tells quite a bit
but also the fact that for example here
we have Little Sicily so this is a part
of town where these Sicilians arrive but
that was formerly little Sweden
yeah so you see how one group of
newcomers moves out and is Then followed
by a new group of people from another
country of origin that was what Burgess
was noticing in 1925. and so this is the
part of the Chicago close to the central
business District close to the loop
in the middle of all these factories
where people who just landed off the
boat
from Europe arrived and so you have
subsequent
groups ethnicities of newcomers who
arrive
people who have been able to climb the
social leather they will move out of
these areas and they are able to afford
a better home
further away from these factories and
they are also able to afford the commute
between home and the world so there's
also a price
to be paid for this so the purpose is
writing there about the zone of
independent working man's hopes
and in his vocabulary which is the
respectable working class is working
it's living in the episode
and so I found it interesting that
um
like here six miles north west of the
loop
West yeah so we are moving in that
direction about 10 kilometers out of the
loop you also have an area of Chicago at
that time where you had quite some
belgians living yeah and Burgess was
also writing about the belgians many of
them were janitors so they also have
like a specific profession uh that many
of them were known
and they also had a clip so you see here
1921 all belgians are equal
oh the um to build a club for belgians
celebrating Belgium space and Belgian
Traditions you have the Saint John
bergman's Church Cynthia
in Chicago and so up to today you can
visit this neighborhood that was marked
by belgians and in the past
yeah but you also had neighborhoods
where you had many Germans or many
Russians or many Italians who had been
able to plan this social leather and who
had been able to out with further away
from this
I've also shown you this map of this
survey going door to door there was a
lot of heterogeneity even in streets but
some neighborhoods were also marked by
this ethnic groups
and then as you go further away from the
loop you get to more Suburban less dense
developments and here you see the
neighborhood of Mount prospects about 25
miles north west from the loop so we are
moving about 40 kilometers out of the
route now 30 to 60 Minutes commute to
the loop by train and so the moment that
these trains are being trained lines are
being built you see this kind of
suburban developments and then you see
and
find prospects 1917
this is a cape to commemorate the 50th
anniversary
but you also see who is living there
long twist Swedish families who have
arrived quite early and will be able to
find this social media that will arrived
a little Sweden but then we moved to the
Zone respectable working men's homes has
very discovered who have been able to as
they climbed the social level we have
also been able to
to this Suburban developments in between
four part
IES
I'm sorry further further red
part of it is becoming more expensive
yeah but you need to you need to see it
uh rent for like you need to pay dollars
per square meter
and so closer you get
to the city center the 10 service
development
and so for that reason it's not about
life what what you can afford but it's
how much you are willing to pay per
second
yeah and so these developments closer to
the sensor are much more dense
yeah so that explains why this picture
and curve is still going down
Burgers so the concentric zone model
and and a theory that has
is still being being being used but even
today if you read about newcomers and
cities and neighborhoods of arrival and
people still refer to Ferguson
conceptualized his arrival of newcomers
in Chicago and the kind of neighborhoods
that they were going through as they
climbed the social touch
yeah
um but you also have other models
um I'm still before the second World War
avoids another researcher who studied
142 American cities
and who stated in the beginning of his
paper that so far reaching are the
changes in our population pattern and
social structure that it can well be
asked whether theories of City growth
and structure formulated for the private
enterprise economy of the late 19th and
20th centuries is not referring to
Burgers but it could be will be
applicable in a future society that may
be of a fundamentally different nature
what happens between 1925 and 1939 in
America what kind of changes could be so
important that you that they have an
impact on the model of uh
yeah the depression so this is about
crisis a moment of economic crisis
yes and when you look at
I will go a couple of slides back
when you look at population growth
and in Chicago then you see that this
crisis 1929 the 1930s but this has a
clear impact also on the population of
as people are eager to immigrate to a
country in crisis the government is also
more strict on who can come
Etc and so
there is a big economic crisis that also
means that there is less migration
whether it's related to less migration
to the states
there are also other
phenomena
yeah so Boyd was writing himself a new
theory of Simply grade growth may be
necessary to fit the effects of a period
when cities grow more slowly
yeah that's what I told you already but
also when Automobiles and airplanes
remove dependency on fixed rails
the car becomes much more important if
you can imagine that a City built for
car drivers looks quite different from a
city that is built for people who take a
tram or a Metro or a train
and he also adds that what is also
different is that there's more
government control and Taxation for
fighting costs for the benefit of the
poor this is a graph that tells you
something about
taxation of the top internal rates in
the states and so you see that this has
been going through quite some changes
yeah and then as described as
when America was hit by crisis that
there was an urge to to have more
effects more income tax to this highest
now what that means is that government
can also intervene more in-house in
infrastructure
etc etc
um so a couple of changes that these
cities have been going through and so
art is saying well these models made for
cities of a particular kind remember
these assumptions of burgers do not hold
true in the cities that I am studying in
the 1930s it's 140. City speakers we see
a lot of different kind of processes
so voids came up with a sector
a sector theory saying that well you
still have this Central business
district in the city because around this
they do not have a couple of
drinks but you have sectors
yeah and the assumption is that when the
city grows
each of these sectors will grow and so
if you have to the now in this case to
the east
sector in which the richest people are
living and the assumption is that when
these group growth or the population of
the city grows that this sector will
also grow to the east
and so you have a couple of different
sectors high class medium
which are also organized by the
transportation
infrastructure and so you would have
industry factories concentrated along
rivers canals Rail lines on roads
immediately next to that you would have
low class residential areas just like
burgers assumed
but Burgers assumed that these factories
and the lowest
low-class areas would be located in a
concentric ring and boy it was saying
well if you look at cities in the 30s in
America and the sector model comes
closer to reality so this is a better
way to simplify how cities are looking
um so sectors rather than concentric
Rings what is also important is that
there's much more emphasis on Class A
medium class low class high class while
Burgers was often writing from these
ethnic groups Italians Sicilians uh
Germans Russians Swedish people arriving
in the city
um
okay a third model
is the one by Harris alone and this is a
graph
or a picture that comes from their paper
we moved on the 1945 and you see that in
their paper they make a reference
already which is concentric so novel by
Burgess they refer to the secret Theory
by Boyd and then they come up with their
own model which is called the multiple
nuclear model of a city
um and you see indeed that they have
this kind of jigsaw puzzle that
represents the city for them in which
you still find number one a central
business district and next to it and the
next with the district with wholesale
light manufacturing but you also see a
couple of other notes that are important
to understand the city for example seven
and outlying business
yeah so this is an important difference
between these two models and that one
there's not just one Central business
district which you also have important
business districts in other parts of the
city
for example in London even in in the
history
they have this economic heart
of the city of the city close to Tower
Bridge and you've got a political Heart
of the City close to Westminster epic
but there is a distance between while in
this traditional models you would expect
them to be concentrated and close to
each other in the central business
district
I also refer to Chicago I say there are
a couple of
Industries or universities which are in
very different parts of the city than
this Burgers model
and expected so they refer to area of
heavy industry and posted the
the river and the lake and then also
this University of Chicago to the South
which is then again like the hook of uh
like an area in which you find middle
class people University lecturers and
people working
in a part of time where you would not
expect them to and so they also look at
these kind of spikes in the big
difference saying that well normally
according to burgers this would always
go down
by the the further you get from the city
center the lower is bitter and curve
would be the lower the price per square
meter that people companies or other
functions are willing to fail but then
Arizona would say well you always find
this kind of local spikes for example
local shopping centers not all the
shopping is happening
the central business district and so
also you can find these local shopping
centers or a satellite City and around
which you find again like is a
decreasing can be transfers yeah so a
third model here is an omen where you
have multiple nuclei
more than one Center basically and you
get this kind of jigsaw puzzle to to
simplify an urban form
in this Theory they only consider those
or well or in that case in that City
yeah every city will have a different
kind of home but their main argument is
that these models are too simplistic
and not everything is radiating from one
Center but in practice you will always
find
it so that's why reality looks more
complex than in decimals
okay
um
why to go back to Chicago why to go back
to theories that have been written 100
years ago I think it's interesting to
make Urban geographers or people who do
Urban studies who made them think about
the form of a city and who is living
where
and so on the left you have here a map
of Chicago
nowadays and each dot basically
represents one person
lost Maps Detroit automatic Network
finds maps for other American cities
like this and so you you see here that
basically the different colors on the
map represent different people who
self-identified with different races
slash ethnicities
yeah so and I think you find people
self-identified as the white in the year
2010 in blue you find people who
self-identified as black in green people
who self-identify as Asian and in Orange
people who self-identify as Hispanic
in the American context uh race slash
ethnicity corresponds very much with
clocks
that's if you would have a map with
socioeconomic classes then you would
also find that most of these
neighborhoods which turn out to be
thinking
and you have a majority of
self-identified as why but this will
also be the better of any business
and that the neighborhoods with people
who self-identified black could be
underprivileged
so now my question for you is which of
these models of urban form the
concentric
remodel by Burgess
a sector model by voids for this
multiple nuclear model can you find on
the map
foreign
models on the map so when you look at
this
closely what what do you see who sees
you find this kind of sectors
yeah
and in heat I have the metro map of
Chicago this will be the center of
business districts you have like pieces
of pie
that starts from the central business so
indeed much of Chicago nowadays
is still looking like voids would have
predicted between these different
sectors
corresponding with different populations
groups different socio-economic classes
low-class high-class medium class to use
the vocabulary line at Five Points so in
this you can still find that yeah
Burgess
okay so what is representative
where it is considered to be relevant
100 years ago we still make maps like
this so for some reason we still find it
important please
but when you look at the pattern
yeah
pleasure
uh
okay so indeed it's very hard to see
concentric sense the ring one because
there will be very few residents of the
central business district
it's also hard to spot concentric Rim 2
it's also a large response concentric
ring three but then when you move
further away from the city center it's
ring number four and room number five
where Burgers would have expected the
better off
residents who have climbed a social
leather you can still see that even
today these are indeed the places where
you find almost exclusively white
dominated neighborhoods and so this this
is still the case
and so this ring number four and five
are still there
is an omen
multiple nucleus
clusters
yeah you can indeed find for example if
you see an example
like is there is
okay so indeed you have a cluster of
this Hispanic people who self-identify
as Islamic in the South and that's
around this uh calumet's River
industry area
yeah you also have a cluster of whites
in a sector that is
blue that is dominated by people who
self-identified as black and this is
this a University of Chicago premises
so up to today you can still see
uh remnants of this Harrison Omen model
and also the reasons why they wanted to
refine or give more detail to this
concentric green model and sector
so I hope that these models
make you think about how different
cities look like and that they also make
you aware of well in different types of
cities
you have different ethnic groups
different social economic classes
make taking out different parts and this
can be very different but Brussels for
example is a city where poverty is very
Central
we have the medieval city but then when
you go out of the vehicle you get to the
19th century development related to
industrialization this is where you find
the poorest neighborhood versus cattle
Beach
these are poor districts
very close to the medieval
you have other kinds of cities for
example Paris where you have much more
wealth close to the city center and
where you have much of the poverty and
very peripheral locations
and so it is interesting to compare
different cities and to understand where
is poverty located where do different
racial ethnic groups live in in the city
and so when you do that
you will also be able to make a a
simplified model of the city that you
are familiar with for the city that you
want to study and you will also come to
an understanding that these burgers and
poison Arizona bubbles are very
simplistic and that in different
countries in different cities you would
have very different models
and I have a couple of examples
this is one from Piercy that is also
used in the textbook where you have in
the British complex is Council Estates
yeah built on peripheral land and so in
a concentric ring where Alice harrisman
and Burgess would expect private
Suburban housing we also have these
Council Estates just like these born
years in the French context where much
of the poverty is peripheral
yeah while that contradicts Birds
the Chinese
city was ever a word of the change
my pronunciation will be very cool okay
nobody cities in China also fast growing
in China you basically have a new look
for an urban citizenship
foreign
and you have villages
which
were taken up by farmers
which are rural pieces of land where you
have people with this brutal citizenship
with the rural living when people from
the countryside migrate to the city they
are able to take up residence in these
old villages
their citizenship if I may say it like
that allows them to stay in this area
so you have in many Chinese cities parts
of the city that look like that where
you have a very formal part immediately
next to a part of the city that looks
much more informal much more dense and
that's because when the city grows over
this Countryside that these brutal
villages
from the past become these villages in
the city where you have a lot of
newcomers arrived and so these Chinese
cities the model of the Chinese City
would look very differently from Burgers
because you have these areas that
used to be Villages or centers of
religious and where you have people with
immigrating from Countryside from other
parts of China who arrived there uh
to this change I think it means
something like Village in the city
and these are foreign
the African City
at the flag of from 1962 very different
again because transport is much more
complicated
and so rich people prefer to live close
to the citizen and the poorest of the
food who arrive from the countryside
will arrive at the very ends of the city
a very peripheral locations where it
takes you two or three hours to get
so these cities look different again
Mike Davis
Los Angeles you might have heard of The
Chicago School burgers for example that
you might also have heard of those
angels group or of course modern
photographers writing from Los Angeles
and Mike Davis and who wrote an
interesting book in 1992 and trying to
make the 1998 UFC who made a model of
how that Los Angeles looked like in the
90s yeah and you might have heard of
Skid Row
it's a part of the city where you have
thousands of homeless people
and living on the streets just next to
the central business district of Los
Angeles say this is the zone of
transition and this is where the poorest
of the poor live
immediately next to the central business
district
but you also end up at that time these
gated to developments
at the periphery of the city where you
had the richest of the rich living in
these gated suburbs so you could also
see that basically this
borders between the different Rings were
being walled and fortified
enclaves
so he was trying to make a mobile
of Los Angeles in the 1990s
barred by this desperate poverty some
parts of the city and then also this
um
both in other parts
and in the end there are still a lot of
burgers in this model there's still the
Central Business districts that are
still core and there is still this
poorest of the poor Living Community
mixed not in the zone of transition
between which the factories and then
this little hell or Little Sicily that
people living on the streets
and then the the more you move out of
the city center the Richer this
neighborhoods get it's also very much
so try to make a model of Los Angeles in
yeah I I
one hour ago I took out a slide with a
bottle for talent and again trying to
understand for the post-socialist city
and look like but then also
using Talon as an example but also
trying to understand like what kind of
developments do we see in these
socialist cities and then in these
post-socials and how can we try to
generalize that simplify
and so the attempts to make a model is
an attempt to simplify reality and to
try and understand what is particular
about cities and what makes Los Angeles
different from Chicago in 1925
so you also have indeed bubbles for
European cities this was a British City
kearsely in this Council Estates but you
could also make a model for Stockholm
and try to think like what is specific
about Stockholm I'll just look forward
compared to other cities
not that I know because this this
attempt has been like it's very much
um and indeed you could think how these
assumptions that Burgers Sunday
or the diet stand up on the slide and
they finally the textbook whether some
of them are
at typically
like for example this idea that cannot
be an early invention so European cities
tend to have
a long history and so for that reason
there are always parts of the city
equipment is already something you have
a growing City
there's also much more State
intervention
so we could think like how the European
city would be different from uh these
assumptions of burgers and what that
would mean then for the model works
I have no bundled but it could be an
interesting it could be an interesting
exercise
and is it something like it
so
it might also
um
in different areas
but some was less strict and less
regulated and it is nowadays yeah when
you also when you have a city that's
growing that fast
that is having one million extra
inhabitants in the very short period of
time yeah then the city grows very
organically I guess and it's also very
hard as a planner to keep up with the
pace but the city is scrolling it
regulation
when exactly it was taken
States
um
[Music]
okay and can you read it
or not snow
well I will ever ever look whether I can
I can see
okay I see some comments yeah
in the example from China how does the
ownership of people with State work is
the city grows over these villages
[Music]
um
okay I will I will I will it's it's time
for a break
um I will have a look at I will have a
look at what I find it in public
that it's hard for me to check this live
stream that also I also need to get out
of PowerPoint to check that out I am
teaching mostly for the people here and
I hope that the live stream Works more
I'm at let's say five minutes break
um it's four past six on my clock here
so let's start again uh nine past six or
ten past six
let's see
what's up
tomorrow
[Music]
there's no difference
foreign
okay
thank you
I've jumped foreign
something
thank you
has heard
one day
myself
yes
[Music]
it is
let's talk
questions
let's continue
with the conclusion for the first uh
hour of the class
let's go through it it seems
that Urban differentiation the fact that
rich and poor little different
neighborhoods the fact that you have
people from different ethnicities
different generations of newcomers that
they live in different neighborhoods
somehow that seems to be some
characteristic of most if not all cities
I've been showing you models from Africa
Los Angeles Chicago
and United Kingdom
and I've been talking about this model
of the Socialist or both socialists it
seems that in each of these levels there
is this idea that different groups of
society whether you define them in
socioeconomic classes or different
ethnicities or
self-identify as a racist but these
different groups they have different
parts of a city
but it also seems the difference local
features impact upon perfect forum
for example this Lake in Chicago
and you could see that there are
references to the wind's Direction in
some of these models migration patterns
Etc and obviously also local policies
and a transport system
a snake intervention in housing this ID
for example is canceled Estates for the
following years
and restrictions of mobility in a in the
Chinese complex system determining where
uh to live or where you could set your
kids to school uh strategies to counter
policies so that also means that most of
these models of urban form even if they
say this is the model of the American
city that they somehow wear birthmarks
that they are situated in a specific
space
in a specific type of Chicago or 1920s
was a model of the growing city and the
place already 10 years later
and this American economy has been hit
by crisis this model did not fall true
anymore because the city was not growing
at that fast pace and so it's always
about situating these models in time and
space and so that also makes it
necessary to provincialize
theories so much
um I'd like to show you some exam
questions to make you think like how how
will I ever
make you
uh like what kind of questions could you
expect from this and this is a question
that I've asked in 2016.
and you have the model of the South
African post-apartheid City by a
particular author and you know how
familiar all of you are with this video
in South Africa repeal of this Advantage
loss
ES
and so you there are some references to
this Legend
and then I ask you which elements of
burgers voids and Harrison
do you recognize in this model boxes
yeah so there could be a way to check
whether you've understood what these
models are about whether you're able to
apply that and to another one
I found it in a book but I don't
remember
if you would have a look I know I do it
I can look it up now
both publicly
I can tell you also because
um
so first hour these classical models of
Earth but also some more recent
place with these World models
but I'm going to discuss now is patterns
of segregation
yeah
how can we look at segregation in cities
and I will use the definition by two
American Authors again Messi and mental
Douglas Messi and Nancy dancer to
American sociologists who wrote a book
called American apartment
so you see this reference to the South
African cities but in the thinking on
segregation this book has been quite
important
and so you see here what is the
definition
first of all they focus on the
residential segregation I could also
discuss segregation in Leisure spaces
how many people 's Force for the places
where people spend their Leisure Time
our desegregated or I could look at work
segregation to people of different
socio-economic classes meet each other
but most of the work on segregation
focuses on residential section what is
residential segregation it's a degree to
reach two or four groups however you
find it live separately from each other
in different parts of the urban
environment
adult Solutions and what you've seen in
these models that I've been showing you
in the previous hours is that in most
cities
different groups
whether you define them in a
socio-economic way
for in this ethnicity race
self-identifying
that indeed in all of these cities
different groups live in different parts
of the city and so in each of these
cities where this models are
right it would make sense to look at
residential circulation
but what is important is that messian
doesn't want to make this more complex
and they say most of the research on
segregation has been too simplistic
because it looked at segregation in one
particular way
and so what I'm going to do with you now
is to look at or discuss five dimensions
of segregation
a pharmacy and then these are called
evenness exposure concentration
centralization and clustering
and most of the research on segregation
is discussing evenness and so I will
also look at it what is evenness
evenness refers
and I'm just reading what you see on the
slide now refers to the differential
distribution of two social groups
among aerial units in a city
and so a minority group
is said to be segregated if it is
unevenly distributed over aerial units
evenness is not measured in any absolute
sense but is scaled relative to some
other group
so we are able to say and this city
this is the example that you see there
the lights are segregated from Plex
or the low socioeconomic classes if you
may call that same like this are
segregated from
rich is segregated from so you always
need these two
so you see here that you can have index
I will use this here
an index of this similarity can be
calculated and I will give you two
examples
some years this goes rather well and
sometimes
this goes rather wrong imagine that you
have a city that is made up of
four districts
and in each of these
you have 75
whites and 25 legs
what would be
the index
of this similarity when I use
the major layer
we need to paste
off of the sum yeah that is what this
great Sigma is mean and now we need to
for each of these neighborhoods we need
to say what is the black population in
an area
divided by the total black population 25
25 100 minus
75 the white population in area one
divided by the total white population
what do we have here for one
neighborhood
zero
I need to calculate the sum for of this
measure for each of these neighborhoods
so that will be zero plus zero plus zero
to zero one half of 0 is 0.
the index of this similarity would be
zero
or zero percent
this corresponds with the effect that
you need to move
zero percent
of the population in order to get an
even distribution of white and black
across the city because you have an even
distribution in each of these four
neighborhoods you have as many whites as
you have in other parts of the system
um you can also look at another exhaust
where you would have
100 Plex living in one neighborhood
100 whites in another
100 whites in another and another 100
white in another name
if you would make the calculation now
then you would get to one
not going to do that with you but for
those who
are able to do this this means the
absolute number of this so if you get to
a negative number here then it becomes
positive again when you calculate it it
will be
then the number will be one
yeah
um because you can I can still do that
with you there's a sum of 100 the number
of blacks in the first neighborhood
minus 100 the total number of legs minus
the number of whites
and for each node each of these
neighborhoods you will get uh to the
number
uh one and here you will get one third
one third one third total two uh half of
two so one meaning you need to move 100
of the population
in order to get an even distribution of
these population groups across the city
either you move
33 Flex
from this neighborhood to this
neighborhoods
yeah and then you can get if you move 33
to each of these then you get an even
distribution of blacks across the city
or you move all the white people through
that black neighborhood and then you
would also get to it even descriptions
of people across the city according to
this neighborhoods
yeah and so this index of this
singularity
ranges from zero even distribution to
one very uneven distinction
and basically it corresponds with the
percentage of people that you're with
oof in order to get an even distribution
of people across different neighborhoods
and so this may be complicated but you
can just look at the practice so how
does this look like you would get to a
number
this is this percentage
[Music]
um
and what you see here for example is
that
um so zero plus an even distribution
that was this example
150 uneven yeah so the more you move to
the right on this slide more uneven the
cities are so what is particular is that
you see that first of all American
cities tend to be much more penetrated
than European ones
yeah so segregation when you look at the
dimensions even this
then you find out that in American
cities the poor for example are living
much more in particular parts of the
city and in the European context they
are a bit more spread across different
parts of the city
yeah
and so you see here for different cities
for different population groups
you see how this has been
yeah and again you always need to
compare it with another population group
so what has done is the tour of ends
verb compared to it than the ones who
are not considered
okay and so it's also interesting for
those who join me to enter
to see that according to these
statistics poverty enhancer in 2005. was
also much more
unevenly spread across the city and so
you had particular neighborhoods where
you had uh
that were marked by poverty much more
than in other Europeans
this will also be a scale issue for
Belgium and we have very small
statistical sectors that will be part of
the explanation
scale is important when these sectors
grow they will mask some of the
concentrations of poverty of Health that
you've been getting the statistics are
defined
so this measure of evenness
some more numbers
again you see that
90 and so you get close to one
Birmingham Bangladesh I read there all
time Bangladesh
so apparently it is Bangladeshi in UK
cities
are living very much in particular
neighborhoods of the city and in these
neighborhoods
you would find almost exclusively
Bangladesh and that explains why you
would need to move almost all these
Bangladeshi to other neighborhoods if
you would like to get to an even
distribution of Bangladeshi in UK cities
and so you see how this measure is being
used in order to say something about
residential segregation in these
different cities
poverty in Copenhagen the first Quinta
quintile will be like the first 20 of
the people according to the income
income distribution is much less
segregated and it's spread much more
evenly across the city than it is in
only other cities that are listed there
so do you understand what this measure
of evenness unevenness means
okay I get now to these four other
dimensions so what messian are arguing
is that we have been looking at
segregation mostly through this lens of
evenness
there are also four other times
which are worthwhile looking at the
question I'm sorry for that example with
the 100 black presidents and one in this
record
I didn't think what does it
what does it mean for it to be one-third
for the for my residential conception
well I'm I'm just I am just for each of
these neighborhoods
I am calculating I didn't want to go too
much into this I am calculating this
and I start from the black neighborhoods
they're the measure or the number will
be 100 divided by 100 the total number
of likes minus net neighborhood in our
zero whites divided by total number of Y
is 300. that will be one
for the white neighborhoods
yeah and I have three of them
the measure will be there are zero
blacks and I have minus 100 the number
of Lights in that neighborhood divided
by the total number of bites 300.
yeah so I get here to 1 divided by three
so I get one plus one third one plus one
third plus one third two
two divided by two is one
but it doesn't say anything about its
neighborhoods I'm calculating something
at the scale of the city and for that
for that I need to calculate this
measure for these four neighborhoods
oh okay
and then I so I I think I kind of
realize
and then I need to make the Sun
of this number in each of these so that
will be some of
one plus
perspective
and I need to divide it
right
that's why
so the index of the similarity is one
in each this case 100 percent meaning
that
either 100 percent of flex or 100 of y's
need to move in order to get to an even
distribution of both whites and Bricks
across the city
okay
four other yeah
[Music]
yeah that's the percentage
so then this would be 100
and this would be zero and if the index
of this similarity would be 0.5
then you would have 50 percent
and that would be 50 years
so you move close to one and you are
close to
this is a measure that you would often
find
I could also be often
checked like our segregation
uh changing across time
that would be the index of the
similarity for first Handler has moved
from
0.40 to 0.50 meaning poor people got
more concentrated over time
for more cigarette sorry yeah
I got less evenly distributed across
five
okay four other
Dimensions I'm going to move through
them rather quickly
residential exposure reversively
sorry refers to the degree of potential
contacts
yeah or the possibility of interaction
in this case
in each of the neighborhoods there is a
similar degree of exposure here there is
when when these people limit their lives
to the neighborhood there will be no
exposures
yeah and so this degree is
pretty close to evenness but not
completely because for exposure and the
number will also be depending upon the
total size of these communities
if the total black population in the
city is very low
then the chances that you will get to
meet a black person are are lower
already yeah so the size of the group is
important if you would make a measure
for exposure
concentration Dimension number three
refers to the relative amount of
physical space occupied by a minority
group in the urban environment
this will be again be dependent upon the
size of this one
we have here Manhattan
and we have in these different colors
again these different ethnic or racial
groups or people self-identifying with a
particular group and so you see that in
shades of purple you have the Asian
population and so you have
China done and that's where most of
these Asians are concentrated they take
up a very small amount of space this is
a dense neighborhood and most Asians
living in Manhattan or living in that
particular part of an exit and so
concentration
the relative amount of physical space
occupied by a minority group
number four centralizing
it relates to the degree to which a
group is spatially located near the
center of an earth
I don't know what the center of New York
would be but if you say it's Wall Street
then these Asians are living very
centralized
and while black Africans
in the case of New York are not living
centralized
the same goes for this example of
poverty in Brussels poverty is very much
centralized
neighborhoods which are marked by
poverty are close to the city center
Parisian case poverty is very much
decentralized that's much more an issue
of this peripheral Bond years
and in the last Dimension is clustery
the degree to which is
um aerial units inhabited by minority
members and join one another or not
I don't know how familiar you are with
New York
but I remember walking out of the metro
station and Flushing close to Flushing
Meadows where you have the tennis
tournament and that was another
neighborhood and that was very much
marked by a presence of Chinese people
yeah so you have
um
clusters of
at least two clusters of Agents one in
this Chinatown Manhattan and then
another one somewhere here in Flushing
yeah and so is
um the presence of Asians is it cluster
no because there is two neighborhoods
um which are quite far away from each
other
evenness exposure
what was it centralization concentration
plus two and so I could also ask you
in the exam
to discuss
the three most relevant dimensions of
Messi and length are the ones that you
still remember
um out of these five to discuss
socio-economic segregation requests
is over the clustered or not
centralized
is it concentrated
or is there an evenness
yeah the data might allow you to say
something about it or not
um I already told you when I pointed at
this High numbers of unevenness in enter
But scale is very important
yeah if this is
a pattern of rich and poor
then you will only detect it as
segregation when you are able to study
it at the scale of these
specific neighborhoods and if your
statistical units are this big
then it would be then this would be a
very even when you're able to study it
at
this scale then this is a very uneven
and so the more refined these statistics
allow you to go the higher one would
assume these levels of segregation or
evenness and evenness will also be
so scale and the scale through which you
look so is something very uh important
as well
I saw a hand somewhere at the back I
don't know where the description is
still relevant yes
um
well I could imagine for example where
you have a CBD
and where do you have four neighborhoods
around the CBD parked by poverty
and you would say that poverty is
centralized
but it's not clustered
and it is also is it concentrated then
relative amount of space yeah
they are related to each other but
there's still something distinct about
it you could also have concentrations of
poverty which are very decentralized
I still put the poor take a very little
space but this is far away from the city
center
and then the question could still be
whether this poverty is clustered
whether you have in the east of the city
or
districts which are adjacents
to each other where is poverty is
concentrated or whether this poverty is
also decentralized
but also not clustered and not
conceptual and so you you could you
could imagine a
is centralized
and you would also expect it to be
somewhere close to it
or not about for for
groups of people in the city
like
um
and you would say poverty is centralized
in
the poor people are centralized in
Brussels rich people are not because
they live mostly on the periphery
something yeah
well then it will still be relevant to
say that
okay so five dimensions of segregation
which also allow you to speak
with a little bit more detail about the
social differentiation that you find
so it's not only about evenness
people living in different neighborhoods
of the city you can also discuss
concentration clustering centralization
exposure
you have another question sorry are you
starting with the confiscation
um does it like matter like the portion
like the size of the population like I
can imagine a city that they're just not
very many very few people are poor there
and then you could have a couple of
neighborhoods well and
it would be called concentrated but you
could also Imagine a situated
power of many people yeah I must admit
that I I don't know exactly how this
would be measured and how you would
operationalize such a measure but here
it will be about
like the size of the group
how how many Chinese do you have to be
about the density so they were talking
about the tower it will also be if they
take a less square meters if they live
um but I don't I don't know how you
would exactly operationalize that in
this kind of way
but for me the important thing is that
you understand that there are different
dimensions so that you can understand
this
uh spatial differentiation between rich
or between like
or between male and female or between
Global sexual
but
she can look at it in many different
ways that you would be able to study it
through these fine language
for me that's that's uh that's important
and I will not ask you how to measure
that's around to how to operationalize
that
I hope that you understand that it can
be meaningful
um to do this and that this is for
example uh
figure from the work of this festival's
photographer from Belgium who said well
you have different kinds of cities
topological and dramatic cities and it
matters whether the rich for example
still need to you could imagine cities
where rich
do not need to come who do not need to
speak to for example in the Brussels
case these poor neighborhoods are so
closely really so closely
um
located to these neighborhoods where
rich people work for example
that you will get a lot of conflicts
around around space but in other kinds
of city that would not necessarily be
the case yeah and so for that for that
reason these kind of Dimensions do
matter
and I could I could ask you to apply
that to a particular City
okay 17 minutes left to discuss the
causes of segregation so why is it
that different population groups take up
different parts of the city
I guess that all of you have
some kinds of ideas what could it be
about like what kind of explanations
with Uber why is it that rich and poor
black and white
Hispanic Asian people of
virgin people of a different class that
they live in a different part of the
city
why is that
example when it comes inspiration or
incoming
City they will often just choose the the
neighborhood
agency something that helps them find
work
system
around
for the country
same language
supermarkets or other services that are
created for the purpose of this
International
you have another explanation
I mean uh probably the difference in the
house and choices
for example infrastructure uh
okay so it could be about what you're
able to afford and the financial limits
that you have it could be about the
choice to live amongst people like you
as possible
they said that some agents don't
know okay
okay
um yeah
um there are many there are many
explanations and it is it is
uh what is important for me that I'm
going to try to do in a very short
period of time is to run through a
couple of typical explanations but I
find important is and that's why I'm
showing you this graph I think you've
seen it already in some of the previous
classes about Professor crosses
um so what is important for me is that
different geographers or
Urban thinkers or people working in the
domain of perfect Studies have been
coming up with different explanations
that have often it matters very much
from which sub-discipline
that you're looking at and so feminist
geographers have been
pointing at different explanations of
segregation then Marxist geographers
yeah so for that reason it is important
to situate these theories to explain
segregation
on this match and my take on it is that
one explanation is not better than the
other but in order to understand what is
happening we need to look at potential
limits of people and Marxist will have a
big theory about it and but also a
choice
and it will be mostly these
days
who are eager to explore the preferences
of people
and why people want to live in a
particular neighborhood and they will
also then
go to interview escape with people why
is it that you move
and so my point is I think it's
important that you
unravel these different theories made up
by these different thinkers from
different disciplines
um quantitative geographers in the 60s
were not so interested explanations of
segregation but they had a rich set of
mapping tools to understand these
spatial patterns
but they were not so interested in
explanations
ecological models Burgers she would go
and read Burgess 1925 concentric zone
model why do these different population
groups can look in different parts of
the city almost like you would have
these Pioneer of vegetations right
imagine a mute area of land first you
will find grass and then you would find
shrips and as the shrubs grow the grass
cannot survive anymore because there's
no lighting
for the for the grass and then you would
get these big trees and these shrubs can
also not survive so you would have
competition amongst different types of
vegetation you could have competition
amongst different populations
you would have Invasion the most desired
parts so we talk about ecological models
because when you read these
um 100 year old theories that often you
find these analogies with
um ecological models
for vegetation
or the survival the fittest
so ecological models they draw on
theories of expansion competition
Invasion succession of different
countries
technology to what you find in among
plants
for Marxist geographers different
neighborhoods different
build environments are parts of circuits
of capital
and so to understand why different
neighborhoods are produced for different
people we need to understand the flows
of capital David Harvey would would say
and
um the circuits in which this built
environment features
for instance I'm not going to discuss
this whole
this whole figure but for example to
understand
supervisation we also need to understand
the what they call from the accumulation
regime in which this supervisation came
about
and how for example after the second
world war in Belgium
supervisation was promoted by the state
also because it was a start of a
consumption spiral when you suburbanize
you need a car
so people will buy more cars you will
need a fridge because this local shop is
far away you will need a freezer yeah
and so there's a whole consumption
spiral that starts when people
suburbanize and so in order to
understand why supervisation of the
middle classes was promoted in Belgium
after the second world war we need to
understand the accumulations regime in
which this functions or
who understands why neighborhoods are
being gentrified to understand the
landscape because many of you have
pluses by material by clicking and as
well then he will explain you how this
rant Gap works
yeah so he tries to understand when you
when you look at gentrification through
a random perspective and say well the
fact that you have
an invasion now of gentrifiers to to
borrow this word from Burgers to
understand that you need to understand
the brand Gap and the fact that profits
can be made in this neighborhoods so
this is part of capital accumulation so
radical Marxist geographers will focus
on the fact that you have the rich in
the suburbs or that you have the rich in
this gentrifying neighborhoods they will
try to understand how that fits within
this process of capital accumulation
better explanation of segregation will
therefore be rooted in the circuits of
capital that's Harvey with strong
in the text by my campaign you will read
about the Neo Weber which there are more
constraints to people than only these
Financial constraints
it's also about discrimination it's
about the social capital when you have
how you hear about houses that
production etc etc and so you will read
about these different
um resources that might be important in
finding that way
and then also the constraints that link
to that
what you have there at the bottom is
discrimination by uh people in the real
estate business
for different population groups in
Belgium you see that there are some
significance
numbers
so it's not only about the financial
resources it's also about your last name
and whether that's Dutch or French or
whether that is an Arabic name that will
impact upon how easy it is for you to
find an apartment or a place to buy in
in Belgium
behavioral geographers they are
interested in the preferences
and the perceptions and the
decision-making of individual so for
them to explain
supervisations and the fact that these
middle class families move to the
suburbs they will think about push and
pull factors why do these people prefer
to leave the city
it is polluted
is overcrowded it's you have all the
grind them
now why are people attracted to the
Circuit so there are different reasons
for them
but in order to understand
segregation you also need to understand
the preferences of these different
populations it's not only about
restraints
it's not only about capital accumulation
it's also about different groups of
people preferring to live in different
kinds of environments as students will
also be segregated from non-students
because we have a certain many of you
will have a similar set of preferences
that make you not live in the suburbs I
guess but that will make you live closer
to the university and closer to places
where interesting things are happening
and then you also read in this text by
Ronald
and you also read about ethnic cultural
if you could also look at these
preferences through an ethnic lens and
for example
um to explain why
people of Moroccan Turkish origin in the
city of antwer why they live in
particular neighborhoods you will need
to understand better Financial
restraints many of them would be rather
poor and so they are forced to live in
in key parts of the city or cheaper
parts
but you also need to understand their
preferences and you can also look at
that through an ethnic lens and many of
these Moroccans will be eager to live
close to a mosque or to his opposed to
Turkish failure or close to a Halal
Butcher and that makes them
particles it could also look through
these preferences where you could look
at these preferences through an ethnic
list
use the same lens to understand why
more and more these Moroccan families or
people or families of origin also move
to the suburbs
there will might also be
a preference really to ethnicity for
example
um who studied this in the answer
context found out already quite some
time ago but
in these ethnic neighborhoods as there
are also being called you also have very
tight networks of social control
so to move out of these neighborhoods is
also too out of this to move away from
the social control in these areas so you
could have another preference that is
linked to this definition
um so the ethnic cultural approach where
you look at these preferences through an
ethnic lens and obviously it can also be
criticized
both modern geographers they will try to
understand how housing is important in
identity kind of ways in which you
conceptualize yourself and the meaning
that housing or living in a particular
part of the city gives to you so you see
here a book entitled the platform the
meaning of house
and housing is more than just a roof
above your head it's also about boom and
feeling at home
and so this post post-modern geographers
they try to understand segregation from
this lens and so they try to understand
what moving to the suburbs means or
these middle class people who did that
in this
was the thing to do if you had the money
you're reading the quote well let me
move to the suburbs and so this idea of
social Mobility
and showing off somehow was quite
important in understanding why this
group of people moved to the suburbs and
we can do the same for
um
for for why these gentrifiers
to move back is often set into the
cities it will also be about a certain
identity and
about how that gives meaning to to their
ideas and how they understand themselves
in comparison with others who then
living foreign
on these pictures
and to get them to live in the city
because it helps them
um to to have a tech space
yeah so if you want to have money to
spend in a city you will need in the
building system you will eat and
in the City
now the city council can
I I I'm not really making myself very
clear but the bottom line is that it's
postmodern geographers decided to
understand why people end up in
different parts of the city through the
lens of identity and how we identify as
people with the place where we live and
what that means for how we look at
ourselves and others looking in other
parts of the city foreign
[Music]
so I could give you another exam
question like look at this map here the
distribution of people of Turkish and
Moroccan origin and answer how would
these different geographers explain it
and many of the explanations that you've
given in the beginning of
when I started to talk about the course
of segregation have been studied by
these different
a geographers working in some
disciplines or people in different parts
of what extent called Urban studies
yeah of course why do we do that is
because we assume that this matters and
that segregation has effects and has
consequences
that many that people have been
eager to understand what does it mean
for a poor person to live in a
neighborhood that is smart Bible I mean
most of the other poor people living
around it does it matter whether you
live in that kind of neighborhoods or
whether you as a person you've been a
more mixtape and yet Miller classes
yeah or does it matter for a city
and when you have this segregation of
blacks living in a particular part of
the city and then why it's taking a
different Gap
or would it be better to strive for this
kind of more even distribution of uh of
blacks and whites in a particular City
or rich and poor or uh young people and
old people whatever social categories
so next week
I will not discuss patterns of
segregation causes of segregation but I
will discuss these effects
and also policies of social mixing that
are related so then we get to the heart
of why does it matter to to study this
um well is because we assume that
segregation of concentration
centralization that is at all ethics for
the people that we have been talking
about for these two hours
so in two weeks time
another class on the effects of
segregation next week
Tuesday
field trip to Antwerp where we will ask
us
on the field many of these issues as
well so I look forward to see many of
you in answer
Tuesday eight something in the in the
railway station
so see you soon
thank you
[Music]