yes
I've done my best now to restart the
stream
maybe you can ask whether it's it's
working it's difficult for me to check
I thought I had been doing what I've
been doing last week it seemed to work
then
but um also for those who use the
streams to to study
I think it makes more sense to use last
year's stream also for today's lecture
for those who are following now because
I I prefer to teach for the ones here
meaning that I will be in front of my
screen I should also put that on again
[Music]
um
or in between in the classroom and that
will not be recorded and last year I've
just been streaming from my office
because we were not
supposed to have lectures anymore so I
feel that it's better to
for all the last year's team and also
for the ones who can't be here today but
also in case you want to study the
slides are 1990 99 the same
so um I think it makes more sense to use
last year's live stream also for last
week's class
thank you
um
do you have any information about the
stream now
you think it's working
okay and I'll I'll do my best to
move it in that direction
um
okay so let's suppose that the stream is
working
if not everyone can rely on last year's
team
um
okay I think quite many of you are here
like I don't know how many students have
expected to have I think 70 or 80
percent this year
um could the ideal of social mix so I I
told you already I told you already that
in many cities across the world there
has been a concern with segregation it
has been supposed that segregation has
negative effects
on uh poor people for example and that
you're worse off when you're poor when
you're living in a neighborhood where
with a concentration of poverty
rather than in a mixed neighborhood
where you have both Working Class People
and another philosophy
um already in the 19th century in the
hey days of the Industrial Revolution
um you have very different groups
um the capitalistic bourgeoisie and the
utopian socialists yeah so both the
Bourgeois and the Socialists who were
afraid
or who were thinking that
um concentrations of laborers in
particular neighborhoods of the city for
example here in Brussels in modern Bay
at that time or an antwer in um and for
the good house but this would have
negative effects
and the bourgeoisie was afraid that
concentrations of laborers might lead to
Revolutions
that socialist thinking would become
dominant with these neighborhoods and
that you would never report that people
would get on the streets okay and the
utopian socialists they were scared that
um
this these concentrations of laborers
would
um make it more difficult to strive for
an egalitarian society
and so on both ends of the political
Spectrum you had people who were
thinking that in places such as
Manchester or ginto Brussels where you
have these new uh working class
neighborhoods that this was something
bad to be counteracted
this ideal is still very dominant
nowadays
and here you see a quote
from
[Music]
well the Brussels Capital Region quite
an old one but I think current policy
documents you would find similar quotes
stating that contrary to the American
city the ideal type for the European
city is based on a mix of functions and
people
I think it's important to make a
distinction between these two things on
the one hand they refer to a functional
mix meaning that they would like to
strive for neighborhoods where you have
a mix of the residential function
apartments and houses
and for example offices
or shops saying that well it's not good
to have neighborhoods where you only
have
a residential friction and other
neighborhoods where you only have
offices
and so we strive for
Brussels with neighborhoods where you
have a functional mix
yeah but then the other thing this is
what we are interested in today is
saying well we also want Brussels like
other European cities to have
neighborhoods with a mix of people poor
people and rich people
and in Brussels there have been many
different moments where this
this topic of social mix has been
agenda
I think those of you
have not arrive to vessels only a month
ago I might have heard of these
discussions around Creator books the
social housing Estates on my list
so in the periphery of the Brussels
Capital Region and therefore yeah quite
some media reports about crime
yeah and then the issue of well you have
all these
to be
accommodated on the social housing
estate in uh in Brussels and in Belgium
more generally you need to fall below a
certain income
stressful yeah meaning that it's mainly
the poorest of the poor that you will
concentrate on these social housing
instance
and so then you had discussions well is
that a good thing is this not leading to
this culture where crime is uh or common
and conservative politicians would raise
this kind of dog service
Progressive politicians would wonder
well is that then a neighborhood where
it is easy for poor people to climb the
social network wouldn't it be easier to
be socially mobile when you are not only
surrounded by other poor people but when
you are living between poor and rich
people alive
a neighborhood in underlift and
obviously also in the wake of these
terrorist attacks in 2015 there were a
lot of concerns also in the
international league
about more of me and there were reports
about more than make as difficult as a
ghetto
it's been looking at the statistics
I think
is the municipality most
people of Moroccan and origin the
boost followers of Islam but it's still
less than half
so in the in international media it was
often reported as this model made was a
municipality with only
uh
Moroccan
people and people of Moroccan Origins
and when you look at the statistics that
was not the case nonetheless
they were concerns hopefully but also
conditionally
um about mobile Bank being a safe haven
for terrorists and breeding graph or
there
are affected you have this concentration
of people of the same origin was
then the reason to be to be concerned
so both when it comes social Mobility
and when it comes to
cultural integration and newcomers there
are concerns in a city such as Brussels
about the concentration of either people
or people of foreign origin these are
two different issues social mobility and
social cultural integration and so I
hint was there a question
um
no I am I'm trying to explain you
I'm not saying that there is that these
are examples one is the social picks but
I'm trying to explain you that in many
cities across the roads and I will start
from a couple of religion examples this
ideal or social mix is high on the
political object and I'm referring to
this paper boss issue and modern-day
after the pillars the text has two
moments where social mixtures highly
debated local media and in the case of
these terrorist attacks also is
international
um Brussels we moved to Ghent
and a former colleague of mine
has written a nice book about
gentrification
his name is
so for those who know the Dutch who are
interested in a piece of things they
they find some interesting literature
there
and you see a quote from an elder man of
the City of Kent
uh talking about for those who know
neighborhoods such as Bridge support
neighborhoods that have a similar
history
as modern big in Brussels or
um
in Antwerp neighborhoods that have
developed in this 19th century
industrial industrialization
and
um so neighborhoods with
um
higher than average percentage of
unemployment higher than average
percentage of people also a higher than
average percentage of people of foreign
what was this elder man saying well when
I attract young families
preferably with a job preferably double
income families that will improve my
social tissue
my textbooks and my neighborhood life
I think these are different concerns the
tech space
is something something important I'm
sorry I'm in Belgium about 40 to 50
percent of the municipal budget comes
from local Texas most of it is a
percentage on the local income tax and
percentage on the
um on the income tax meaning that if you
have more rich people in your
municipality that you will have a higher
Municipal budget
and the other part comes from lent and
house value
um but so why does this elder man again
find or that attract young families
preferably with a joke
middle class of the white families is to
improve this local Tech space to have
more budget for the city of cats but on
top of that
he's saying it's also important to
improve my social tissue and I will go
further into that but often there the
underlying thought is that for example
when you have rich and poor people then
you have
families with the job and families
without a job that you will get diverse
social networks for example and then in
these networks jobs can be found or
people can be helped with homework Etc
and so this
ID for the importance to attract young
families prefer preferably connections
it's not only for to improved Tech space
of the city but also to improve the
social tissue and neighborhood life
in very much a similar way and we moved
to the city of Antwerp and we have been
visiting this undcredible port
neighborhoods the neighborhood where I
think 25 of the newcomers in Antwerp
passed through before moving to other
parts of the city and neighborhood that
is quite similar to this transition zone
that Burgess was describing in 19th
century Chicago
and I've been talking there about a lot
of regulations
and then affected shopkeepers in the
neighborhood but also
regulations that concern the subdivision
of houses
and you see there that in the previous
governance agreement in Antwerp it was
stated that the city wants a larger
share of single-family dwellings in this
particular neighborhood in the housing
Supply in order to attract families I
always find it interesting to see this
kind of words often youngsters means
young people or foreigners what you see
here is that families is used to call
this mantis
double income families often wide
structures so that is why the
transformation of single-family
dwellings into smaller housing entities
is not desirable and for those who join
to enter we have been discussing how
could you support the arrival function
in this neighborhood well when people
are looking for a very cheap place to
live and they will rent a room for even
just a mattress
and that's what they look for the
cheapest roof above their heads what you
see here is that the city of Antwerp is
not supporting the Bible version but
finds it important to bring another kind
of people uh to this neighborhood namely
richer families
so again you see efforts here
to
um
to earn this unto elephant North into a
socially mixed neighborhood where you
have newcomers next to uh white families
who can afford
to buy such a big house
just for for the use of one of one
family
in the art in the article by Tom Slater
and you've also seen references to
the situation in the UK
and the United States and and he refers
to this housing market renewal projects
where
um different in different parts of the
country
neighborhoods which were mainly
inhabited by poor people often poor
people of foreign origin you had
demolition projects and you had the
creation of new dwellings that tried to
cater for different audiences
and again you see the
this is a quote from the artist later
you see that the ID was that
um in these neighborhoods that have been
transformed uh that the inhabitants the
people who used to live there were
seriously disadvantaged by where they
lived and the idea was that living in
such a neighborhood being poor in such a
neighborhood
accessor based poverty makes it worse
about basically living in such a
neighborhood is worse than living in
another name
and that it will be more difficult to
find out of poverty in such a
neighborhood other parts of the city so
for this reason I was a big problem and
project to basically demolish much of
the housing in these neighborhoods and
to build new houses that catered for
different audiences
um Slater also refers to this hope six
program in the UK and the U.S sorry
for example Cabrini Green a neighborhood
a couple of miles to the north of the
loop in Chicago last week I've been
talking quite a bit about Chicago a
neighborhood with a very bad reputation
for drug use
and many crime and many other things
and again what has been done there is
that many of these
apartment books have been torn down have
been demolished and that
you houses have been built again trying
to cater for another kind of it's trying
to bring the middle class to a
neighborhood that was previously mainly
inhabited
and then in the separation of the PS you
might have heard of this function system
where many of the original residents of
the neighborhood such as that brother
voucher and basically to give them a
discount on
their parents price in other parts of
the city trying to encourage them to
move to better off
neighborhoods in other parts of Chicago
so again you see attempts to mix
neighborhoods
in the conviction that the concentration
of poverty is bad that it leads to crime
and it leads to drug use and that it is
bad for these inhabitants
South Africa
yeah
well I think the outcome
um
there are many many papers about this
and many scholars are looking at
different sites of this metal
but
um
I think in the article by Tom Slater and
page
369 I see here it is stated that No
Effects have been reported for a number
of outcomes
and that adverse effects on the delete
delinquency
and physical health of
um adolescent males in particular have
been reported
um but positive effects on adult mental
health and education and health of young
women so it depends very much
what you're looking at
but in any case
studies who tried and to find out like
what happened to the people who moved to
middle class neighborhoods and found
fairly adverse effects and in any case
one good question whether such a
well because the
project
was the best one to try and improve the
situation of poor people in Chicago
yeah
I will discuss the the effects of such
programs in more detail but before doing
that I wanted to highlight that in many
countries across the world us UK many
Belgian cities
and basically all over Western Europe in
South Africa
attends have been made to create
socially mixed neighborhoods in the
conviction that's a segregation as a
concentration of poverty is bad for
people living in uh
foreign
[Music]
of projects that you see here are about
bringing the middle class to
neighborhoods which used to be uh
predominantly predominantly
dysfunction program that I was just
talking about is also doing the other
way in doing it the other way around
because it tries to bring poor people
um to middle class neighborhoods so this
is also a project where
middle class neighborhoods are also
becoming more more mixed
because by giving these rent subsidies
through this voucher system it allows
people
underprivileged people to move to a
better of parts of the city as well
but I will I will come back to that
um
for now
well
we it's good that you already started
wondering about every
ethical difference
but as I said for now it's it's
important that you see that
in many parts in many corners of the
world this
um ideal of socially mixed socially
mixed neighborhoods seems to be a very
stable kind of idea
and it's very predominant among policy
makers both on the left and on the right
so on both ends of the political
Spectrum you find this pretty poor
neighborhoods that house people of
different origins or people of different
socio-economic efforts
two questions we need to ask about this
is it possible then to create social
indexed mixed neighborhoods and then
third and is it or second the second
question is it a desirable to do that
and
the article white illustrator gives or
turns later gives in this article a very
clear answer
referring to this whole six
program in the United States and housing
markets renewal in the UK is stating
that what have they done they have
basically just shifted over the
elsewhere this has not been a remedy to
Poverty this has just made poor people
elsewhere in the city
the mode of production that shapes Urban
environments which we live
it's referring to the capitalistic
system there the system of the the mode
of production of capitalism
produces concentrations of poverty that
many
policy makers as we have seen rejoice in
breaking up yet that same mode of
production churning intact produces
further concentrations just down the
street
I still remember one of my former
professors saying that well many of
these attempts to create socially mixed
neighborhoods by attracting middle class
people
to
for example poor neighborhoods
in Brussels has just shifted this
poverty elsewhere and for that reason he
um
he made this comparison with moving
chairs on the deck of the Titanic people
remain poor that you just make them move
somewhere else but this does not
improve their socio-economic position
this does not help them to climb to
social media in in the text 5 and again
all you've also also seen this reference
to water but
oops
so when you look at that
um it it seems to be very hard to create
a social mix
yeah the same goes for Brussels I've
been referring to this article by
material by clicking already in chapter
one
um and basically what mature has been
doing is to study people moving out of
gentrifying neighborhoods in bristles
what happens to people who move out of
neighborhoods in Brussels that are
gentrified
and basically he made a distinction
between different clusters of people and
if I'm correct then cluster one
consisted mainly of Highly Educated
young professionals where do they move
as neighborhoods in Brussels gentrified
they move to Antwerp and Yash and also
some of the municipalities of rabba one
law and these are municipalities
these people find a joke in another city
in another part of Belgium they move out
of this gentrifying neighborhoods and
they
move to a place closer to the place
where they cook and that's where it is
cluster two
consisted of more working philosophy
last people with a lower than average
income where do they move
first of all to
um
well municipalities along the canal
and such as Holland and hillford
I don't know how familiar all of you are
with the geography of Belgium already
but these are also municipalities small
towns that have gone through a process
of industrialization and where you will
find small houses that will be cheaper
than the houses you would find in these
gentrified team records in Brussels yeah
so what you see here is that
gentrification comes with displacement
for example through a municipality such
as Villanova
but as you see these clusters you can
find rather far from Brussels
many
towns cities in this 19th century built
of industrialization in person in
Belgium so these are municipalities
where you would find housing or a rather
cheap price
yeah so if you follow material by
clicking his arguments then you would
see well what happens here is that by
trying to improve
the lives of poor people in Brussels
through creating the social mix
attracting the middle class to these
neighborhoods what you see is that these
people move
are displaced to other municipalities
they also have concentrations of poor
people that but they are located in much
worse situations locations when it comes
to finding a job
and so what is happening here this is
Shifting the chairs on the deck of the
Titanic poverty still exists but by
attracting the middle class to some
neighborhoods or Brussels you move
poverty elsewhere
to places where people can afford to
live
and these are
neighborhoods that we have been visiting
in inshallah for example
where buying a house or renting an
apartment will be much cheaper than at
least in in section or some of the other
gentrifying parts of Brussels
this map shows something very similar
for Android
those who join to antler might recognize
its first ring the medieval answer the
second ring
19th century industrial antler
um and what it what is not
um
visualizes is a synthesis index of this
advantage and you see that in some
neighborhoods there are no big changes
uh in the last years in this index they
are yellow
for example Louis ball
social housing Estates that we have
visited remains yellow situation there
does not really change
you also see other parts of the city
for example a luncheon
at the area around the museum that we
have been growing up
you see that this is blue yeah and many
of the inner city neighborhoods in
entrepreneurs for example are also blue
yeah
at the same time you see that other
parts of the city for example medicine
outside of this 19th century well that
you see a worsening of the synthesis
that's also here through this map you
could see that well some neighborhoods
are attracting or middle class people
but poverty is shifted elsewhere in the
city is moving to other parts of the
urban region and this map is just uh
giving you the situation for the
municipality of the city of Antwerp but
if you would include the whole province
of that or you might see that for
example
for people who know culture
um
the Drupal region
we have display factories factors in the
past that you would see a worsening of
the situation
so we can try to attract middle class
people that's what the city of Ventura
Pacific building you can try to attract
the middle classes back to the city
but this displaces
people from these neighborhoods who
cannot afford to live there anymore so
this moves over the elsewhere
Russian
well I I'm a submitted I don't know all
the applications in this in the specific
index but I guess it will be about
average income
unemployment and maybe some other
complicators that say something about
this thing
um but I should have I should have put
so much of what we see here
confirms this ID of Slater when clicking
in that well trying to create a social
mix in some parts of the city will
shift poverty will make poverty move
elsewhere I will create
that's what Slater said will create
other concentrations
of poverty this is just down the street
inshallahua for the case of this
gentrifying neighborhoods Over Us in
bone for This Ginger flying so that's
verb in medicine in government in other
parts of these Urban regions
there are examples in the world where
mixed neighborhoods are being created
but that is only possible
when City councils or governments can
have a serious impact
open
upon who's living in in specific
neighborhoods
um in some parts of the world
um Scholars write about inclusionary
housing or inclusionary zoning
forcing for example real estate
developers who develop a high tower full
of apartments
to
um
dedicates a certain percentage of these
residents residential units to people
who fall below a certain income
threshold
and so you can create
a socially mixed neighborhood
if you force
real estate Developers
to
um
well in in newly built projects
to have a certain percentage of
Apartments of for people of a certain if
they fall below a certain inconsistent
in Antwerp I've been talking about this
caltex neighborhood
this was the length of the port in
public hands and so the city council
could also sell this land to Developers
with a lot of conditions and so
developers could buy this lens under the
condition that's that they built 25 of
the residential units for social housing
15 rent 10 to buy and that they
reserved 50 of the units at affordable
prices
and that was not fairly affordable but
at least you could not ask whatever you
wanted these prices could not Skyrocket
could not ask whatever you wanted for
these residential units and so you could
argue a socially mixed neighborhood has
been developed here almost from scratch
there's all these white blocks that you
see here are new and only the brown ones
existed but that was possible because
the lens was publicly owned and could be
sold to developers under the condition
that they reserved this kind of uh
units for certain categories of people
and then we could look who is able to
rent or buy these units well in the belt
in case you need to fall below a certain
income at thresholds in order to be able
to eligible to be eligible for a social
housing
yeah the same goes for this
affordability
um criteria
um I don't know what how what was the
price exactly but I see here that um you
could earn up to 58 000 Euro of family
uh almost 4 000 Euro added for each
additional person so these are quite
uh quite High I think already but the
bottom line is that these developers
could not just build whatever they
wanted
that they needed to meet certain
criteria and that they also needed to
reserve quite a bit of number of units
for people
belong to different income computers
at the lowest income categories social
housing
so associately mixed neighborhoods when
it comes to Green goals yeah when it
comes to poverty and wealth could be
created but that was only possible
because there was a serious intervention
of the city council
in in this in Belgium
the the government or public authorities
are not really able to intervene that
much in terms because it's only laser
flop there's six percent of the units
which are social housing in Brussels are
10 and all the rest
um with a couple of exceptions minor
exceptions all the risk is the market
it's either people's own house or people
who rent a house from another office
but there are cities across the world
where you have 50 social housing okay
enough for example or Amsterdam is
another city a high percentage
it also means that as a council you can
intervene quite a bit the rule is where
in the Belgian case where
about 90 of the people need to find a
house or accommodation on the market you
will see that attempts to create a
social mix quickly lead to displacement
and quickly lead to concentrations of
poverty elsewhere in uh
particular house mix looks like and how
much facility councils can intervene in
in the house
um
there has been a time when the social
Housing Association sold kind of quite
some units
in any case there's a little bit of
Courage
and this type of models are attractive
for the developers right this question
about like I would think developers are
thinking about profits yeah as long as
they as long as they can still make
profits this is possible
and the same goes for this inclusionary
housing as long as a developer is able
to
make profits then this is awesome
in this case I don't think that the
developer said to pay a lot of money for
the city to get this piece of
them and because they were also asked to
because they had to develop the parts
and the streets
and they had to take there to develop
this social housing
so the city could have earned much more
money by selling this piece of land for
the highest price to a developer who
wanted to build a Sparkles for the
wealthiest of people that shows to do
things different
and there are many parts of the world
where we have these kind of schemes
hello
um
okay is social mix feasible the answer
is yes
it is feasible it is possible to create
socially mixed neighborhoods but it is
very hard to do that in a situation
where the market rings
because then
trying to attract middle class families
to a poor neighborhood will lead to
displacement of poor families to other
parts of the urban region in this case
that will not happen because you reserve
25 of the neighborhood to people who
fall below the certificate
and as long as these units are social
housing is 25 will remain there for this
population
and so you
allow
for people to live
in a neighborhood
where
belongs to middle class for the upper
middle class at 25 percent
um hope these units goes to very rich
people who can afford to spend one
million euros
another question
and like this could be like
social takes early in this one
particularly
radius area in the city but then
wouldn't this be like our classic
example actually should wear like um
capital is being
for illness because even I mean just
from experiences your housing I don't
know
example usually these are like very
up-to-date luxury buildings and um there
are so affordable and social housing
however this then changes
so it might there might be different
but then the general effect would
actually
benefit
development
found it not like actually the people
who are living there beforehand and
maybe have to preserve it
um
but I think in this case you talk about
people who lived there we're just
understand already that was not so much
the case here because you only had a
couple of hundreds people you developed
a neighborhood for thousands of people
um it was a neighborhood that was uh
more to related I was not so much
put in this
wouldn't this just be another example of
gentrification
and not really attempting to solve
or trying to
purchases
but like is it it depends how you how
you define it
also you would say gentrification comes
with displacement and displacement would
be an essential part of gentrification
in this case
there might be a displacement of the
people who lived in these brown houses
and will live there already
before the rest of the neighborhood
before the white parts of the main route
were being constructed
but there will not be a displacement in
this 25 units which are either rented
out or sold as social house because you
will need to fall below a certain
incompatible in order to buy or rent
these places and no matter what happens
in the rest of the neighborhood as
humans will still remain
reserved for people probably not
income threshold so this is a way to
make sure that this place
even if you buy this kind of
so you will not be able to sell them
and if you rent them out
then this is also under the condition
that fall below the circle
everything else
as this whole area has been gentrified
there has been urban renewal in this
whole area so it's only in this very
small part where you they were able to
create the social studies
yeah yeah one important thing is the
scale the scale at which we discuss
things that we are talking about a very
small scale the neighborhood of a couple
of thousand people but indeed if you
discuss it at a scale of Antwerp then
you would see that this whole area
around this red square that we've just
been talking about has been going
through an improvement of this
disadvantaged index and has been going
through a very very
strong gentrification sorry that's
you're completely just a very fair
cooler I'm sorry but then I'm just
curious how it works here like
um
developers can get
tactics or like benefits from the garden
for providing sir
called public housing because that's how
it works
well I don't know about these these tax
rebates but for sure the lens price for
which they were able to acquire this
well the price for which they were able
to
buy this piece of land from city council
was much lower than it would have been
just a market with a gate
okay is it is it
yeah yeah more questions
but um I know
okay now we move to the next question is
it then good or bad is it desirable to
create such a neighbor now what you say
is that well the kind of shops that you
find
the most dictators for the meats and the
desires of this 75 percent of residents
and a lot of tourists and visitors who
like to visit that part of the city
and so that could be a reason to say
well it's not desirable to do this
because these people will not find cheap
food in the area or the kind of
a product statement like they would like
to buy but that shows that we are moving
to uh the next question
is social mix uh
and I guess it would be time for a break
I'm running a bit behind schedule
I'm wondering there is a three-hour
and three hours are dedicated to
urban geography last week I've been
limiting my last two hours would it be a
big problem if I would go if it's over
these two hours of course
okay I'll I'll just go through the
slides and
we'll see we'll see uh what time what
time but I think it's better to have a
break now before moving to this next
question is it desirable create this uh
five minutes and then we continue
[Music]
thank you
very random questions
yes
thank you
uh
questions
anyways
there is
Paris
thank you
um
[Music]
thank you
questions
is it
maybe I should have known this earlier
so let's continue with this uh in the
next question my social mixed desire
I think I might need to skip question
number four
um or part number four and in any case I
believe it's time to uh
to go into the arguments here
um
sure the overarching Assumption amongst
policy makers
and also the dominant hypothesis amongst
researchers
seems to be that where you live
affects your life chances
yeah whether you live in Antwerp
in this line blocking
this social housing estate believe
or whether you live as a poor person in
alternate North where you have all these
shops
and ethnic bars and you have
employment close by Etc
that makes a difference
yeah so the basic question
of researchers has been can impoverished
neighborhoods neighborhoods with a
concentration of poverty can they make
their residents worse
because
maybe two observations before our look
into the different arguments the
different
ways in which this question has been
answered
observation number one is that
researchers
working in different sub-disciplines
I've been showing you this diagram last
week already
research is working in different
sub-disciplines of human geography or
Urban studies more broadly have been
answering this question differently
and where would you position translator
on the map
what kind of Joker is he
do you have an ID
Marxist geographer writing about the
capitalistic moment of production
and he's a Marxist geographer
and he's mainly interested in
socio-economic
issues
yeah
what happens to poor people when they
live in a poor neighborhood
other geographers have been asking
different researchers for example
relating to ethnicultural
segregation as of all article wide by
for example deals with
ethnic segregation
and not with social economic signage
a Marxist geographer such as Tom Slater
will be interested in
socio-economic segregation where the
poor and rich people live and is that
meaningful
in the eradication of poverty for
example
so you see the different geographers
have been asking different research
questions when it comes to these effects
of segregation
they have also been using different
research methodologies
we use large service they have a survey
of 1 000 people in order to answer these
questions or do you have qualitative
research where you interviewed 30
families
number 13 30 people living in a
neighborhood or displaced from looking
so different research methodologies and
then you've also been reading
that there might also be different
ideological underpinnings
uh underlying the work of these
different so I think it is important for
you to understand that just like I
argued last week for the causes of
segregation and the different arguments
that have been
even for why people live
in segregated neighborhoods but also
when it comes to these effects of
segregation and the broad literature
around it the people working in
different positions and different
sub-disciplines of human geography
geography have been giving different
answers to these questions
another remark
that I want to give before going to the
answers to that question is that it is
important
to see that studies on neighborhood
affects their birth marks what do I mean
with it is that it matters rare a study
takes place and often for example
literature of the effects of segregation
studies conducted in the United States
that the conclusions of these studies
have been used for example to influence
policy in Western Europe
and while it is
quite important to see the differences
between these different contexts last
week I have been highlighting for
example that and when it comes to
desegregation in dishes and it turns out
that segregation in the United States is
much stronger more prevalent than it is
in Europe
yeah so that's an important difference
when you take the conclusions from one
country to the other
the welfare states in Western Europe has
been much more developed than in the
United States so when it comes to
poverty and the eradication of poverty
this is a completely different issue in
a western European context than a disc
major Latin America
so it's important
that you contextualize studies on
segregation in the United States for
example and then you just do not
transfer these conclusions to
to Europe
many of the
um
studies on neighborhood effects and the
effects of segregation have been
conducted in the Netherlands and also
this Dutch context is a very peculiar
way
and where for example concerns about the
bailiff that's what you see there a
particular neighborhood in Amsterdam
have been quite important in stimulating
This research field
I'm doing for time
but this far right politicians in the
Netherlands have always been brother but
for two decades already have been a very
vulgar yeah and that's also important to
understand why and this research field
has been sort of developed in the
Netherlands so important to
provincialize distance and to understand
that a study in Vienna or in Antwerp or
in Brussels or in the United States that
it's important to contextualize and to
understand the specificities of this
particular context
I have seven answers to this question I
remember the question can impoverished
neighborhoods make their residence worse
off or when I'm interested in ethnic
cultural segregation and neighborhoods
with the concentration of uh people for
origin make integration more difficult
yeah
um
seven different arguments the first one
The Social Network archives I think many
of you might have heard of the work of
Robert Putnam
focusing on social capital or the social
capital the connections among
individuals the social networks the
Norms of reciprocity reciprocity and
trustworthiness that arise from
making a distinction between owning
Capital what is bombing Capital these
are social networks connections Norms of
reciprocity between socially homogeneous
people for example people of the same
ethnicity are people of the same social
and economic group
distinction between bonding and
breaching and approaching Capital being
actions networks launch of reciprocity
and trustworthiness during socially
heterogeneous
for example people of different
ethnicities
are people of different social economics
and the argument is often that reaching
capital is important for social Mobility
yeah for example if you're poor
from your middle class neighbor you will
get to hear about jobs
and it is a person who's working I mean
there is a job opportunity in the office
where this person learns he might share
this knowledge that she might share it
with is for her name
to work and when you do not speak Dutch
it might be good to have this white
middle class family this Empire City
Council was so interested in living next
to you because you maybe they can help
yourself or daughter with homework
um as they Stitch and so these are the
IDS behind this argument saying that
well it's good
to have mixed neighborhoods because
these mixed neighborhoods will lead to
heterogeneous networks they will lead to
breaching capital and that will be
important that will be to the benefits
of poor people living in such a
neighborhood
and so one reason why you would want to
create a socialist neighborhood is
because you want to create heterogeneous
social networks because you assume that
bridging Capital will help poor people
to be socially mobile and to join them
to for example through education or true
choice
and so this is one of the seven
arguments
that underpins this ideal of social mix
but when we study how people live
it turns out that
people are rather Mobile in a city do
not limit their lives to a particular
neighborhood
and that many of the social networks
that develop in a neighborhood spend
different neighborhood borders and this
is a study from
in China looking at the social networks
of people living in four different types
of neighborhoods and in each of these
neighborhoods the conclusion is that
most people get to know people through
work
yeah and spent time with colleagues also
um after after working hours
and many people also get to know people
through kinship
from a childhood through the schools of
their children
and they are actually quite a small
amount of social networks in each of
these neighborhoods less than that
percent
[Music]
um
what um when you look at the social
connections of these people there is a
quite a small amount that helps in these
neighborhoods and no matter in which of
the four types of neighborhoods they
look
people seem to develop mostly
bones
connections networks with people from
outside the snake
and so this idea that by bringing the
middle class for example to the middle
class to a cool neighborhood that this
would be a way to create these social
networks and when you look at this then
these social networks also develop
outside the neighborhood so why to focus
so much on that neighborhood where
people live
very culturally kind of like
culture e
ffort
in other countries you mean yeah the
situation would be different
donations
well I told you it's important to
understand the context of this of this
study
but in any case also for for Western
European cities if you if you would
study this process over time I think you
would find out that connections are less
neighborhood based than they used to I
can imagine that this neighborhood will
still be important
and people still get to know a lot of
um
other families for example through their
children through the school in many
countries of the world we have a school
pitching system where living in a
neighborhood me sending your kids to the
same school and so for sure there are
many reasons why this would be different
in other countries but overall I think
this argument
truth that there are also many social
networks that the total outsides the
neighborhood of course there are also
studies that focus on burning produce
and say well these people are less
mobile than rich people and so it's
exactly for these poor people that this
neighborhood is an important
uh
ground of network population
much more than it is for rich people
and if you do not have a job if you do
not have the money to buy a bus ticket
now that's neighborhood context will be
an important one for social networks to
be develop that's also for different
categories of people this might be
different
but still I think it's important to see
that networks do not only develop inside
a neighborhood that there are also
networks in other parts of other parts
of the city
or with people living in other parts of
this
um
drawing
white double income families
to a neighborhood such as model make and
if it's possible will that then make
these networks diverse a study by Sabina
Rick and Mike
in a German cities I think it was Marx
law in the old area
and they have been interviewing uh the
white
uh middle class people in this example
two women
about their social meds and there is
quite a lot on this diagram I might need
to explain it so you see the women in
the middle and then you have different
scales
you know the neighborhoods you have the
city you have Germany and you have
outside of Germany and so people
who are the important people in your
life ask that and we put them on this
diagram saying well there are people
inside the neighborhoods people living
in the same city but you also know
people in the same country and people
also living roles and for different
people you would get to different
diagrams and what they also did is to
map a contact frequency
so if you have frequent contacts this
error will be more bold than it is for
people so you can have a rare complex
and then they also met the level of
Education an indicator for a class
room saying well are these people that
you frequent are they people of with the
same educational background
middle class people high education
Highly Educated or are these people who
do not have Universal qualifications
now the other thing that you see here is
the type of relation between frequent
these people or do they provide you with
emotional support or instrumentals
materials or a good talk for example on
the issues so it's quite a complex not
but what you see is that first of all
just like in the Chinese example many
people have social networks that are
part of a social network with people
living outside the neighborhoods and
what you also see there is that most of
the connections that these middle class
women in these underprivileged
neighborhoods develop are with other
people with the same educational
qualification so the idea that's
bringing middle class people to another
privileged neighborhood will create
heterogeneous social networks in which
you find poor and rich people people
does not seem to hold true here because
the middle class people that you attract
to these neighborhoods create mostly
social bonds with people like them with
other middle thoughts
the episode is bridging capital
that was the reason why you wanted to
make this neighborhood there's not
really developed
another argument is that
creating a mixed neighborhood
might disrupt the strong ties that exist
there already the only Capital that
exists and the strong forms of social
economic emotional support that people
of the same ethnicity for example
provide when they live in a neighborhood
part of the city
so residents living in this interested
parts of cities Slater argued fall back
on what they know and what they have
each other is bonding capital is crucial
in the lives of poor people in the lives
of newcomers who have just arrived to
the city they will look for core ethics
first
and if you create a mix if you want to
create a mixed neighborhood in these
parts of cloud for example by attracting
another class they will displace some
people and that will disrupt this
bonding Capital Network system
yeah so
what I'm trying to do
is to say well there is an argument
there why you would create a mixed
neighborhood but you also have
a couple of counter arguments as to why
argument might not work or the whole
reason underlying that argument might
not work
social networks
yeah Social Capital owning and bridging
capital
I guess you you got the point there
a second argument is called underclass
Art
and this is an argument that has
developed in the United States in the
1980s
and at that time there was a big
discussion
between structuralists
who look at the causes of poverty in the
declining economic base
and for example Marxist geographers
saying well there is a shift from a
fullness to a post for this capitalism
and this makes it harder for these
people to quiet job
or the arguments that you've heard in
the classes by that Apostles about
polarization
is there a declining job markets
so you're looking for structural causes
of poverty and on the other hand you had
cultures except poverty is dead because
you have a culture of poverty
poor people have certain attitudes have
a certain behavior and this keeps them
in poverty so that was an important
discussion between these two
and this underclass argument
is part of this cultural history of
looking at poverty yeah who is this
underclass
they're not talking about all poor
people in the case of the United States
in the 1980s 33 million people were
consistent who was this underclass that
was a minority in this minority five
million people yeah people who followed
below the
income threshold for which they are
considered to be poor disproportionately
Black and Hispanic minority in this poor
minority but what defines them it's not
so much the poverty or their base but
their behavior
okay there's probably lawlessness drug
use out of Redwood Birds lack of
employment welfare dependency and school
faith
and also these culturalists blame the
poor
to be poor because of their own behavior
and
the way they look different
and so this is this underclass argument
so what is the argument exactly that in
ketos or in neighborhoods where you find
the concentration of poor people that
you find more unemployment more welfare
dependency more early School Leaving
more truancy or criminality more
gambling more direct abuse more alcohol
abuse more out of Bedford Sports teenage
pregnancy more dysfunctional values
whatever that may aim due to
okay
socialization affects within these
things
if you grow up in a neighborhood like
that
and your peers
the people of your age the people that
you frequent
will have a higher chance to be
criminals or gamblers or drug users or
alcohol abusers Etc
and that is why in such neighborhood you
find more of this
we also find a lack of role models with
a job without a drug addiction without
an alcohol
IC and who were not teenage mothers Etc
so there's a lack of
positive role models
and you also have this peer group effect
and so why are you worse of living as a
poor person in a poor neighborhood the
argument of this culture this was that
is because you have these Norms you have
a lack of these role models and you have
these peer group effects which made it
well that's why it's your worst of
living
they also refer to physical
infrastructure institutional networks
the argument was
that but this has been quite an
important argument many policy makers
have been facing
or helping arguing for socialists
because of this
because they were convinced that living
in a poor neighborhood increased the
chances that you found a job less
important than you leave school early
and because of of your friends doing the
saying that you don't go to school
because your friends would do so as well
that you would turn into a criminal
because this is the example that you
have seen mostly
okay now even when there would be a link
between what is on the left and these
poor neighborhoods then it can still be
wonders whether what is the causal
relationship
between these two
here on the map you have Chicago again a
city that we are getting quite familiar
with you see the poverty level
in these neighborhoods that the darker
the red the poorer the neighborhoods are
and you see
people arrested
for a drug use or
something like this the possession of of
Turks
and what you see there is that uh
there is a correlation
between
poverty and the concentration of poverty
this neighborhood and the use of quality
correct and coping is much scattered
much more scattered and but you also see
that in the other neighborhoods where
you have a concentration of poverty that
is much less the case
now I can also wonder to what extent
this graph
is the result of real drug use or the
policing of these Neighbors
if you have a police force that is much
more
on the outlook for drug use in certain
neighborhoods well that it's logical
that this will show up in English
statistics
so there are many reasons why one could
raise concerns about the causal
relationship in this case between drug
use on the one hand and the
concentration of poverty on public so it
could start to criticize like how these
statistics came about one can also see
that for certain drugs there seems to be
a correlation for other circles one can
also see that you have concentrated
poverty that corresponds with a lot of
arrests for drug use but that you also
have neighborhoods with concentration
concentrated poverty organ specialists
so there are many reasons why we would
start to question whether there is a
real cause of relation relationship
concentration of poverty on the one hand
and all these other indicators here on
the slide on the other hand
and another another argument against
this underclass argument would be well
again socialization
be disappears to not only live in these
neighborhoods
these Role Models do not only live in
the neighborhood and Barack Obama could
also be around
yeah engine can can get these Role
Models through TV or the the music that
you're missing so why this focus on the
neighborhood again
third argument for social cohesion
arguments
and here you see
um the basic line of thought
of this of this argument where the
ethnic minorities live isolated from
native touch they have less contact with
Native touch consequently they do not
acquire an adequate command of the Dutch
language are not likely to adopt such
Norms values and will not succeed in
socioeconomic terms
so here you see a mixing of arguments
about ethnic segregation
and socio-economic Mobility
saying that well if you live
in a neighborhood with a high
concentration of people of foreign
background
who speak their mother tongue and who
are less good in speaking Dutch
and if you have less contact with
native Dutch people then you will not
acquire an adequate comment language you
are not likely to evoke Dutch morals and
values and therefore
succeeds another argument that has been
quite an important
in the kind of rhetorics and the kind of
discourse of policy makers advocating a
social mix
saying for example it's not good that in
modern Bank you have a high
concentration of foreign
why is that not good well these people
will not get to speak Dutch and they
will not integrate to use that word they
will not adults touch notes and values
and that will make it harder for them to
climb to social media
again one can Wonder yeah is it only in
the neighborhood that people could get a
chance to develop this kind of
relationships with Native touch even
arguments true you could look at what is
researchers do I will not go into the
into all the details that they say about
as own that's a place where people
develop social networks you've got
leisure activities through which people
can develop
you've got work and you've got the
transport between these three different
so it's important to look at all these
domains and to see what happens between
people
and then you might see that this
neighborhood in which these people live
is less important
another counter argument with focus on
the importance of local culture it's
only because you have a concentration of
people of a certain ethnic background
for example that you can support
the shop that sells
ethnic products that sell the food that
sells the food from the home group where
it allows you to have a church or an
association by focusing on a particular
ethnic group and these kind of places
might be very important they will act as
a protective space they will act as a
safe space in which these people feel
like they've gone and this feeling of
belonging might be very important for
them to and to find a life in this new
country where they are living
the social cohesion argument
a fourth argument will focus on local
services
yeah and it will say that for example in
in
neighborhoods with the concentration of
poverty that you will have less public
and private Services there will be less
shops there will be less Banks and you
might also have less Public Service
these are examples from lootball social
housing estate that I've been talking
about today already and the closure of a
bank and there is no ATM anymore in our
paper
the argument could go well if there
would be more middle class people then
there would be higher interest from
Banks to have an ATM
or other other ships
Chicago
food deserts I don't know whether you've
ever heard about this term but if you
look at healthy foods
grocery shops where can you find them if
you see a map with these different
racial groups I remember it is this
self-identification in the case of
America that is a survey for which
racial group to itself identifiably
identified you see neighborhoods
predominantly white black Hispanic Asian
diverse and you see that in many of
these black neighborhoods which are also
the tourist neighborhoods you find that
it's very hard to find healthy food it's
very hard to find fresh vegetables like
fruit because the shops are so far
yeah so the argument would be that it's
better to create mixed neighborhoods
because that will attract a diverse set
of
um shops and services to these
neighborhoods
we've already been talking about this
that the question of course is what kind
of shops and what kind of services do
you get in the case of this Mentor
eyelasher District one person said well
but this people will not feel
comfortable shops and they will also not
find the products they would like to
find
that's also in gentrifying neighborhoods
and what kind of
shops do you find there
is a shops catering for
people who look for the cheapest food
possible because they have only five
euro to spend in in the last three days
of the month
or is it cafes or restaurants who try to
cater for these
incoming Gentry Fighters
so it's important to look at the
different shaded demands that will
result from creating a mixed and so the
question is if you've mixed name routes
will these shops and services cater for
these poor people
because if that's not the case then it
will displace the shops that existed
there already ended catered For This
audience
in answer we've also been talking about
a lot of these
specialized services that you might get
in neighborhoods
and at least
money transfer short steps or Food Shops
like some African vegetables or
Thai ingredients
and the question is if you try to mix
these neighborhoods to these kind of
shops and these kind of services still
be able to to be to remain or will they
also be displaced because this place
will be involved by a fancy coffee shop
that is mainly catered for these Gentry
farmers so questions around shops
Services catering for different
audiences
argument that you find in the literature
is a political one
starting from the observation that many
neighborhood associations for example
are well mainly run by middle class
and that middle class people are are
much more focal in expressing their
concerns about the people
and so one could say that well by
attracting the middle class to a poor
neighborhood this neighborhood will be
higher on the political agenda
um and I I have this quote there from
that I read at the end of the Excursion
inshallah in my channel for people
stating well there are also taxpayers
why don't you listen to us
yeah so the idea is that by mixing
neighborhoods you will put these
neighborhoods higher Jim
I'm in Belgium people from outside the
EU without a built-in passport we are
able to vote
but this will not be the case in every
country and so you can have a
neighborhood with a lot of people from
outside the room who do not have a say
in vocal politics and why would this
local mayor address the concerns of
people living
any of these people are not able to
Express their needs and to put a stamp
on the political agenda then why would
you do so the argument is well middle
class people are
able they have these connections with
politicians or at least they will be
listened to
um
well in I'm not going to go into into
that into that example
um but it dealt with the Emperor of
Highway
and that issue of air pollution to the
observation that most of the
neighborhoods lying next to that Highway
are rather so one good question what
would happen with this whole issue of
the whole debate around the highway if
these neighborhoods could not be your
neighborhoods bogus income but rather
than they were the highest activities
so the political arguments
by mixing neighborhoods we will put them
higher on the political agent
of course the issue isn't my report
she's not listened to poor people
political agenda without these middle
class residents
the sixth argument is a bit different
the spatial mismatch does not focus so
much on the issue of segregation but if
you follow these five dimensions of
um
Messi and London it focuses on
concentration clustering where do poor
people live in which part of the city
are these neighborhoods with the
concentration of poverty and this is a
diagram from Cape Town quite an old one
but it's still very much the game the
case where do you have job opportunities
in light and where do you have
population where do people live and
where do they where where could they
and most of the job opportunities are
still in the previously white
neighborhoods particularly in essential
business district of Cape Town but most
of the poor people in Cape Town are
living quite far away from these places
so there is a mismatch between the
places where it's good lift and the
places where the good potential work and
so it's not just important to focus on
segregation and the fact that poverty is
concentrated
in these more peripheral neighborhoods
in the case
but you need to focus then also on the
distance between various neighborhoods
are and the places where these people
could work so there's this the spatial
mismatch argument focusing on the
mismatch between place of residence and
potential places of the world
Western European cities tend to have a
better public transport than North
American for southern
so one could argue this argument will
hold less true in the case of Brussels
for example because even if you live in
Philadelphia there are good training
connections to Apple short places
um this is a map
for Brussels
job density you see two clusters the
inner city
and all these offices and the area
around the airport
um where the poor people in Brussels
live mostly in this 19th century belt
around beginners meaning that there's
not so much of a spatial mismatch if you
live in Mozambique you can walk to many
job opportunities of course the question
like this where do you have both skilled
job properties
so if you don't need a lot of Education
when you see that more or less the same
clusters
their scores as Jobs shift
towards the airport the issue is what
are the transport connections between
Golden Bank St
Josephs and these areas where you find
the growth of most new or most new jobs
and in the case of Brussels the issue
will also be
what are the language requirements for
these jobs because these are jobs
flounders what kind of touch proficiency
do you need and often for these jobs
that will be touched and French maybe
also English so just language wise these
jobs are already quite difficult
so the spatial mismatch argument
focusing on the location of these poor
neighborhoods so it's not just
how mixed these neighborhoods are
whether poor and richness side by side
but where do these concentrations of
poverty occur
last argument stigmatism
and this is an argument that Slater has
been writing about it is important to
look what happens outside of these
neighborhoods understood
you know why is it harder to climb the
social leather to embroider out for all
of the equivalents because teachers who
live outside this neighborhood come with
a set of stereotypes about pupils in
these schools and that will not give
them the same
educational chances as people going to a
school in other games
or if your postcode is I don't know what
is the postcode if you apply for a job
and you okay
if you apply for a joke and this is your
address is there
debt and potential employers might
already come the set of stereotypes why
not too high
so why would it be good then to create a
social mix well one could create or what
could argue for a social mix because
that will reduce the stigma located or
the stigma attached to these things
and of course there might also be other
ways to work on that stigma you don't
need a mix to do that you also can make
people living outside this neighborhood
which you can make them aware of
and what has really happened inside
and so but this stigmatization my
potential employers or teachers or
policemen who work in these
neighborhoods but who do not live there
could be another argument as to why a
social mix is necessary
yes
so are people living in impoverished is
it well does it make does it matter
whether you are poor enough
mostly poor neighborhood surrounded by
people like you or whether you live as a
poor person in a mixed neighborhood does
that matter there are seven arguments
that I have given now as to why that
could matter
okay for each of these seven I've also
given a couple of counter arguments
as to why creating a mix could actually
be a bad thing to distract the ties that
exist already yeah or is not necessary
because people find peers and Role
Models outside the neighborhood
or people will middle class people
arrive in these neighborhoods will not
create uh social networks with the
people
Etc so for each of these arguments I've
given a couple of counter arguments
what about the privileged
I will skip that
in Tom Slater's paper you will find many
arguments for that
um I will get to a small conclusion
okay so when we discuss this ideal
social mix and we discuss the question
is social mix feasible is social Mis
desirable then what is my take on it I
think Avis romaville
who has been doing a lot of work on
housing here in Brussels has summarized
this quite well
the concept of social mixed you rights
which now legitimizes a good part of the
regional interventions in the area of
housing here in Brussels she's talking
about the Brussels capital region and
how the ideal of social mix for the
concept of social mix has legitimized a
good part of this intervention
is according to her not very convinced
convinced
the gentrification which is underway in
the central neighborhoods
in those neighborhoods where
these authorities are doing making a big
effort to attract military
indicates that when there is a mix
it is only a Prelude to the eviction of
the most disadvantaged via the
mechanisms of a completely deregulated
real estate markets we live in a city
but only ten percent of the total
residential units our social housing
yeah there is almost no control over the
remaining 90 percent
and so if you try to attract
middle class residents
to this 19th century
an industrial neighborhoods around
Brussels if you do that then it will
push out over the elsewhere you've seen
it in the snap of I clicking where do
these poor people moving out of a
gentrifying neighborhood so that they
move to build world
to ask to dedicate to however
you move poverty elsewhere
so when there is a mix it can exist for
a while but then it's only a produced to
the eviction of the most disadvantages
because rents will go up eventually
and these poor people that live there
are not able to afford these rents I
will need to move elsewhere to find a
place
so this social makes feasible
in the case of Brussels with very little
uh controlled of authorities on the
housing markets no this is not feasible
she said
is it desirable a second question that I
asked even if this eviction could be
avoided even if you think of a situation
25 social housing every 50 percent and
you will not evict this poor people from
these neighborhoods then she argues
there is nothing to indicate that these
disadvantaged populations would
eventually benefit in any way from this
mix
and why because the attraction of this
building of families would change the
shops will not lead to this
heterogeneous networks that these policy
makers dream
that will not lead to the kind of social
cohesion that underlies this
social cognition
does not
um make the kind of role models
with people who believed in this
underclass argument
and we're hoping for Etc
and so she's arguing in the case of
Brussels again it's important to
provincialize these studies and to
understand the complexity of the
Brussels case only 10 social housing
poverty at this moment concentrated in
neighborhoods with quite a good voltage
very close to these jobs and so there
are many particularities that we need to
understand but what she is arguing is
that the kind of social mix that this
Brussels Capital feature tries to tries
to create leads to the displacement of
people to neighborhoods to parts of the
city which are much much less connected
through job opportunities
where you find much less shops and
services
Etc so too much
worst locations actually and even if
this kind of mix could be realized she
argues then this is not desirable and
disadvantaged population will not
benefit from this this will not help
them to climb the social benefit and she
will draw on all the seven counter
arguments that I've given uh to uh
substantiate this claim
so
well I think when you
I remember that I once asked an exam
question such as put yourself the shoes
of the man of Antwerp you are now the
mayor of network but you
um
promulgate social mixed policies or not
the question was a bit more complicated
but summary I think it's important that
when you have such a question when you
ever work for a city or when you need to
discuss this from an academic point of
view I think there are a couple of
questions that you need to ask
yeah the first one is whom are we
talking about
why do we treat why do we want to create
a social mix
is it because we say well this is the
interest under privilege or I've skipped
now most of this
a part of the class could it also be in
interest of the privilege I remember we
were in Prescott one of the Richard
richer richest municipalities of Belgium
and some of you said well it'd be good
to have some uh more diverse details
because people might for example change
the way they think about poor people if
they have some of them living books by
you see that all of the arguments
so far have been dealing with the under
privilege so for that reason I think
it's important to ask
what about the crystals
and in the discussion
seminars that we have next week there
will be one paper that I've written
together
that deals with it so we have a chance
to come back to this true I think I'll
discussions
do we only focus on
socioeconomic segregation are also are
we also interested in this ethnic
arguments have you seen for example in
the social cohesion argument the two
were conflated and so do we want to
create a social mix in the interest of
ethnic minorities or does the ethnic
majority
if that still exists because more and
more cities in Belgium do not have an
ethnic majority
but we also
think about this group and we want to
promulgate search boxes
are we interested in the second
residence who are there already or are
we mainly thinking about newcomers or
arrivals
and so I think this question for whom do
we want to create a social effects in
whose interests is the first one that
you should ask
a second one is the issue of scale
I told you last week already scheduled
is the Crux of the matter if you want to
calculate segregation in dishes it
matters at which scale you do so in
Belgium we have this very small
statistical units and for that reason we
find that there's
high levels of segregation but if you
would make the statistical units bigger
then there would be less signage
your comments about the Reds Square
relates to this we can create a social
mix in this very small neighborhood and
if you would look at the bigger picture
if you would look at this I mentioned
area as a whole then you would find out
that there is no social business mostly
wealthy people who have settled there
and so I think scale
is a very important issue as well as the
question where do we want to create
assumptions
I think that most of
the social mix literature is concerned
with this disadvantaged neighborhoods
the focus is on these neighborhoods and
the need to create Associates
if you would look at more than make you
would look at socio-economic position of
people and if you would look at the
ethnic maker of this neighborhood you
will find out that modern day is maybe
the most socially mixed neighborhoods or
Brussels if not Belgium
and most of the homogeneous
neighborhoods are white Suburban
municipalities so why are we only
concerned with this disadvantaged
neighborhoods Hawaii are we not
concerned with the homogeneity of many
of these Suburban groups
which are better off is there a need to
create a social mix as well or not and
I've inverse cards for those who joined
to enter by talking about the way they
protested against the trend against the
local Asylum Center against any attempt
to uh well to to make this
municipality
I could even argue that most of the
literature and most of the concerns of
policy makers Target only those
disadvantaged neighborhoods which are
centrifiable which have the potential to
attract middle class newcomers because
that's good for the next but then the
question becomes rare is this possible
and then enter we have been on this
triangular Square Bowling plane well if
you look at the houses there there are
many fancy
um houses
which are
potential homes for rich uh families
but if you move more to the north you
only find very small houses which will
never attract this kind of
where do you have debates about social
mix about the need to gentrify
neighborhoods well only in certain
in a limited amount is disadvantages
so I think this rare question is an
important one where are we interested to
create the solutions
you will notice that these discussions
focus on a very limited number of paper
you know the issue is never discussed in
other parts of the city
it's also important to look at the issue
of scaling I already discussed that but
here again many of our Maps only focus
on Antwerp or the Brussels capital
region while I've told you that many of
these quarterback effects
have consequences in other parts of the
urban region or even other parts of the
country if housing prices in Brussels go
out business effects inshallahua this
makes us walking around in Machinery to
see the property there
okay or we go to Chrome search
in French quite far away from Brussels
effect
s or Nino over leading it yeah all these
municipalities are affected by this
gentrification of
us and so it's important that we discuss
this issue at the scale of
at least the urban region
so for whom in whose interest do we want
to create social mix where
so you want to do that which
neighborhoods are we actually talking
about
and then I think it's also important to
focus on this why question
if you want to create a social gifts to
counter poverty
or even to stimulate this cultural
integration and I think that there might
be many policy Alternatives which are
less
costly and which may have much bigger
effects
yeah I'm not going to go too much into
this but you can imagine that you can
try to combat poverty not through the
spatial intervention
but through other accounts social
welfare Etc
is it to improve the local Tech space
we've seen this quote from this elder
man of cats and I think for many Belgian
cities this will be an important one why
do we find gentrification importance
yeah and why do we want to attract the
middle class to the city it is because
that is good for our Municipal budget
yeah but then even then I will always
eat this rhetoric of this is in the
interest of the people that included and
this will eventually help them to find
the social media
create social mix to counter racist or
classes stereotypes what would that mean
I guess that would mean that we would
rethink where and for whom we try to
create a social mix and you see that in
most of the policy discourse this is
quite absent
however if stigmatization is one of the
reasons why living in modern day
makes your life more difficult than
other parts of the city but it is about
stigmatization and discrimination and
what kind of spatial interventions that
would be needed to counter these
stereotypes I think you would create
social media completely and different
way
so this is a bit of an open-ended
um
conclusion with a lot of questions but I
hope that
by giving you Arguments for social mix
and counter arguments guests
and by encouraging you to think about
the context
in which you want to create a social mix
or not that you are able to think
critically about the effects of
segregation and the needs to create a
social mix or launch
yeah
um five plus seven I propose that
um we almost leave it here for now we
still have time to discuss all these
issues next week in the seminar all
these texts will deal again with
patterns of segregation and the effects
of saying so I think it's good that we
have time to discuss this
next week Monday for the geographers
and the people from planning and have
awesome students is this information
correct
next week Monday we have eight
papers eight presentations to discuss
I don't see any
comments so I suppose that this is the
schedule as it is and then next week
Tuesday and Thursday we have two other
seminars for students from moose
and Thursday students from four cities
yeah is that correct
yes all your presentations are there you
find your names
this is the information
10 minutes
and we will I will need to be rather
um strict which is 10 minutes
maximum
especially having AIDS presentations in
the first seminar but also in the other
seminars I prefer to uh keep the time
and to limit these presentations to 10
minutes because otherwise there's not
enough time for discussion these are
discussion seminars not presentations
so limit your presentations to 10
minutes include a slide with title names
email I don't know all of you so it's
important that I'm able to mark the
presentations to connect this with the
right students remember that I need a
core court or arguments a link with the
required readings
remember that we also expect all
students who have read all the papers of
the required readings
so I'm supposed that Slater has been
read by Kevin Olsen and preserve and the
textbook a chapter like what's your name
and then important
in order to not to lose too much time
with technical issues I would like all
of you to send your PowerPoints or ETF
or whatever you're going to use to
support your presentation at least 30
minutes before the seminar to my email
address
whether we transfer link if necessary
and if you want me to check with the
presentation works on my computer
then I suggest you to do that maybe
already the evening before and then ask
me maybe check whether the PowerPoint
approach or do it in a PDF so that's the
different PowerPoint versions things may
change
but please send them before the
presentation so that I have the time
so let me know whose time with swapping
laptops and
laptops that can't make the connection
with the screen Etc
just to make sure that we are all able
to present and that we have time to
receivers and that will also allow us to
discuss everything that has been said
and last decision
okay then I would look forward to see
you next week
[Music]
all right
this is so stupid
not talking about questions
foreign
thank you
again
yes I
like bye
yes and yes
[Music]
when the first version
yes and then these people have been
added to the list yes
maybe there could be a way
that yeah
if not for next week then for
what would you prefer to do it
but
yeah because now it's hard for me
okay yeah
[Music]
yeah
I've done it next week so it's
foreign
[Music]
sure
so the first thing is can we call like
any project that things to attract
investment or hence the apology of life
in a neighborhood like this uh doing a
taxi and this kind of products can we
call they are social mix projects
because
that's 100
you still have a project
improve
public spaces
so like do they say that they are social
based projects like openly
so in some of these I've shown you some
some parts from policy games
okay
in order to attract another kind of
presence
yes
do you have any other if you have
already used some references that talk
about Brussels
in the presentation I haven't shown that
but
there is quite a rich people Geography
okay so it finally shows papers I will
find something well I think you will
find a lot of women who benefits from
home ownership support policies in
Brussels that's where this this quote
comes from
clicking and moving in out of Brussels
much of his work is on gentrification
but you will also see that some of his
papers deal with
social mix in relation to uh
gentrification specifically so there's a
lot of work
yeah from here
uh and the other thing that I don't know
if I'm mistaken but I have the
impression that there is not actually
evidence that social actually works like
you presented some arguments
but they're not
recorded life is
more like suppositions and
well I think the infamous
trying to find out the
effects and and showing that there are
some cases where
people might benefit from such things
but even any questions
mixed neighborhood so it's quite costly
yes what would happen
the structural problems if you reduce
all this money to
try and comment over
again so even
turns out social response
just yeah so so even even if you could
turn out that by creating social mix you
improve
the situation
any questions that is what would happen
so
it should try and attack it
it's not through spatial
we're trying to okay
yes
thank you
improving schools
we have also time to discuss next next
yes
[Applause]
foreign