hello it seems that
we are beginning to uh
to join this lecture today I hope you
can hear me
we're starting in four minutes but I
still would like to make sure that
everything is working here so if you're
not hearing me let me
know in the chat or over here but I
think
seems to be working
foreign
just to check can you all hear me and
see me
um it's a funny question to us these
days but
yes we can great very good thank you
fantastic I'm happy that we not running
into technical troubles right away
um let's start with five past to uh to
give everybody enough time to join us
um
so grab a grab a drink a tea or coffee
or whatever it is that you like to drink
at this time of the day and uh
and let's try to make this as pleasant
and experience as possible so five more
minutes I'm gonna switch up the video
for a moment and join you then
foreign
oh yeah please tell us or tell me in the
chat
um which I have open here just in case
welcome all of you
um I'm sure that you've had that so many
times already I really wish we could
meet face to face in a in an actual
lecture room at Pub
um but uh I'm still happy that we're
doing it in any case in this very
unusual or maybe for you actually
already a very normal format by now who
am I you might be wondering my name is
I am a postdoctoral researcher here at
vub
and I'm the last of the four white males
to tell you everything about urban
geography so uh I come last but I hope
um this was not been a very tiring
course by now and you still have the
energy and then will to to follow
um over the course of the next two
lectures two sessions I will be sharing
with you my perspective my ideas about
Urban transport and Mobility
um well it's a lecture so it's very
difficult to make it highly interactive
but I will still try to ask you some
questions and
um I think I hope it's possible for you
to try to respond to them not only
through chat but basically you know turn
the audio on video and
um I don't think it will be a
conversation but at least it would be
nice to hear some other voices not only
mine for two hours and then two hours
again and of course this is followed by
a discussion seminar so you will have
read or you have read already some
articles and I hope we will have a
discussion there
um so that we we can make this whole
thing a little bit more interactive than
um then it is usually the case through
these uh online online courses
right
um I hope you can also see the slides
can you not those of you who have the
video on
do you see them perfect very good so
um excellent so Urban transported
Mobility it is uh if you have any
questions concerning the content or I
don't know the quality of uh video audio
let me know in the chat I'll try to read
this as I as I talk
multitasking and try to interrupt me if
you yeah if you have any you know
questions if you disagree if you if you
have some burning issue let me know or
let us know and then I'll try to stop
and address that all right great so what
is the plan for the next two sessions
today we're going to talk about a
historical hegemony of two different
main sets of approaches to Urban
Geography of transport and next week
we're going to try to deconstruct all
that to address this in a critical
manner and to understand how to look at
Urban transport immobility from a
critical set of perspectives
so without further Ado today we're going
to start with a bit of a historical
overview of the relationship between
transport and the city uh how this
relationship evolved in
these two directions
and discuss as much as possible as much
as time will allow us to this historical
hegemony of two main sets of approaches
on Urban transport and geography so
neoclassical and sustainable
perspectives of urban transport
but before we begin
um I'm really curious about what your
expectations might be I imagine that a
lot of you when you know starting a
course of urban studies or geography
didn't really expect to study transport
why would the transport be important for
understanding cities and their geography
what do you think would any like anybody
like to say something or type it in the
chat that's the moment we're going to
have a few of these open questions
throughout these four hours together
why study transport when studying cities
why why is that important or not
um I I did actually expect transport to
be part of the the study because to me
at least
um it Alters the way the city is
structured sometimes it's structured
around a specific mode of Transport
um like there's differences between
um
um what they call like Harbor cities or
cities more in the middle of land
something and I think it makes a big
difference with how with a geographic
development so to me it's actually I
think it's it's a key factor right so it
would have some impact on the urban
Forum on on so it's spatial arrangement
of the city why else
there are many reasons as you can
imagine but what comes to your mind
I think it also like Matilda already
mentioned before uh one main aspect is
sustainability and cities how to like uh
to to reach the climate goals so okay
it's yeah linked to different
transportation systems or so to think of
let's say environmental impact of of
cities and transport being a big part of
that
um possibly or being part of the the
problem right so generating emissions
CO2 and other gases that yeah
contribute to the climate crisis all
right what else
I think something has to do with job
opportunities
for example in Lagos in Nigeria
we see people moving for hours
um go to town to to look for a job and
go back again so eight hours they're
spending in in casual right right so
transport is well without transport it's
difficult to get around the city and and
use its different functions and uh
use different opportunities that the
city might provide like employment
education Leisure many other things all
right
any last point before we move on does
somebody have a great idea to add this
little discussion
well okay well I think today yes it's
quite
um actually is this slide a little bit
cut or do you see it yeah I think this
will be better now so today when you
open the news I think it's difficult to
not to notice that transport is well
very present I would say in the in the
public debate last year I'm just taking
a few examples here last year you
probably
um read about or maybe even participated
in a witnessed huge protests that
erupted in Chile studying in the capital
of the country which of course
very much addressed uh
um fundamental structural issues in
terms of how capitalism develops in this
in this country and how it has its Urban
or spatial impact but the beginning of
the protest was so the final you know
dropped that actually led to the
eruption of those and all those strikes
in these uprisings was the increase of
public transport first and specifically
the underground phase
in Brussels that's the top right corner
we've in the past years we've witnessed
a series of protests in public space
that address uh the increased presence
of the car which supposedly these
protests claim takes space from the from
the people so decrease the quality of
our life
um negatively impact the the quality of
um quality of every living health
conditions especially of of children and
then the figure in the top left I'm sure
that you all know Greta
uh who refers to transport of course she
doesn't talk only about the transport
boy when she does when she makes this
very political statement of not
traveling by plane and using only trains
to go to her meetings or or
conferences at least before copied she
did the idea there is to to show us that
there isn't a necessity for us to engage
in some social and environmental
transition and transport is part of this
transition so the way that we've moved
around the way that we've lived is
essentially unsustainable it's
detrimental from the environmental point
of view we need to change that radically
uh meaning in a very drastic way so
really
um
in a very profound way but also in terms
of speed of that change in order to
address what shared and devices the main
issue today the main problem today which
is the climate crisis or the climate
catastrophe that is that is imminent
it's I think easy to yeah just by
following the news to realize that well
something is profoundly wrong with with
uh with the way that we are Mobile today
and that has to change and indeed the
industry or those who are the the key
actors in terms of producing transport
is there to of course respond with some
solutions at least so we're being told
that at least one of the solutions or
one of the series of solutions that are
that are available are those of
platform-based economies of shared
digitalized smart Giga economy related
Mobility or mobilities so we for
instance in the future uh living in the
city we don't have to have a car as we
know detrimental to human environment we
can rent one through an app we can drive
electric cars which are readily
available in public space in our cities
we can use one of these electric
scooters and many other modes of
Transport that have boomed in recent
years in in many many cities of the
flogo north especially but also Global
South and Brussels uh I'm sure those of
you who are from the city who have been
there for a couple of months now
you know you can observe many of these
different practices of Mobility very
present in the city and some of them at
least
um being part of a narrative of of some
change of some future of something that
is shaping the way that we that we live
and move around the city
from a more scientific perspective one
answer why to the question why study
transport is that quite simply and this
is I think actually the very first
sentence of one of the most seminal uh
textbooks on German of Transport
geography there wouldn't be no
Transportation without geography and
there will be no Transportation no
church free without transportation and
transport of Transportation in North
America
um is an essentially geographical issue
the idea is and again it's the same
textbook the transport allows to reduce
the distance to zero of course that
reduction never really happens but the
idea is the transport allows to
manipulate space and time that is
required to to conquer to cover that
space
and I think beyond that very dry
definition of the relationship between
the two what's quite important is that
well it's very hard to imagine not only
contemporary but also
pre-modern ancient societies without
movement without without transport it's
it's something that has always been
fundamental for for human societies for
human settlements and today and that's
something that I will try to show you in
these two two lectures and in the
discussion that will follow the week
after
transport is absolutely fundamental for
for studying the city and I think it's a
fascinating entry for for studying what
cities are today with problems might be
found in the not only transport problems
but social problems facial problems
economic problems related to all
different challenges that at first at
least do not seem to be transport
related but in fact they are being
negotiated articulated contested soft
sometimes but more often unfortunately
created through transport through the
production and distribution of of
transport
so we will try to unpack this
relationship starting by uh let's say
more of a historical analysis so I'll
start in mid 19th century in cities in
western Europe uh in what we can
identify as a pre-industrial era
and we will bring that analysis to the
1960s 1970s let's see how much time
we've got uh for this today too uh well
let's say the beginning a major crisis
that formed or framed the debate in a
way that it is Being Framed still today
so some kind of a setting of a
contemporary challenge or series of
contemporary charity challenges related
to to transport and Mobility
all right
so
um
the main point here I don't want to
spend too much time on this historical
part because I don't think this is the
well it's it's not contemporary so
perhaps it's not as interesting as many
challenges that are happening right now
the main point here is that Urban
Transport Systems are are very strongly
and strictly related with Urban form and
with a spatial structure so the
development of cities is conditioned by
the development of what we call
transport modes from walking so just
walking on foot to the bicycle to public
transport and and to the car
and there is a persistently strong
relationship between the intra-urban
transportation system and the
organization of the Metropolis as
Mueller who wrote one of the most
seminal again textbooks on on the
history of Transport geography tells us
and there is a variety of different
Urban forms and spiritual structures and
land use patents which are related
specifically or very closely to the
development of different transport laws
and as far as I understand you've
covered quite a few of the most
important models of development Urban
Development throughout history with with
Nick you can not hear if that's the case
and or deny the fact that if you if you
didn't but I think that this was this
was covered at some point and the idea
here is that and a lot of these models
although not explicitly mentioned
transport was actually absolutely
crucial so the idea was both purchase
and announcer movement Mills mentioned
that without the development of
different ways of moving around the city
um the development which of course to an
extent erroneously they try to model or
predict would not be able to to happen
um well the debate has been there in the
in the in transport geography until the
1970s 1980s how to how to model that
relationship how to analyze it and
whether in fact it's it's more the
development of the city that drives the
development of transport of the other
Iran whether it's the development of
different transport modes that drive the
development of the city it's not a
particularly interesting debate today
but it's important to acknowledge that
geographers were very early on Urban
geographers interested in the
development of Mobility
one also rather imperfect and symbolic
rather than you know analytical way of
describing this is through identifying
some cycles of innovation so looking at
different
um scientific developments uh come uh
well some scientists would say in in
these kind of crucial moments and
there's a bundle of different
Innovations coming together so at the
end of the 19 18th century as you can
see at the left-hand side of the graph
and the invention of water power
textiles iron then some 60 70 years
later the steam engine rail production
of Steel etc etc each of these bundle of
Innovations allowing you to of course
create a more efficient that usually
meant faster and more energy efficient
way of moving uh of course not only
within but also between cities changing
not only the way that people move but
also the way that the city itself could
be could be organized in in space and in
this sense we could although of course
this is not a perfect you know robust
typology but we could
come into some kind of agreement you
don't have to accept it and I'm happy if
you if you raise some some issues with
it but we could divide the development
of the city around the development of
Transport by identifying four different
let's say stages I wouldn't call them
errors but a city that is a
pre-industrial city that largely was
based on walking uh since
um motorized transport was uh was
generally speaking not uh well it was
just not there and having a horse would
be an extremely expensive investment so
basically most people walked an
industrial city which uh developed
around
um the birth of what we could identify
today as public transport first horse
driven carts and then motorized ones
then the fordest city which very much
developed around the not only the
invention but rather domestification and
the panelization of of private vehicles
or private cars and then a city of today
the post Forest City which uh very much
Builds on the development of Transport
modes that use the ICT information and
information and communication
Technologies
and of course
um Aviation so the city does is very
much related also to the development of
of all the typology of spaces related to
to Flying to airplanes both passenger
and and cargo transport
are there any questions at this stage
before we dive into
these different four stages
I don't hear any yeah yeah go ahead
um
[Music]
it's linked to conductive
um because we saw something like that
with lessons of Nick
yeah I would say so I I think that it's
one of it's one of the ways of um
I wouldn't say that it's specific yeah
that it completely matches conductance
ways but the idea is the same uh that
there is some kind of development of uh
of innovation within the capitalist
system which allows to gain some
competitive Advantage which device
allows to create uh some kind of growth
machine and then this competitive
advantage over time is is uh is lost so
that we have a decline until it picks up
again what I think with chondratic is
still not clear is whether this new wave
so the one that here in this graph
happens after the 1990s it's very clear
so as far as I understand although I'm
not a specialist here there is a
discussion whether this new wave is with
the digitalization and software
engineering is actually materializing or
whether we've arrived at a global system
in which there is uh no growth of
um well at least within industrial
production it's rather a financial or
financialized growth
um but it's it's a good
um let's say it's a good hunch it's the
idea is more or less the same it's the
same intuition
also the problem with this clearly is
that it's not uh I mean this kind of way
of trying to understand what happened in
cities around transport in the past two
centuries is extremely Western uh
focused or very eurocentric
so so this would not be a story of of
cities in most of Latin America Africa
south Asia and also uh post Soviet or
Soviet world right so the global South
and the global east as it's sometimes
even called today it's not really part
of this
um well the story that is told by this
graph
um we will try to address this but um
it's yeah it's um that will happen at
the very end of the last of the last
session to try to decolonize a little
bit our knowledge about transport
geography because it's extremely
westernized and extremely eurocentric
right let's let's dive into that
um
right so the pre-industrial city right
um well I guess it's quite uh
self-explanatory it's not very difficult
to understand I mean the the idea is
that the city basically is
um well since there is no motorized
transport modes and
um having as I mentioned having a horse
or a horse car it's an it's a cost it's
a fortune it's an absolutely uh
luxurious good
pretty much everybody walks and since
everybody walks uh the city could not be
um cannot be too big for people to cross
it on foot with within more than 20 30
maybe 40 minutes so a traditional
Global northern European city would have
until
let's say end of the 18th century no
more than five kilometers in diameter
and that would mean of course here for
example you have a map of Brussels from
from that time that will mean that
within the city walls which existed for
for military purposes for defense
you know how to be a very high density
of of different functions of different
users
um and uh for other reasons that we're
not going to dive into today the great
Street pattern was also very common from
Middle Ages onwards also very
importantly since these well not maybe
since but as these different functions
were were mixed
um maybe this mixed city was allowed
partially also because of the fact that
the division between work at home a
division that is absolutely fundamental
for a lot of writing on transport
geography that focuses on that morning
and evening commute from home to work
and work from home that did not exist
most people worked from home most people
did not have to move
um to to reach we can say they employ
for the employment that they had or to
engage in some kind of productive
activity that would be renumerated to to
um gain some kind of salary or profit
things and this is all Brussels first
Brussels uh the map of it and then uh a
view of the of the city center where you
obviously well you basically see a lot
of pedestrians and uh not much else in
terms of in terms of Mobility modes this
began to change with a series of
inventions first a steam engine an
electric engine in both
um
well the invention started at the end of
18th century and and moved also to the
19th century then the bicycle
um I'm moving very fast here in time
when bicycle was invented in the
60s of the 19th century I think 1867
more or less
of course all these inventions first
being on Curiosities and again very
luxurious Goods bicycle being something
that was much more used for us as a form
of pleasure before eventually becoming a
mode of Transport for for many workers
all that it meant is that they gradually
uh led to mechanization of of land
Transport Systems
and
we see that gradually happening here so
these different inventions particularly
steam engine and nature also the
discovery and then Discovery information
that allow to produce electricity uh
meant that uh towards the end of the
19th century appears a completely
different amount of Transport which
revolutionized uh cities of the time
which is that of first a host drone
streetcar and then an electric street
car which started to be introduced in
European Western European cities around
1890s and then became extremely Popular
by the 1920s
that led to well we moved to this second
state let's say to the industrial city
led to a huge revolution of of how
cities could be conquered by its by its
inhabitants how they could be managed
navigated by by its inhabitants
um
that also allowed or led to the decision
to to engage in construction of a number
of underground uh tramways as they were
first called The Underground systems
first
uh in London and 18 as early as 1863
then Budapest in 1896 and the First
Northern American system in Boston in
1897.
and that that marked the beginning of of
as I said a revolutionary change in a
golden era of the development of Railway
Transport Systems as Railway networks
expanded tremendously and became the
dominant land transport for both
passengers and for Freight and that was
valid or is valid for both inter-urban
and intra intra-urban transport
why was this invention revolutionary
well of course because
increased speed allowed to cover
increased distance so suddenly the for
instance the idea of of still living
within the very medieval perimeter of
the city uh was or started to be to be
questioned the idea of expanding the
city to the suburb or connecting the
villages and the suburbs to the to the
city proper began to to make a lot of
sense so that led
um
was one at least one of the ideas why in
a number of uh cities across Europe City
walls where um were demolished
see that here in in Brussels so first uh
horse drawn card I think it's a
photograph from the 1890s
so end of the 19th century and
1910 uh I think it's a great Royal in
Brussels you already see and uh no I
think that's is that a horse
I think it actually is already it's an
electric one although I don't see the
cables I thought it was an electric but
I think it might still be
um pulled by a horse although you don't
see that from uh well the drum that is
heading in our direction does not have a
have a horse pulling it
right so
I already mentioned this in a little bit
so a revolution in urban travel a
breaking uh mode that's allowed to
um to rethink the air before made an
impact on it in a great way breaking
this idea of a compact dense medieval
city allowing to extend what we what was
considered to be a city to up to 20 or
30 kilometers in Diamond if you think
that the previous
um let's say model of a city had up to
five This was um
an expansion of four to six six times
what also appears in in this process uh
of course it's not all related to
transport but it's happening at more or
less the same time and it makes a big
impact on on what transport is in the
city and what a role is is that this
expansion of the urban form in space
allows for some specialization of
different functions especially economic
functions and what it also creates or
contributes to the creation of is the
creation of a working class of of a
specific group a social group of course
Very diverse internally but a group that
um sells its time for a living that uh
of course with the Industrial Revolution
does that not anymore at home but
actually starts what we start calling
commuting to its uh to its workplace
where
things are being produced what profit is
being made and where their salary
workers is exchanged uh for uh for money
for a salary
um that separation as I mentioned being
absolutely fundamental for decades of of
analysis of transport to to come so
focus on this commute from from work to
home and vice versa
moving to the next some technical issues
here moving to the next uh stage of
Urban Development we can put it very
very roughly of course a fundamental
invention of of the car not only the
invention of the car proper because the
well the vehicle itself I mean we can go
back to the first the diesel engine
invented in the 90s of the 19th century
pneumatic tire four-stroke engine
invented a few years later and that led
to the construction of the first
automobiles as they were called back
then in 1890s
um but it was fundamentally the
massification of of the current the
invention of this particular model uh
which I'm sure you've
or a lot of you probably have heard
about already the Model T by Ford uh
which began to be produced in 1913 and
famously Mr Ford said that this model is
available in any color as long as it is
black the idea being that with
unification of
universalization of the model uh getting
rid of any options of any customization
of any personalization
um and also the implementation of today
is being called taylorism so reaching a
near automated way of producing this
this vehicle with very strictly measured
time for every single activity that
that was part of the production process
the final price of the production and
the final price for the consumer could
be reduced as much as possible meaning
that this product this commodity could
be available to to White masses and that
does begin uh from the 1910s already but
especially from the 1930s uh when indeed
the price started going significantly
down the era of of the automobile the
era of a mode which I'm sure that if you
you know turn on the news about Brussels
or any other Western European North
American city uh by that debate also uh
is very very present in many African
Latin American South Asian cities
um it's a mode that is very much on the
agenda whenever you talk about whenever
you hear about transport
and we're going to talk about that I
guess tonight if not in a week as a very
uh well as a very present mode of
Transport in our cities and also very
problematic mode of Transport that
attracts a lot of condensation a lot of
uh
um a lot of anger and a lot of
um creative and critical thinking in
terms of what's the alternative to the
to the automobile
so it's been almost a century now that
our cities if we think about it from the
global North uh I don't know benefiting
or suffering from that from that no you
tell me
um
famously from 1913 to 1927 Ford managed
to build 15 million units 15 million
Vehicles making it the second most
produced car in history right after
Volkswagen Beetle
um which was also they began the
production a little bit later but also
in the period between the first and
second World War
so why uh well this we've covered
already mostly but well the most
important thing here is in the last
bullet points I mean why is the car such
a revolutionary and such an important
mode of transports to be to be mentioned
here is that for the very first time
Mobility
um modernized Mobility is an individual
exercise it's no longer only a motorized
or a horse horse-drone streetcar that
allows you to cover long distances of
taking a train a Suburban train that
takes you to the factory and back but
it's an it is an individual vehicle an
individual product that allows you to
reach unprecedented levels of of
individual Mobility
and of course that uh immediately uh had
a very important impact on on the way
that the cities are planned and and
imagined
um
well
without running the risk of uh or maybe
a little bit of you know drawing some
kind of caricature this impact
um starting from especially the second
world war when when it was a very strong
Narrative of the need of modernizing
um cities especially in North America
and Western Europe
a lot of cities be became basically
um
well perfect space for for for for
driving around a space in which huge
amounts of infrastructure for this
individual car based Mobility was built
this process started a little bit early
in the US and the 1940s and 50s already
and after the second world war
um that narrative was started to be very
present in in Western European as 50
both of these images by the way come
from a really wonderful film by uh
Jacques tatti I believe it's called
playtime from the 1967 which I really
recommend you watch it's a great
critique of this idea of this training
of modernity which also very much hinges
on on the idea of having a car of um
of driving around
um and well moving to more serious stuff
I mean accommodating the current city
meant that
serious infrastructure had to be built
uh series have had to happen in in
cities at the time for for the car to
receive this kind of space
um
some of the most important projects
happen in the US as I mentioned on the
on the left hand side you've got the
Franklin Delano Roosevelt drive and
opened in 1966 in New York on the right
hand side the infamous Ponte Morandi in
in Genoa in Italy 1967 which
unfortunately collapsed I believe two
years ago which also symbolized of
course it's a it's a terrible terrible
event but for for many it was a very
powerful symbol of this infrastructure
crumbling and an important question of
what to do with these relics of
um of modernity or past modernity
whether they should be in this case
rebuilt or maintained or invested in
whether this is something that we want
to gradually dismantle uh and and stop
subsidizing the maintenance of these
infrastructures is um undoubtedly very
costly
and the next slide uh does anybody have
a clue where this city is
very good well done yes this is the uh
I don't remember the name of the road
but uh yeah yeah it's in the next slide
I'm so silly green belch are nine built
in 90 or opened in 1976. I don't know if
you've ever had the experience of of
driving this but it's really uh it's
uncanny it's it it makes me personally
feel as if I was in some uh Chinese or
other Asian City where you're on this
elevated platform almost gliding through
through the city so it's really one of
the
uh I think most extreme or more extreme
cases at least in this part of of Europe
of
um really plowing through through a city
to build this Motorway uh Ring Road
but chalawa was not the only one I mean
we are after all or I don't know where
you are right now but most of us are in
Brussels right now and Brussels was
definitely also a playground for many of
these many of these ideas and the idea
of bringing the car and opening the city
to the car
like in American cities at least that
was the comparison used in Belgium
became particularly strong and
particularly
um potent among the political class the
decision makers around 1958. what
happened in 1958 I guess you've heard
that date before
any non-belgians
1958 why is that important for Brussels
the atomium and why would the atomium be
uh well okay the World Expo symbolized
by the atomium and why would that be
related to the car
um you really don't have any ideas
I mean if you opening a World Expo for
the very first time in Belgium and
inviting I don't remember how many
people actually visited the Expo in the
end but millions of people uh visited
the city why why would a car be
important of the car be important in
that regard
so for putting Belgium on the map
yes it's to solve the idea of I mean not
the idea the problem of congestion is to
bring these masses to the Expo and back
is to allow for a better communication
but also to put Belgium on them to show
that Belgium is a modern country to show
that it's it's on you know Cutting Edge
and being Cutting Edge in 1958 and those
who meant opening the city for the car
and
building huge infrastructure or start at
least to build huge infrastructure that
would accommodate this new modern uh us
like
um American way of of mobility of moving
around the city
uh so yeah uh some things that are quite
quite Unthinkable today uh were going on
at that time so this is Gohan plus uh I
think it's in the 1960s
so of course Expo was a symbolic event
it didn't really uh I mean it was it was
not just tipping points there were a lot
of Dynamics happening at that time and
the Expo was maybe a more of a symbolic
moment but it is around the time that
the level of motorization so the level
of ownership of cars in Belgian
households and similar processes are
mentioned in Belgium here but similar
things were going on in France in
Germany
uh in the UK it went through the roof
um so it was
it was very very common back then to uh
to invest in a car as a symbol of of
advancing as a household as a symbol of
social Mobility not only a physical uh
geographical Mobility that of course
meant that more and more space had to be
given to the car and as the car became
more present more people bought the car
so the circle was closed and it was a
vicious one
in Brussels specifically well one of the
most important infrastructures built at
the time is the Petit Center so the Ring
Road that surrounds the Pentagon of the
city I'm sure that you've all have been
there so essentially the
well the the framing of it right the the
actual shape of the Pentagon comes from
the city was the second walls of
Brussels uh coming from the 14th century
uh completely destroyed which defined
the historic center of the city still
and until the 1950s it was a very much
an urban Boulevard in which one could
stroll and and walk very much like in
the
drawings rather than photographs that I
showed you at the beginning from this
city of walking city that was very much
defined by by The Pedestrian mode of
moving around
um and in relation to the 1958 that had
to be gradually uh transformed so a
series of first tunnels were built then
uh the service was raised to uh to open
to the car it took 20 years of work
which is not a very unusual thing in
Brussels uh to do so two decades of
extremely heavy work uh and very
destructive work whole neighborhoods
have to be relocated destroyed to
rebuilt
um so opened in 1976 uh with 15 tunnels
surrounding the city also quite
importantly and that's maybe a bit of an
extreme story that not necessarily
happened also in France or in Germany or
in other Western European cities but
what was very crucial in Brussels is
that the engineering teams or the
engineering offices consultancy officers
who would call them today would receive
a personal bonus on top of their salary
for every kilo kilometer of an
underground tunnel built so that led to
creation of a huge push to build
underground infrastructure for Mobility
both for for cars but also for railroad
and Metro uh and that led to a creation
of very important expertise in building
these underground tunnels uh which of
course once you have that expertise you
of course want to keep building more
because that's what you are very good at
doing and that problem in Brussels well
problem of situation exists until today
where we have huge teams of engineering
Specialists who specialize in building
underground it's in steep in the public
transport company in Brussels half of
the company is responsible for for Metro
for maintenance and construction so you
can imagine that what you want to do of
course is to keep building and Metro
which is what they are currently doing
in Brussels
um moving a little bit or zooming out a
little bit from cities
um the large-scale diffusion of of the
car or the automobile is a mass
consumption project of course was uh
strongly also influenced or maybe also
LED so it's a two-way Dynamic to the
emergence of first Nationwide Highway
systems in the first one uh created was
of course the one in the US the American
interstate highway system which began to
be not maybe completely built from
scratch but the first framing of it and
continuous gradual addition to the
network in 1956.
um which was of course back then uh that
symbol of modernity that
um in many many places in Belgium being
one of them influence the definition of
the idea of what was Modern what was
cutting-edge was technologically
advanced
today of course uh it's not the us
anymore that it's the leading uh country
or the leading power in terms of the
development of Transport technology and
and highways in particular uh that
system that American system has been by
now surpassed definitely by the one in
China the national trunk highway system
here I have a little bit of an old graph
but by 2011 as far as I can read it well
but already 2009 the total amount of
kilometers of motorways in both
countries us and China was equal and the
one in China of course was Rising still
very
um very steep but you can see that this
I don't like the term but let's say the
catching up or this idea of following a
little bit in the footsteps of what the
Americans did in the 1950s in China
happened in an extremely
um short time which not only because of
the construction of the motorways but
this was a very important part of the of
the construction boom meant that
um
from 2006 2007 onwards now the situation
is a little bit different because of the
ongoing crisis and also other problems
the Chinese economy uh suffered from but
the consumption of the the demand for
concrete in China was bigger than in all
other countries around the world
combined so this was really a boom of an
unprecedented scale and we will see a
few other graphs and down the lecture
which
show us that while in many cities many
countries around what we might be
thinking that we are moving away from
the current right now but that's the
idea that the other parts of the world
that did not experience this development
at the same time as Global noise are now
and definitely contributing to um to not
even I would say Persistence of
automobility but actually it's
continuous rise on the global scale
what was very important going back to
the Belgium uh context of the 1950s and
1960s it's also difficult to say what
was first the car or the suburbs or the
suburbs and the car but the two were
extremely uh strongly linked with one
another having the car
and as I mentioned as I explained the
car became a very common popular and
cheap commodity not only defined how we
moved to to uh to work and you move
around the city but actually it's again
redefined what the city is so suddenly
areas which would be normally considered
rural become accessible and become
interesting for people to to settle in
the idea also being and that you have
more space more freedom
you are close to you are close to Nature
etc etc these days it might be it might
feel like it's something of the past
something that is uh yeah not
interesting to to many urbanites of
today day but back then it was
absolutely the way to the way to go the
way to live the way to think uh that one
should invest as a household in
the home Marketing in property Market
um
the special
[Music]
results of of that of the double Dynamic
of motorization on the one hand
suborganization on the other was that if
a pre-industrial city had more or less
10 of its space devoted to transport and
Mobility an industrial a modern city has
between 15 and 30 percent and that's
rough estimates from Western Europe to
up to 60 percent in in some American
cities of space will be given to uh to
Mobility infrastructure which is
principally uh highways and and parking
lots which of course uh is a is a huge
spatial cost
and uh well another development of
course is that uh the commuting area as
we we start to call it so the the actual
um
definition of what a city is regardless
of administrative limits and different
boundaries of course this would be often
divided into some municipalities and all
it goes up to uh 100 kilometers in
diameter so suddenly what is a city
becomes
um or starts becoming a little bit vague
in the sense that the old Urban course
of course do not hold all the functions
anymore and we start seeing cities
um expanding in this economic uh
economic terms
well
without running into the risk of of
simplifying things a little bit too much
but what happened in a lot of cities
both in North America and in Western
Europe is that as the car became more
and more popular and as moving by car
became absolutely common
um and if you basically had a middle
class job and that's that's what you did
you lived in the suburbs and you
commuted to the office job by car
Transit companies or mass transit
companies public transport companies
started to run into serious financial
difficulties so
um traditionally uh when they were
actually set up in the 19th or end of
the 19th century 1910s 1920s they would
be private companies very often private
arailroads bringing workers to the
suburbs and dark or bringing the
Bourgeois and people who wanted to enjoy
Leisure outside of the city and then
back
as they started to run into trouble in
some countries and that's usually the
case in Western Europe they would be
nationalized they will be taken over by
the state as an important part of
military infrastructure but also an
important part of Mobility
infrastructure and kept but they roll
the societal role would definitely
decline so it would be it would become
something not necessarily for the middle
class but rather for the working class
Belgium here is some sort of an
exception because a lot of commuting
here and due to the fact that the
railway system was traditionally been
very dense
hadn't happened and still is happening
uh very much through public transport
but that's definitely not the case in
the UK for example or definitely not in
North America
but and sticking to North America
um in a number of uh cities over there
the process that happened uh was
inversed so the decline of public
transit did not lead to any uh
investment by the state either on the
federal or the state state level uh but
rather
um
eventually a dismantling of of public
transport systems happened and a very uh
particular story is that of the General
Motors Company so one of the main
producers of of these Mass Commodities
the cars
um who throughout the 1940s basically
bought a number of public transport
companies mass transit companies as they
are called over there and purposely led
to the decline uh why well the idea was
quite simple and it was basically to get
rid of the competitions that public
transport
um could have
um could have posed to the to the
individual Mobility to to the car so the
idea was to push public transport out of
the market and again
um
I just saw the comment from somebody
and and again yes the idea of course was
that this was also framed by the
discourse of modernity and and advancing
as a society
um I forgot to mention but we will be
taking uh a break in both today and then
a week uh I don't think that you know
sticking to the screen for two hours is
a healthy thing to do so we will take a
break actually in three minutes probably
for about five minutes
uh just in case you're getting a little
bit tight
but this uh total decline or some could
even say a disaster in terms of what
happened to mass transport must transits
or in public transport was not uh always
the case so as I already mentioned in in
some countries uh public transport
networks are actually what being taken
over by the state and even invested in
and one important thing that happens or
you know a symbolic project that
happened is that of copenhagen's finger
plant from 1947 uh so basically their
the decision was made to create an
alternative or maybe not a substitute
but an alternative parallel to car
commuting basically Suburban rail which
follows the shape of five fingers uh
corridors that would not only be
transport corridors but also along which
a number of different functions
especially residential but also economic
work related functions would be
um placed as well and that was uh as far
as I know one of the first plans that uh
tried to achieve what we call transport
oriented development or development
Urban Development that happens around or
in this particular case a long transport
corridors to allow for different
Mobility options back then maybe
environmental issues were not so much on
the agenda but the idea was that people
would be able to get more efficiently to
work not only by car but also by
Suburban rail
uh in our lovely Brussels well things
were not so
not so easy or well things were a little
bit in between so on the one hand the
car was definitely the king and actually
it's one of the uh slogans in in
let's say Brussels centered Academia and
public debate Carr became the King
around the 1950s with the Expo of the
1958 and still very much is a very
present and very privileged mode of
transport
but public transport of course did not
disappear and one of the particularities
of Brussels is that unlike in Charlotte
for example or many cities in Germany or
in France especially tramways for
example were never completely dismantled
and you would see and I can't think of
any specific names right now in France
but there are cities in which tranway
network existed uh 1940s 50s and 60s and
then was completely dismantled to open a
surface space to the car so what
happened in Brussels is that the Trump
was basically put underground so you see
on top left
which is that magnificent Urban Waterway
these days and you see a tram trying to
plow its way through the through the
city standing in a traffic jam the idea
uh well of course the city is packed the
space is limited with the rise of
mobility and individual mobility and the
rise of the number of cars traffic jams
happen the decision there was May need
not to make more space for the tram
would make to make more space for the
car so strategic decision was to put the
tram first on the ground creating a very
particular mode of transports made in
Brussels called pre-metro premature
which then eventually
um as it was actually planned was
converted into into a full-scale as we
call it in Brussels heavy metal look you
can actually see in pre-metro still and
that's line three and four in in
Brussels the tramline that goes from
north to south of the Pentagon which as
you probably have heard
is now well will soon be converted into
a proper Network once and the new metro
line from God you know and northwards is
constructed uh so you can for example
see I don't know if you ever had a
chance of of uh you know noting that the
platforms and although this is a trump
stock the platforms are actually much
much wider than usually would be in the
case of a tram and they are much longer
basically they were built I think
already back in the 70s anticipating a
proper Metro we are now in 2020 so
finally the Metro is is happening
although well it's a controversial
project to say the least
um let's take a little break here not
longer than five six minutes so grab
another tea or a coffee and I'll see you
back in four or five minutes all right
great
see you in a moment
welcome back overview I hope you grabbed
another drink or whatever it is that you
are having or grab another notebook to
keep noticing things although of course
you've got the recording of all this
um and I can see that some people are
asking questions
um I might also ask you if up to now up
to now everything has been clear or if
you've got any questions about what I've
been talking about if yes please raise
your hand just speak up but I think it's
an interesting question that Mika asked
here in the chat with um
indeed what was happening right now is
that we have an increased desire for
uh what we could say is a pre-industrial
city a city of walking of uh short of
distances density of users mixes
um does anybody have an opinion on this
would you agree would you not agree
or maybe Mika whoever he or she is has
an opinion
that's me
um
yeah I wasn't sure if it's really linked
to the pre-industrial city but when you
explained
um
how how it was looking how how it looked
like I thought about like actually it's
exactly what today's planning is about
like this
uh mixed use this like
a narrow uh streets where you yeah with
walkability and short distances and I
mean maybe it's also really a European
perspective
maybe it could be like a new role model
of today's planning does anybody have an
uh an opinion on this would anybody like
to react
I can compare with for example in
interrupt
um I'm living
[Music]
um
in the center of the city and
what we see is uh that the place for
um private cars is reducing for example
they they put parking lots under
undergrounds for making some some
leisure activities or Parks or something
else so we see a movement I guess when
we focus on that and definitely in
Brussels depending on the policy now
um it's more ecological
minded and we see more
um opportunities to to reduce
parking lots and and more movements like
for example in unspec land yeah
um
so this pedestrian area of Brussels yeah
yeah and we couldn't imagine I guess 20
years ago so we see different movements
yeah there is definitely some kind of
shift happening I mean we are not in the
1960s or 70s not where like what is
right now on the slide things have moved
on the present of the car is definitely
put on the question but is this about
going to a free industrial city what
would be the problem with that or would
be the risk of
um just reverting to walking let's say
if that's what the pre-industrial city
was about
does anybody have you know an opinion on
this
there is no wrong answers here
Vitality is saying that new Mobility
plans are aiming at the best of use of
all Technologies we have now with
maximum inclusivity
yeah I guess so
um the proof is in the in the you know
well depends on how they of course
implement it and and it's the idea of
course is that everybody is included and
we use all the Technologies we have
in practice we will see that it's a
little bit complicated
um
maybe it's also the like when we were
looking at the Metro System that it's
more about underground transportation
so like separation okay
transportation systems mm-hmm somebody
somebody else started uh talking who was
that yeah that was me and also
also what I wanted to bring up was the
where industry
industry or small businesses are still
located and where people can have you
know
um can find jobs almost in their in
their neighborhood that it it you know
especially maybe jobs that don't
necessarily pay so well that wouldn't be
interesting for other people to to
commute into the city too and I think
these kind of businesses are a bit under
pressure from the reduction in space
that they have on you know to to
organize these productive activities so
I think yeah space in front of there in
front of the street to to actually do
their deliveries and I think there's
attention there in the kind of city
um you want and the way you want the
service different neighborhoods and
different
um different areas so one of the cases
was like um these smaller construction
um supplies kind of stores maybe in the
area of lack and like not far from the
canal you know serving a kind of a
secondary places where you know you just
wouldn't go to Bricco for those kind of
um materials you would go to your
neighborhood and that's that's becoming
harder with uh you know to to maintain
in a in an urban environment that gives
more space to walking and to to to to
um yeah to bike lanes and so on so
that's on the one side it doesn't mean
that I agree but it's I think one of the
one of the pressures that is being
um this is being felt by by that by that
group I mean I guess what's what's
important what you said and to relate it
also to what I was talking about before
and what we tell you there is the
writing is that there is some with each
of these technological shifts of course
they are very
um I mean it's a very broad sketch these
things were not happening in in sudden
turns it's a it's a process but the
space is valorized in different ways and
for example if we see here in this slide
as I mentioned
um
clearly space became very limited with
the rise of the cars and the decision
was made that the space is extremely
valuable and it should be given to the
modes that it's the most efficient in
terms of speed as the most rational mode
also not only economically or or
temporally efficient so other modes like
public transport or I don't even mention
cycling there had to disappear or be
moved elsewhere and I think what's
happening right now is some kind of
revolarization of space
um but space is always limited so if you
take it uh I mean if you give it to one
or some set of users
which I think also perhaps we will have
time to talk about it next week has a
clear class component so there is a
clear middle class idea and behind
opening Central uh Urban spaces to
walking cycling and public transport and
taking it away from the car so if you
give it to these kind of users you have
to take it away from others in this case
the car
and I think an important question is to
ask well if we want the car to disappear
from the city like from Brussels who is
using the car right I mean who is who is
dependent on it for example these
businesses small shops that um I don't
know either well I mean they play
productive activity requires
accessibility by car but also I think
um probably you've heard and right now
in this pandemic crazy times people are
talking about 15-minute neighborhood and
the idea of how
the pandemic has shown us that we can
well since we uh essentially many of us
stop a lot of activities we started
walking around and cycling and all that
so the idea that maybe we could use this
to reorganize the cities around uh 15
minutes perimeters walking pyramids
within which we can all find all the
uses and functions that we need but I
think an important question there is who
actually lives so close to a good school
a good job and all that and then
Brussels but in many other cities there
will be a lot of people who need to find
employment uh quite far from where they
live and a lot of them would have to go
by car to to get to that job so what you
know what then
um
I will continue with the with the
lecture but I hope there will be space
for for more for more questions
um there was one point that I want to
make that is you know I don't want to
say main conclusion of this historical
trajectory but I think an important
Point
um to keep in mind in in all this is
that
um
it's not just a well it's not just a
descriptive you know took the fox of
what different modes of Transport were
there and and how it impacted the urban
reform I think this is something that is
maybe a little bit interesting but
essentially I don't think it's very
critical and doesn't really allow us to
understand uh too much about how the
city functions or functioned in the past
I think what's very important though is
that with each of these shifts with each
of these
um turning points and dynamics that led
to to uh to a shift in terms of how
people moved we were getting closer and
closer
um to the situation that we have today
which is that transport is absolutely
crucial uh not only for the development
of cities but for the development of
the socio-economic system which we live
uh today on a global scale which is that
of of global capitalism uh so it would
be import impossible for for the current
socioeconomic relations to to develop to
the point that they have developed
without transport and without the
development of transport and vice versa
so outside of the capitalist system
there probably would not have been such
such a push for development of
individual vulnerability for example and
individual Mobility by car that is
propelled by fossil fuels uh with all
the geopolitical and environmental uh
atrocities and impacts that this this
produces
um essentially transport or transport
geography is a discipline uh required
space Not only to be conquered
physically intensive distance basically
uh moving from A to B would become as
fast as short of a time as possible but
also uh some kind of imaginary and
cartographical colonization or
conquering of space if we go back to end
of the 18th century for example in
Europe uh well the majority of people
who inhabited uh well maybe eight of the
17th century could be a little bit less
controversial but the majority of people
who lived on our continent and
definitely the majority of people who
lived on our planet did not live on the
jurisdiction of any state or any any
state Administration they essentially
lived outside State structures of course
State States and administrations existed
but most people lived in villages in
areas where once in a once in a while a
tax collector would maybe show up it
would be quite easy to avoid the
encounter with that kind of gentleman
rather not gentle woman I'm afraid
so
it's at this point and I think transport
is absolutely crucial for understanding
of why this happened and how this
happened that there happened or began to
happen some kind of strategic expansion
of State infrastructure and state
Administration predominantly related to
security reasons and search for you know
different forms of capital uh for
instance slavery so trying to uh reach
different places where bodies could be
could be snatched taken into captivity
and then and then sold or propelled into
productive activity
um but for the state to be able to
organize this process it had to develop
its cartography it has to develop its uh
dominance its knowledge its control over
the over space
and here we see a map of France in 1632
which is essentially well we've seen
some roads we see some cities and and
connections between those
um but this radically changes with uh
the development of States interest in
terms of the resources uh as I mentioned
bodies people but also of course other
natural resources would anything that
you can mine and well I don't know I'm
not a specialist here in terms of who
you can be interested in as a state but
uh what essentially happened is that
um
from a natural space a space that was
inhabited a space that was lived uh we
started moving into a fire name of
obstructive of uh of absolute space that
is very much related to the
consolidation of of States
infrastructure as a way of organizing
social and material order that is on the
ground to bureaucratically govern it to
rule it from the distance from a very
top-down perspective
the example of France is very
interesting because literally over there
the decision was made of course not
immediately not at one meeting but
progressively
um it was a state bureaucrats arrived a
decision to divide the state in more or
less equally shaped
um
areas the Departments and based on a
regular grid on the left hand side you
see there's some kind of
conceptualization of this on the right
hand side we see a result which is the
the actual the eventual Division I think
one of the first ones uh in in the in
the French territory I think today of
course it's not exactly the same that
has developed for uh different
historical reasons but the idea was very
important that the seven the
administrative reform of the 1790 would
replace some old feudal uh tribal even
uh division of territories
into
um it would be replaced with abstract
bureaucratic logic that would be applied
and more or less the same way in each of
these each of these territories each of
these uh departments
as we can skip uh what was very
important in this in this development is
that the state needed very much uh
um Universal
[Music]
um
and how to put it a reliable system of
measuring space and other related
phenomena such as for example time or
quantity it might be very difficult for
us to to imagine this but the
unification of of measuring systems both
of time and space and quantity was
something that took a very long time and
it was definitely not in place until end
of the even 17 or 18th century so it
took a very long time to actually make
sure make sure that all the inhabitants
of a given nation state of a given
territory would actually subjugate
themselves to the usage of of a unified
that's the word I was looking for
unified metric or measurement system so
for example the unification of the
metric systems in Germany took place in
as late as 1868 in Austria in 1871 and
Hungary three years later in Russia in
1919 and in China only in 1959. what
does it mean it means that there existed
of course ways of measuring but there
will be culturally dependent or there
will be spatially dependent so a
particularly a unit of measurement a
foot an elbow
would mean different things in different
Villages would mean different things at
the different times of the day or yeah
it would mean different things whether
it would be the activity of selling or
of buying so for example you would sell
a small bag of rice and buy a big one
um
there was a difference between and
that's in many pre-colonial African
communities kingdoms there will be a
division between strong measures for
selling goods and weak measures for for
buying loans so there was a huge
diversity of different ways of measuring
space measuring time and measuring
quantity all that in order and also
because of and again this is a two-way
Dynamic the development of the transport
system and the development of State as a
institution or a set of Institutions
that had to control space quantity and
time gave way to a unified system
of which transport is absolutely Central
and here I mean the symbolic one meter
which is of course a huge abstract
agreement that we are in that this is
what one meter is and same could be said
about a kilogram a second and many
others
moving a little bit more uh well going a
little bit more into transport here
um I mentioned time and for example as
late as in the 18th century uh distance
between particular cities and as a
result of travel time speaking in
particular cities such as in Germany
we're not fixed or or set
um so in 1881 German Railways or
different kinds of German Railways
because there was no one National system
followed five different time zones which
were different not by one hour but by a
different amount of minutes which meant
that basically one area I guess they are
here color coded would be five or seven
minutes ahead of the other one which
meant that the passengers had to do the
calculation themselves it was all an
oral agreement and an ongoing discussion
between
um between the passengers and the staff
to understand at what time uh things
would happen what time the train would
depart leave
Etc
um
and as I mentioned the this integration
of of measurement system integration of
uh of different modes of Transport
networks allowed the state to control to
consolidate the territory and to
um and to yeah to basically be able to
develop socioeconomic relations that we
take today very much for for granted
um this was absolutely crucial I mean
the reason why I'm making this a bit of
a digression and the departure from you
know this historic uh trajectory is that
this was absolutely crucial this
colonization of space and colonization
of what we consider to be a very much of
a social or could consider a social
activity that movement and transport is
was absolutely crucial for the
development of again what we take very
much for granted the global networks of
wires cables railroads highways in this
particular case I already show you that
um that map
allowing transport to to lubricate the
capitalist global global system
and today this colonization of space uh
if we can call it this way it's no
longer a national matter is no longer
nation states that are propelling this
process it's something that is happening
very much on the on the global scales
um
what was very important in this very
long trajectory I started very quickly
at the end of the 17th century and now
we are in 1950s what was very important
is that a whole science developed around
uh this colonization of different
measuring systems of different uh ways
of of living and interacting with space
and this science of this scientific
field
I think we can call it a set of
neoclassical perspectives on not only
transport but also in economics on
social life which in transport itself is
very much present is very much dominated
by
um on the one hand transport Engineers
on the other hand transport Econo
economists what I'm talking about here
is basically
um the main say and I will not talk a
lot about this but basically if you went
to
um a master degree which I'm very happy
you did it but if you went to a mass
degree in in transport management or
Logistics at any Technical University
this is very much what you would be
learning today
I guess at this time of the Neo night
which we are a bit more boring I hope
than what I have to offer but
um hope there is no regrets here in the
room today but uh if you want to be an
engineer and if you want to be an
economist to build roads this is
basically what you what you learn why is
it called neoclassical transport well
very much it relates to new classical
economics which deals with uh a
cold-blooded analysis A study of
distribution production of goods outputs
and and income through uh and that's
absolutely crucial supply and demand so
a system which has to be in a permanent
equilibrium
which essentially looks at transport as
a part or a separate Market in which
transport is a good commodity which is
offered in the market passengers being
the being its consumers
um
what is important here there are two
main principles which very much today
again in Academia but also very much in
the world of practitioners so the wealth
of those who plan roads who build roads
who claim that we need a new metro line
we need Motorway or that this or that
particular mode of Transport is
absolutely essential for for
contemporary cities to thrive
so these two dogmas say that on the one
hand transport is an essentially
rational discipline it's a it's a
discipline that is rational because it
has to be developed by by experts it's a
top-down discipline that requires this
top-down cartographic vision of space
which can be reduced to its absolute
Universal measures
um that also means that there is a
science behind it which means that it's
not an issue that can be fully opened to
a public debate it's a it's a part of
urban life that has to be developed by
experts and only experts can have the
final word in terms of decision making
uh in terms of how transport develops
why and and using what most
um there is a very strong prediction
there in this uh in this in this field
of of knowledge that transport geography
or or transport economics engineering
are essentially objective Sciences they
are they are much more on the side of
science sciences and Humanities for
example they they purpose being pursuing
objectivity and truth that's a quote
from another very important textbook on
on transport geography the idea being is
that we can arrive some kind of absolute
truths in terms of what is good
transport and wonder what is bad which
essentially are translatable
transferable from one locality to
another so if uh if we go back to the
1950s if the US cities develop
motorways and develop car infrastructure
which is efficient and rational this is
a solution that can also work in dense
medieval European cities uh such as the
ones in Belgium Brussels for example
um
crucially this line of thinking and that
maybe didn't develop in the end of the
17th or 19th century but was definitely
a result of this uh process that I
called the colonization of space
this field of of thinking and and
producing uh transport Consolidated
itself around the 1930s and 40s and that
propelled
um measurements and engineering studies
that allowed to to construct these
um into urban and intra-urban Motorway
systems and this very much continues
today following a rule of predicting uh
demand for for Mobility predicting
passenger flows or traffic flows and
providing necessary infrastructure for
it so basically most of Transport most
of which transport models do is predict
where would these flows go and provide
essential infrastructure an extension of
a
of Road Lane a construction of a new
Motorway construction of a new Metro uh
line and you name it
so that's one part of the rationality of
Transport the other part is that the
assumption is that the user itself uh
and uh it's yeah yeah the user itself is
also a rational being it's a homo
economicus it's an it's an economically
minded being that
um almost on a regular basis on a daily
basis conduct some kind of economic
analysis in terms of what is uh an
efficient way of of reaching a
destination B from from point A in terms
of time in terms of cost
um being making pragmatic free and and
very much utility-based choices in terms
of how to move and where to move
so in other words a market a market that
is being governed by by the laws of uh
of Economics which very much in this in
this line of thought are being compared
to the laws of physics a lot of these
models would have for example allusions
to gravity so gravity models that uh in
a natural-like way pools uh flows of
passengers to some destinations rather
than others because for example economic
activities present in an area
so that's
principle of Dogma number one and number
two is that uh there is this very strong
conviction and funny enough still not
fully fully proven but uh but the
conviction is very much there that
investment in transport infrastructure
uh of course uh that part is not
controversial leads to higher speeds uh
leads to lower travel times at least
lower transaction costs if you want to
move from A to B or yourself or some
Goods it's basically cheaper leads to
Economic Development so the better
infrastructure we have the the higher or
the better the growth of a locality so
if you want the city to be economically
prosperous uh wealthy you need
um you need Quality Transport
infrastructure
um
so that very much is on the pin by this
um by this quote that I already
mentioned earlier today that the unique
purpose of Transport is in fact to to
limit to reduce space and time that is
needed to cover the space to zero that
that is the unique purpose of of
movement in in the city which also means
that the travel time itself is an
unproductive activity because from the
monetary perspective if you want to go
from A to B
um well you want to get there as quickly
as possible the time of getting there
itself is not a valuable activity now
there are I mean there's a flurry of
problems here starting from the fact
that if you actually ask people through
studies uh what they do when they take
the metro or where they cycle which is
such a complicated and multi-faceted
activity they very often say that this
is actually a very important part of the
day that commuting on public transport
for example allows them to catch up with
friends to read to relax to meditate
cycling being as I mentioned
multi-faceted activity allows people to
get relaxed work out
get an endorphin kick and and all that
and that's so much more than just moving
from from one place to
um to another
um but again without trying to draw some
kind of caricature I think it's
important to to understand that this way
of thinking about transport leads us to
a formulation of an absolutely
fundamental problem uh in inverted
commas that a lot of Engineers transport
Engineers transport economists recognize
and that problem is congestion if you
focus on a fluid flow of
passengers cars whatever the transport
mode is any obstruction to that flow any
obstruction to that model is a is a
problem that has to be solved
and that problem has to be solved
because otherwise the system is
irrational that's talking about number
one and
the second reason is that uh and unless
you do that you uh you can
um
hamper the economic growth the economic
development of of the locality that
you're in in charge of
as I mentioned this uh this beneficial
supposedly beneficial relationship
between transport development and
economic development so better roads
mean better transport better exchange of
goods and services
um that of course Works to some extent I
mean you can you can see that happening
theoretically at least from scratch in
um in many cities many countries of the
global South but then uh this relation
has never really been theorized it's
never really been proven and it will be
extremely difficult to to make that
claim in cities that are postmodern so
such as Brussels or many other cities in
the global North but actually
increasingly also Global South so
addition of infrastructure especially
road infrastructure car infrastructure
um and it's anticipated impact in terms
of economic growth Economic Development
it's it's a very controversial issue
that
um well it's not really we don't have
any tangible proof or tangible enough to
to uh to say with certainty that this is
the case
but it's an argument that you can hear a
lot and including in Brussels and
Belgium
is this clear do you have any questions
this is usually where people are
scratching their hands a little bit so I
want to make sure that you are okay
uh nobody is writing anything in the
chat no Angry comments I keep
advancing here then
um so what happens when you when you
believe that what you do is is rational
and and it's very important for Society
for economy
well you essentially engage in I mean
um developing more and more and more to
elaborate and complicated mathematical
models that try to predict not only to
describe what's happening without
actually trying to predict uh what is
going to happen and what is now
happening very much in the business of
transport economics and transport
engineering is modeling human behavior
so trying to predict uh where people
will be interested in going and not
anymore where where they are actually
are heading and where these flaws are
being distributed in an urban
environment what's crucial here is that
this field is extremely not only
extremely Technical and quantitative but
it's very indescriptive so this logic of
Transport Supply and transport demand is
is devoid of any social uh cultural
political uh relations so
when I say that a transport user this
homo economicus is considered to be this
rational utility-based uh person or
figure that makes these rational choices
in terms of where they go and how any
issue of gender any issue of class or
ethnicity of age is
um at best mentioned but given a very
little weight if we are talking about
modeling so these different aspects can
be given different ways given different
importance importance different levels
of levels of importance and these issues
are quite simply not not there and of
course we will be discussing this a
little bit I mean these different
critical approaches such as
well some anti-capitalist marxists
feminist
uh any radical Theory social theory the
exposure to those in engineering
programs is close to none
um which basically means that without
trying to be you know too critical about
the engineers who are trying to do their
job
um basically they they are really not
aware of of the complexity of social
relations and spatial relations that are
happening in the city so everything that
you've learned with David bass and Nick
by now this is this is simply not there
um a city according to this vision is
essentially a a model that can be
um constructed calculated and put in
place and you can predict what will
happen uh tomorrow or the day after
based on that in any City in the in the
world
now that thinking uh has a very yeah
very very strange uh way of Imagining
the city essentially if a city is or any
Urban space is more of a field of
application than than actually a side of
any Dynamics or conflicts or
contradictions uh different interests in
terms of what should be happening in
that space in that in that society and
I'm sure that you've all come across um
uh maybe even these drawings or similar
ones from from Nicole busier and his and
his friends and allies who basically
imagine that this is exactly what should
happen in in a modern city that these
models not only related to transport in
this case also to housing or generally
Economic Development should be literally
applied in a city
um so the idea there would be that in
order to for that model to be as
efficient as possible everything in the
city especially it's medieval it's
pre-industrial uh remnants would have to
be raised the city would have to become
black empathy slave on which this model
could be applied
so
even though
this maybe wasn't its most extreme in
the 1950s in the 1960s when these Urban
motorways were being constructed when as
I showed you these Urban tramways and
Brussels were being put on the ground
and a lot of heavy construction offers
destruction had to be done this thinking
still very much applies this if you if
you tune in to Engineers from
construction offices in Brussels or
elsewhere in Belgium
northern Europe the idea is that uh
planning still has to fall follow uh
some rational rules of solving
congestion uh in Brussels for example we
have a Belgium a long-standing debate
about what to do with the Ring of
Brussels the Ring Road whether it has to
be expanded or not every single time
there is an engineer talking on the
radio or on the news what their solution
would be is to add to the infrastructure
because basically if you have traffic
jams that generates lost time that's
detrimental to the economy you have to
expand that infrastructure in order for
the flows to be more fluid and
unobstructed
This Modern neoclassical thinking also
uh well thinking about the fluidity of
flows and and removing barriers to these
led to a separation of different modes
of Transport so this is this is why we
would have uh overpasses uh food bridges
that would allow of well separate
pedestrians from Cars For example so
allow the cars to have
um a smooth smooth space infrastructure
to for movement while pedestrians would
have to
cross it uh cross it over all the energy
and that of course also
um that line of thought would be very
much related or very much inspired also
by the development of individual
Mobility via VIA the car right so the
car being not only this extremely
freeing mode of Transport also a very
rational and very fast way of moving
around
now
we arrived to the 1970s let's say and
something very important happened around
that time
would anybody have an idea looking at
the pictures uh What uh what I have in
mind
not change the way that we look at the
car the change of the way we look at the
transport
the only crisis in the oil crisis I
guess somebody already mentioned that in
one of the classes
so the oil trucks of the 1970s
um when first in the 1973 uh the
organization of our petroleum exporting
countries so essentially the the Persian
Gulf countries uh instituted Noel
embargo in the 1979 Iranian Revolution
uh took place that's not something that
you can easily model that's geopolitics
for you and what basically happened is
that the global oil prices went through
the roof
um not maybe for a moment for a longer
time but and then they went
um down a little bit to a level that
allowed of course for for car-based
Mobility to to continue but the what
basically happened was that
um on a global scale
decision makers people who were in
charge of Designing transport
infrastructure realized that this
Limitless Mobility by car has its um
it's its economic cost First of all that
fossil fuels might not be as available
as as they as they used to be but also
around that time began to begin some
kind of uh
move to this slide already uh
reflection on on different externalities
of different also social and
environmental costs that are related to
to car based Mobility these
environmental costs being for example
are predominantly noise
of course accidents health related
issues uh mostly related to pollution
that is that is created by by individual
costs
um
and around that time I mean maybe it's
also difficult for us to imagine but
until the 1970s the idea that a car uh
to be efficient in terms of its fuel
consumption it has to be safe in terms
of making sure that if it hits other
vehicles or with his pedestrians or
cyclists it has to be more or less safe
and and that there are these different
areas of the car that uh that absorb the
the energy of the impact that was all uh
essentially noted there with some
exceptions uh a car was
um the cars were not efficient from the
from the economic perspective from the
environmental perspective either
uh what changed is that well I'm again
moving very fast to these uh through
these developments but what changed is
that there was uh first a reflection on
the environmental and impact of the car
itself
um and a general reflection on the on
the question of sustainable development
of development that
allows uh future generations to benefit
from the same resources from the same
opportunities that we are we are
benefiting from today so some kind of
beginning of a reflection in terms of
the planetary limits of of the growth
that our societies are of the societies
at the time where we're engaging in
and also an idea that uh
uh cities are absolutely crucial for
that in that process that in order to
arrive with uh at sustainability of the
development on the planetary level uh
cities have to uh have to also be
transformed in order to become more
sustainable
why is that important and we arrive to
to today to contemporary situation well
it's important and yeah this is as also
the title uh says this is the
let's say a
another set of also very dominant and
very very important hegemonic
perspectives on transport sustainable
Urban transport this is because
transport is recognized today as one of
the most important sources of um or
contributors to pollution here we uh see
that it's at least 14 of CO2 Emissions
on the on the global scale as the uh
direct emissions
um and also while the graph I would say
that it's a little bit controversial
because you also could add much more in
terms of the different other related
course on construction and and the way
that housing is constructed as as a
function of of availability of Transport
but let's say we stick to the 14 of
global emissions being related directly
to transport which makes transport one
of the
um well here I'm a little bit wrong that
is the largest single source of global
Transportation emissions because you
immediately see that industry is at 21
but it can be also boiled to the
different sectors and all that but
what's very important with transport is
that this um definitely one of the
fastest if not the fastest uh Rising uh
contributed to to emissions so every
year the increase is the highest among
all economic sectors globally so Global
Climate problems are essentially
increasingly transport problems this is
uh this is let's say maybe not Point of
Departure but one of the main
reflections of this perspective on on
the issue
what also is very important is that as
you see on the left hand side the global
proportion of people living in in urban
communities is rising so one if in 2010
we were already after this magic uh
threshold of 50 or more of people living
in cities as opposed to the countryside
in 2030 the projection is that it will
be 60 of people living in cities and
that will go up to at least 67 in 2015.
of course this is a mantra that I'm sure
that at least those of you who follow
the master and urban Studies have
already heard before that we are living
in an urban society that you know and
our planet is essentially in urban and
urban planetary urbanization there's a
lot of Concepts uh flying flying around
but it's important and it is a fact that
increasingly the global population
becoming more and more urban it's in the
cities that a lot of these problems will
have to be addressed so the urban
Mobility is not only the transport is
crucial for solving the climate crisis
but it's the urban transport that
constitutes definitely a very important
uh challenge that has to be addressed so
we see that and that's the right hand
side graft graph that Urban Mobility
demand for urban Mobility is rising uh
almost exponentially
and that's expressing trillions of
kilometers per year here uh that it Rose
from uh 2010 to 2030 by uh 68 percent
now we might think that with all the
reflection on externalities that cars
have and produce an environmental and
social aspects that are very detrimental
to to our lives
um that we are moving away from the car
this is a perspective that we already
had a short charge on that there is a
shift so we start to look at Urban space
a little bit differently we want less
cars to be present in it and in fact on
a global scale
um if you look at the on the left hand
side as a cumulative figure so the
global number of all registered cars uh
the rise is is ongoing and it's um and
it's huge and that's
well also seen in the graph on the right
hand side where we see non-cumulative
yearly amount of cars being sold
on a global scale so we see that every
year the amount of cars being sold is
rising 2019 being some sort of an
exception we have a little bit of a drop
but what the graph doesn't not show is
the amount of SUV so the sports utility
vehicles as they are called which went
through the roof in 2018 and 2019 their
contribution environmentally speaking
being much uh High a few times higher
than regular vehicles what also you can
see over there is that in Orange if you
see that the contribution we can call it
this way of the European Union countries
in terms of the number of cars sold is
more or less stable so here we don't see
um an important rise if you look at
India in Gray and then on China in Blue
uh here the difference between 2005 and
2019 is significant
so there is a lot of economies some call
them developing economies I'm not really
a fan of the word but um
a lot of nation states a lot of
societies where where the levels of
motorizations were relatively low and
this commodity is is definitely becoming
uh more and more available it's not
exactly the same process that was
happening uh in in northern Europe or
North America or Western Europe or North
America in the 1940s 50s and 60s but uh
it's definitely a steep rise of
motorization of Mobility levels which
raises a lot of environmental questions
but also ethical issues in terms of
whether this is something that
um well we now with our Western Northern
eyes are looking at very critically
matter of fact it's something that these
people these societies have the right to
engage in as as we did as our parents
and grandparents did some decades ago
um but what is very important here I'm
going to skip this one slide is that
this debate if we can put it this way
shifts its attention so we're moving
away from the problem of congestion the
problem of uh
unobstructed flows uh the problem of
rationality the problem of Economic
Development we see that this Economic
Development has its
um environmental price if we can put it
this way and in a very important and
very important and symbol of that in
mobility in transport is the car is is
the car is the
important contributor to to that uh to
that cake in terms of pollution in terms
of externalities of
um of transport
and next time so we still have a bit
time for questions maybe discussion
we're going to talk about specific
examples of how transport develops along
this line of thought
but and I think we'll be uh well it's
definitely not the only thing we're
going to do because as I will also
explain in a week
um that perspective also is extremely
Limited in its lack of social and also
spatial understanding of the city so a
simple critique of the car as the
problem is also leading us into a number
of traps which mean that our
understanding of how people enjoy or do
not enjoy Mobility because of the class
the gender the ethnicity and many other
factors is extremely Limited
so I put a little comma here
um I wonder if you have any questions
any points of discussion
we still have 12 minutes so we might as
well use them
just ice
I might
um
try to initiate a little discussion here
about about popularity of cars and
um
and the Smiths that we're now seeing of
of the of the of the lifestyle on high
speed and Etc
um I observed a curious a curious thing
that on TV in Belgium at least I don't
usually watch TV but I happen to watch
uh one night with my friends like a
generic Belgium Belgium program and
during the advertisement
uh period all the ads a vast majority of
them were about cars
and uh
in any or in all ways they were trying
to sell either a lifestyle the
ecological ecological idea that new cars
to be can be green and Etc but I was
wondering if we might ever arrive to to
to this
um to this thinking that we should not
be advertising this anymore as we don't
advertise cigarettes or I don't know
hard alcohol on on
TV and in media and whether it makes
sense or it doesn't
it's an interesting thought we will
actually come back to it next time but I
wonder if somebody has already you know
an opinion on this
should advertising car cars or sales
cards would be banned because it's
but for society
maybe I can even add to this that
um
I've been watching Belgian TV for a long
time as I'm convention and um
I there always used to be uh car
commercials but in the last two years
um actually most of them has have been
for SUV
uh cars or like there's been a bit shift
to
making commercials for SUV cars which
yeah I find really strange yeah
well
um yeah I think it's it's happening and
I was considering to put another graph
that shows the increase of SUV sales and
really before 2015 it was this Market
hardly existed it really became uh a
thing in the last two years at least in
in Western Europe I think it was a
little bit different in Eastern Europe
and Russia Ukraine
[Music]
some cultural reasons also really bad
roads and a lot of rich people
um but um
okay but that seems that if you tune
into the mainstream culture if you show
TV and and advertising in between
programs the cars are still very much
there well maybe not regular cars but
more SUVs as you say
um
I think it's an interesting observation
anybody else has some some thoughts on
this or another things
[Music]
be yeah quite hard to uh prohibit the
advertisements if there's no uh real
alternative for the car for example in
in Flanders yeah there's an extreme
suburbanization and it's uh Mobility is
not
uh not that good to get to to different
places such as work or Leisure so yeah I
think first a better alternative for the
car needs to be installed
and and what is that alternative
yeah maybe better public transport
um safer also in cities but also in just
Town safer uh bicycle Lanes or yeah
and yes uh yeah car sharing more if not
really an alternative for cars it may be
less having each household having two
cars or three
um and in Belgium there's also the big
problem of
the the companies having giving cars to
their employees
uh which has spark debates a lot
yes in Belgium in fact most of new cars
being installed on so-called company
cars which uh
paid for by the I mean for those who
don't know who are not from Belgium
um
it's a system that allows you to get a
free car from your employer it's
basically a way of giving somebody a
salary bump because it's tax-free and
um bonus if you increase somebody's
salary they would have to pay tax on
this you don't pay a tax on the company
car
um
but then why do you think people uh well
because it seems that
I described some some kind of a shift of
thinking and some reflection on these
environmental problems that the
corporate uses and all the nuisances
that it causes but it seems that people
still drive why why do you think they
still do it
why is it still so popular
and maybe I can refer to this I think
there's like the
um exactly what you were talking about
before like
um certain
um
yeah so
factors which which cannot be
um
um somehow persist before like like
urban planners cannot
um no sorry
um like certain things you cannot plan
and like it's an individual approach
that the symbol of the car is still like
deep in the mind of a lot of people that
they it's like a day um routine that you
get into your car and drive to the to to
your working place and I think that's
exactly the problem that it's certain
um changes in the transportation system
cannot be made by other planners or
transport Transportation planners but
um have to be made in in in the society
or in the in symbolism of of a car so
it's a mindset it's a cultural
habitus sociologists would say it's a
way of imagining how we interact with uh
with the world or how we move through it
but I think the example of the company
car also shows that something else it's
not exclusive but it's also a policy
that there are a number of political
instruments that make it uh
I mean if we go with that uh
simplified logic of making a rational
economic choice uh how do I go and where
do I go it simply makes this decision
more more simple more rational it makes
sense to have a car from an economic
perspective as well in in many cities
still
um
yeah if I could maybe add to that also
that's structurally there is a lot of
government as well like policy support
not just like the company cars but as we
saw these days with the crisis I think
we try to boost like not to to allow our
automobile manufacturing automobile
companies
um Cromwell because of the employment
opportunities that they provide so
strangely enough actually some of the
financial
loss or some of the new
um funds for to stimulate the economy
have been directly towards I think
Individual Car ownership purchase of
different people so I think when you
when you see that it's
it's a big imperative a big push if if
you can have access to that as well yeah
I think same goes with Aviation I don't
know if you follow that on the news but
one of the first maybe not first but one
of the early discussions in terms of
some economic package for stimulating
the the economy in Belgium was towards
the the aviation companies the argument
being is that these industries create
jobs and these jobs are valuable
well
um I'm not saying whether this is right
or wrong
[Music]
but the argument is there that these
modes of Mobility also produce
employment
I think that relates a little bit to
this aspect of Economic Development this
anticipation that you know since this
way of moving around our cities or our
Societies in general uh is very
important for the economy to to to keep
growing to keep persisting
um
are there any other comments maybe from
some people who haven't spoken yet
you have some thoughts
some comments
um I was also thinking about security
like
um the the use of the car is still
um like yeah done by many because maybe
it's the last like it's the most secure
way of moving around in some cities and
also like I'm thinking and like as a
woman as a girl like moving around the
city at night usually like um I mean not
here in Brussels because I don't have a
car here in Brussels like back home
um I would go by car at night
um just because like
um yeah it's not very secure to move
around uh with like public transport or
even by bike so I would say like yeah
it's it's a matter of security as well
and
um it's more like a structural problem
uh to change so I guess more steps have
to be taken in that sense
yeah it's a very good point it existed
before the pandemic and now it's uh it's
become even more more of an issue so
early data uh shows us that uh
especially the upper middle class or
upper class people have uh have bought
themselves a new car to uh to separate
themselves from the from the danger of
interacting with others earlier this
danger would be related to maybe
criminality or general lack of safety
especially at night especially for women
perhaps but now this sense of danger and
the car is this kind of bubble that
allows you to separate yourself from
whatever danger Society holds it's it's
even stronger
[Music]
um
I think what's important also uh we will
talk about this a lot uh next time is
that this goes very differently for for
different people I mean it sounds very
obvious but uh whether you look at the
situation from a class perspective or
from a gender perspective or from a
racial perspective
I think all these three uh also age is
very important all these four then apply
in Brussels very much
uh the way that people arrive to a
decision in terms of why they go where
they go and how they go it's it's very
different from class to class from
gender to gender and
etc etc
so this homo economicus Paradigm is
extremely problematic there but so is I
hope I will convince you of that this uh
direct critique uh of the car because uh
different people use the car for
different reasons and not always it's a
individual choice but also there are
some structural issues at play uh also
indeed some cultural inertia some ways
of being that were installed and
promoted for decades which now we are or
some of us
living in City centers
are critical of but things have things
are quite different if you're uh from a
different class and living in different
areas of the city
um I don't mind taking one more or two
more questions but it's eight already so
we are very free to leave if you want to
I don't want to take too much of your
time
well
great
um I'm glad this is working from the
technical perspective at least
yeah I will uh I will see you next week
that we have program I know that in
covet times Well it's not happening but
no no I was I was told that uh yeah yeah
I was uh
was trying to do it but uh it's not
possible unfortunately I wish we could
and do it the idea is for those of you
who are in Brussels next semester but
all of you will be right
um
well
I mean
um let's say
[Music]
well we don't know of course what
happens in a few months but the idea is
that if in Spring we are more or less to
you know more into face-to-face meetings
than we do the Excursion then
we imagined with David bus and others
what would happen if we meet with 40
people and try to keep distance I think
this would uh you know we would hit
YouTube very quickly I think trying to
walk through the city in this
arrangement
so
no and also in December I mean it would
be very strange uh from my experience in
the end we would definitely try to keep
together just to keep warm it's it's
cold right so
um we will do that in Spring I hope it's
a nice Excursion uh from what I've heard
uh people usually enjoy it
um even though it's only about transport
but yeah uh
uh I'm sorry about that I wish I wish we
could do it yeah this is the reality
we're living in
um I hope you care of a great rest of
the week I'll see you all next week uh
the links are there so it seems that
everything is clear and working so
that's brilliant
um enjoy and have a good have a good
week
thank you for the like John thank you
very much