[ Music ]
>> Welcome everybody and evening.
Welcome to the second session.
of urban social geography. Thanks for being here despite the live stream and the
recording. I think it really makes sense to be here so we can have a bit of an
interactive session. How did you arrive in Brussels first week? Everything going
Okay, yeah.
Yeah, okay.
Your landing still a little bit.
How did you find a stonselow for those attending?
Did someone attend?
Stonselows, yeah.
Then I'll live up to your expectations more or less.
And you find it weird and they started with over 50%
of the urban population lifts and cities.
That was on the first slide.
OK.
We didn't have a deal that she would put that on there.
But I can see her critical minds.
You can start thinking about first slides so that we have
her answers here.
Ready?
OK.
Today we'll be talking about--
I could say an important chunk of research into urban geography.
Most of my geographers, yes.
I haven't. No, last week that. Yeah, it didn't work.
Yeah, you remember? Yes.
Okay. That's what, no, this system doesn't work.
I'm not sure why.
have a singing voice, so I'll try to project my ideas.
And if you don't hear it, I can give it a bit higher or louder.
But maybe we should be a little bit quiet
and then that will help as well.
So, rural cities, global cities,
one of the big debates I think in urban geography
and urban cities more widely.
It's also a very long standing debate going back
at least the eighties, which probably also explains what you had to read all
stuff that you may or may not find outdated. I hope it's not outdated. They're
all text but I think it's still relevant in one way or another and we'll also
try to discuss that a little bit. Now what's the structure of today? There's
three main parts of this lecture. First of all, we're going to discuss, I mean very generally,
the centrality of cities and city regions in the global economy and we'll take you through
three complementary views, I've used that built on one another by Joe Friedman, Sosca,
Sosca, and Alan Scott. Secondly, so that's kind of a conceptual theoretical discussion.
Secondly, we'll have more of a methodological discussion, which deals with how given these
concepts how we can actually measure and say something empirical about world cities and
global cities.
And one of the main methodologies there is the methodology by GOG, which is the globalization
and world cities research network, which was founded somewhere in the 1990s by Peter Taylor.
has been one of the main, you could say, empirical methodological contributions to the
debate from that period.
And third of all, as we'll learn, there was some kind of a dominance by Gorg, if you will,
in this area of cities in globalization.
And there is a dominant voice, there is also quite a bit of friendly and unfriendly critique
criticism toward this particular framing of global safety and world safety formation.
And I think going into these debates is actually quite telling as to how we define global
cities where we think that that criticism is justified, whereas perhaps less justified,
very beautiful with other kind of issues. And I'll be talking about four of those
points of criticism. One you could call the post-colonial critique, a social
constructivist critique, people that talk about state riskailing on the role of
the state and then finally some brilliant minds that had something to say
about financialization, okay, and that may alter our reading of what actually
happens in global cities. But before we start, my question to you, why are cities central
in the global economy and what would it mean to say that cities are actually powerful,
economically powerful? Take a minute, talk to your neighbor right-time few notes and think
about what your own should-could be. Go ahead.
(audience laughing)
[ Background noise ]
(people talking)
(people chattering)
[ Music ]
[ Background Sounds ]
Okay, first idea is the most creative walks.
Yeah, so how are cities central and global economy and why how can we see that you're powerful?
Is he burning hand?
Please, raise your hand.
I'm just celebrating focusing on either of us
to focus on.
And so basically, like in the papers
where we were kind of pointing out
that the [INAUDIBLE]
the congress centers of markets and of national companies.
And that's why it gets more and more forward sometimes
even more than the nation states are
motivated because they become a part of this international network
of those protocols they use.
And on the other hand, it's like most of the
effectiveness, most of the capital,
mostly not to be rural these days,
but also like function capital is placed in those big cities.
And that's why you have kind of helped this
when you call the migration of high-perfiting
those doors to go home, we'll see you.
- Okay, thank you.
So if something with these are the seats of corporate power
and perhaps it leads that goes around those corporations.
Okay, otherwise there's, yeah, the battery.
(mumbling)
[ Inaudible ]
Okay, so not just economic processes, but also the power of people and ideas culture's diversity.
Okay, all the ideas?
Yes.
This is built on the way, for example,
but flows, because this is the only thing
that we would do, that all these flows come together
in large cities, and then it becomes more than,
it goes from this large city to another large city,
a better, most better than the national level.
Instead of going from the large city
to the enterprise by venturing,
the most between cities and that's excellent.
And what is the substance of these flows?
It can be anything that can provide
to acknowledge to people who are in this community as well.
Okay, one of the things, yeah.
- I think about, I think that they,
I think government has been telling,
you know, they told me I like budget and make
rural, that affects, you know,
like, separate people, all of the people.
- It's kind of the Benjamin Barber argument,
what if Mayor Siru to the world,
world. There's a lot of context, you could say the main equipment centers are also important
political centers and the national economy and the national politics. And it seems to be also that
there are some kind of an extraterritorial or supernatural authority there as well.
Okay, thanks a lot for your answers. I think there's other options to talk about, but I think you
already got to some of the essential points. I'm going to show you a bit of a data list of figures,
But just to give a little bit of exhibits as to how important economic terms
then and perhaps also think that political terms, some world cities or world city regions or
global city regions are. This is a list and this is research by a certain man named Alombrecht
from the early North East. Nick compared the main, you could say leading metropolitan areas in
in Western Europe. So it's by no means an international comparison at the global scale.
But it's comparing Delta Metropolis. This is basically Amsterdam, Rotterdam, the Hague, etc.
The Flamish Diamond, which is roughly speaking Ghent Antwerp, Nervin Brussels,
which is kind of the economic heartland, if you still remember in Belgium,
Rairan-Rur area, which is Western Germany, kind of old industrial area, which is a large
conservation with a lot of industrial activity, or at least it used to be.
You, the France, this is basically Greater Paris and then Greater London is Greater London.
Okay? So comparing these five areas on a number of characteristics and you also see
the next figures, what he kind of finds is that these region city regions, much of
often areas are punching above their weight.
If you compare the share in a national surface,
so the size in terms of built up structure,
then the complete territory is actually quite small.
And you compare that to figures in population,
this largely outweigh the share in national territory.
And then when you look at the share of these areas in GDP,
which is kind of the value,
total value of all economic transactions,
which is a full measure in many ways,
but it's one way of starting to compare national economies.
We see that these areas actually
point about their rates.
So for instance, when you look at the Flemish diamond,
to take the Belgian example, 30% of national service,
52% of the population lives there,
but 63% of all economic activities actually
they place there.
More striking figures are even there for Paris.
London only 1% of the territory about, we
could say, 1/10 to 1/5 of the population,
but in terms of economic power,
especially in the case of Paris, it's way bigger than you
would in this.
So on large agglomeration and concentration,
of you could say economic transactions
that is taking place.
It also means that a lot of these places
tend to be richer than their hinterlands.
So it's kind of a runaway process at something
when these activities that are taking place there,
that generates more wealth per capita.
So this is GDP per head.
So it divides the value of economic activities
by the total population in that city.
So typically these places are richer than your pain
average and also compared to the rest of the encounter.
In that sense, when you look at Brussels,
Brussels is, you could say, the richest city in Belgium.
In principle, richer than the rest of Belgium.
But as we discussed last week, there's
a lot of this well actually in leaking to the periphery,
which is actually in flawless and mononia.
So it doesn't really show when you look at
at figures from the press of capital region,
but the same would actually apply.
Another way of looking at it is that,
and this was kind of referred to by
the concentration also of ideas innovation people.
It's very difficult to measure that.
One way of doing it is looking at patents, right?
Which is a kind of certification,
legal certification that something has been invented in one area or another,
a COVID vaccine, some kind of a chick, an algorithm, whatever.
And it has intellectual property on it.
So, and it can be commercialized in one way or not.
But it's a very, you could say, post hoc, exposed kind of measurement of places.
And there, there, there, a measure of innovation.
But it's a way to compare different areas.
What you see is that here it's a bit more mixed, a few, for instance, in France, you
see that Paris is actually outperforming the rest of the country.
This is far less the case in the UK, but it is the case in France's "The Flammish
Dark."
It's a bit more of a bit mixed picture, but we see that in general there's a tendency
to locate, you could say, innovative processes
as evidence to battles.
There's a lot of innovation that is not being measured here,
no social innovation, for instance.
It's really linked to technologies, high-end services
and these.
When you look at the structure of labor market,
you see that typically metropolitan areas
These also show a higher share of highly educated, highly educated work.
So substantially bigger, say in the delta metropolis,
it's 30% of highly educated people compared
to more or less 20% in the rest of the netlands.
And you can have a look at the other cities
to see how it fits.
So a different kind of labor market structure,
which tells us something about the kinds of activities
that are probably taking place there.
And another indicator there is when you look at
the employment figures across different kinds of sectors.
So there's the three sector model
that's agriculture industry and services.
And we see that obviously agriculture is very small,
but that's a constant everywhere,
but that there's a significant large share
and services in these metropolitan areas
than in the rest of the country.
So it's, these are places that are not marked
by industry, but by service economies.
So these are just a number of exhibits
that tell you something about the economic importance,
but it doesn't really tell you why these places are important.
It's just kind of a hint that something is going on.
And actually you already mentioned quite a few ideas
of how we can theorize the centrality
or at least conceptualize the centrality and power
in off cities in the global economy.
One of the main texts that is in the reader for this week
was this relatively hypothesis by John
to throw red it so you can just interrupt me
if you want to interject something.
But I just want to give you a number of notes
of my personal notes on what John Friedman was actually
writing about.
So a bit of context to this thesis or high hypothesis,
it's a hypothesis that groups a number of observations
from the 1980s tries to come up with a bit of a research
a gentle, that meets empirical testing.
Right?
But you need to understand a bit more of this context
of the 1980s.
People of my age have to have the habit of starting history
in the 1980s, because it was the decade they were born.
If I was 10 years older, I was probably
going to refer the 1970s.
But as a toddler, this was my context, right?
So you have to remember that 1980s was this emerging kind
idea that we would experience the end of the city. It was the rise of information and
communication technology on a very democratic large scale, not yet the internet, but that was
emerging in the 1990s and being democratized, cheap mass transportation became very cheap to fly around
the world, shipping became something that was very affordable and what we kind of see is a complete
restructuring of the economy, this kind of reaching its high day in the 1980s. It was already going
on in the 60s and 70s, but by the 1980s what became obvious is that we are in a new situation,
which we'd call the new international division of labor with new kinds of geographies of production,
much more to the global east and far less centered on the old industrial areas in,
say, European and America, what we've been discussing last week. And we see that this new
centrality of cities need theorize. If cities are not the places where a lot of goods are produced
and hence where you get some kind of a trade surplus when you start trading these commodities,
say textiles, etc. with other places in the world. What is then the kind of source of power
that cities actually hold? And what John Friedman comes up with is a look to answer this question.
We have to look at how cities are actually being inserted. And indeed an urban system that is not
only national but a separate national is actually a global urban system. You have to understand it
And most in the 1970s, a lot of the tradition in urban geography was looking at urban systems
in a very nationalist way.
It was a methodological nationalism.
It was looking at Argentina.
You have Buenos Aires, which was the central city.
And then you had a number of smaller towns.
But there was a huge concentration there.
And it left to some blind spot, as to what actually the position of these cities were
and processes that went beyond national economies.
And as these processes became ever more prominent,
it requested a huge--
you could say conceptual innovation that started
to emerge in 1970s and it is hence
the importance of freedom theorizing, conceptualizing
about world city.
So a global urban system and the kind of main underlying
hypothesis-- sorry, yes.
So the last part, what I was saying is that you have processes of globalization, which means
that the way that urban geographers were looking at urban systems, the king obsolete
in one way or another.
They were mostly linked to how economies were functioning at the national scale, looking
into, could say, where productivity is located, how could we
get flows organized, how capital flows, etc.
But as an increased share of the economy became, you could say, international or transnational.
Yes, the first thing that needed to happen was some kind of a conceptual framework or apparatus
that allowed to understand centrality at a different level.
But differently, instead of talking about national urban systems, people started talking
about global urban systems. But looking at centralities. So what
freedom kind of started to argue also on the basis of his reading of David
Harvey in 1970's Ammano Acastels is that we can only understand what goes on in
cities if we relate that to the position of these places in this global
urban system. So it's the kind of their function that they take in the global
economy or rather in this global urban system that will have to explain
what we find in certain places. Turn around on the other side of that corn is that this global
urban system or this global economy can also be embarked explained through what is going on in
P global cities or in this case world cities. We use the terminology. So, it's the processes that
emerge and are steered and controlled from these places that will have an impact on them.
larger macro processes in the global economy.
So that's kind of this dialectic global system,
macro level urban system world cities,
and they're kind of co-productive or co-constitative.
So one of the main excerpts are key observed excerpts there
from his world to the hypothesis, which is kind of very point
is key cities throughout the world are used
by global capital as basing points
in the spatial organization and articulation
of production and markets.
The resulting linkages make it possible to arrange a world
cities into a complex spatial hierarchy.
So it's about appreciating how indeed capital is--
and its actors--
is kind of basing itself in cities as they organize
global production and commercial activities.
So that was kind of the main focus.
And if we understand that, we will start explaining
why certain places are important and others less,
and why some cities are dependent on this process,
and why others are actually powerful.
So yeah, as I said, it's a period of view economic restructuring.
The laws of a lot of functions that were typically taking place
in cities, and I mean, John Friedman was writing
from Los Angeles, which was a very production-centered town
or city.
And it was losing functions.
What he observed was still a huge concentration
of skyscrapers, portraits, head porches.
But production had long left.
So this kind of conundrum was how do we explain that?
How do we make sense?
And indeed, as I've been explaining,
you had as the new international division of labor activities
that were being off-short to other parts of the globe.
And the emergence of a new set of enterprises, corporations,
multinational corporations, if you could say,
an American firm would be globalizing
or multinational corporations where it was actually kind of hard
to still identify to what extent
they were still connected with some territory.
Yes?
Let me say that the production activity has low left.
What is the expectation of these production activities?
I mean, it was the question when I was reading the text.
- Yeah, I mean, obviously it would depend on the city
that we're talking about, but think about what happens
in cities like Brussels, I mean textile industry,
all kinds of production facilities for consumer goods
that were initially
I mean, think about washing machines,
in editing that you use in the kitchen.
These were typically produced in the post-door era
in, you could say, the high income industrialized countries.
But because there was, you could say, pressure on the profitability
of these activities, because the wages were rather high.
These activities were offshore by a national,
emotional and not in national corporations.
And one of the main motivations was the search
for lower wages.
Or you could say, let's regulate labor markets
than what was occurring in the traditional industrial areas.
Yes?
[INAUDIBLE]
You make other countries, others.
and this bill is in just one thing,
all the other firms are the big things.
So, so they need to be for a different experience
and moving everything in the world
to have kind of summer.
- Yes, yeah, indeed.
I mean, and sometimes a little bit of confusion there
because people sometimes say, okay,
the industrial activities shifted to the periphery.
So I think in the first instance,
it's the initial periphery of the city.
I mean, the volume is suburbs.
But I think even, and it had something to do with,
you can say more,
the urban geographies, the land trends,
the ground prices in cities,
because it's, I mean, in large surfaces.
And it's easier to organize the rifries,
but at the later stage, they would basically,
I mean, these activities were either cut
because of investment and technology
and because you needed less jobs.
to make the same products and for there were shifted to other places around the globe.
So this is kind of what started to occur.
I mean some people even in some industries it was already in the 1950s.
This didn't happen over a day.
But it culminated if you were in the 70s and then the early 80s, which was a period of crisis in a lot of cities.
So, yeah, this new type of corporate,
actable to national corporations,
transnational corporations,
and how they organize global production networks.
So, a production network that used to be
kind of regionalized,
or nationalized in one way or another,
relied on local suppliers,
ended up being global.
I mean, if you have tried to order a bike in the past one year,
you know what it means to depend on
global supply chains or production networks, it's just an intensely fine-tuned process.
If anything goes wrong, I don't know, a tanker blocking the Suez Canal or something.
It's a precarious situation, but that's the kind of reality global supply chains.
And it's a part of the economy that's extremely dominated by these multinational corporations.
just some figures. I mean, there's a timeline there in 1960, there's about 66 billion.
What was kind of foreign direct investment, sort of for the technical terms here, but it means
direct investment in setting up factories. So you build a plant somewhere else,
so like Mercedes-Benz builds a plant in Korea or something, I'm not sure if they did.
are two-yota builds of plans in Texas.
In this kind of foreign direct investment logic,
M, it boom basically.
And you look at the figure of the 2016,
I could update that, I should probably do that.
About the third of the global economy
is actually equivalent to these,
and the I think, yes.
Foreign direct investment.
It's not too important,
but you just have to understand
that this is a measure of transnational flows.
So it's a measure of what part of the economy
is not local but is actually global or transnational.
And it relates to the investment activities
while large corporations to set up greenfield investments
as a skull.
So imagine a greenfield where you put into factory
those such as Brownfield redevelopment, which is an ex-site, which is then a refurbished
or one way or another.
Okay, so these are those kind of activities.
So 90% of this global economy of this FDI is concentrated in these multinational corporations
and slowly getting to my point here.
This is also why John Freeman was looking at multinational corporations and their geographies
to identify and conceptualize world cities.
So for jump treatment,
treatment at the cities where a lot of these headquarters
by these international corporations were located,
were, I mean, those were those cities
that they identified as world cities.
So since they saw important in the global ecosystem.
Okay.
So as he says, world cities are then to be sites
for command and control.
And he really saw these corporate headquarters
as the place is that controls and command it
in various ways, either to governance systems
by decision making, by the internal structure,
how global production was being organized.
And his kind of methodological hypothesis
was if we map these headquarter geographies,
we will actually be able to map the global urban system.
And we'll also understand the relation between different kind of cities as to who controls
what.
So it's a way to look at the power in this global urban network.
Some places are more dominant, hold more command and control functions than others.
Okay.
So I then came up with this map or cartogram or whatever you want to call it.
And yeah, it's certainly dated because Soviet Union is still on there and it's not
not part of this figure, which is also debatable.
Maybe there were not, I mean, say,
your American corporate headquarters there,
but for sure there were links,
even with the Soviet Union and capitalist countries, for sure.
But the whole point is that what Friedman actually does here
is translate the critical tradition of world systems theory,
which is a way to explain uneven development
in the global economy to an urban framework.
So it identifies three kind of areas, globalization,
arenas, if you will, one centered on Asia,
one on North America, one on Western Europe.
And typically, it finds a power balance
where you have powerful cities with a lot of corporate headquarters
in, you could say, the northern part of the hemisphere
and more, you could say, subordinate roles
for countries in the global south.
So when you, for instance, look at Northern America,
you have Los Angeles, Chicago, and New York,
which are identified as core cities with a lot of headquarters.
And they're kind of organizational networks
stretch to the global periphery.
So there's connections with the Rio de Janeiro, for instance,
Buenos Aires.
And these are kind of semi peripheral cities
who also hold command and control functions
and headquarters, they're oriented towards these centers
in the global north, could be that there are subsidiaries
of large corporations that are organized in such a concept.
So it's a way to explain how power is distributed
in this global urban system, and also starts
to explain why perhaps some places benefit more
from this integration in the global urban system than others.
So it would probably lead to an accumulation of wealth
in cities in the global north, to some extent,
also in the Senate periphery, think about Rio de Janeiro.
But at the same time, it would also work
as some kind of a funnel of siphon
off a siphon actually of surface toward the global north.
For instance, a US corporation producing stuff
energy, data, in part there will be benefits locally but at the same time there will also
be an extraction of surface value to the global market.
So it's also a way to understand, believe in this global economy.
I know it's a lot, sometimes a lot of economic terms but just to give you an idea, a
restructured global economy and the imaginary of a global urban system and city-staking
and different role in that on the basis of their command and control functions which
frequently defines as headquarters functions. So that's world cities. World cities,
corporate headquarters, command and control. I'm just giving you a number of key concepts there.
A second way of theorizing it is, and that's why I also have the other texts,
I could have given you the entire book, the Global City, but it would have taken you a week,
probably, or at least a few days to actually read it. It's still in flight to Dusso, but it's a kind of
shorter kind of version of the argument, which kind of explains what centrality is to
Saskia Susson. Okay, but I'll give you a bit more context by referring also to her book,
the global city. So one of, you could say, what has been
argued to be one of the seminal pieces talking about cities in
globalization, it starts kind of from the same rooms as
Richmond. I mean, it had been a very intense conversation in
the 1980s about what is going on with cities, they have
shifting functions, they're faced with the industrialization,
etc. There's also fiscal crisis of the local state. A lot of
cities were in trouble if you saw the movie.
Pixie Driver with the young Robert Teneiro,
he's driving around the relaxed New York in a city
neighborhoods are in trouble.
There's a lot of blight.
So cities were struggling to think about what
our functions could be and what is going on, especially
in 1970s, is a complete restructuring of these urban
economies.
So for Susson, it's less only about, you could say,
new command and control function about headquarters.
She looks at the complete restructuring of urban economies
from, you could say, manufacturing jobs
to service economies.
So we already saw that the majority of economic activities
in metropolitan areas are services.
But she particularly focuses on a particular subset
of these services, which equals advanced producer services.
So in the coming months, you will probably
start to hate the notion of advanced producer
services or being treated by it.
But it's a kind of--
I mean, you probably never heard about it.
A night of the day I, before I ever read about it.
But it tells it's kind of trying to capture those very
sophisticated, if you will, professional services
and service inputs for other firms.
So in themselves, they don't really produce much.
But still, their input is very important
for other corporations.
Think about financial services,
law, management, consultancy, accounting,
and auditing, advertising, et cetera, et cetera.
So these are not really producing things
that you can buy and consume at some point.
This is actually very knowledge intensive,
sometimes it's also called knowledge intensive business services,
which are kind of consumed as the art produced.
So legal advice is kind of produced in face-to-face meetings.
Think about a corporation that wants to set up a shop
or a plant or an investment in China, a European firm.
Probably you want to check, I think we are too, with a large international law firm that can give you a lot of experience as to what the regulations are for investment and other China.
you would need dedicated financial services.
How do you finance your international expansion?
You would need the advice of auditing firms accounting firms
because probably you want to attract some further funding
by issuing, I don't know, stocks above,
or something like that.
So financial investors would want to look at your activities.
Advertising, yes, how are you going to sell your cookies, cars, et cetera in China?
You need to know something about the local market or local markets, the sensitivities.
So yeah, you may want to adapt your practices there.
You may need to advise of management consultants because you may say that you want to globalize, but how are you going to
manages process, what kind of responsibilities do you give
to your managers in China?
Then they have the autonomy to take decisions.
Will you work with the central command structure?
How will you think about the profitability
of your activities, et cetera?
I mean, it's not a course in business studies here,
but just imagine as a firm that you want to globalize,
there's a lot of things that enter into the picture.
And probably these kinds of inputs that you need
are so specialized,
does it make sense to start producing them yourself?
So you just buy very specialized inputs.
You get in touch with lawyers, consultants, et cetera.
They would fly in and charge the hell out of you
and then run off and maybe a direct advice was, okay.
So it shifts to the service economy.
but with the globalization of production and globalization of markets and financial markets,
we see that certain service firms are becoming increasingly important.
And these are these advanced producer services, services given to producing firms.
And what she says is, look, instead of looking at headquarters of corporations,
we best look not at the multinationals themselves, but we best look at where these APS
firms are located.
And it's not just that they have kind of cold control
over global productions, networks, as you could
imagine, corporate headquarters where
CEO with a big cigar takes a decision of slashing
10,000 jobs in Belgium or something.
It's more dilute, diluted form of control,
which he talks about, is more about control capabilities.
is the assemblage, or we could say,
in the entire mixture of these kind of service economies
that allows firms that use these services
to exert control of the global scale.
So multinational corporations that
have a long story to start short depends
on yet another set of players, advancement use the services
to actually be able to manage global production.
So that's kind of her reading, not just corporate headquarters, but look at these notes
of advanced producers.
And the second important element that she links to that and will talk more about that
next week, and because it's a slightly different topic, is that this APS economy, this high
and service economies, also is an important engine in producing polarization, the other kind
of process that could use polarized cities, but an important driver according to Susson
is the highly remunerated salary stop in these kind of activities and this will have an
effect on this city. So it produces an outcome where you have high and low skilled labor forces
in APS or around APS.
And at some point, it could also even
lead to what she calls the peripheralization of the core.
So there will be a drive also to boost informal labor
markets in parts of the local economy.
But we'll talk more about that next thing.
So that's her idea about global cities.
And in the end, global cities
a site for the production of specialized services needed by complex organizations for running
a spatially diverse dispersed network of factors offices and services out there.
The production of financial innovations and the making of markets both central to the
internationalization expansion of the financial industry.
So for Sussan it's both about and you're free to refer to Sussan because it rhymes
with lessons as other students have done so before and make movies about.
So it's both about global production networks but also the running of global financial
markets.
So it's not just the production of goods themselves but also connecting to the world of
finance to get investment in these production.
So that's what SARS-CoS-CoS-CoS is talking about.
And the paradox that she sees is that as there's a kind of a dispersion of activities
at the same time there's a growing need for concentration.
The more dispersed global production networks,
the common financial markets,
the more the need for centralized control
or control capabilities over these markets.
So that's kind of the paradox of cities,
despite the internet, et cetera,
or virtualization of activities,
there's a continued role for face-to-face interaction
and interpretation in limited set of cities.
So why are APS located in a limited number of cities?
Well, she talks about different kinds of thought dependence.
So it means that one situation establishes itself
is kind of the whole kinds of self-reinforcing mechanisms.
So if there's a concentration, there's a deep market
and services.
So if you go to London, for instance, you're
quite sure that you will find everything.
If you have these kind of services,
some kind of a labor market culture
where we'll emerge around that.
You'll find a specialized labor there.
And yeah, in a lot of world and global cities think about New York
or London, some kind of a Yup culture,
young urban professional culture,
has emerged within these kinds of APS firms.
There's also a lot of synergies between these firms
and I'll tell you a little bit more about that.
So also these different KBS firms work together
as they service their clients.
And what is even more striking is that these APS firms
in and of themselves also become global corporations.
So they also set up international networks
either to follow their clients
or to remain credible as a global, as a vehicle act.
So a number of reasons why this kind of geography reproduces itself and is increasingly anchored
in a number and a limited number of global cities.
So my barracks, for my dear colleague from the Metu-Yehan Kickingen, who did a kind of
nice set of maps on law firms and Brussels.
It's kind of interesting to see that the concentration in global cities, you could say,
when at the more abstract level also translate into clusters
at the metropolitan level.
And that tells us something about, you can say,
the more micro-sociologies and geographies
of these kind of professional serves.
So what you see is on the left-hand side, the law firms.
The big picture of foreign law firms, the smaller insect
map is Belt and Ferns, the number of commonalities
avenue in these which is kind of center of a very rich neighborhoods or set of neighborhoods
and some Brussels as a location of boats. I think Belgian,
a group of people. I love from the local garden offer. What is foreign law firms or what
is special? For the foreign law firms they're very much concentrated around the EU district.
Okay, so a lot of activities
I'd have something to do with the client or clients
that are located there, which is either directly
European Commission or firms that want to not be
European Commission.
And this is kind of a process that we'll talk a bit more
when we do the tour and Brussels in the end of next week.
So micro geographies are also produced micro clusters
produced at the urban level.
The same is Vincent Stu in London.
Some great work by Cook at all.
Not Captain Cook, but another cook.
So we cook top this figure.
Obviously what you see there is a city of London,
which is also a very particular jurisdiction
in and of itself.
It has some kind of an exceptional room
that doesn't follow the regulations of, you could say,
the continent in this case of the UK and enough itself.
It's governed in a very weird way.
I never recall how exactly.
I don't know if you can make sure that the bridge is themselves.
But it's kind of a self-port,
I mean, the self-regulate itself,
governed jurisdiction on the island,
where corporations also have a large say in.
So within the limits of the long run, you find particular regulations there.
That's why the stock exchanges located there.
And all the financial institutions are located around.
And then besides that, the specialized district, the legal district, etc.
So the tendency of seeking proximity is also evident there.
A bit more on this, because of ABS complex, as I said, these firms also
interacted one another. So this is some work we did in Brussels. We took a corporate survey
aimed at APS professionals so we sent the survey around with with legal experts, expert,
ICT experts, etcetera, bankers and they kind of listed how they interacted with other APS firms
either in their daily practice for themselves or as they were giving service to their customs.
Okay, and what you find is actually quite a bit of interaction with sector itself.
And also particularly between sectors in law and finance, law,
accounts, and law, and accounts in financial services.
So just imagine as a corporation, what often happens is that when you issue some kind of financial
of product, think about a share or something
or you want to go for a loan.
Namely the financial institution, we need a law firm.
That needs to kind of come up with the prospectus
or check the prospectus that is made by financial institutions,
auditors and accountants that have a look at it.
So this is a kind of connected thing to financial markets.
What we also found is quite some interaction
between ICT and financial services.
This has something to do with,
you can say the virtualization of finance
that is currently going on.
So quite a bit of interdependencies
between different sectors will also explain
why does a need for proximity?
Yes, that's a question.
That's a very good question.
What do I remember from these percentages?
I think, all right.
So I think that it's standardized to the,
you could say the largest link.
So we looked at, you could say the intensity of interactions.
And we found that within financial services,
this has the strongest link.
So it's a relative scale.
So that's the strongest link.
It's 100%.
And then when you for instance look at the duration
between law and financial services,
the strength of the time between law and finance is only half of the kind of relations
within the finance itself.
It was measured in a different way.
It's measured by frequency.
So on a regular basis, how much do you hire advice in, you could say, "No, it's
or et cetera.
But there's other ways of measuring that for sure.
So it's one way of doing that.
So yes, this kind of gravitational pull towards other actors
in this APS complex explains kind of the reproduction
of global cities.
And another one was indeed this globalization
of strategies of APS firms themselves.
So they're both clustered and they're
globalized at the same time, deloed--
well, I mean, it's part of its branding process.
HSBC is the same thing.
So it's playing on both being global and tapping
into local knowledge.
You may think about that what we want,
but it's certainly part of their corporate strategy,
the geographical strategy, et cetera.
Yes?
OK.
- I think that's the public early days,
but I think that's what we have all about,
how open and forward to performance
that's been happening.
- No, I was taking care of my children.
But I think that's a good point.
I mean, I think for sure, there has been a tremendous impact
on business travel.
But it's also kind of a long discussion
as to what extent you need business travel
these are the video conferencing and all the kinds of things.
So there's already quite a bit of research in there.
There's also, you can say, more ethnographic approaches
that are kind of questioning the actual day-to-day
relevance of having a global network.
But definitely, artists offices really being used,
or I think they need there to have an address
and populate websites.
And then you may actually find that it's much more
concentrated within a number of global cities
despite having a very global network.
And it could be other ways of organizing yourself.
I haven't done very clusters or meetings or conferences
to make things work.
That there's also, and we'll read a bit about that,
practice of the governments of people that are based
in London, that are then two years based in Singapore.
So there are a lot of kind of strategies.
But yeah, the main kind of question in the DB is COVID.
Now the final proof that there's an end to the city,
I think that's hugely overblown.
And I think there's quite a bit of reasons
about the knowledge and density of certain practices
that explains why face-to-face interaction will prevail.
Just as when you think about teaching,
There's hopefully some added value to face the face teaching
overlooking at a screen.
And it has something to do with the interpretation
of information and is being shared about how
grounding processes work.
We think the same about certain concepts, et cetera.
And if you don't do this face-to-face,
you just miss out on this micro feedback loop.
If this would be online, I wouldn't see
nodding or frowning, so I would be in trouble sometimes.
But I think it's clearly, it's a very important question.
There will probably be a more strategic use of these sites,
and there will also be a more selective use
of face inflection, which would, I'm ultimately also
input, input, APS activities, and your geographies.
But it won't do a dissolution, I think, personally.
I see no theoretical reasons why that should be obsolete.
But it's research that could be done.
I mean, there's a whole class of people, digital nomads.
These are more, you could say, self-employed.
They don't depend on other inputs.
And their production process think about setting up
a website or something.
You can just go to Bali and do that from there.
But even there you see the emergence of temporary clusters,
other digital nomads that are in Bali,
discuss stuff, et cetera, et cetera.
So I think even there is a social aspect to that.
And you get the return of centrality,
even where you don't expect it.
And it seems to be something that is related to the fact
that we're talking about cognitive cultural capitalism.
And that's an excellent bridge to what Alan Scott is talking about
in his version of Global Siki regions.
So we talked about world cities, or the headquarters
Susson talks about global cities.
You look into a wider complex of these advanced services
that sit around corporations.
And then Alan Scott says, well, you and your world
and global cities have to explain something like this,
which is a much larger coloration, which is urban to some extent,
which depends here on San Francisco,
and it's easy to notice.
But how do you make sense of this wider San Francisco Bay area
with a lot of, you could say, centrality,
but it's not necessarily connected
to core metropolitan areas.
So what kind of--
and Scott is talking about it says, yes,
very nice that we talk about this classic.
world and global cities when you look for South Africa, South Asia, South Asia,
North New York, London, Tokyo, later on Chicago, and meet metropolitan areas.
But there's other kind of structures, morphological structures,
polycentric regions that do not necessarily fit the definition that South
assassin or John Friedman is talking about. And it also links a little bit to what we discussed
last week. How the city looks like or where the urban is can actually spill over metropolitan
areas. Okay. So clearly places like Silicon Valley. They're not dependent on the poor urban area
per se, but they're also kind of an example of the need for proximity in high-end advanced
sectors. So what our consensus is that, yes, something is right, but the kind of wider
process that is going on is a process towards centrality in knowledge-intensive
activities. And this pertains to APS firms that are located and you can see the core
metropolitan areas, but it also applies to high-tech firms, the GAFAS platform corporations,
etc, etc, all these kind of innovations that came out of sort of conf
of the confederate since, or when you look at the per-refrigerate delta, which is a kind of much more
of all-centric production area in the southeast of China. It's also a form of centrality,
where you have some metropolitan areas or metropolitan course, but it also goes
beyond there. So what interests our Scott is more, yeah, this driver of centrality, built
APS themselves. And he says, look, this centrality that SARS-CoS-SUSAN finds is actually part and
part of a wider shift towards cognitive cultural captions. Right? So CCC and it means that
a lot of economic activities, crucially depends on knowledge inputs.
And types of knowledge that are not generic,
not standardized, that are not easily appreciable
at a distance.
No, you need interpretation, dialogue with clients,
dialogue with other colleagues to make
sense of what is going on, because it's a very complex matter.
need to make sense of the situation collectively,
and hence there's a drive for proximity there.
Okay?
And this applies to an increased part of the economy,
which also means that it's a goes way beyond
how it produces services.
So, and the spatial form it takes is one of global city regions.
So you have more,
pulling more frequency,
polycentric kind of structure.
And his kind of metagography, if you will,
is a world of global city regions,
that has kind of interconnection, interconnected
and blazer role in these global production
networks in global markets.
Yes.
Hi, can you really understand my news
about how we can from China to India or APS?
Yeah.
Because as I understand that, the [INAUDIBLE]
And this need is kind of connection to this ABS that are all this service has connected to.
Well, the point by Scott is that, yes, an ABS law firm's fund, etc.
There's a clear need for proximity to the reasons that we've been discussing,
but there's also a place to other parts of the economy.
Think about high-tech, think about education, you know, whatever.
And these are also prone to these agglomeration dynamics.
And that is because increasingly the production process
is knowledge intensive.
Just compared to, it's a 50 years ago,
it would have been a very standardized process
just make 1,000 cars per week.
This is becoming increasingly customized.
It's much more about prototyping,
it's much more about failure in particular cars.
I mean, I don't know anything about cars,
but I'm stuck with cars.
So it's much, much more just in time delivery,
it's much more tailored rather than mass production.
That used to be the case in the 50s, 60s, 70s,
and this has shifted.
Roughly in the 1980s,
where it was more about flexible production systems,
where you could say the connection with suppliers,
but also customers who are in the game much more important.
So it's a kind of broad scale restructuring of the economy.
So also explains why proximity matters,
not only in each of those that you serve,
but more broadly to the economy.
- But I don't understand what drives this company
to gather instead of providing for example.
- Okay, well, I have a whole lecture on that
and I can look at the lessons, right?
But I mean, and part of the story is you could say
the contemporary benefits of economic agglomeration,
which has something to do with what economic geographer
calls the externalities.
By being there, you get certain benefits
that you wouldn't get if you're not there,
stepping into high-scale labor,
high-scale labor, for instance,
and venture capitalists, et cetera, et cetera.
But there's a lot of what the whole part of the penancies as well.
And we do look at the story of Silicon Valley.
used to be a lot of government investment there.
Think US military and the semiconductor business
making chips and those kind of things
was huge funded by the federal government
in NASA, DARPA and all kind of ministerial defense.
And a lot of these innovations
were then later on commercialized by private players
who then used these technologies to build their own platforms.
And this great work by my Anna Madzukata, for instance,
through with great economists, says,
well, if you look at your iPad, almost every critical element
there piece of technology can be related back
to some kind of federal investment, et cetera, et cetera.
So which brings them to an argument about,
is it really private innovation that we're talking about,
or does it have something to do with the sustained investment
by public authorities in these kinds of investments?
The same is true for big pharma, for instance.
It's even first easy to come up with the new vaccines,
and these are then commercialized by Pfizer, et cetera.
So it's a very complex story, and no clear answer
is a field of its own.
But what we need to understand is that this proximity
and the centrality goes beyond cities themselves.
OK, so it's much more prevailing process.
But, Phil, I mean, the point being is that at some point
APS firms, even in these global city regions,
they would still have some kind of a role
to play as connectors, think about Silicon Valley firms
that come up with new technologies,
or that one can make a profit of these new innovations.
They would have to be kind of certified back then that their intellectual property would be
tetanus probably very likely that would be San Francisco based law firms that would then
specialize.
Okay.
All right.
Yeah.
[INAUDIBLE]
Well, I mean, you now, this kind of--
these are the debates.
I'm just rehearsing the date of the 1980s, 90s.
Slow to get into the Northeast.
We'll move through that throughout the lecture.
But this mainly tries to capture what went on in the 1980s
and what was the starting point, if you will,
or the theorizing of world and global cities.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah.
Well, there, so the question is,
do I extend as the Rust Belt at Global City?
I don't think, I mean, it will.
Alice Scott would really see that as a global city region,
because it's mostly, you could say,
a remnants of an older process of industrialization,
which was much more focused on mass production.
So think about fact-reasoned Pittsburgh, Detroit,
et cetera, et cetera.
the Ford factory. And this was kind of in the history of the US. It was a kind of process
of industrialization that was finalizing again. But it's returning since the 60s, 70s.
And then you had a switch to the some belt states. A lot of production, especially in the
car industry, was taken over by Japanese investments. And a lot of states were the labor
writes were less protected. So I mean the difference would be to what it's
I mean it's just one example but a question would be to what extent Duke in
this day in age, knowledge and tactic, intensive production activities are
over at the state place in the Rust Belt, think to some extent this is the case
but it wouldn't be an leading example.
I don't want to be exclusive.
I think it could be visualized as such,
but it would be more of an empirical question
to what extent is actually taking place.
Whether it's just a morphology of old industrial area,
like the rural area,
or whether there's some kind of integrated region,
which you do see in Silicon Valley
because it's kind of organized about technology.
We could perhaps argue that it used to be a global city region of yesterday year, but perhaps the globalization was less advanced there and then or at least it would be with the different.
Okay, just to say there's different conceptualization,
that's why to capture function with also the morphology of these places.
I think it's something to reflect on and comparing where you get.
Yeah, I think in the interest of time,
I will have to move on because I'm using a lot of words.
I think it's important that things are clear.
Second of all, and I might speed up a little bit,
I want to give you a methodological example of how people actually dealt with this conceptual apparatus
of world and global cities and global city regions to measure these processes or empirically study these processes.
So this is the work by the globalization and world cities research network.
And it basically starts with whatever of questions I mean.
When you look at some of these claims,
I mean, it's one thing to say, yeah,
we have the acknowledge growth city formation process
of global city formation process,
or to say that interurban connections are already important.
And actually, when you start diving into this,
you quickly run into trouble.
And this is actually something that was kind of noted
already in the '90s, so a very long time ago,
but I want to give you the entire development of the agenda.
That is actually quite a few insight into world city network
information.
So we had a number of case studies in the '80s and '90s,
especially with Soskea Sosen, all particular set of cities,
long the New York et cetera, et cetera.
There was all kinds of hypotheses and claims
about the insertion in a global urban system.
But actually, invariably, there was very little insight
into this.
So what connects cities, how central was cities
in these urban systems?
It was kind of very much an ad hoc answer that you get
to the extent that generally short sets,
there's even a dirty little secret
in world cities research.
Actually, empirically, there's very little
on the actual connections being made between cities.
So we don't really know a lot about this.
And this is something that kind of a research gap
to use new liberals,
academic speak,
that globalization and world cities
with search networks should answer.
And there was a number of ways of trying to do with that.
People tried to work with secondary data in 1990s
of starting 1990s, thinking about for instance, yeah,
looking at the flows of airline passengers.
So how are cities connected by airlines?
And this is gave rise to these kind of hyperb
type of research that shares you.
It's a raw city network of the basis of airline flows.
Any idea whether this is a viable method.
And we measure the centrality of cities in the global economy
by using air life flows.
Well.
[INAUDIBLE]
All right.
Yeah, so major airports are not necessarily in closed cities.
Yeah? Other ideas? Yeah?
I'm going to find any of that as well.
Oh, okay. Other kinds of sources to be used.
Okay. So the flow of bitcoins.
Okay. Yeah.
I mean, more particularly with these kind of data on airline flows, other ideas?
Yes.
This is also a commercial model for a company
where you hear, absolutely.
- You're very, very bad at the department.
- Absolutely, yeah, all right, yes.
(muffled speaking)
- That's exactly the same.
I mean, it's debatable.
I mean, are you measuring economic importance
or are you measuring economic control?
- Yeah.
[ Inaudible ]
>> Yeah, that was also the kind of, yeah, there's a hub and spoke system.
People write about papers flying where you don't want to go.
So it doesn't really connect.
I mean, there's a lot of people in the break.
Yeah, I think it's not necessarily to do anything there.
Yeah. And you'll write this.
[INAUDIBLE]
Yeah, yes, yes, absolutely.
Yeah, OK.
So I mean, at first sight, you can do something
because it's a kind of intuitive picture here,
especially when you look at the front top of the hierarchy.
So you find that New York and London is actually there.
But then you quite quickly go into all kinds of anomalies.
Yeah, these hub airports that are not necessarily relevant.
There is destinations which tell us something about economic importance,
but not necessarily about the importance in terms of controlling the global economy,
which is kind of a different kind of process.
Yeah, I was going to say something else about that, but it's, yeah, I forgot about it.
Yeah, so we can also think about new data collections.
And so your bitcoins is one brain.
And I want to pick your brain a little bit more on that.
But before that, I mean, just saying that one
of the big struggles in the 1990s that research
is where researchers work on front with.
And this is still the case today.
And you'll probably notice in some of your courses
is that a lot of the statistics are collected
at the state level and not necessarily
at the urban level.
And Peter Taylor, the by now emeritus professor
that founded the globalization and multidisciplinary
network always referred to this notion of state
districts.
It connected to statistics and indicators
that were collected by the national state
to measure the national economy, et cetera, et cetera.
And at some point, the centrality of cities,
in economic process, has only creeped in slightly.
So we have sometimes at the national level
indicate about cities, but then intercity connections
and flows, it's very hard.
Think about trade flows, for instance,
(speaking in foreign language)
It's between national economies,
but if we have to assume them probably,
the major metropolitan areas will be more tight
in this growth and others.
Yes.
(mumbles)
But the previous slide,
in the beginning African-
[INAUDIBLE]
Sorry.
Yeah.
We have a lot of resource
extraction happening in these places.
No, but these--
I mean, it's always a question.
I will return to that.
The power of representation.
This is the result of where you cut off the list at some point.
So it's the most connected places
It's just a sense of passenger flows.
But there's another realizer on upgrading that.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, yeah.
Absolutely.
How do you get the rear screw?
Well, you can turn it around, and you can focus on Africa.
African cities and how they're connected in global, global
airline afterwards.
So you can do some kind of if you will, but not the analysis.
It's actually something that we did that look at the
evolution of African cities globally.
airline networks, and it could tell you, give you a hint about how these places are
according to nationalizing globalizing through their airline networks, which you can then
could still be a very rough figure.
And it would also, as we found, capture all kinds of processes, the liberalization of the
airline industry in Africa, rather than the increasing importance of some cities in the global
So yeah, just to give you an idea of what is the trouble when you start looking for
your kind of data, you perhaps can think a little bit about what other kinds of approximations
you could use.
And that was exactly kind of a conundrum or thing that people were chewing on in the 1990s
and as it became evident at some kind of new metajography was needed.
I'm using metagography in a sense that it refers to
associate spatial structure, if you will,
it helps to make sense of the world.
So it's a geography that explains how processes work.
Like the nation states tells us something
about what extent
either sectarian politics is able to territorialize,
need to make it difficult. Whereas perhaps the world city network tries to capture the
integrated fashion of economic processes. And this is actually what Manuel Castelles was
writing about in the 1990s when we were talking about this space of flows which he put into
opposition with the space of places. So he said, well, we have this traditional view of the world
as a mosaic of territorial states which are kind of yeah if you put them together you get the
world map but there's another kind of geography that is out there which is discontinuous so it's
kind of it's another continuous space these are kind of islands if you will that are connected
to flows of goods, people, money, knowledge etc etc so this is kind of character
rising the space of flow.
And it's kind of, it's a socialization process,
a sociologist.
So it's a society emerging on that.
And it was kind of kind of visionary.
But I, he intended to be visionary in a sense
that this would be the norm.
So we would be the common network society.
We can wonder about that.
But what is kind of still relevant, I think,
is that there's a tension between these spaces of flows.
So these islands of connected urban areas,
which is to some degree detached from a mosaic of city stance.
And there's all kinds of oppositions between that.
If you look at the election map in the UK,
none of the election map, the referendum map.
And you look at the leaf or remain float,
it was clear that London wanted to stay in,
which tells us something about the importance
of being remaining connected to,
we'd say other financial centers
on the European continent.
The rest of Britain, I mean, summarizing now,
was against that,
which shows that there's a disconnect in the daily lives
of people to the interest of a city.
I'm not saying that the leaf campaign
actually connected to the real needs of Brits,
but that's another kind of discussion, okay?
So this space of flows served as a kind of new metagogy
which then was an impetus to start collecting new data,
which ultimately brings me to the raw curiosity
and I'll try to be as brief as possible in the interest of time.
It's also not something that you need to...
No, you don't study this by heart,
but it's a way to kind of appreciate a certain methodology.
So just go to this website once, at least.
It's hosted by Lovedra University in East England
and then the Midlands.
It's a very interesting source for urban level case studies
on connectivity between cities.
It can also use for other courses, I think,
of the course by bus, for instance.
So it's quite an inventory of nice case
that is there.
So what's the starting point of this, you can say,
project by globalization and what's
the research network was, is let's take APS firms
as the clearest indicator species of this new space of flows.
So there's a new space of flows that
characterize how the global economy and global society works.
And as we read Castell's Sosen, it's very likely
that if we use these corporations,
we'll be able to indicate a command and control functions
of cities.
So the starting point are the geographies of APS firms
that tell us something about world and global cities.
The reason is, as I explained earlier,
these APS firms are in and of themselves.
International players, they have a global city geography,
if you will, so it makes sense to start looking
And the idea is that you can actually build a model on the basis of these APS
geographies and the model is based on the co-presence, the shared presence of
APS firms in multiple cities.
Summarized is one firm in Brussels and London.
It will make connection between these two cities and we can assume that it will
will be so kind of flow of probably emails, telephone calls, ideas, there will be
second-man's, people will travel between these officers, money will flow between
these officers, etc. So the shared presence of APS firm in multiple cities, so
one firm being located in multiple cities. So in a three-step spirit with any
model you need to specify it, then you can measure it, it's filling it to a data,
And then hopefully something comes out of this model.
Okay?
So, yeah, how does GOC solve it?
So, just as a random example,
a number of global or rural cities,
New York, London, Brussels, Kuala Lumpur,
and these are kind of contained spaces with a number of firms in there.
And these are APS firms.
And so there's the mobile, this thing, cities,
and they host APS firms.
Some of these firms are actually the same, okay?
So we have by now transformed corporations
such as Arthur Anderson, resident bank,
Kiffin Chan, the law firm,
Booth, Allen, Hamilton, noise,
that's insurance company.
But just to give you some questions.
So how is it specified?
What does God do?
It says, well, oh, there's a firm here
in London or Brussels, how important is this firm actually?
Okay, so you try to measure this in an objective,
or at least standardize way so that you make the same
per every time, or that you write every time.
So you say, okay, for this one office in Brussels
by Barclays or something or HSBC, a bank,
how important is it?
And we use a very standard scale, zero to five,
no offense are easy, you give it a zero.
Oh, it's the global headquarters, that is a fine, okay?
It's the only agency, but it would be, I don't know,
KBC or something like that, large belting back, okay?
And then there's a whole range in between.
A typical office would be two,
maybe a regional headquarters, and there's a lot of those
and Brussels that actually control European activities
would be a three or four.
So this is kind of the idea.
There's a hierarchy in office functions
and we can measure this in a standardized way.
If you have service values,
you can also imagine what the importance of the connection
between two offices would be.
So a very important office and Brussels,
and a very important office in London
would probably generate more traffic in terms of emails
some phone calls, which is then again a proxy
for, you could say, the importance of the activities
in global command language.
So it's basically calculating the intercity relation
the R value there by multiplying the service values.
And so very basic, so you have a very important time
is a very important one, if you are very strong relation
between these two places.
OK.
I'm going to get like that.
Can I imagine the connection?
So they took a line, the more important connection
between these kind of offices.
And you can populate a complete matrix with that.
You can do that in the filter until you drop that,
or you don't have the energy to look for more information
on office networks.
So this is kind of the basic one.
And it allows you to do, for instance,
this guy thinks that there's three cities in this very short list
New York Singapore and the app work.
And they have these different front
and it gets from ABC and D.
And we can could imagine a novel where you say, okay.
And for a global office in New York,
a very important office,
or a regular office in Singapore,
and a regular office in
and it would be a bit different for BC and D.
So just one example, I'll see there.
What you can then do is start to measure the connectivity
of cities.
Thus far we've been talking about first
and what the importance of the city has for a firm.
You can also think about what is now
the strength of a city's connection based
on the presence of first.
What you do is you basically summarize all these different types between cities for one
one six.
It sounds a bit complex but it's really easy.
So what you would do is think about the connection between different cities on the base
of the corporate networks.
So think about five times two plus five times two would be the connectivity generated
by first-grown, so you can be four times two.
Your, you'll be five times one.
And in this step, I think I was five.
And in some, you would get a figure of 40.
It's purely irrelevant example,
but it would give you the highest connectivity
in this model, right?
And then for the other kind of cities,
we could do similar exercises,
and for it would be generating
activities for a and even just a low presence on its front. But you would generate
someone activity for eight and for a. And also summarize that. And what you could
also do is express this as a proportion of most connected city in this tiny
example of New York. And you would get to say, well, enter is four times
connected as well as New York. So New York is is our leading
We'll sit here, then we have Singapore and then Andrew.
So a very, very small example to tell you how the structure is.
Service values, thinking about connections between cities,
and then summarizing these connections.
And that gives us an overall view of the connectivity of the city in the world,
sitting there.
So we have specified the model.
And then you can start measuring it and filling it with data.
And how has GOC done this?
Well, specification obviously refers to the APS firms.
And this kind of nice is that this measurement
has occurred several times since, I think, 2,000,
but every time in the same way.
So it kind of definitions of categories
of these kind of APS sectors has been in the same,
and has been numerous kind of reiterations
of these measures.
So five sectors are connected to SELSA's interpretation.
Can't see advertising, financial services, insurance,
law, management, and so forth.
Basically, what God does is the leading firms, 175 firms,
based on Forbes and other kinds of corporate lists,
that tells something about turnover, the size of these folks, et cetera, et cetera, are
kind of selected.
And then what is also done is, yeah, you could do this with an infinite number of cities.
Well, not infinite, but a very large list of cities.
But to avoid a bit of, I don't know, it's not biased, but to get a manageable data set,
You could say the largest cities or what we know from certain countries as economically
and important cities are selected in this list.
So it's not a purely inductive exercise.
It's kind of an informed decision to include some cities and other products.
So all the firms, a lot of cities, and then on the basis of information that we can find
on corporate websites, we made a decision as to how important offices are. And then you
can basically start filling the entire matrix. So just an example to share how this works.
I mean, you think about just look at the website, can be quite tough, but you can actually
hold all of these websites, find very detailed information at the address level of these
offices and all of these corporations are very proud that they're located in the
meeting world city is kind of a brand new so quite often you can fly down yes
yes you avoid the deforestation that's a very good idea
I think yeah I'm not sure whether it's going to take away all the noise that
that's what you're internet. So yeah, so it's a really accessible source of information,
but obviously it's also a bit of a guesswork and you need to come up with some kind of
interpretive guide to meet these websites and to make decisions as to how you will
give attached value to these phrases. Okay, just one, and then you can build these kind of
matrices. So all of them are all of countries, a lot of cities. And then you can start applying
that problem. Okay, so it's an approximation of the importance of cities in these corporate networks,
and it has the level of kind of sustained analysis or modeling of these interactions on that
basis. And then maybe already have seen these kind of maps. So a lot of world-saving network research
then start to look into the actual geographies that are being produced. So this is some research
from a while ago. It just shows the absolute levels of connectivity, so the global network connectivity,
and the darker pieces are the most connected places and then the lower the light colors by the
less one place. So it gives you an idea. Take a good look at this map. What you learn from that
or what you find striking anything striking here. Does it confirm what you thought? You learned
Can you think? Yeah? No? Yes? I don't really get a comment on the situation. I said, "If I do this, or if you do this, the word happens. There are not a few routines in this." So, where there's so many neuroships. If you think that you said that you can kind of think of the largest in these things, you do a piece of permanent largest in the number of populations.
I know.
No.
So, but it's a list.
So there's a number of criteria.
I mean, population is one, but it's also in certain countries.
I mean, it's also looking for its business, its written down economic importance.
So in Belgium, it would also include these entities, which is absolutely not a two million
in happen in the city so but we know it has important opportunities.
Now just to be clear, these are not 525 cities,
but it's a selection I think it's 123.
So it's focusing on the most important cities,
which as a result, apparently gifts,
a geography that is skewed towards,
it's a Northern America Western Europe
and then has a bit of presence elsewhere.
>> Yeah. >> I'm just thinking, like, this thing is like, about 50, just, yeah, I think, like, it's like that.
Like, it's like a whole life, like, you know, in relationship that a global that type of business.
Like, I don't know if you have a good case. >> Yeah, absolutely.
>> You know, that's a good case. >> For making sense, you know, which I found in a bit,
a lot lower probably not, but the money, but like, how many people, you know,
>> I agree 300%.
So the question is, does this represent cities and globalization or does it represent
the location strategies of APS first?
And to what extent is this the same?
So the question is to what extent do you go along and
claim that it gets from foreign indicators species of commandment control. I think to some extent
this is the case but there's clearly other processes but I think and that's something that we'll
return to later on. We have to I think another key distinguish between say more economic drug
a few readings whereas there's also more urban studies critiques some people say that you're not
capturing globalization here. And this whole process we should look at?
Yes, that's true. But it doesn't discredit one particular reading or one particular focus on the
process, as long as we're clear about what it is that measures and what it is it has. But I
completely example that remitances, I'll return to that in a second, is very appropriate.
So this we have to be careful that we were not switched to some kind of imperial
act here to try to claim that one process dominates something, but it was a specific
equation. Same here is the same period that's a kind of comparison between two periods in time.
I mean there was a data collection that allows analysis in 2000 and I'm just before the crisis
in 2008, I mean the previous crisis, we get them all.
So comparing the structure of the world city network,
which is effectively on the aggregate level,
the structure of corporate strategies and the interpretive fees.
And I mean it's kind of interesting to see that even before
the Euro-American or North Atlantic financial crisis,
there was already a shift going on in terms of strategic importance
of cities in the east, and I mean both in eastern Europe,
and the global east, so I'm talking about Chinese cities,
for instance, so if regions were interested in secular shifts
within the structure of the world economy,
it shows that it's also reflected in the corporate geographies
of these ATS firms, which knowing that they're
important inputs for global corporations
There's something about developments on these cities
in how capital circulates on the global scale.
So it tells us something that everything,
and that's also why Rob uses heuristic.
And there's some modesty connected to that.
Heuristic is a kind of a starting point.
As a searching device, where he's like,
oh, what the hell is going on in, let's say, lightly?
It's dark reds.
What could be the process going on?
How does it explain that-- how do you explain that it's
one of the worst performers, if you will,
and it was so much connectivity,
whereas it's a very important transit
hub between that in America and a northern America?
Is why is it losing its functions?
Is it because Latin America is becoming
less important for northern American capital?
what could be going on there?
I mean, you can think about numerous other examples there.
And it should be, I think, and that's
how I personally use it, the starting point for analysis.
And a difference set to a different set of methods.
You could do a case study, follow the thing,
follow your nose, and try to problematize
these kinds of findings.
But it's a way to refer to her back to that.
And it gives you-- that's, I think, he added value,
some kind of standardized overview.
There's a lot of things that we can say about that. I really need to press on because
it's taking a bit more time than expected. Are you still okay to proceed? I promise that
we won't take 25 minutes but maybe 20 minutes if I'm lucky?
Is that okay or do you want to break? Why is this going to be there?
Yes you can. Yeah, is there a collective need for a restroom break?
Is that a yes hand? Yeah, two minutes because we really because we can't take too much time.
So if you project that in 20 minutes, your bladder will break.
Go now.
(audience chatter)
(crowd chattering)
[ Background Sounds ]
(people chattering)
(people talking)
(audience chattering)
[ Inaudible ]
(audience laughing)
(audience chattering)
(people chattering)
(audience laughing)
(audience chattering)
(people chattering)
(people talking)
(audience chattering)
[ Inaudible ]
(inaudible)
(audience chattering)
(audience laughing)
(audience member speaking)
[laughter]
(audience chatter)
[ Inaudible ]
[ Background Sounds ]
[inaudible]
(audience chattering)
[ Music ]
Thank you.
We can see.
Please thank your seats.
Yeah.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
Please thank your seats.
Yeah.
So yeah, this one's in that view of breach should appreciate by now a long tradition of
rural and global cities research, then this kind of severity informed the general by
core.
But at some point, and especially the early technologies, there was a danger that, or at
least this recent agenda was, was in terms of this, you could say dominant or hedge
of monitoring the wind in urban studies or for citizens in global
ization. And as such, it's also raised quite a bit of criticism. And I think it's debatable
to what extent this is just quite some points of this. Certainly as other points, I think
I'm personally, but I'm also kind of involved in these debates a bit more in the wild.
I'll just take you through them. And I hope to do so within the next 20 minutes.
Right, I think we can say, I still think that the aristarch can be powerful to the map and
spatially analyze global connections, but clearly something can be said that. I'll just skip that
and cut the business. One of the most important things and most French and critiques
I think it was Lawrence, I think the beginning of the notice by a famous scholar Jennifer Robinson,
South African working from London, wrote a book, Ordinary Cities. However, papers was
World Cities or a World of Cities where she kind of
was with frustrated with this dominance of world cities research
in the debate about city city globalization.
And it says, and she says, well, it's quite a different thing
about world cities for the globalization of cities more
wide.
And that's good reasons for this difference,
or the lack of what world and global cities
research was doing.
Then in addressing cities in globalization,
Since I've seen the map, a lot of the cities around the globe,
and especially in the global south,
are basically dropped off a physical, natural map, right?
So we find that there's a lot of connectivity
in your Western Western European,
or the American Asian cities,
but it's actually very little to be told
about African cities that basically not represent the environment.
So an issue of representation there,
in her view, but it also deals with how we conceptualize world and world cities.
And in her argument, we focused too much on a limited number of economic processes,
whereas all the kinds of connections remain unsteaded.
One of the examples that was already given was, yeah, you can look at remittances,
and you would get a completely different view, perhaps,
on these carbon networks.
So how kind of claim is that, by doing so,
by these, say, geographical and sexual biases,
well, cities of search has ignored
the wrong position of numerous ordinary cities
in the global economy.
And there's a tendency to, you could say, offer
a Eurocentric global city theory,
and then projecting that other areas of the world.
So, a postcolonial critique,
it's concerned with, you can say,
power relations in the production of theories and concepts.
And how these concepts and theories are reproducing
existing inequalities.
And these are also geographical,
so it's social, spatial, and even as the global scale.
If we keep on kind of reiterating the dominance
of certain kinds of activities, come up with certain kind
of maps, measuring things in a certain way,
in the anthropod of the process and part of the body,
if you will.
So I think there's certainly an argument to be made there.
I think representation is problematic in my own research
that was also kind of the starting point
of why it was interested in looking
into Islamic finance as a way to understand Middle Eastern.
World's deformation process is not to a traditional lens
of the classic APS firms, but to look at, okay,
to what extent or local norms and ethics,
religious and other regarding finance,
giving rise to a global sector in an overt zone,
that could then also start,
So I was in the back interurban connections.
That was kind of what I did in my own work on Islamic finance.
So I certainly am extremely sensitive to this autumn.
But at the same time, we also have to be clear
that part of this criticism perhaps also out of place.
I think Jennifer Robinson really starts from an urban studies
critique, which you also understand.
You can say globalization and its plurality,
not just economic but otherwise and even within economic processes,
or why diversity, rests for God.
I think that the purposes, how can we understand
the reproduction of uneven development
on a global scale, at least in the free-to-manion tradition,
where it was about how can we explain the fact
that there's still under development
and on the rate that the Frank serves in the global south,
does it have something to do with the support
and position of these cities in macro processes,
macro capitalist process?
So is it something with the extraction of value,
organized through these corporate networks
and supported by these previous firms that actually explains
why these cities are not on the map?
So is this a result?
Is this not a neglect of these places?
The fact that these places are not represented means
either bypassed by these core protectors
or that they potentially are subordinate in those process.
Which could then be a question of, is this really case?
Can we look into these processes?
So sometimes a bit of a confusion, I think,
between kind of a deliberate choice,
not only include certain places
whereas some of these maps are actually to be taken
as a result of a critical analysis.
I do agree that in a number of,
You could say analysis that are more technical in nature,
in terms of the world city network,
this kind of critical edge was sometimes lost.
And there's a kind of mission drift towards mapping networks,
whereas the connection to process of uneven development
was less clear,
it's a bit of my personal crusade
to make the connection to the critical agenda again.
So this, but certainly,
Jennifer Robinson points us to be very clear
clear about what it is that we are measuring
to this kind of growth analysis and what we're not.
So it's about placing them at these kind of methods
in a wider, you can say,
a firmament of methods to work with that.
Now, with this also connect to what kind of practice
we wish to endorse within the tradition
of urban studies, in the sense that,
And this is kind of our personal disappointment
with a lot of research that has followed the work
by Jennifer Robinson, the version for Amazon itself.
But there's a lot of tendency with we're which Jennifer or Jenny.
And a very reductionist representation
of her legitimate claims.
And we actually wrote a paper about this
with these religious title,
to kind of throw that and speak, where we kind of deal with distilling what is kind of
justified criticism and where we think it's a bit too much.
And what we particularly regret is that some of the criticism has led to disengaged or
a plumberism where it's a kind of rejection, so in the genus to do something else without
taking stock about of the knowledge that is produced here.
So what we try to then propose is some kind of a middle ground is a more engaged form
of urban studies debate, which also means that you say yes, these kind of global white
analysis or well-setty research.
In general, we need to put it in its place, but it doesn't mean that we can try to work
at this concept to make sense of places beyond the short list of world cities.
It would be that I'm battling and I'm defending and explaining myself in different kind of race and unnecessary race.
But let me try to make it work clear.
Because they are very rude.
Manila. We don't need world safety concepts.
The world city is a Euro mountain invention.
I can't do anything with that.
It could be something that you could say.
We need a conflict of the Middle Eastern city of the Asian city because everything is particular
and then we need to build that theory and then it's so unique in particular that you can't land.
So people disagree and say, look, there's no one-on-one projection of world city formation as a process
on a city like the Hudefur instance or Manila.
But we'll have to work with the concept to see to what extent it does explain something
of what we find and what extent it doesn't.
And perhaps we need to enhance or tailor that first find the concept.
And in the process, we potentially may even learn something about the place that we study.
But at least we still remain in the position that we can speak back to the original debate,
which is I think the point of urban studies
that were not lost in translation,
will try to connect with some kind of organ eye
or overarching debate,
even if you're studying very diverse places.
- Now, yeah, I won't say too much about this two cases
because it's also part of our discussion seminar,
but just to point out the kind of contrasting cases.
So in one paper we looked at the LUTs,
which is kind of interesting place.
we put a more by exact,
that role-to-information process.
So what you see is a built environment with skyscrapers.
They obviously took a hit and are taking a serious hit currently
with the entire term of the country, isn't.
But on the first side, say, OK,
there's actually, when you start looking at APS activities,
it's actually very little going on there.
There's a lot of very little regional headquarters, the ferry there were international firms.
But when you then start looking into yes remittance flows and the Aspara, you find that almost one-fifth of Lebanese economy is made of these remittances.
And a lot of it faces that, to a BS professionals, that are located in the Gulf so it's our McKinsey trained, but agreed consultants, McKinsey's living,
that is them advising the Saudis or people in Dubai, the elite leader of Dubai,
that earn their money there, send back their money and buy a hugely overpriced apartment
in the city centre of the Greenhouse. The real estate market which is then
kept artificially booming by almost free credit from the central bank of Lebanon,
which is also the personal property of the living families of Lebanon.
So it's kind of connected.
Now in any case, it shows you that if you follow your nose,
in a sense, there's still awesome characteristics
of world to deformation, especially in the role
of a high-skilled labor.
But it's a kind of--
it's in some of the parts of regional capacity building,
regional circuits of failure that are kind of connected
back to the city.
So it's function as a capital sink to the region,
rather than as a kind of server service in the liveries.
If you look at Manila, it's kind of the opposite.
You'd say, wow, a lot of activities there,
a lot of APS firms, they're all there.
But then you suddenly into these activities,
and there's something that you know,
a collaborative has done.
It's basically part of the largest one of the largest
outsourcing sectors of tendencies that you find.
So a lot of back office activities,
for global banks and other kind of service providers,
but it's not really come up in control,
or not at least not what we think of it.
And it may also work through
and what it can explain in terms of the segmentation
of the labor market,
but because it would not be high-end managers
that are then gentrifying neighborhoods,
but it may arise through middle-class or something.
So it may result in other kinds of labor market structures.
But at least we can still refer back to world cities
and start comparing to what is going on elsewhere.
So this is an example of an encompassing approach
to try to encompass diversity in your research design
and try to make sense.
So that's how we solve it.
I won't say anything more because I want
to leave something for the debating session.
The second point of criticism is social constructivity.
Again, it's the same in the sense that representation matters.
And this is the great work by Dory Massey,
who was a transatlantic nice economic juggler for from the UK,
thought about spatial divisions of labor
was one of the leading voices in a lot of progressive debates
in geography.
And she also wrote a book, "World City in 2007,
I wish kind of engaged with this agenda."
And what she basically says in this book is, yeah,
world cities are not just a given, an economic geographical
reality based on, as we said, the clustering
on these ABS firms, their labor markets, et cetera, et cetera.
They are, but they're also a product of discourses,
representation, et cetera, et cetera.
So they're mediated by political interests, elites,
others, and other actors that project certain discourses
about world and global cities and these also have ultimately performative effects.
So they produce or go produce certain realities.
It's a bit kind of knowledge theory.
So the world is also to some extent shaped by how you represent this.
And then you can be an ardent, very strong believer of that and say, okay, the world is
almost exclusively,
reducible to how we represented
whereas others would work more in
kind of materialist fragrance,
okay, not everything is shaped by words, right?
So I think I'm gonna look at the other,
it's kind of something to think about
toward extent, representation actually matters.
Now, Jourine explains this for London,
and she says, yes, it's a globalized financial center,
but the way you perceive it
and the way the city reproduces itself
is the outcome of a decade-long battle of representation,
which was led by government finance elites, politicians,
not often not seldomly connected to all boys' networks
that have been projecting the world city status of London.
And this has become some kind of a hedge in life.
Unquestioned, near-liberal growth strategy,
has been part of that new liberal strategy since the eight.
And the kind of ideas that what is good for the financial industry is good for the city.
What's good for the city is good for London, what's good for London, what's good for the Saudis,
what is good for the Saudis is good for UK.
And dear Europeans, what is good for the UK is also good for Europe, so please deregulate the Afghans.
So it's a rhetorical strategy she calls the passport total where the part is there to represent the whole.
So it's the interest of the city of London which are projected to be the interest of the UK citizen.
And again, as Brexit has shown, this has been quite radically rejected.
Again, whether legitimately or not.
So, yeah, there's this neoliberal growth strategy, and it also was connected to legitimate
legitimate material decisions.
In the sense that, if you look at this course, it's about dust, heat, growth, you need
a new runway because of capacity issues.
Yes.
London cannot keep up with its global safety status or it cannot grow its connection to
new emerging markets if it doesn't have an extra runway.
So please, papers go away or needle your ears.
But we absolutely need this.
And in global city discourse is there to justify it.
But also when you look at the construction of the UK,
colony in the '80s, I mean, closing the mines, et cetera,
et cetera.
And this has produced very uneven outcomes in the UK.
A lot of cities in the north and opening
mining areas in the industrial areas.
So decline.
And at that point, what would have been interesting
is low interest rates, that could boost investment
to restructure these peripheral economies.
That didn't happen.
And at that point, there was an inflation,
there was high interest rates, which made,
but simply money very expensive.
And which made that it was very hard
to seek investment into these areas.
And obviously, there was only interest of the Southeast,
which generate an influence into financial services,
et cetera, which then further grew global city London.
So it's a particular political agenda
that is behind there that has produced there.
There are final points that we as academics
or academics to be are not neutral bystanders
and her claim is that especially when you start looking
at these world city rankings that GOC
is claimed to produce.
This is part of the problem.
It's kind of fueling the self-fuling prophecy
as giving people in the city of Roman.
The instruments that they exhibit to say,
look, we're still leading city parts
Dubai is closing.
Please, come on.
We need further investment in the city
or we need the regulation or something like that.
So that's kind of her also attention-preteaken
in a sense that yes, world cities research is performative in that sense.
So yeah, just a few slides there, and I'll return to that.
I mean, the pictures that we have of representations that we have of London are the
glitz and glam quite often, and it's typically the city.
But then how city is kept, the city of London is kept working on the wider metropolitan
and how it remains often undiscovered
or something that we'll talk about next week.
- Yeah, and this is kind of battle of representation
is ongoing, this is a bit of a data figure
and still with Theresa May there
who was going for a global Britain agenda.
And again, you see that this kind of city elite
is trying to push it in the whole campaign
in a certain way, threatening to leave the city of London,
which would then impact, you could say,
the global city status of that city.
So it's kind of still the same repertoire
that has been used at times when Brexit was still
unfinished business, probably not still not unfinished
business, but for that.
Now, I think, and then I really almost have the close
performativity is a very important criticism.
It's something that we should be very reflexive about.
It basically means the influence that it
reduce kind of figures that you could use the maps
that you produced or what they spend
to their shape and impact.
Theality to what extent are they picked up?
What is the responsibility of a researcher
to keep ownership over his or her results?
do we have an impact on that?
And it's something that is also very important
to reflect on in relation to world cities and global cities.
And there I think my personal stance is that we should
probably not exaggerate the influence of world
and global cities research in the sense
that it's only part of a much wider phenomenon
of city rankings, et cetera, et cetera.
And as you will start looking at it,
It's often behaviors from themselves that come up with all kinds of rankings and they're
much more picked up in popular debates, but for politicians that once again, a world in
global cities status, provided and referring to GOG in and of itself.
I mean, it would be a pleasure to actually know that people would meet economic papers,
but I think it's actually quite limited.
So yes, we need to be reflexive about them at the same time.
It could give me a little bit overblown.
And rankings are produced probably by other factors.
I'm sorry to run through this.
Another point is--
this is a criticism that deals with, to what extent,
world and global cities takes into account,
because of political economy processes,
or the politics of global city formation,
I think that connects to the work of Dorian Massey.
And it's kind of an agenda that was pushed
by new Brenner, especially at the end of the 1990s.
And he says, well, it's not just economic geographies,
it's not just agglomerations, clusters, et cetera, et cetera.
What we need to account for is the restructuring
of the economy and what he says, a rescaling of the nation state.
So the way capitalism is being governed
is not exclusively at the national scale,
but something is happening at the same time
it's becoming super national.
So you get a whole kind of international organizations,
IMF, OECD, et cetera, et cetera.
And Europe, Europe being union that starts
to increasingly govern the economy.
And at the same time, there's a kind of devolution,
growth in the importance of regions, of cities,
as governance layers, and some kind of a hollowing out
of the national level.
So in the words of new Breneary talks
about globalization, as the undoing of the state,
will that be because the re-spatialization
or re-territory realization of the state,
where it attaches itself to new spatial layers.
And it calls these new state spaces
to which you have new kinds of new state projects.
The road project.
So to summarize that seems a bit complex,
but there's a shift in how national economies are
being managed in terms of spatial scales.
It's also happening a much more entrepreneurial way.
And I'll say more about that next week.
But the point is that these are politically negotiated
process. And you can have a look at this overview slides to the kind of detailed
process that are going on there. But just to give one example, they also kind of gave last week
Brussels, it's kind of in this straight jacket of the Brussels capital region, where it doesn't
refer to the spatial scale of the actual netfalls in area of ordinary economic weight of
of the city, whereas in other contexts you see the formation of the larger metropolitan areas
as governance structures, where global city front foot is now a fresh line line, which
have kind of worked in a global city region, organization, which has its own governance
structure etc. So there it's easier to appreciate that emeritus when you compare that to
So it's a rescaling process and you see that in a lot of Europe being contacted not
seldomly also kind of pushed for by the European Union, who likes to see the Europe of
regions.
It's kind of this idea that you need larger entities, city regions or regions, to kind
of take control over up to scale economic processes.
So, yeah, a sensitivity to how the state,
especially reorganize itself to all extent,
there's new governance layers to manage
also these economic processes.
That was kind of also added to the state.
And then finally, very final slides,
is this kind of a critique or a criticism
by people working in the realm of financialization.
I'll say much more about that,
if you take the economic and financial geography course,
it's all about financialization.
But just the point of the fact that
this criticism deals with what it is
that is going on in world cities.
So it doesn't really criticize the relevance
of command and control practices in world and global cities.
But it says that perhaps the nature
of these activities has transformed
to the past 20 or 30 years.
So financialization, what does it mean?
It means that an increasing part of economic processes
or value-based processes of profits generally
versus well occurring, you could say,
reproductive activities, but is somehow
connected to financial service.
So financial investments is by owning financial assets
rather than actually produce something that people get rich
and also explains a real way in the qualities
between those who have large huge amounts of wealth
and others who rely on their nature
but we'll say something about that next week.
So financialization also means that there's a lot
of pressure on corporations to generate returns
for financial investors.
So it's not just about competing with other capitalists
to be the most efficient drug producer
or cooking manufacturers.
It's also to do so, to generate as much shareholder value
compared to your competitors.
It's one, I mean, this kind of quote,
corporate financialization.
It's the restructuring of corporations
so that the shareholder value is actually being created.
So perhaps world cities are still
about seamless service for globalization,
so the management of global production process
is networked.
But this other side, financial markets, perhaps,
needs to be taken much more seriously.
And these ABS firms may be more in broad and broad
in broad process of finalization, rather than productive
as logics.
So yeah, just--
So yeah, I think what I say here,
we also need to become a obligatory message for other reasons
than the ones that have been assumed already.
And that's why in one paper we talk about an augmented
world city hypothesis is not just about generating value
from productive activities, but it's also about extracting
extracting value to rent extraction practices from those global production networks.
And you can see that, for instance, when we have corporations attract funding, you need
a whole amalgamation of connected ABS firms to issue, in this case, a Euroball, which
is not kind of an offshore investment instrument.
And this is a firm, a real-state corporation,
out of Northern Germany, and kind of pays all these people
to issue that on a global scale.
So to finance its real estate projects in Germany.
So, well, cities are mobilized to attract funding
and to optimize that in a particular way.
The same thing happens when you look at the other side
equation when value has been produced, the point is that you limit the
taxes that you have to pay on your service value. Otherwise, shareholders are
in the police and you're competing with other firms to pay as much share
other value as possible. This is a classic example by Google who is using
Don't Dutch, Irish, sandwich to make sure that it minimizes its taxes, right?
So it puts, I mean, I say it's a bit as an accident, I don't know, then by the way,
but it places some intellectual property in an environment that surrounds it through the Netherlands,
towards the back of Ireland, and then it passes through the Caribbean to optimize that structure.
It's also something that firms like Deloitte and law firms are also engaged.
So it's the optimization of these kind of financial structures and
materialization is also a very important function of world city.
So in the end, I think to summarize the picture,
it's about, I can say, representation.
You can think about world cities as kind of Mount Everest's aggloperations of wealth.
That has been generated among the little down below across the territory.
But you can also think about how to call an English-dumerion gas 11 kilometers deep.
Where a value that is being produced elsewhere is being extracted to.
is basically putting a drain on the global economy.
And if you look at what happened during the financial crisis,
the financial sector created a whole surplus.
If you will generate a lot of profits,
then came the crisis.
And I mean, I think in Europe it was the figure of $700 billion
that financial sector was kind of bailed out.
It was even more in the US.
So it's a huge figure of saving these kind of activities,
where in general they actually put in that drain
on the floor when they come.
So we really have to think about world cities
in a critical way, what do they contribute,
or what are the actors in world cities,
what do they contribute, and what kind of things
effects are more problematic.
I'm very sorry to take a little bit more of your time,
But that was kind of four ways of being critical about world and global cities.
There's no time for Q&A now, but next week we'll continue.
I mean, we can start with some questions next week if you'd have them.
And we'll go to the flip side to the point.
About flip side of the coin is just polarization.
So what does it mean world and global city formation for these very places?
And these are the two texts that you're worried and fighting to reach.
Thank you.
(audience applauds)