[Music]
I don't know whether there's, I see some people with a laptop,
which you mind to check whether the webcast is working.
Could you click on the link of the link of the live stream?
I think it should be, it should be working I think.
um...
[inaudible]
So, I'm very glad I'm trying to try to do anything.
And I think that some of you might know me, and many others might not show me.
I am the excurable of these, these class, and the next one, in a trajectory-urban social
geography.
And I consider myself to be as our own social geographer, so that's a good thing I think.
Most of my research has dealt with migration, newcomers in the city, segregation, whiteness.
I've done a PhD with case studies and plumbers in South Africa,
so many years in Cape Town. I've studied how white-milliplast people move through the city.
Now, what's kind of people they get to meet in the city,
etc. So I've done some work on the geographies of encounter, the geographies of migration.
And this year I have decided to work less at the university and to spend more time with my
kids and more time on my bike. I like to cycle. And so it means that I have reduced my workload
at the university. I still have a 50% teaching assignment. I teach social geography in the first
year, Bachelor of Geography. I teach some classes in urban geography. I also take the students
on a field trip to Estonia. This will be the geographers this year. I've also done that for the
master in urban study students two years ago, was the last time I think we did it.
And I'm teaching a course on the city and migration that's a title at the University of
to move. So I have quite some teaching assignments, also supervising some master's thesis
to PhD thesis. So that's what I'm what I'm doing. I've written here in my presenter,
through M.I. and I'm another white male, mid-aged, middle-class man that you get to see here.
I think this issue of positionality is also an important one, especially in the kind
issues that I will discuss when it comes to diversity, when it comes to migration, whether
my experience is in the city. And so I think that's also something important to point at
and something that we could discuss also further in a semester like whether this is something
important or not to you. But there will be not so much time for discussion today. There will be
time for discussion in the seminars and that will come soon and there will also be time for
discussion on the field trips. I'm going to run through two field trips for the students.
This is for the four cities and the master of urban studies students so not for all the
other ones. But we have one excursion to Antwerp and one excursion to Shaldrwa next week
that I'm going to run.
And so I wanted to share some practicalities.
And I don't like the fact that I'm somehow bound to my laptop,
but this is for the live stream.
So let's say, I hope that it's working now.
But so first of all, next week, Tuesday,
I think 40 of you have signed up to go to Antwerp.
Is that correct?
Who will join me to Antwerp?
Yeah.
I will hand out some excursion guides.
I bridge a ton in color by accident.
I don't know how happy the department
will be about that.
(laughs)
If you get these paper copies in full color,
so you can take one if you join me.
Don't take one if you don't join me
because then I will not have enough copies from everyone.
And what is important, and that's something else
that I want to hand out,
is that I'm living in Antwerp,
and so I will meet you in Antwerp railway station.
Great.
To be in one wallet.
Who is joining to Antwerp,
and is familiar with this rail pass or go pass?
No one?
Yeah, some people.
So I would agree to you and I would like you for all the people that joined.
I'm going to bring it online.
And so it says, this is a French.
You can also fill it in Dutch Corimiglish.
The day, Tuesday, the dates in the Belgian system with the month here,
then the place in America, beef that will be Brussels.
and then and you need lines for everyone.
It's a bit complicated because you have tickets for those under 26 and other
tickets for those over 26. A bit more expensive.
So I'll give them to you.
>> That means that you are responsible for that.
>> That's good.
>> Yeah.
>> It's good.
>> I think it's good.
>> Yeah.
>> All right.
So it's important that you meet on time, the 22/8 next week Tuesday we are leaving
a rather early with a train that will have as a destination on Vericund, Nordr
bookum which is a small station to the north of Antwerp but it's important that you get off at
Antwerp in Central. Yeah so the group will meet 740 you take you make sure that you get on the
train 752 and then I and Louise will make sure together with all of you that you have a line for
each students, you get on the train and it will be platform 5 I guess if you're late you pay for
your own ticket. So use let's use that as an incentive. I will not reimburse anyone with these
late. You should travel with the group and then you all arrive at the same time according to the
schedule at 835 and I will meet you on the platform. Yeah so that's what we do. We will go cycling.
I hope that everyone was aware of that. It will, it is November, it will be cold, it will be wet.
So make sure that you bring some gloves and some rain gear because it might, it might be cold.
Bring the excursion guides, especially now that it has been printed in full color,
because we will use that quite a bit. And we are going to discuss basically the topics of the
this class and next class. So we will discuss segregation and social mix in the field in Antwerp.
We will get to cycle about 25 kilometers, that's quite a bit, but it has worked out every year.
Nicely so I trusted it will be the same. We're a mouth mask on the train. I don't know what the
regulations will say how we need to get around in enter. We are quite a big group. I might
split you up a couple of times and bring a lunch or buy one in enter. I will give you an hour
to have a lunch but we will be in quite a fancy part of time so it might be more complicated
to find a cheap place there but not impossible. So you will complete these rail bosses and go
bosses and then you will when you arrive in Enterp, you will give these two to me.
Next week, Friday, I will thank you to Charlotte Wop, or some of you who will join me to
Charlotte Wop. Okay, so a similar amount of people and we will meet in the Brussels railway
station, Central, so that's important. Ten minutes later, but still quite early, at 10 to
eight in order to be on the train at seven past eight. Yeah, again, the same system that say I will be
responsible for the rail passes and the go passes. If you're late, you will need to get in touch with
a fellow student to know where we are. I'm not going to wait for you at the train station in
shall the war, but also you need to pay your own ticket. Okay, and we're going to hike. First through
the city but we will also climb some of these at least one ash heap the riddle in French so this
small mountain of like leftover from the coal mining it is quite steep it can be wet so you should
also have some good shoes that allow you to to do that bring a pen and paper and I will bring
you a similar kind of excursion guide probably in black and white for the
shadow-gawah excursion and you can again bring a lunch or buy one in
shallow one. Do we have any practical questions about these trips? Yeah?
That's a good question. I think in shallow gawah I will end around five, meaning
you can get back to Brussels around six, but I have a habit to give you the possibility
either to get on a train back to Brussels, but I also suggest you to walk back to Shah
Leghua train station. But if you want, you can be back in Brussels at six. From Antwerp,
we will end at six the very latest, because that's the moment when I need to give back
the bikes to the biker until agency. And so that means that you should be able to be back
in Brussels at seven. Some other practical questions? No. And I'm looking yeah.
No you will get a helmet you will get a look. If you're very eager to take your own bike to
enter, you can do it on the train and it's a bit of a hassle but you will get a nice rental
you will get a helmet if you want and you will get a look for the bike as well.
So I will see you next week. I will see 40 of you.
Next week, Tuesday in Antwerp Central Railway Station.
I'm looking forward to that.
So these are the practicalities about the excursions.
I'm glad that I was able to share that
and personally rather than just another message in the town of us.
And today you're not in session one.
You're in session four.
You had an introductory class.
You had two classes on world city formation and polarization
in world global cities.
And basically today we will continue with it on the theme of
class three and I will we will discuss segregation.
We will discuss patterns of segregation and we will discuss causes of segregation and next week
I will discuss effects or consequences of segregation. So these are two classes that fit
very well together and there is a clear theme for each of them patterns causes of segregation
today. Effects consequences of segregation next week. I assume that all of you have read
these two texts. Have you maybe we can also have a look? Who has read these two texts?
Yeah, you can be proud about it. Who has not been able to read these two texts? You can also be
proud about that. Okay, so I see that more people have not read it, not read them rather than read them.
For the discussion seminar, I think it's important that we have like a shared knowledge and these
two texts for this week and the two texts for next week will be the shared knowledge together with
what is being shared in the class. So I hope that all of you will be able to read these two texts
and the two for next week by the time we have the discussion. So
and okay today I have basically three topics. I will discuss first these classical models of urban
form in the text by Pat surely, which was a textbook chapter.
There was a reference to Bergus.
I'm going to talk about Hoyt.
I'm going to talk about Harrison Omen.
Some classical models of urban form
that have been generated by Chicago School Scholars
in the beginning of the 20th century.
Then secondly, I'm going to discuss patterns of segregation,
meaning that we will discuss how to measure segregation
and how you can look at segregation
from different angles. And then at the end of the class, I will discuss some
courses or segregation. Why is it that people live in different neighborhoods of the city?
Why is it that you can find white people in one part of town and people of Black African origin
in another part of town? So this is the topic list for today. And I'm going to start with this
classic a land use model by Bergus. So those of you who have read the textbook chapter by Patchoni
have been reading about the Bergus. He was writing from Chicago in 1925. I think that's important.
I will do the live stream like this. I think that might also still work. It's everyone able to
to give you as a back here.
Yeah.
Okay, so that's going around the world.
So what was Bergus doing here is trying to understand
how cities were looking like?
And what kind of groups of people
that could find in different parts of the system?
And you were stating that basically you had five
concentric rings,
the heart of the city that was the loop,
loop I will discuss that later it's a term from Chicago basically the central business district.
Around that you have to assume a transition that's how it involved it and around in the
queer zone of working, working, math schools. There is a residential zone, a suburban and another
residential zone which is called the community. So five rings around the city. And why was it
and that you have these five rings, well,
because different functions in the city
and different groups of people
were able to pay different rents in the city.
So the theory was that in the center of the city,
the center of this district,
you found, for example, the headquarters of an office,
because they were able to pay the higher rents
that you had so close to the city center.
And third in our main property, that was the theory.
You would find, for example, suburban boats, not very dense,
because these people were able to spend too many less
of rent for their part of the forest.
And so this bit of rent theory was basically
underlying this novel of concentric links on the city.
Yes?
The term model can be a little bit confusing.
And because it could give you the impression
that this is an ideal type like this is how we sit for poop.
But Virgus was trying to do, but basically
to simplify reality and to understand our city's
spur, not necessarily how they open it.
How our cities, and we try to simplify it.
and that's how a simplified version of Chicago
of Western cities looks like.
I told you already written in 1925
and that's very important.
Why?
Because we are at a moment in time,
this is the population of Chicago from 1840 to 2014,
We are at a moment in time 1925,
when this population of Chicago has been growing through
an exponential growth for many, many years.
Yeah, and that also explains why
tourists was making a model of the growth of the city.
Yeah, it's not a model of any city.
It's the model of a growing city,
and you tries to understand
how this growth of the city grows.
both in terms of a growing population,
but also a city that is characterized
by an expanding area.
This built-in environment is grown.
And so it's a level of the growth of the city.
And writing from Chicago in 1925,
well, this is a very particular growing city,
this is a city of immigration, but all of immigrants
from all over the world, but from Europe, in particular initially,
arrived in a very nice settle.
And then you see that in 1900, you have less than 2 million people,
and you need to go only 10, 15 years later
to the five Mother-Mimics people
have to the population.
So this is a fast growing city,
both in terms of population and in terms of the area that is built up.
That's also expanding. That's also true.
It's also a city that is characterized by a Virginia population.
So what you see here is the result of a survey going from house to house,
One thing of people's door and then checking whether there is someone English speaking in white
Irish in green German in purple Dutch in dog furbled Russian in red etc
And so you see that this city was characterized by
Energy in this document all these people coming from different countries for origin arriving in Chicago at that time
So it's a particular city that
Burvis is writing from and I'm saying that because I want to argue that
This theory that
Burvis made up and which he thought was universal for growing cities was in fact a
Theory that was mostly applicable to Chicago
So here you see a couple of assumptions which are also mentioned
in the text that you read or that you're going to read,
the assumptions and principles that were underlying
this theory of the model of the growing city,
the growth of the city.
So you see that the assumption is that there
is this cultural and social effort
to eat off the population.
You can also think of other cities and countries
which are less marked by this kind of diversity.
The second assumption is that there is a commercial industrial
based to the economy of the city,
which you think of other bases to the economy of the city.
What kind of other bases could you have
rather than commercial best show?
- Right.
In the horizon, if you go to a city,
that is marked by tourism,
and for example, each stream
could be of any important place.
And a while in a commercial industrial city,
it's in the political center of business districts.
The center of the city is dominated by a touristic place.
Well, many of you would get different time.
I have also saw other time.
as a member of the UN at the other side.
See, find it.
Everything's based, yeah, when you were getting a heritage.
I could also imagine like cities that draw a lot of
deliveries, a religious basis to the city of
Temple or church would be central places.
So you can take off other kinds of cities.
And then the idea of burgers would be that this model
of the group, personal warfare.
Right, ownership or property, economic competition for space,
you can imagine other cities in the Soviet Union,
for example, land and economy, different kind of cities.
And for expanding area and population of the city,
many cities in Europe are nowadays marked by shrinkage.
in eastern Germany, for example, Genova in the thinkability city that has been
marked by Shriepitrofennial on top. Detroit, that will sit in both America, but
that's gone through a similar.
Fifth assumption, transport is equally easy, easy rapid and cheap in every
direction within the city. It's hard to imagine how that would ever be
possible because you will always have transport infrastructure that will allow you to move from one end of the city
which more quickly to another end and to another part of the city. Number five the city center is the main
center for employment and therefore more studyable. You'll also think many other kinds of city
you have for example the airport is an important help and you have a leak and
big developments for rockets. So these things are more attractive because of
differences in terrain. I told you I did my PGD on Cape Town you've got the
Atlantic Ocean you've got table mounted. You can imagine that these differences
in terrain are very important to understand how this city is formed. You have no
concentrations of heavy industry. Yeah, and you have no historic survival of an
burial and your spatter in any district. There is no heritage to you have 19th
century housing or a medieval harvest city. And so, Virgis himself already
acknowledged that it's our techniques to be added, I'm quoting there, that neither
Shikago, nor any other city fits perfectly into this ideal scheme.
Complications in Shikago are introduced by the lake front,
but a lake in Shikago.
And so there is a difference in Shikago River,
another difference in the rain.
Railroad lines, which mean that the transport is not equally
seen rather cheap in every direction.
and historical factors in the location of industry,
in which might mean that you have concentrations of heavy industry,
some parts of the city.
Et cetera.
So you see the acknowledgement that,
well, I'm trying to formulate
a universal model of urban growth,
but underlying my theory are a lot of assumptions and principles,
which make that basically unwriting,
I'm writing up a model of a specific city.
Chicago and basically my model was called for Chicago.
There's not even both for Chicago itself,
because there are many congregations.
I will discuss this further in a bit like.
In urban studies we have been going through a moment where we started to realize
many of our theories are provincial. When we write about gentrification and we make
theory of gentrification, then if we make a case on Brussels then we write a very Western kind of
perspective on gentrification. So it's necessary to deprovinsulize our theories. I find it
interesting that already 100 years ago there was this awareness that, well, me, Burguz, I'm writing
from Chicago and this is important to understand.
So how did this model look like?
I will run through this central central,
most central,
concentric ring is the loop.
Why the loop?
If you ever winch the ideal,
you focus metro lines that all converge in the city
and where basically this whole metro is making a loop
taking back the line from where it's going. So you have these elevators metal track, in a loop, in the shape of a loop. And so that's why the central business is the kind of scope.
So this is the place where you have shopping, where you have offices, where you have headquarters, companies where you expect to find theaters and etc.
etc. Because these are the functions that are able to pay the highest rent, the highest price
for the central one pitch. Why do they want to be in the central location? Well, these are all
functions that need to draw office workers, shoppers, de-entergoers from all corners of the city.
And so for them, it is important to be in the central location that is easy to reach from
everywhere in this. So they want to be in the room. She got on 1925 pictured the
media on IP, busy streets, the first skyscrapers of the world in the city, earlier than New York,
and so we have basically the first city where you have this, I'm just saying that like this
the classical central business district
from the North American town city.
So, so soon, one, the central business district.
Around this, you have the zone,
in transition, the zone of transition.
Basically what you find there is factories.
Why do these factories want to be located there?
They also rely on labor that needs to come in by a trend, by a metro, etc.
So they also want to be in a central location that allows them to bring in workers from all corners of this.
But they are not able to pay these high prices for length, that these functions on the previous slides were able to work.
So we will find a second to bring in which you have these factors.
Not only factories, you also find neighborhoods there.
Who wants to live close to these factories?
Nobody.
This is very poor, you took this very dirty.
These are very bad living services.
So who ends up here?
The first generation of immigrants
from different countries of origin.
Yeah, and as soon as these people are able to force
move to a better part of town than they will do so.
These names that you find on the pictures, little hell,
those quite a bit.
But also the fact that, for example,
here you have little Sicily,
so this is a part of town where this Sicilian is derived.
That was formerly little Sweden.
So you see how one group of newcomers moves out and is followed by a new group of people
from another country of origin.
That was what Berghis was noticing in 1925.
And so this is the part of the Chicago, close to the central business district, close
to do, in the middle of all these factories, where people who just landed off the boat
from Europe and Iraq. And so you have some secret groups, and these are these of new commerce
school Iraq. People who have been able to climb the social ladder, they will move out of these areas.
And they are able to afford a better home, further away from these factories, and they are also able to afford the commutge between home and the world.
So there's also a price to be paid for this.
So, verbus is writing there about the zone of independent European France, who's dead.
And in his vocabulary, respectable working class is living there.
So I found it interesting that I hear six miles northwest of the loop, more west.
So we are moving in that direction about 10 kilometers out of the loop.
You also had an area of Chicago that the family had quite some Belgians living.
And Berghis was also writing about the Belgians.
Many of them were geniters.
So they also had like a specific profession
that many of them were home forms.
And they also had a colloquine.
So you see here, 1921, whole Belgians are equal.
They built a colloquine for Belgians.
Celebrating Belgian-based and Belgian traditions,
We have a St. John Burickman's church, Cynthia and Bechmans in Chicago, and so after the day you can visit the neighborhood that was marked by a Belgian son of the post.
Empathy also has neighborhoods where you had many German or many Russians for many Italians
who had been able to find this social weather and who had been able to out with further
away from these effectiveness.
I have also shown you this map of the survey going door to door.
There was a lot of heterogeneity even in streets that some neighborhoods were also marked
by these ethnic groups.
And then as you go further away from the loop,
you get to more suburban, less dense developments.
Here you see the neighborhood of Mount Prospects.
About 25 miles more west from the loop.
And so we are moving about 40 kilometers out of the loop.
Now 30 to 60 minutes commute to the loop by train.
And so the moment that these trains are being trained lines are being filled,
you see these kinds of suburban developments.
And then you see my prospects 1917.
This is a K-trick of my memory, the 50th.
And this was the ring of the day.
But you also see who is living there,
on the twist, 3D shadowies who have arrived quite early
and were contained like a flying this source of color,
and we'll arrive a little bit on Sweden,
but then we'll move to the so-and-well,
respectable working and its homes as very as common,
but we'll be able to, as they climb to the social weather,
we'll also be able to,
to these suburban developments in bringing forward.
- So I have a question about the French private,
and it seems like all of the stuff,
the city of France, but the craftsman,
like it seems like the party is important,
it seems like the French is too.
- I'm sorry.
How do you feel that they're rent?
They're a part of it.
Is it revenue, how do you work?
I think the part they have.
Yeah, but you need to see it rent for like you need to pay $12 per stream.
Yeah, and so closer you get to the city center,
the tensor is developed.
We saw it.
And so for that reason, it's not about like what you can't
afford, but how much you are willing to pay per stream.
And so these developments closer to the center are much more dense.
And so that explains why this bitter and poor
is still going down.
Now, yeah.
Virgus, so the concentric zone model.
And a theory that is still being used--
but even today, if you read about newcomers in cities
and neighborhoods of arrival, and people still refer to tourists,
maybe conceptualized.
This arrival of newcomers in Chicago,
and the kind of neighborhoods that they were going through,
as they climbed the social networks.
But you also have other models.
I'm still, before the second world war,
and points another researcher who studied 142 American cities and who stated in the beginning
of his paper that so far reaching are the changes in our population pattern and social
structure that it can well be asked whether theories of city growth and structure formulated
for the private enterprise economy of the late 90th and 20th centuries is now referring
to veriviously would be well be applicable in a future society that may be
of a fundamentally different nature. What happens between 1925 and 1939 in
America? What kind of changes would be so important that you just have an
impact on the model of the world?
Yeah, the depression.
So this is about crisis, a moment of economic crisis.
Yeah?
And when you look at, we'll go a couple of slides back.
Yeah, when you look at population growth and in Chicago,
then you see that this crisis, 1920 by the 1930s,
But this is a clear impact also on the population of shiitaj.
As people are eager to immigrate,
and to a country in crisis, the government
is also more strict on who can come, et cetera.
And so there is a big economic crisis that also
means that there is less migration related to less migration
to the states.
There are also other phenomena.
of white was writing itself, a new theory of civic grade growth made
necessary to fit the effects of a period when cities grow more slowly,
and that's what I told you already, but also when automobiles and airplanes
removed dependency on fixed rails, the car becomes much more important.
You can imagine that a city built for car drivers looks quite different from
city that is built for people to take a tram or a metro or a train.
And he also adds that what is also different is that there's more government control and fixation of high incomes
for the benefit of the poor. This is a graph that sells you something about
taxation of the top income rates in the states. And so you see that this has been going through
going through fights and changes. And as described as when America was hit by
prizes that there was an urge to do it, so we have more texts, more income texts,
these highest power that means is that government can also intervene more in-house
in-game infrastructure, et cetera, et cetera. And so a couple of changes that
is it we have been going through and so what is saying well these models made for cities of a
particular kind remember these assumptions of burgers to not hold true in the cities that I am
studying in the 1930s this 104 cities because we see a lot of different kinds of processes
So, Hoyt came up with a sector of...
... At a sector of theory, saying that,
"Well, you still have this central business district in the city."
So, around this, you do not have a couple of concentric rings,
but you have sectors.
And the assumption is that when the city grows
at each of these sectors, a little growing,
And so if you have to the, in this case, to the east sector in which the richest people
are living, and the assumption is that when these group groups or the population from
the city grows, that this sector will also grow to the east.
And so you have a couple of different sectors, I class medium class, both class, which are
also organized by the transportation infrastructure. So you would have industry
factories concentrated along rivers, allows rain lines and roads. You may at the
next day that you would have both glass residential areas just like
burgers assumed. The burgers assumed that these factories and the lowest
world-class areas would be located in a concentric ring.
And Oric was saying, well, if you look at cities in the 30s in America,
and the sector model comes closer to reality.
So this is a better way to simplify how cities are looking.
So sectors rather than concentric rings,
what is also important is that there's much more emphasis on
and medium-class, low-class, high-class. While Virgus was often writing from these ethnic groups,
Italians, Sicilians, Germans, Russians, Swedish, and people arriving in the city.
And...
Okay, a third moment is the one by Harry's and all, and this is a garage for a
a picture that comes from their paper. We wrote now on the 19th or 25 and you see that in
their paper they make a reference already, just got sent to it. So mobile by burgers. They refer
to the sector theory by Boyd and then they come up with their phone mobile, just got
controlled people locally modeled of the city and you see in date that they have
this kind of jigsaw puzzle that represents the city for them in which you still
find number one essential business district and next to it and next to it
this trick would also a live manufacturing which you also see a couple other
notes that are important to understand the city for example seven and
outline business systems. So this is an important difference between these two models and that one.
There's not just one central business list which also has important business districts in other parts
of the city. For example in London and even in the history, there is an open state. You have this
economic hard of the city, of the city, close to the dollar bridge and you've got a political
heart of the city, close to the westerns there, there is a distance between us to, while
in this traditional bubble, you would expect them to be concentrated, close to each other
in this central business district. They also refer to Chicago, they say there are a couple of
industries or universities which are in very different parts of the city than this
burgers model, quite more, and expected. So then we refer to area of any industry
that I call it, close to the river in the lake. And then also this university of Chicago
for the south of the, which is then again like the hook of an area in which you find
of the military people, the university, the pictures, and people working at the university.
And part of the town where you would not expect that to.
And so they also look at his kind of spice in the big
witrant, saying that well, formerly according to Ferguson, this would always come
down by the further you get from the city center, the lower
is bitter and occur with me. The lower the price per square meter that people of poor companies
or other pensions are willing to fake, but then Aristotle would say, well, you always find this kind
of low spice, for example, local shopping centers, not all the shopping is happening in the central
business district, so you can find these low-risk shopping centers or a satellite city and around which
you fight again like this, the increasing
and the threat force.
So the third model, head is an omen,
where you have multiple, nuclei, more than one center,
basically, and you get this kind of itself
was to simplify perfect force.
In this theory, they upon consider those 10
[INAUDIBLE]
Well, in that case, if that's the table,
they work.
Yeah, every city will have a different kind
of form of them in argument that these models are too simplistic.
And not everything is ready, anything from one center
with the practice you will always find, but then one.
So that's why reality looks more complex than in these minutes.
OK.
And why to go back to Chicago, why to go back to theory
that have been written 100 years ago?
I think it's interesting to make urban geographers
of people who are not studies, to make them think about the form
of a system and who is living where they are.
And so on the left, you have cleared a map of Chicago
nowadays and each dot basically represents one person to put the ultimate Detroit
ultimate report, finds maps for other American cities like that and so you see here that
basically the different colors on the back represent different people who self identify
with different racist slash ethnicities. So then making you find people self identify
and the climate is too wide in the year 20 then in blue we find people self-identify this
black in green people who self-identify this Asia and in orange people who self-identify
this Spanish.
In the American context, the race, the ethnicity corresponds very much with class.
And so if you would have a map with socio-economic classes, then you would also find that most of these neighborhoods, which turn out to be a big number of times, where you have a majority of people, so identified as white, so it would be the better of neighborhoods.
And the neighborhoods, with people who self identified, black, could be underprivileged neighborhoods.
So now I question for you which of these models of urban form the concentric
remodel by Virgus, the sector level by wood where this multiple nuclei model
can you find on the mat.
It will not be a lot, so you can find elements of basically all three models
on the map. So when you look at this close, what do you see? Who sees that?
>> For now, when you see a question, it might be a question, but it's too sweet to be a find that's
right out. >> Mm-hm. You find these kind of sectors.
And indeed, I have the Metro Metro Chicago. This will be the central business district.
to have like pieces of pie that start from the central business.
So in the scratch of Chicago nowadays,
it's still looking like for it with a predicted
with these different sectors corresponding
with different population groups,
different socio-economic classes,
low-class, high-class, medium-class.
They use the vocabulary by, by point,
so in these, you can still find that there.
So, what is represented on the map? In these terms, it's considered to be relevant, but yes, so we still make that like also for some reason. We still find it important to do that. But when you look at the pattern.
So I would feel like more of a over-the-contestive
I would say our own focus is about it.
But that's just a bit of a fight.
From the airport, so indeed it's very hard to see
concentric sense, the ring one, because there will be very few
residents of the Central Business District.
It's also hard to spot concentric ring two.
It's also hard to spot some trickering three.
But then when you move further away from the city center,
it's a ring number of four and a ring number five,
where a bird is really expected to better off.
Residents who are blind to social better,
because still see that even today,
these are indeed the places where you find almost exclusively
white, dominated paper roots.
And so this is still the case.
That's what this ring number 4 and 5 are still there.
Every single woman is multiple, quickly.
[inaudible]
Yeah, you can define, so for example, to see an example,
example. It's like his neck, like running, posture, sound. I hear that. Yeah, let the rest of it. I do. I like it. There are two questions. Okay, so in the future I have a cluster of these, I think, people who sell identified as his colleague in the South. And that's around this, a caliber to river. In the street area.
Yeah, you also have a cluster of whites in a sector that is blue, that is dominated by
people who are so identified as black.
And this is this university of Chicago crests.
So up to today, you can still see remnants of this horizon, almond bubble.
And also the reasons why they wanted to refine or give more detail to this consensus
green model and sector.
Yeah.
So I hope that these models make you think about how different cities look like.
And that they also make you aware of well, in different type of cities.
You have different ethnic groups, different socio-economic classes, making up different
parts of the city.
And this can be very different.
And for us also for example,
is a city where poverty is very central.
We have the medieval city, but then when you have
the medieval city, you get to a 19th century government
related to industrialization.
This is where you find the poorest neighborhood
across the spectrum of each world,
and it's just a small Los Angeles.
These are poor districts of the city.
And they are very close to the medieval artists.
You have other kinds of cities, for example.
Paris, where you have much more wealth,
close to the city center.
You have much of the poverty and very peripheral.
So it is interesting to compare differences
and to understand various poverty,
located where do different racial ethnic groups live in the city.
And so when you do that, you will also be able to make a simplified model of the city that you are familiar with,
the city that you want to study.
And you will also come to an understanding that this work is on point and there is an open bubbles are very simplistic.
And that in different countries, in different cities, you would have very different models.
And I have a couple of examples.
This is one from Kiausli that is also used in the textbook.
But you have in the British context, these council estates.
Yeah, built on peripheral land.
And so in a concentric ring where Ellis,
and
Burgess would expect private suburban housing,
you also have these council estates, just
like these volunteers in the French context.
very much of the poverty is horrifically,
while that contradicts a burden.
The Chinese city,
was ever a bird of the Cheng Cheng
truth, my pronunciation will become a bird.
Cheng Cheng,
nobody said this in China, also fast-growing.
In China, you basically have a noodle or an urban citizen.
The Google system, probably the third.
And you have villages, which were taken up by farmers,
which are noodle pieces of land.
And you have people with this noodle citizenship,
with the noodle living.
When people from the countryside migrate to the city,
they are able to take up residence in these old villages.
And because then, who took this citizenship
you might make, say it like that,
allows them to stay in this area.
So you have a many Chinese cities,
parts of the city that I look like that,
where you have a very formal part immediately next
to a part of the city that looks much more informal,
much more dense. And that's because when the city grows over this countryside,
that these rural villages from the past become these religious in the
city where they have a lot of newcomers arrived. And so in these Chinese
cities, the model of the Chinese city, we've looked very differently from
because you have these areas that used to be villages or centres of villages,
where you have people with emigrating from countryside, from other parts of China,
who arrived there.
So this change from true, I think it means something like village in the city.
And these are areas that I was just talking.
The African city, the play of a whole pro-life in 62, very different again.
Because transport is much more complicated, is African cities.
So, bridge people refer to the close to the cities and the poorest of them who are
right from the countryside will arrive at the very ends of the city,
and very peripheral locations where it takes you two or three hours to get to the south.
So this city is looking different again.
My Davis, Los Angeles, you might have heard of the Chicago School, Burbs, for example,
that you might also have heard of Los Angeles, who of course modern photographers riding
across Los Angeles.
And my Davis, and who wrote an interesting book in 1992 and tried to make the 1998
for me, a model of how people's angels look like in the night.
And you might have heard of Skit Row, this part of the city,
there's thousands of homeless people living on the street,
just next to the central business district of Los Angeles.
So this is the song of transition, and this is where the poorest of the poor live,
He needed the next to the central business.
But you also had a pet bike,
these gated developments at the periphery of the city,
where he had the richest of the rich living in these gated suburbs.
I'm sorry, you could also see that, basically, these borders
between the different drinks were being walled, fortified,
that is anchorage in the city.
So you're trying to make a mobile of Los Angeles in the 1990s.
Mark Vage's desperate poverty, some parts of the city, and then also this fell in other parts of the city.
And in the end there's still a lot of burgers in the small.
There's still the central business district, there's still the Corro, and there's still this forest of the poor living community next time.
in the zone of transition between mixed the factories and this little hell
or little system, but people living with the streets. And I'm not more able
out of this at the center of the rich earth, it's never good to get. It's also
very much good. So trying to make a follow up, Los Angeles, in that
that I did.
I'm also a little touchy.
Sorry.
Thank you.
Yeah, I-- one hour ago, I took out
the slides with a couple of four
telling-- again, trying to understand, for the post
socialist city and wood light, but then also using
ballot as an example, but also trying to understand
what kind of problems do we see in these socialist cities
and then in these post-social cities.
and how can we try to generalize the simplify.
And so that attempts to make a low is an attempt
to simplify reality and to try and understand
what this particular about cities.
And what makes Los Angeles different from Chicago
in 1925.
So you also have indeed puzzles for European cities.
This was a British city.
curiously in this council estates that you could also make a model for a
stuck hole and try to think like what the specific of a stuck hole
I understood the problem from better to all the cities and then we're like general models
by I think it's not because I'm so in there by the general one
I think not that I know because this this
This event has been like a special fashion of American events.
And indeed, you could think how these assumptions that burgers some that are that I have
some not only slide in it, finally fixed.
But there's some of them are, are, uh, actively European.
Like for example, this idea that there can be an early on energy, so your peak city
is then to have a long history.
So for that reason there are always parts of the city,
and to always something to have a growing city,
in a sense area, so you always have 30 land users
and you have a history of the city.
There's also much more state intervention in Europe.
So we could think like how European city
would be different from these assumptions or burgers.
I want that with me that for the mother-world.
I have found that, but it could be an interesting--
it could be an interesting exercise.
Good thing how it is, what makes--
what is particularly European out of the city?
And is this something like it?
I just told you that the rest of them
took different from Paris.
It was just two hours, so I'm not allowed by three.
So it might also be possible.
So I think it's like our idea of what we did
to know when we studied college for dinner
with joint comedy, why is there--
because I think alumni are going to be
in this three days, only last time
in the built-in scenario.
Since then, there's three for all.
Like, what will happen?
I know there's so much projects through your sewing states.
And I assume that, for example, when
the nervous was making up the model in front of the body.
That's almost less strict and less regulated.
And it is non-dicks.
And when you're also in you have a city that is growing that fast,
that is having 1 million extra inhabitants in the very short period of time.
And then the city grows fairly organically.
And then it's also very hard as a planet to be put with the base, but the city is growing it.
but I must have been in the eye.
Don't know so much about song in regulation.
When exactly it must become a state.
- I'm gonna mention the problem with the questionnaire
and the single that--
- Uh-huh, okay, and can you read it?
Or not to know?
- So I said that to, well, I will ever look
whether I can I can see.
Okay, I see some comments.
Yeah.
In the example from China,
how does the ownership of people of these states
where is the city grows over these villages?
Okay, I will,
I will, it's time for a break.
I will have a look at it.
I will have a look at what I find in public borders
It's hard for me to check this livestream that also, I also need to get out of PowerPoint to check that.
I'm teaching most important people here and I hope that the livestream first.
I'm going to say 5 minutes break. It's 4 past 6.
On my clock here, so let's start again 9 past 6 or 10 past 6.
[Music]
(drumming)
(banging)
[Music]
(mumbling)
[inaudible]
(inaudible)
[ Inaudible ]
The action goes from the start.
Yeah, I feel like I'm all in.
I feel like I'm all in.
I know.
I'm actually in there.
I'm seeing the cash flow away here.
Sitting over there.
Since I said this, I can't see anything.
I'm so sick.
I'm sick.
This is a dying fire.
[inaudible]
[ Inaudible ]
(audience member speaking)
[inaudible]
(crowd talking)
(mumbles)
(crowd chattering)
[ Inaudible ]
[inaudible]
(mumbling)
[Music]
[inaudible]
(mumbling)
I'm going to go to the city of San Francisco.
I'm just going to put it on my hand.
[inaudible]
All of those issues are like
[ Inaudible ]
I have lots of slides with a conclusion for the first
So I will be asking if I will show you, let's go through it.
It seems there's urban differentiation, like that bridge, and four of them are the
neighborhoods.
There are people from different ethnicities, different generations of view colors that
they live in different neighborhoods.
somehow it seems to be some characteristic of most different whole cities.
I've been showing you a levels grow.
Africa, Los Angeles, Chicago, United Kingdom, and I've been talking about this model of
socialist or socialist.
It seems that in each of these levels there is this idea of different groups of society
and whether you define them in social economic classes
or different ethnicities or some of identity
by race, but these different groups
take a different part of the city.
And it also seems that different local features
impact of a permanent forum.
For example, this link in G.D.
I hope you could see that there are references
to the wins direction in some of these models,
migration, patterns, etc.
And obviously also local policies and transport system.
Stay in the region in housing,
desire B, for example,
the Scouts of the States for the body use
and the pre-career city.
And restrictions of mobility in the Chinese context
of the system determining where to live
or where you could set your kids to school.
strategies to counter the hypothesis.
So that also means that most of these models of urban form,
even if they say this is the bottle, the American city.
But they somehow wear bird marks that they are situated
in a specific space in a specific time.
The model of Chicago for 1920s was a model of the growing city.
And with this already 10 years later,
when this American economy has been hit by crisis,
is modeled with not all true anymore
because the city was not growing at the fast pace.
And so it's always about situating these models
in time and space.
And so that also makes it necessary to provincial us
at the theories about it.
Oh, great.
And I like to show you some exact questions
to make you think like how will I ever make you--
like what kind of questions could you
you straight from this and this is a question that I've asked for in 2016.
You have the model on the side African, both of our state city,
by a particular author and then all our familiar,
all of you are with this studio fund.
Apart from that, so let's recap,
repeal of this, Apart from that, also.
Ateez, Nelson Mandela.
Right.
So you have some references to this legend.
And then I asked you which elements of variousoids and errors of the
Do you recognize in this model?
What about that?
Sit.
That's really a way to check whether you understood what these models are
about.
You're able to apply that to another one.
Yeah?
>> I was touched.
>> What are we doing?
>> Don't anyone have to take time?
>> Yes.
the following model.
They have, I found it in a book that I don't remember,
which is perfect.
They should ever look and know I don't.
I can look at it.
I don't know if they'll do the thought.
I can tell you also the thoughts.
So first, our these classical models of perfect form,
but also some more reasons
and place with several models.
But I'm going to discuss now with patterns of segregation.
How can we look at segregation in cities?
And I will use the definition by two American authors
again, Messi and Beno Duchs-Smesi,
and Nancy Netton to America's sociologist,
who wrote a book called American Apartments.
So you see this reference to the silent written signals.
But in the thinking on segregation,
this book has been quite important.
And so you see here, what is the definition?
First of all, they focus on the residential segregation.
I could also discuss segregation in leisure spaces.
how many people who play sports or the places
where people spend their leisure time,
how we are desegregate, or I could look at work segregation
to people of different socioeconomic losses
meet each other on work, but most of the work
on segregation focuses on residential segregation.
What is residential segregation?
It's a degree to which two or four groups
of every unit, find it, this separately from each other in different parts of the urban
confiring. And that's the decision. Now what you see in these models that I'm going to show you
in the previous hours is that in most cities, different groups that you find them in a social
economic rate for this ethnicity, race, self-identifying,
that indeed in all of the cities,
different groups to live in different parts of the city.
That's all within each of these cities,
where this model is.
Eight.
It would make sense to look at residential segregation.
As a more, is the messy and dense one
to make this a little bit more complex?
And they say most of the research on segregation
has been too senseless because it looked at segregation
in one particular way.
And so what I'm going to do with you now
is to look at, for this, just five dimensions of segregation.
For messy and then, these are called evenness, exposure,
concentration, centralization, and plustery.
And also the research on segregation
is discussing evenness.
So I'm also to look at it.
What is evenness?
Evenness refers-- and I'm just reading what you see on slide now--
refers to the differential distribution
of two social groups among aerial units in a city.
So a minority group is said to be segregated
if it is unevenly distributed over aerial units.
Evenness is not measured in any absolute sense,
but it's scaled relative to some other group.
So we are able to save in this city.
This is the example that you see there.
Lights are segregated from blacks.
Or the low socioeconomic losses, if you may call it,
same like that, are segregated from a high socioeconomic
bridge is segregated from. So you always need these two groups. So you see here that you
can have index, here is this here, and index of this similarity can be calculated. And
I will give you two examples. Some years this goes out of the realm and sometimes this
goes wrong. Imagine that you have a city that is made up of four districts. And in each
of these, you have 75 whites and 25 whites. What would be the index of this similarity
When I use the measure layer, we need to take half of the sum,
that is what this great sigma is being.
And now we need to, for each of these neighborhoods,
we need to say what is the length of relation in an area.
If I just write total length of relation, 25 to 5, 100,
minus 75 the white population in area 1 divided by the
social white population.
What do we have here for one neighborhood?
Zero.
Yeah?
And it would calculate the sum for this measure for each of
these neighborhoods so that there will be zero,
a 0, 0, 0, 1/2, 0, 0.
The index of this similarity would be 0, or 0%.
This corresponds with the fact that you need to move 0%
of the population in order to get an even distribution
of white and black across the city.
Because you have an even distribution.
In each of these four neighborhoods,
You have as many whites as you have in other parts of the city.
And you can also look at another example,
where you would have 100 legs living in one neighborhood,
100 whites in another, 100 whites in another,
and another 100 whites in another neighborhood.
And if you would make the calculation now,
and you will get to one, not going to do the computer,
but for those who are able to do this,
this means the absolute number of this.
So if you get to a negative number here,
then it comes closer to the end.
When you calculate that, it will be,
then the number will be one.
Yes.
And because you will, again,
so do that with you.
This is a sum of 100, the number of price
in the first neighborhood minus 100, the total number of x,
minus the number of y's in the neighborhood zero,
and 500, 100, 300.
And for each number, each of these neighborhoods,
you will get to the number one,
and here you will get one, third, one, third, one, third,
total two, half of two, one.
Meaning you need to move 100% of the population
order to get an even distribution of these population groups across the city. Either you move
33 flecks from this neighborhood to this neighborhood. And then you can get if you move 33
to each of these, then you get an even distribution of flecks across the city. Or you move all
the white people to that black neighborhood. And then you would also get to the reason this
some people across the city, according to this neighborhood.
And so there's an index of this singularity,
range is from zero, even this distribution
to one fairly uneven distribution.
And basically, in corresponds with a percentage
of people that you would be moved in order
to get an even distribution of people across different neighborhoods.
And so this may be complicated,
But you can just look at the practice.
So how does this look like?
You would get to a number.
This is this percentage.
And what you see here, for example, is that--
so 0 was an even distribution.
But this example, Y_hunder, very uneven.
And so the more you look at the prides on this slide,
more uneven disease are.
So what is particular is that you see,
as first of all, American cities tend to be much more
unpleasable than European ones.
Yeah, so segregation, when you look at the dimension,
evenness, then you find out that in American cities,
the poor, for example, are living much more
in particular parts of the city.
in the European context, they are a bit more spread across different parts of the city.
And so you see here for different cities and for different population groups, you see how this has been
done. And again, you always need to compare it with another population group. So what is done is
the poor of Edward compared with then the ones who are not considered to be.
And so it's also interesting for those who joined into M-Turk to see that according to these
statistics, poverty in M-Turk in 2005 was also much more unevenly strengthened across the city.
So you had particular neighborhoods where you had that were marked by poverty much more than in
other European schools. This also is scale-ish Belgium and in a very small statistical sectors
that's a part of the explanation. Scale is important, but these sectors grow. They will mask
some of the concentrations of poverty of health that you get in this at least 60 to the
or defined. So this measure of evenness, yeah? So more numbers, again you see that 90,
and so you get close to 1, Birmingham Bangladesh, I read there, "All time Bangladesh,
called the Bangladesh. So apparently this Bangladesh sheet in UK cities are living very much in
particular neighborhoods of the city. And in these neighborhoods you would find almost exclusively
by much and that explains why you would need to move almost all these Bangladeshic or other
neighborhoods if you would like to get to an even distribution of Bangladeshic in UK cities.
And so you see how this measure is being used in order to say something about residential
segregation in these different cities.
Poverty in Copenhagen, the first quintile will be like the first 20% of the people according
to the income distribution is much less segregated and it spreads much more evenly across
the sick and is in all the other cities that are missing there. So do you understand what
is measure of evenness and evenness means? Yeah? Okay. I get now to these four other
dimensions. So what Messian and Desmond are arguing is that we have been looking at
segregation, goes through this lens of evenness. There are also four other dimensions,
which are worthwhile, I will leave it.
That a question.
- Oh, I would sort of make for an honest example,
with the one hundred black residents in one end,
and then the two-second, right, I didn't say,
what does it, what does it need for if you want there,
for the, for white residents in one second,
and black residents?
Or did I need to put that on? - Well, I'm just,
I am just for each of these neighborhoods.
I am calculating, I didn't want to grow too much into this.
I am calculating this.
And I start from the black neighbor roots.
Their measure for the number will be 100 divided
by 100 to the total number by minus the neighbor
within our zero whites divided by total number
of whites to be 100.
That will be one.
For the white neighbor roots,
and I have three of them. The measure will be there are zero
of legs and I have minus 100, the number of whites in that
neighborhood divided by the total number of whites 300.
Yeah? So I get here to 1 divided by 3, 1.
And so I get 1 plus 1/3, 1/2 plus 1/3 plus 1/3, 2
divided by 2, 2.
But it doesn't say anything about these neighborhoods.
I'm calculating something at the scale of the city.
And for that, I need to calculate this measure for these four neighborhoods.
>> Okay, you can add on this.
>> And then I think I realized I know how to do it.
>> And then I need to make the sum of this number in each of these.
So that will be sum of 1 plus 1/3 of 2.
And I need to be vided.
But that's 1.
But the index of the similarities is 1 in this case.
100% meaning that either 100% of x or 100% of y's
need to move in order to get to an even distribution of both wide sunwax across the seat.
Okay.
Four other, yeah?
[inaudible]
Yeah, that's the percentage. So then this would be 100, and this would be zero. And if the index of this
the same level would be 0.5, then you would have 50%.
And that would be 50.
And so you move close to one, and you are close to zero.
But this is a measure that you would often find in the loop,
in the loop.
And it would also be often checked like our segregation
changing across time.
And it would be the index of the similarity
first hand work has moved from 0.40 to 0.6 in an equal dot order concentrated over time.
Or more say you need it. Sorry, I'm not using it because more say good.
So I got less evenly distributed across time. Okay, for other dimensions I'm going to move
to them rather quickly.
There's a potential exposure, which first is the degree of potential context or the possibility
of interaction.
In this case, in each of the neighborhoods, there is a similar degree of exposure.
The other is when these people limit their lives to the neighborhoods, there will be no
approaches. So this degree is fairly close to evenness but not completely because for exposure
and the number will also be depending upon the total size of these communities. If the total
black population in the city is very low then the chances that you will get to meet a black
a person are lower already.
And so the size of the group is important if you would
make a measure for exposure.
Concentration, dimension number three
refers to the relative amount of physical space
over five by a minority group in the urban environment.
So again, it depends on the size of this one.
3F here in Haton.
And we have been these different colors
again, these different ethnic or racial groups,
or people self-identifying with a particular group.
And so you see that in shades of purple,
you have the Asian population.
And so you have China,
and that's where most of these Asians are concentrated.
They take up a very small amount of space.
This is a dense neighborhood.
most agents living in Manhattan or living in that particular part of Manhattan.
So concentration, the relative amount of physical space occupied by a minority group.
Number four, center of the city.
It relates to the creed to which a group is spatially located near the center of an
I don't know what the center of New York would be, but if you say it's Wall Street, then these
Asians are living very centralized.
And while like Africans in the case of New York are not living central anymore.
The same goes for this example of poverty. In Brussels, poverty is very much centralized.
these neighborhoods which are marked by COBRT are close to the city center.
In the Parisian days, 40 is very much decentralized. That's much more an issue of these peripheral
volunteers. And in the last dimension is clustering. The degree to which these aerial units
inhabited by minority members and join one another or not. I don't know how familiar you are
with New York, but I remember walking out of the metro station in Flushing, close to Flushing
Meadows where you have the tennis tournament and that was another neighborhood and that was
was very much marked by a presence of Chinese people.
Yeah, the Soviet have clusters of,
at least two clusters of agents, one in this China attack,
an attack, and another one somewhere here in Russia.
Yeah, and so is the presence of agents,
is a cluster, no, because there are two neighborhoods
which are quite far away from each other.
Even this exposure,
for the centralization, concentration, cluster.
And so I could also ask you in the exam
to discuss the three most relevant dimension
of messy and messy,
or the ones that you still remember.
to these five to discuss social economic segregation process.
Is over the Western or not?
Is it centralized or not?
Is it concentrated or not?
Is that even the same?
And the data might allow you to say something about it or not.
I already told you when I pointed at these high numbers
of unevenness in entered, that scale is fairly important.
So now here this is a pattern of rich and poor
and you will only detect it as segregation
when you are able to study it at the scale of these
specific neighborhoods.
And if your statistical units are this big,
then it would be, then this would be of any events
you're able to study it at this scale, then this is a very uneven. And so the more refined
these statistics allow you to grow the higher one with assume these levels of segregation or even
this unevenness will be. So scale and the scale through which you look is something very important
this one. I saw a hand somewhere at the bank and I'm only with the discretion for the relevant death.
[ Inaudible ]
Well, I could imagine, like, some already have a CBD.
And we have four neighborhoods around the CBD,
part by poverty.
And you would say that poverty is centralized,
but it's not clustered.
And it is also-- is it concentrated on it?
The role of this amount of space and a less
They are related to each other, but there is still something visiting about the digital
associations of poverty, which are very decentralized.
They still put the poor paper-pated space, but this is far away from the city centre.
And then the question could still be whether this poverty is clustered with the you have in the east of the city
or this is roots which are adjacant to each other and is over deep, concentrated.
Or rather this poverty is also decentralized, but also not clustered and not translated.
So you could imagine you could imagine you need to start playing poverty decentralized.
You also expected to be some of the close to the majority.
They are not.
Well, for groups of people, in a sense of data,
they should not understand that today or what,
and I should not present something.
Some are in the center of the arms of the thing.
And you would say, "On routine is centralized in the people, our centralized in Brussels,
rich people are not, because they want to be able to do it. And they can't do it. And they can't do it. And they can't do it. No. No. Okay. These are what's known. And this can create a safe, safe, easy, easy. This is for John's family. Take care of that.
[INAUDIBLE]
Well, then it will still be relevant to say that.
It's not a danger.
OK, so five dimensions of segregation,
which also allow you to speak with a little bit more detail
about the social differentiation that you find.
So some only about evenness, people living
in different neighborhoods of the system.
You can also discuss concentration plus three central
activation exposure.
There's another question.
Yeah.
I'm just wondering what the concentration,
does it matter like the portion,
like the size of the population?
Like I demanded a city that they're just not very nice.
Very few people are bored of their,
and then you should have a couple of neighbors
that are in the first book,
and that would be all concentrated,
and how we can help the management experience.
How are many people?
Yeah, I must admit that I don't know exactly how this
would be measured and how it would operate
in a certain measure.
But here, it will be about the size of the group,
how many Chinese do they have?
It will be about the densities that you are talking about.
Tower, it will also be a dangerous square meters
but it implements neighborhoods.
But I don't know how you're with exactly operationalized
that's in this kind of way.
But for me, the important thing is
that you understand that there are different front
pages that you can understand this spatial
differentiation between racial or between like the bias
or between male and female or between normal sexual sexual.
You can look at it in many different ways,
but that you will be able to study it through this final language.
For me, that's important.
And I will ask you how to measure
that's around to operationalize it.
But I hope that you understand that it can be meaningful to do it.
And that is, for example, a figure from your statistical
for culture, for example, you have different kinds of cities, topological and German cities. And it matters whether the rich, for example, still meet a different indigenous cities where rich, do not need to come to meet, do not need to be to.
For example, in the Brussels case, these poor neighborhoods are so close to it.
Okay, just do these neighborhoods where each people work, for example.
You would get all conflicts around the front place, but in other kinds of cities,
that would necessarily beat a case.
So for that reason, these kinds of dimensions do matter.
And I could ask you to apply that to a particular city.
70 minutes left to discuss the goals of segregation.
So why is it that different population groups take a different part of the city?
I guess that all of you have some kind of ideas about it.
What will it be about what kind of explanations would you advise it that rich and poor
and the whites, Hispanic, Asian, people of the origin, people of the cross, that they lived
in a different part of the city.
Why is that?
>> Tell me when it comes to creation or in coming city, they will often choose the name
of the book, for example, like the world age of tea, coming to come to sign for,
[ Inaudible ]
You have another explanation?
I'm in the early early days, different in the health and strength, and then the health and strength.
Through example, teachers are concerned. A public thing in the present world, one in an area.
Okay, so it could be about what you're able to afford and the financial limits that you have to be about, choice to live amongst people like you.
[inaudible]
[ Inaudible ]
>> Okay.
>> Yeah.
>> There are many explanations.
>> And it is important for me, but I'm going to try to do
in a very short period of time is to run through a couple of typical explanations.
But I find important is that I'm showing you this crop.
I think you've seen it already in some of the previous classes by the University of
of Austin.
And so what is important for me is that different drug workers or urban thinkers or people
over a human domain of students that have been coming up with different explanations, that also it matters very much from which sub-discipline that they are looking at.
And so family and instructors have been pointing at different explanations of segregation than Marxist-chair-person.
And so for that reason, it is important to situate
this theory to explain segregation on this match.
And my take on it is that one explanation is not
better than the other.
But in order to understand what is happening,
we need to look at financial limits of people.
And Marxists will have a big theory about it.
And but also a choice.
And it will be mostly these.
there are the even older history childrens
who are eager to explore the preferences of people
and why people want to live in a particular neighborhood.
And they will also then go to interview and say,
why is it that you move subverts?
So my point is, I think it's important that you unravel
these different theories made up by these different thinkers
from different disciplines.
quantitative geographers in the 60s
were not so interested in explanations or segregation,
but they had a rich set of mapping tools
to understand these spatial patterns,
but they were not so interested in explanations.
Ecological models, Bergus, she would go and read Bergus,
1925 concentric solo, why do these different population groups
and look at different parts of the city.
Almost like you would have this pioneer fit of fit.
So imagine the beauty area of land.
First you would find grass,
and then you would find shrubs,
and as the shrubs grow, the grass cannot survive anymore
because there's no fighting for the grass.
And then you would get these big trees,
and these shrubs can also not survive.
So you would have competition amongst different types
of which they should put their competition
amongst different populations.
You would have innovation to most desire parts.
So we talk about ecological models.
Because when you read these 100-year-old theories,
that often you find these analogies with ecological models
at your vegetation or the survival of the fittest
almost.
So ecological models they draw on theories of expansion, competition,
in patients, your session of different countries,
in analogy to what you find in among plants.
For Marxist-Jokers, different neighborhoods,
different built environments, our parts of circuits of capital.
And so to understand why different neighborhoods
are produced for different people.
We need to understand the flows of capital,
the entirety of its state,
and look at the circuits in which this built environment
features.
For instance, I'm not going to discuss this whole figure.
But for example, to understand super-binization,
We also need to understand the archivalization regime in which this super-venisation came
across.
And how for example, after the second world war in Belgium, super-venisation was promoted
by the state also because it was a start of a consumption spiral when you suburbanize,
you meet a car.
And so people will buy more cars.
You will need a fridge because this local shop is far away. You will need a freezer
Yeah, so there's a whole consumption spiral that starts when people so urban
So in order to understand why
Superventization of the millic losses was promoted in Belgium, March 36, of course
We need to understand that a group of patients received enriched this function sport
to understand why neighborhoods are being gentrified
and to understand the rent.
Which many of you have lost us by material thinking
and as well that you will explain
how this rent gets worse.
So he tries to understand when you look at gentrification
to a rent gets, say, well, effectively have an invasion
of gentrifying us to borrow this word from burgers
to understand that you need to understand the red gap
and the fact that profit can be made in this neighborhood.
So this is part of capital accumulation.
And so radical marks as drug workers will focus on the fact
that you have the rich in the suburbs or the jail,
and the rich in this gentrifying neighborhood
stable type understand how that fits within this process
of capital accumulation.
Their explanation of segregation will therefore
be rooted in the circuits of capital that Harvey is trying.
In the text by Michael Benvener, the review and the read about the neo-reb
reb
area, there are more constraints to people than only these financial constraints. It's also
about discrimination and it's about the social capital that you have. Are you here about
different resources that might be important in finding a place to it. And I also
the constraints that link to that. And I want to have there at the bottom is
discrimination by people in the real estate systems for different population groups in
in Belgium. You see that there are some significant
and so it's not only about the financial resources that you have.
It's also about your last name, whether that's sexual
French or whether that is an aramic name that will
impact often how easy it is for you to find an apartment or
a place to buy in Belgium.
behavioral drug efforts that are interested in the preference and the perceptions and the decision-making of
visual. So for them to explain
suburbanizations and affect these middle-class families move to the suburbs.
They will think about
push and both things. Why do these people prefer to leave the city? It is
or humans, this overcrowded is the animal,
grime, and so on.
Why are people attracted to the surface well
that are different pieces for them?
But in order to understand segregation,
you also need to understand the preferences
of these different populations.
It's not only about restraints,
it's not only about capital accumulation,
It's also about different groups of people
preferring to live in different kinds of environments.
Students will also be segregated from non-students
because we have a certain, many of you will have
a similar set of preferences that make you not live in
the suburbs, I guess, but that will make you
the closer to the university, closer to places
where interesting things are happening.
And then you also read in this text by
a long time can be done.
And there's a regular one you will also read about
at the cultural.
You can also look at these preferences
through an ethnic lens.
And for example, to explain why people
are broken, Turkish origin in the city of Antwerp
by they live in particular neighborhoods.
You will need to understand their financial restraints.
And they have them to be rather poor.
And so they are forced to live in cheap parts of the city
or cheaper parts of the city.
But you also need to understand their preferences.
And you can also look at that through an ethnic lens.
And many of these more weapons will be
either too close to a mosque or too really close
to the Turkish paper or close to a halal butcher.
And that makes that kind of a big box.
So you can also look through these preferences.
So if you look at these preferences through
and ethnic lips, you could use the same lens
to understand why more and more these more
African families or people for families
or for origin also move to the surface.
That will also be a reference really to a visit.
For example, government bail along
who studied this in the enter of context found out
already quite some time ago, that in these ethnic neighborhoods, as there are also people,
they also have very tight methods of social control, so to move out of these neighborhoods
is also to output this, to move away from the social control in these areas. So you
could have another preference that is linked to this reference. So the ethnic cultural
approach where you look at these preferences through an ethnic lens and obviously it can also be
a criticism. So if Mother and Joker first they will try to understand how housing is important in
identity, kind of raising the truth, conceptualize yourself and the meaning that housing or living
in a particular apartment since he is tasting them. So you see here a whole new title, they
They clap under meaning of house.
And how is it more than just a roof above your head?
It's also about home and feeling at home.
And so these post-post-mother-joker
they try to understand segregation from this lens.
And so they try to understand what moving to the suburbs
means for these milli-class people who did that in the 60s.
That was a thing to do if you had the money,
you're reading the quote, well,
and then you move to the servers.
And so this idea of social mobility
and showing off somehow was quite important
in understanding why this group of people
moved to the servers.
And we can do the same for,
for why these gender fires move back
this often set them to the cities.
It'll also be about a certain identity.
and spend a lot of time to keep the output to see here.
This is also something that is very much promoted by the citizens.
And for example, skier to get these gender fibers and little phosphon, these white, little phosphon,
the tuxion, on these pictures to get them to live in the city because it helps them to have a text space.
So if you want to have money to spend in the city, you will need in the building system,
you will need people currently not from the part of their ecosystem.
And in the city, the city council can do this.
So I'm not really making myself very clear, but the bottom line is that the social and
of the majority of the sites understand why people end up in different parts of the city
through the lens of identity and how we identify as people with the place where we live,
what that means for ourself and others looking in other parts of the city.
I've been really into these slides, yet again the bottom line for me is that to understand why
people live in different neighborhoods that we might need all these
feelings and then it will be about the Marxist idea of capital
implementation. It will be allowed to nail
very many resources and constraints that we have looked at. It will be
about the preferences of people that assume this
picture of the first very interesting will be about
identity formation and what is for mother's
geography of first-born interests. So I could give you another
exam questions. Look at this map there, this confusion of people of Turkish and Moroccan origin
in Antwerp. How were these different photographers explained it? And many of the explanations that
you've given in the beginning of the... So when I started the form of the also of segregation,
having studied five different drug workers learning some disciplines for people in different
parts of what is simply cultural mistakes.
Of course, why do we do that?
Is because we assume that this matters and that segregation has effects and has
cultural interests.
That many people have been eager to understand what was the key for a poor person to this
and neighborhood that is part by whole.
And most people who are people who are living around it doesn't matter whether you
And that kind of neighborhood, the way that you
as a person is in a more mixed neighborhood.
And you have middle class, which is the same.
And we're doing it.
And we're doing it for a city.
And when you have this segregation
of legs living in a particular part of the city
and have a wide-staking of different kinds,
or would it be better to strive for this kind of more
even distribution of legs and a wide-stin
the particular city, or region tour, or young people and old people, whatever social imagery
we used to do.
So next week, I will not discuss patterned those segregation, causes those segregation, but
I will discuss these effects of segregation.
And also, policies of social mixing that are related to them, you get to the heart of
why doesn't matter to study this?
Well, is we just reassume that segregation, concentration,
centralization that is a whole ethics for the people
that we have been talking to them for these two hours?
So in two weeks time, another class on the ethics of segregation.
Next week, Tuesday, feels like to end work,
There are various guests on the field, many of these issues as well.
So I would forward to see many of you in a tour of the Tuesday 8th something in the real
So see you soon.
soon.
(coughing)
(upbeat music)
(mumbling)