I have done my best now to restart the stream.
Maybe you can ask whether it is working.
It is difficult for me to check.
I thought I had been doing what I have been doing last week.
It seemed to work then.
But I am also for those who use the streams to study.
I think it makes more sense to use last year's stream,
also for today's lecture,
for those who are following now,
because I prefer to teach for the ones here,
meaning that I will be from my screen.
She'll also put that on again.
Or in the classroom, and that will not be recorded.
And last year, I've just been streaming from my office
because we were not supposed to have lectures anymore.
So I feel that it's better to draw in lost the SZ and also for the ones who come and be
here today. But also in case you want to study the slides are 99% safe. So I think it makes
most sense to use lost years of live streets also for last weeks.
Do you have any information about this tree now?
I think it's working.
Okay, I'll do my best to move it in that direction.
Okay, so let's suppose that the tree is working.
If not, everyone can rely on last year's theme.
Okay, I think quite many of you are here.
I don't know how many students I'm expected to have.
I think 70 or 80% is here.
Good, the ideal of social mix.
And so I thought you already,
I told you already that in many cities across the world,
there has been a concern with segregation.
And then we're supposed,
that segregation has negative effects on poor people.
So, add that you're worse off when you're poor,
when you're living in a neighborhood where
with a concentration of poverty, rather than in a mixed neighborhood,
where you have both working class people and a good class.
Already in the 19th century,
the heydays of the industrial revolution. You have very different groups
the capitalistic bourgeoisie and the Ethiopian socialists and so both the bourgeoisie
and the socialists who are afraid or who are thinking that concentrations of laborers
in particular neighborhoods of the city, for example here in Brussels in Bolognese at that time,
and for it and to work in an unfair report and put it out,
that this would have negative effects.
And the bourgeoisie was afraid that concentrations
of laborers might lead to revolutions,
that socialist thinking would become dominant
in these neighborhoods, and that you would never
recall that people would get upstream.
And the utopian socialists, they were scared
that these concentrations of lasers would make it more
difficult to strive for an egalitarian society.
And so on both ends of the political spectrum,
you had people who were thinking that it
places such as Manchester or Gental Brussels,
where you had these new working laws, neighborhoods,
that this was something that to be contracted.
This ideal is still very dominant nowadays.
Here you see a quote from
the Russell Scapfoe region,
by the old one working,
current policy of the country,
which I'm similar quotes,
stating that contrary to the American city,
the ideal type for the European city
is based on the mix of functions and,
and I think it's important to make a distinction
between these two things on the one hand they refer to a functional mix, meaning that
they would like to strive for neighborhoods where you have a mix of the residential function
of artisans and houses.
And for example, offices or shops, saying that well, it's not good to have neighborhoods
they only have a residential fridge.
And other neighborhoods where your only have offices.
And so we strive for a Brussels with neighborhoods
where you have a functional mix.
And the other thing, this is what we are interested in.
A is saying, well, we also want Brussels
by other European citizens who have neighborhoods
with a mix of people, poor people and rich people.
And in Brussels, there have been many different moments
where this topic of social mixed
has been on the political agenda.
I think there is a few,
but not surprised to Brussels only a month ago.
I might have heard of these discussions around
paper, was social housing estate,
Unmanlyed.
Sorry, the periphery of the Brussels capital region.
And therefore, you have quite some media reports about crime.
And then the issue of, well, you have all these
to be accommodated on the social housing estate
in Brussels and in Belgium,
more generally you need to fall below certain income
And meaning that it's mainly the poorest of the poor that do concentrate on the social housing
instance.
And so then you have discussions, well, is that the good thing?
Is this not leading to this culture where crime or con- and conservative politicians would
erase these kinds of those sorts?
Progressive politicians would wonder, well, is that then a neighborhood where they're
it is easy for people to climb the social building. Wouldn't it be easier to be socially mobile
when you are not only surrounded by other poor people, but when you are living between
and poor and rich people are like it. So beta-bles, a neighborhood in on the left,
And obviously also in the way of these terrorist attacks in 2015, there were a lot of concerns
also in the international youth, about knowledge and their reports about knowledge,
as they were doing as a get-up. I've been looking at the statistics. I think
of all the makers of the most people of Moroccan origin,
the most followers of Islam, but it's still less than half.
So in the international media, it was often
reported as if Mollum May was immunistic, but with only
Moroccan people and people of Moroccan origins.
And then you look at this example, it's not the case.
Nonetheless, there were some concerns,
hopefully, that also could be a penalty.
About Mollumbe being a safe haven,
for there is a breeding ground for their central tech
that you have this concentration of people
of the same origin was then the reason to be, to be concerned.
So both when it comes to social mobility
and when it comes to cultural integration, new commerce,
there are concerns, ethnicity, such as Brussels,
about the concentration of either two people
or people of foreign origin.
These are two different issues, social mobility
and social control in the future.
As I said, was there a question?
- So, the structure of five people?
- No, I am trying to explain you.
I'm not saying that there is a desire to plan
or supply in the social mix,
but I'm trying to explain you that in many cities
across the world, I will start from a couple of intelligent examples.
This idea of social mix is high on the whole of the knowledge.
memory, very to this data, most issue, and more on the
app to the errors, the text as to moments, where social mix
was highly debated. Local media in case of this
terrorist, the text also is informational.
Um, Brussels, we move to Gint,
an informer colleague of mine,
that's written a nice book about gentrification
in the nation, in this name is a spot called Tukkau,
so for those who know the church and for our interests
that they find some interest in the literature.
And see a quote from an elder man of the city of Kent
talking about a production of Kent neighborhoods
such as wish support,
neighborhoods that have a similar history
a small make in Brussels or in Al-Terepa North in Antwerp.
Neighborhoods that have developed in this 19th century
industrial industrialization.
And so neighborhoods with a higher than average
percentage of unemployment, higher than average percentage
of people, also a higher than average percentage
of people or for an average, etc.
What was this elder man saying?
Well, when I attract young families,
preferably with a job, preferably double income families
that will improve my social tissue, my sex base,
and my neighborhood life.
I think these are different health
serves the dead space, something important, I'm sorry.
In Belgium, about 40 to 50% of the municipal budget
comes from local taxes.
Most of it is a percentage on the local income tax
and percentage on the income tax,
meaning that if you have more rich people
in your municipality, that you will have
a higher municipal budget.
Yeah. The other part comes from Lent and I'll study you.
So why did this other amount of Ghent finally
for the trends? Young families prefer to leave a joke.
They look lost from the white families.
They still improve these local text things.
So you have more budgets for the city of Ghent.
But on top of that,
It's also important to improve my social tissue, and I will go further intuitive, but often
there the underlying thought is that, for example, when you have rich and poor people,
when you have families, really good job and families without the job that you will get
diverse social networks, for example, and that in these networks, jobs can be found for
people can be held with homework, etc.
So this ID for the importance to attract young families,
we call it refurbishment.
It's not only for to improve text-based obesity,
but also to improve the social tissue and the labor
of life.
In very much a similar way, we move to the city of Annenberg,
And we have been visiting this unperturbed port,
the neighborhood, the neighborhood,
where I think 25% of the new covers in Enter
passed through before moving to other parts of the city
and neighborhood that is quite similar to this transition.
So the burgers was describing in my own sanctuary style.
And I've been talking there about a lot of regulations
that affected shopkeepers in the neighborhood,
but also regulations that concern the subdivision of houses.
And you see there that in the previous government agreement in
Enter, it was stated that the city wants a larger share of single-family
developments in this particular neighborhood in the housing supply in order to attract families.
I always find it interesting to see this kind of word.
Often the youngster means young people of foreign backgrounds.
What you see here is that families excuse me,
what is land is funnel-in-mail families,
all of them are white countries.
So that is why the transformation of single-family
develops into smaller housing entities is not desired.
And for those who joined the mentor,
We have been discussing how could you support the arrival function in this neighborhood?
Well, then people are looking for a very cheap place to live and they will rent a room
for even just a mattress.
And that's what they would for the cheapest roof above their heads.
What you see here is that the city of Hanford is not so poor, the arrival of the church.
defines it in importance to bring another kind of people to this neighborhood, namely richer
levels. So again, you see efforts here to turn this out to an open north into the social
the mixed neighborhood where you have newcomers next to white families who can afford to buy
such a big house just for the use of one family. In the art in the art, people by
I've been here a lot of times, and I've been here a lot of times,
and I've been here a lot of times, and I've been here a lot of times,
of foreign origin, you had demolition projects and you had the creation of new dwellings
that try to cater for different audiences. And again, you see the, this is a course
from the Army Department of State, you see that the idea was that in these neighborhoods
that can be transformed, that these big inhabitants,
the people who used to live there,
were seriously disadvantaged by a rare name.
And the idea was that living in such a neighborhood
being poor in such a neighborhood,
accessor-based poverty makes it worse,
not basically living in such a neighborhood
is worse than living in another name.
that is only more difficult to find out a poverty in such a neighborhood of the parts of this.
So for this reason, it was a big, big and project to basically the knowledge match of the house
in these neighborhoods and to build new houses that cater for different audiences.
Slater also refers to this whole sixth program in the UK and the US sorry.
For example, Capri Nichri, a neighborhood of miles to the north of Peru in Chicago.
Lastly, there have been quite a bit of a Chicago.
A neighborhood with a very bad reputation for drug use and any crime and any other things.
And again what has been done there is that many of these apartment blocks that have been torn down have been demolished.
And that you houses have been built again trying to cater for other kind of hope.
It's trying to bring the millic loss to a neighborhood that was previously painted in evident fire.
And then in the situation of the SU-minded hurdle, this far geosystem,
where many of the original residents of the neighborhood such as that,
other voucher, and basically to give them discount on their rent price,
in other parts of the city trying to encourage them to move and to better off
neighborhoods in other parts of the ocean garden.
So again you see attempts to mix neighborhoods in the conviction that the concentration of poverty
is bad that it leads to crime and it leads to drug use and that it is bad for these
inhabitants.
South Africa? Yeah? I want to know what's going on, how come about it?
It's the... Well, I think the outcome, there are many, many papers about this and many scholars
looking at different sides of this medal, but I think in the article by Stom Slater, page
369 I see here. It is stated that no effects have been reported for a number of outcomes
and that at first effects on the delinquency and physical health of
Adorsant males in particular have been reported but positive effects on adult mental health and
education and health of young women. So it depends very much what you're looking at, but in any
case studies who try it and to find out like what happened to the people who moved to middle
class neighborhoods, found very at first effects and in any case one good question whether such
Well, because the project was the best one to try and improve the situation of computer and Chicago.
I will discuss the effects of such programs in more detail. But before doing that, I wanted to
highlight that in many countries across the world, US, UK, many built-insities,
and basically all over the Europe in South Africa.
And then step in,
to create socially mixed neighborhoods
in the conviction that segregation
and the concentration of poverty is bad
for people living in just the situation.
- One question, okay, yeah.
Why is there this idea that I can't speak?
Like, you know, there's a target.
[ Inaudible ]
>> I don't know what to say.
I don't know how to make the definition of inclusion.
In any case, I think it's another coincidence that all of these projects that you see here
are about bringing the middle class to neighborhoods which used to be predominant for
And the future.
This fire-shark program that I was just talking about
is also doing the other way,
doing it the other way around because it's
nice to bring four people to a milliposs neighbor.
And so this is also a project where milli-class neighborhoods
are also becoming more or mixed.
Because by giving these rents subsidies
through this fire-shark system, it allows people
and the religious people to move to a better off parts
of the city as well.
But I will come back to that.
For now,
we, it's good that you already start to wondering
about effects of these programs.
But as I said for now, it's important that you see
that in many parts, in many corners of the world,
this ideal of socially mixed,
socially mixed neighborhoods seems to be a very stable kind of idea.
And it's very predominant among policy makers, both on the left and on the right.
So on both ends of the political spectrum, you find this pretty four neighborhoods
that house people with different origins or people of different social economic backgrounds.
Two questions we need to ask about this is it possible then to create social index mixed neighborhoods and then a third visit or second the second question.
Is it desirable to do it?
And the article by a little stator gives, or those stators
gives an historical, apparently clear answer referring
to this whole six program in the United States
and housing markets review rule in the UK
is stating that whatever they don't,
they have basically just shifted over the elsewhere.
This has not been a remedy to overty.
This has just made full people elsewhere in the city.
The mode of production that shapes urban environment,
extreme net,
it's referring to the capitalistic system
there, the system of production of capitalism,
produce concentrations of poverty
that many policymakers, as we have seen,
rejoice in bringing up.
yet, at same mode of production,
churning in tech produces further concentrations
just down the street.
I still remember one of my former professors
saying that, well, many of these attempts
to create socially mixed neighborhoods
by attracting middle class people
to, for example, who neighbors?
in Brussels has just shifted this over the elsewhere. And for that reason, the
he made this comparison with moving chairs on the deck of the Titanic. People remain poor,
which you just make them move somewhere else. But this does not improve their socio-economic
position. This does not help them to climb the social ladder. In the day's fight, I can't
all you have also seen is reference to water bed.
So when you look at that, it seems to be very hard to create a social mix.
The same goes for Brussels.
I have been referring to this article by Martin,
like Knee King, already in Shadow 1.
And basically what material has been doing is to study people moving out of
gender-ifying neighborhoods in Brussels. What happens to people who move out of
neighborhoods in Brussels that are gender-ifying? And basically he made a distinction
between different clusters of people and if I'm correct, then cluster one
consistent mainly of highly educated German coefficients.
Where do they move as neighborhoods in versus gentry5?
They move to and to work and gensh and also some of the municipalities of Plava,
one of them.
And these are municipalities.
These people find a joke in another city, in another part of Belgium.
They move out of these gentry5 neighborhoods and they move to a place closer to the place
and that's where it is.
But the tool consisted of more working-wise people,
people with a lower-than-average income,
where you then move first of all to,
well, make difficulties along the canal,
and such as Holland and U of Warden,
the home of our familiar all of you are
to the geography of Belgium already,
but these are also usability small towns
that have gone through a process of industrialization
and where humans find small houses
that will be cheaper than the houses you would find
in these gentry-fly neighborhoods in Brussels.
And so what you see here is that gentry-ification
comes with displacement, for example,
to a municipality such as Phil Moore.
So as you see these clusters you can find rather far from Brussels,
Cenvois, Laudien, Mols, many town cities in this 19th century
built for industrialization in the Indian culture.
So these are municipalities very much find housing for a rather
cheap price. So if you follow material by thinking this argument, then you would see,
well, what happens here is that by trying to improve the lives of poor people in Brussels,
through creating the social mix, attracting the middle class to these neighborhoods. What you see
is that these people moved, are displaced to other municipalities,
where you also have concentrations of poor people.
But they are located in much worse situations, locations,
where it comes to finding a drug for it.
And so what is happening here is a shifting the chairs on the deck of the Titanic
over these still exists, but by attracting the middle of the loss to some
neighborhoods from Brussels, you move forward the elsewhere. To places where
people can afford to live, and these are neighborhoods that we have been
visiting in Isha, the Walker, and Salk. We're here buying a house or renting an
apartment will be much cheaper than this in San
actually, for some of the other genshifying parts of process.
This map shows something very similar for Antwerp,
those who joined to Antwerp by a recognized
its first reading, the medieval Antwerp,
the second reading, 19th century industrial Antwerp,
and what is not...
visualizes is a synthesis index of this advantage.
And you see that in some neighborhoods,
there are no big changes in the last years
in this index.
They are yellow, for example,
blue fall social housing estates
that we have visited the remains yellow situation.
There does not really change.
You also see other parts of the city, for example,
A luncheon, the area around the museum that we are doing.
You see that this is blue.
And many of the inner city neighborhoods
in Alberta, the North, for example, are also blue.
At the same time, you see that other parts of the city,
for example, medicine and dirt on the outside
of this 19th century, well by a sea of worsening
of this synthesis.
That's also here.
Through this map, you could see that, well,
some neighborhoods are attracting
four million plus people,
but poverty is shifted elsewhere in the city
is moving to other parts of the urban region.
This map is just giving you the situation
for the municipality or the city of Antwerp,
that if you would include the global programs
of the vendor, you might see that, for example,
all for people to know the future.
Or they're high in the people region.
They're yet to be split effectors,
to be protected to the boss,
that you would see a worsening of the issue.
So we can try to attract villain loss people.
That's when the city of the service,
You can try to attract the middle of the law, so it's back to the city.
But this place is people from these neighborhoods who cannot order their
anymore. So this is whose poverty elsewhere?
Yeah.
Question?
[inaudible]
Well, I must admit that I don't go all the imitators in this specific index, but I guess
it will be about average income, unemployment, I may be some other indicators that say
something about this name.
But I should have put this.
So much of what we see here confirms this ID of Slater
when clicking in that well, trying to create a social mix
in some parts of the city.
Will shift poverty will make a poverty move elsewhere.
I will create, that's what Slater said,
will create over concentrations of poverty.
This is just down the street in shallow go up
are the case of these gentry flying neighborhoods of Brussels, in bone for the gentry flying.
So that's where in medicine, in Berlin, in other parts of these urban regions.
There are examples in the world where mixed neighborhoods are being created.
But then it's only possible when city councils or governments can have a serious
impact upon who is living in specific neighborhoods.
In some parts of the world, scholars write about conclusion that we housing or inclusion
every zoning forcing for example real estate developers who devour a high tower
full of apartments to dedicate a certain percentage of these residents
residential units to people who fall below a certain income threshold and so
you can create a social-emixed neighborhood. If you force real estate developers to
well in a newly built project, you have a certain percentage of apartments,
of four people, of the certain, in people, are fully low-surfing in countries.
In Enter, I've been talking about this Catholic's neighborhood. This was the land of the port in
public hands. And so, this is the council could also sell this land to developers with a lot of
conditions. And so, developers could buy this land under the condition that they built 25% of the
There is digital units for social housing, 15% rent, 10% to buy.
And then they reserved 50% of the units at affordable prices.
And that was not very affordable, but at least you could not ask whatever you wanted.
This prices could not skyrocket.
You could not ask whatever you wanted for these residential units.
And so you could argue, a socially mixed neighborhood has been developed here almost from
scratch because only it's white.
The looks that you see here are new and only the brown ones exist.
But that was possible because the land was public owned and could be sold to developers
under the condition that the reserve is kind of.
it's for certain degrees of people. And I make a look who is able to rent or buy these units
without in case you can follow a certain income threshold in order to be able to be eligible
for the social housing. Yes. The same goes for this affordability criteria. I don't know how
what was the price exactly. But I see here that you could earn up to 58,000 euro of
family, almost 4,000 euro added for each additional person. So we are buying quite high
incomes already. But the bottom line is that these developers could not just build whatever
they want. That they need to meet certain criteria and that they also need to serve
Why the British number of units for people belong to different income units.
At the lowest income, the degrees, social housing, and then the points of house to work.
So, a socially mixed neighborhood when it comes to income, when it comes to poverty and wealth,
could be created. But that was only possible because there was a serious intervention
of the Sydney Council in this.
In Belgium, the government or public authorities
are not really able to intervene that much in housing.
Because it's only days of blasters, 6% of the units,
which are social housing.
In Brussels are 10% and all the risks,
the development sessions, minor exceptions,
all the rest is the market.
It's either people who are home, house,
or people who rent the house from another market.
But there are cities across the world
where you have 50% social house in that workshop
or under the dump is another small,
a high percentage of social house.
That also means that as a council,
you can be to be quite a bit in who it is where.
in the dodging days where 90% of the people need to find a house or accommodation on the market,
you will see that attempts to create a social mix quickly lead to displacement and quickly
lead to concentrations of poverty elsewhere.
And this is very much the dependent on how this particular house mix looks like and how much
because the councils can interfere in the housing.
(mumbling)
- So it's a place?
- There has been a time when the social housing association
sold out of the white, some units, that they know it is.
In any case, there's no research.
And these type of files are a project for the developer.
This question will be, I will be in the chat.
As long as they can still make profits, this is possible.
The same goes for this inclusion of housing.
as long as the developer is able to take profits, then this is also.
In this case, I know that the developers have to pay a lot of money to sit and get this piece of debt.
And because they were also asked to cater for these public sectors, they had to develop the parts and the streets.
And they have to say that in the local social house, to the city quit it very much more money by selling this piece of land for the highest price to develop and to build a sparkles for the obvious people who chose to do things different.
And there are many parts of the world where we have this kind of skis.
Yeah.
[ Inaudible ]
Okay.
Is social mixed feasible?
The answer is yes.
In this feasible, it is possible to create socially mixed neighborhoods,
but it is very hard to do that in a situation where the market rates,
and because then trying to attract middle-class families
who are poor neighborhoods will lead to displacement of poor families
to other parts of the country.
In this case, that will not happen, because you reserve
25% of the neighborhood to people who fall below a certain interest zone.
And as long as these units are social housing, these 35% will remain there for this
population.
So you allow people to live in a neighborhood where 50% belongs to
a village loss from the upper middle of the class and 25% of these units goes to a
baby, which people can afford to spend one million here or one.
Another question?
Yeah, I have a question.
For instance, it would be like,
social takes early in this one,
for instance, areas, areas of the city.
But then when in this view, I'm asking for an example, actually,
can't wear a capitol of the city.
For example, for keeping, I mean,
just from experience,
to work out, I don't know,
for example, usually if you are,
like very up-to-date luxury, the lane there are so affordable and so powerful.
However, this has been changed if it's given up to a track.
So it might be different people of different things from the system.
But then the general effect was actually that it's upper class and the capitalist developed.
It's not like actually the people who are living there beforehand and maybe I could reserve a
It's a good question. I think in this case
People who lived there were just a fish that were ready that was not so much the case yet because you only had a couple of hundreds of people
You develop a neighborhood for thousands of people
It was a neighborhood that was more true than it was.
That was not so much worse.
Just, I guess it was, of course, like,
when there's a, when there's an example of
gensification, people all around it,
and not really attempting to solve.
They're trying to
[INAUDIBLE]
Well, I guess it depends how you will argue the 100th.
Also, you would say that your vacation goes with displacement
and displacement with the essential part of the change of education.
In this case, there might be a displacement
of the people who lived in these brown houses.
And who lived there already before the rest of the neighborhoods,
before the white parts of the neighborhoods,
were being concerned.
But there will not be a place in these 25% units,
which are either rented out or sold as social house.
Because you will need to fall below a certain income
order to buy or rent these goods. And no matter what happens in the rest of the day's
request, the students will still remain like reserves for people following those income
threshold. So this is a way to make sure that these places will not happen. Even if you
buy these kind of, you will not be able to sell them, and if you rent them out, then this is
There's also another condition that's followed below.
So it's just the average.
But it's only applied to the red part here.
Yeah, indeed.
That's the current moment.
Everything else at this whole area has been
identified that has been over-renewaled in this whole area.
So it's only in that very small part,
where they were able to create a solution.
So this is the my area of it though.
Is it really achieving a solution?
Yeah, one important thing is to scale the scale of which we discuss things.
Now we are talking about a very small scale neighborhood of a couple of thousand people.
But indeed, if you discuss it at the scale of Enter,
then you will see that this whole area around this red square that we've just been talking about has been going through
and improvement of this, this advantage in mix and has been going through
at, at very strong gender education. Sorry, that's, they're completely just a
fairly fair film. I don't need violence. I'm sorry. But then I'm just curious
how it works here. Like, um, due to the private health, we can get tax based
or like, and it's from the government or the YH.
It's from the government because I was a member.
Well, I don't know about these these
thanks for your base, but for sure the length price
for which they were able to acquire this.
Well, the price for which they were able to buy this piece
of length from the city council was much lower
than it would have been just a market with a firm.
OK.
Okay, is it yeah more questions? Okay now we move to the next question. This
is it good or bad?
Is it desirable to create such a name?
Now, I'm going to say in the globe,
the kind of shops that you find really good with that.
The most big caters for the needs and the desires
of this 75% of residents and a lot of tourists
and visitors who like to visit the market.
And so that could be a reason to say, well,
it's not desirable to do this.
because these people will not find cheap food in the area
for the kind of problems they would like to buy.
But that shows that we are moving to the next question,
the social mix desire.
I guess it would be time for a break.
I'm running a bit behind some into.
I'm wondering there is a three hours or a decade
to over-joker.
Boston has been limiting by Boston powers.
We've been big for all, we have a goal of its power
just two hours and one for us.
Okay, I'll just go to the slides.
We'll see, we'll see what time, what time,
but I think it's better to have a great job
before moving to this next question.
is a desirable way to start with five minutes and then we continue.
(coughing)
[coughing]
[Music]
[inaudible]
very random question but I can't find her.
Can you hear me?
This is a bit harder except you're coming back.
Well, James, I should be able to pass the roll.
That would be great.
I'm going to get a seat.
I want to hear a...
Oh, no.
I want to get a seat.
But I want to get a seat.
(inaudible)
(mumbling)
[inaudible]
And it was really a secret note of that, it was so hard.
(crowd chattering)
[inaudible]
(crowd chatter)
[ Inaudible ]
(audience chatter)
[inaudible]
(mumbling)
[ Inaudible ]
[inaudible]
I'm going to go to the library right now.
[laughter]
I was going to go to the library right now.
I said, "You're still here, right now."
[ Inaudible ]
[inaudible]
(inaudible)
(mumbling)
[inaudible]
I'll say what's up girl.
And I'm gonna try and find a friend with him.
It's not the problem.
I just wanna be a little bit crazy.
I'm gonna try and find a friend with him.
[Music]
which I propose to continue.
[ Inaudible ]
>> So let's continue with this question
by social mixed desire.
[ Inaudible ]
I think I need to skim the question number four or part number four.
But in any case, I'm really excited to go into the arguments here.
And the overarching assumption amongst policy-makers and also in the dominance of high-pumpies
Amongst researchers seems to be that very good lift affects your life chances. Whether you lift an end to work in this line clock, this social housing estate, live power.
or whether you live as a poor person in un
And they make their residence verse 4.
Maybe two observations before I were looking to the different arguments,
the difference and the ways in which this question has been answered.
Observation number one is that researchers working in different subdisciplines
I've been showing you this diagram last week already.
Research is working in different sub disciplines
of human geography, urban studies, or broadly.
Have been answering this question, different?
A rareal two positions, a lot later on the map.
What kind of geographer is he?
Do you have an ID?
Mark says geographer, they're writing about the capitalistic
of protection.
And he's a Marxist chauffeur.
And he's mainly interested in social economic issues.
Yeah?
What happens to poor people when they live in a poor neighborhood?
Other chauffeur first have been asking different police
members, for example, in the ancient New York,
and the cultural segregation.
as a whole article by
my paper and
whose written deals with
ethnic segregation
and not with
social and economic
segregation
amongst his children
children for such as
false later
only interested in
social and economic
segregation
and who are at the reach
people live
and this is that meaning for
in the eradication of poverty for example
so you see that different
have been asking different research questions when it comes to these effects of
segregation. They have also been using different research mental
colleges. We use large surveys. They have a survey of 1,000 people in order to
answer these questions or do you have called it negative research where you
the Interfuge Thirds Fellows,
and we're 13 people living in a thing,
or this place from a thing.
So different research,
mental politics,
and then you've also been reading
in the article by Adam Slather,
that that might also be different ideology
under things,
underlying the work of these different.
So I think it is important for you
to understand that just like I,
I could last week for the courses of segregation
and the different arguments that have been given
for why people live in segregated neighborhoods.
And also when it comes to these effects of segregation
as a role that's been showed around that
that people are working in different conditions
and different sub-disaboots of human geography
have been giving different answers
to these questions.
Another remark that I want to give before going
to the answer to that question is that it is important
to see that studies on neighborhood effects
bear birthmarks.
What do I need with that?
Is it matters to bear a study of the eclipse?
And then often, for example, the literature
of the effects of segregation.
Conducting studies conducted in the United States,
the conclusions of these studies have been used, for example,
to influence policy in Western Europe.
And a while it is quite important to see the differences
between these different contexts.
Last week, I have been highlighting, for example,
that when it comes to desegregation,
in the United States, the United States is much stronger or prevalent than it is
in Europe.
So there's an important difference when you take the conclusions from one country to
the other.
The welfare states in Western Europe has been much more developed than in the United States.
So when it comes to poverty and the eradication of poverty, this is a completely different
issue in a Western European context.
And this is an American.
So it's important that you contextualize studies
on segregation in the United States, for example.
And then just to not transfer these conclusions
to Europe.
Many of the studies on neighborhood effects
and the effects of segregation have been conducted in the Netherlands.
And also this Dutch context is a very peculiar one.
Where, for example, concerns about the value,
and also to see there, or particularly neighborhoods
in Amsterdam have been quite important in stimulating
research field. And being for dying, I don't know whether you're interested in going.
But this far-right whole addition to the Netherlands have always been proper for two decades already, have been kept forward.
And that's also important to understand why this research field has been sort of developed in the Netherlands.
So important to provincialized students and to understand that a study in Vienna or in
Antwerp or in Brussels or in the United States that it's important to contextualize,
to understand the specificities of this particular context.
I have seven answers to this question.
Have you remember the question?
Can impoverished neighborhoods make the residents
worse off or when I'm interested in
ethnic cultural segregation and neighborhoods
with the concentration of people for origin
make integration more difficult?
Um, seven different arguments.
The first one, the social network
I think many of you might have heard of Robert Pootman, focusing on social capital,
but the social capital, the connections among the visuals, the social networks, the
norms of reciprocity.
There's the rules of desiring and trustworthiness that arise from, making a distinction
between holding capital, what is falling capital.
These are social methods, connections, loans, or reciprocity that means socially homogeneous
people.
For example, people of the same ethnicity are people of the same social and economic group.
Distinction between only and bridging them of the preaching of the capital, being connections,
that works, loans, and reciprocity, and transporatiness, being socially heterogeneous.
For example, people of different ethnic countries are people of different social economies.
And the argument is often that rich in capital is important for social mobility.
And for example, if you're poor from your middle class neighbor, you will meet here about
jobs.
And it is a version who's working.
And there is a job opportunity that
office workers, persons, persons in my chair is
knowledge, but she might share it with his
worker name.
Work and ready to do not speak Dutch, it might
be good to have this wide middle class
family, this university council.
So interested in living next to you, because
you maybe they can help yourself or go
with homework as they speak.
So these are the ideas behind this argument,
saying, well, it's good to have mixed neighborhoods,
because this mixed neighborhoods with leads to heterogeneous networks
that will lead to bridging capital,
and that will make importance.
That will be to the benefit of poor people living in such an effort.
And so one reason why you would want to create a social
expert is because you want to create heterogeneous social
networks.
Because you assume that rich in capital will help poor people
to be socially mobile and to join with it.
And for example, through education or through jobs.
And so this is one of the seven arguments
that underpins this ideal of social works.
But I'm going to study how people live.
It turns out that people are rather mobile in a city
to not limit their lives to a particular neighborhood.
And that many of the social networks
that people in a neighborhood spend
different neighborhood borders.
And this is a study from Guangzhou in China.
looking at the social networks of people living in four different types of
neighborhoods and in each of these neighborhoods the conclusion is that most
people get to know people through work and spend time with colleagues also after
after working hours. Many people also get to know people through kinship from a
childhood to schools of
graduate children.
And then are actually quite
a small amount of
social mentors in each of these
neighborhoods, less than that
percent.
And, well, you look at the
social connections of these people.
There's quite a small amount that
helps in these neighborhoods.
And no matter the reach of the four
types of neighborhoods that
People seem to develop mostly boats,
connections in that works with people from outside this language.
And so this idea that by bringing the middle of the last work,
the middle of the last two of the middle of the neighborhood,
that this would be a way to create these social networks.
And when you look at this, then the social networks also develop outside.
So why do you focus so much on that neighborhood that people live?
I'm just very
[inaudible]
In other countries you mean
the situation would be different.
I told you it's important to understand the complex
and the context of this study.
But in any case, also for which
that European cities, if you're
a study, this process is over time.
I think you would find out that
connections are less neighborhood-based
than they used to.
I can imagine that this neighborhood
is more than being an organ.
People still get to know a lot
of other families, for example,
through their children, through the school,
in many countries of the world.
You have a school kitchen system
where living in a neighborhood
and sending your kids to the same school.
And so for sure there are many reasons
why this would be different in other countries.
Have an overall, I think this argument is still true
that there are also many social networks
that have outside the neighborhood.
Of course, I also studies that focus on
foreign neighborhoods and say,
well, these people are less mobile and rich people.
So it's exactly for the school people that this neighborhood is an important
ground of network for each. Much more than this one, which you know.
If you do not have a joke, if you do not have the money to buy a best-in-game club, that is neighborhood context will be a form of form for social networks to develop.
So also for different countries, people this might be.
But still I think it's important to see that that merge is another one we've felt inside
the paper.
That there are also networks in other parts of the city, or with people living in other parts
of the city.
German, drawing, white, double-inkled,
families to a neighborhood such as molar make.
And here is possible, well, then
make these networks, a study by Sabina Rick
and like a un-person in German cities.
I think it was not explored in the food area.
And they have been interviewing the white,
middle class people in this example to women
about their social net.
And there's quite a lot on this diet,
everybody might need to explain it.
So you see they're women in the middle.
And then you have different scales in the neighborhoods.
You have the city.
You have Germany, and you have outside of Germany.
So people who are the important people in your life,
ask that, and if you put them on this diagram saying,
well, there are people inside the neighborhood,
people living in the same city,
but you also know people in the same country
and people also being grown.
And for different people, you would get to different diagrams.
Then what they also did is to map contact frequency.
So if you have frequent buildings, this arrow will be born both then it is for people through
you to have rare contacts.
And then they also have met a level of education and indicators for class in the Indian
countries.
So you will learn these people that you frequent are they people with the same educational
background.
They would cost people high education,
high-educated, or artists people who do not have
any personal qualifications for this one.
Now, the other thing that you see here
is the type of relation to a frequent
these people or really provide you with emotional support
or instrumental materials or a good talk,
or example, how to be used in poverty.
So it's quite a complex map.
So what you see is that first of all, just like in the Chinese example, many people have
social networks, there are Bartovus social networks with people living outside the neighborhoods.
And what you also see there is that most of the connections that these middle-class women
in these under-religious neighborhoods develop are with other people with the same
education qualification.
So the idea that bringing the middle of class people
to an underprivileged neighborhood
will create that an routine is social networks
in which you're finding more enriched people.
There's no single whole truth here.
There's a middle class people that's
you're attracted to these neighborhoods.
The eight mostly social bonds with people like them
with other middle and false people.
And so this bridging capital,
That was the reason why you wanted to exist,
neighborhood.
That's not really the problem.
Another argument is that creating a mixed neighborhood
might disrupt the strong dice that exist there over it.
The bolding capital that exists
and the strong forms of social economic,
emotional support that people are the same,
that Mississippi, for example, provides you
when they live in a neighborhood,
part of the city.
So residents living in distant parts of cities,
slaves are argued, fall back on what they know,
and what they have each other,
this building can also be crucial in the life's home
for people, in the lives of newcomers,
where just arrived to the city,
they were looked for all that excursed,
And if you create a mixed neighborhood in these parts of common, for example, by attracting
the middle class, there will display some people and that will disrupt these bone-in-capped
open-assists.
And so what I'm trying to do is to say, well, there is an argument there, why you would
to create mixed neighborhoods, which are also left
a couple of cancer arguments.
That's the why this argument is
by not to work or to hold a reason
and applying the argument to my not to work.
Social networks, social capital,
owning and bridging capital.
I guess you have a few kinds of points there.
The second argument is called under-place arguments.
And this is an argument that has developed in the United States
in the 1980s.
And then finding that there was a big discussion
between structuralists who looked at the causes of poverty
in the declining economic base.
And for example, Marxist, Trevor first saying, well, there
is a shift from a forest to a post-fortress capitalism.
And this makes it harder for this people to fight with chocolate.
or the arguments that you've heard in the classes by the past of our polarization,
is there a declining job market for this.
So you look for structure of a goal of a scope forward.
And on the other hand, you have culture groups,
except poverty is dead because you have a culture of poverty.
That poor people have certain attitudes,
have a certain behavior, and this keeps them in poverty.
there was an important discussion between these two.
And this under-class argument is part of this cultural
history of looking at forward.
And whom is this under-class?
They're not talking about all four people
in the case of the United States.
In the 1980s, 33 million people were not.
Who was this under-class that was a minority
in this minority, 5 million people.
And people who follow below the income threshold
for which they are like considered to work.
This proportionally black and spelling minority
in this poor minority, but what defines
that's not so much over the ordinary base,
but they're behavior.
They're throwing lawlessness,
to reduce out of record words, lack of a warm and welfare dependency
for school faith.
That is sort of this culture, this lane to the poor,
to be poor because of their own behavior and very
able to do this.
And so this is this under-class argument.
So what is the argument exactly that in kettles or in neighborhoods
So you find the concentration of two people that you find is more than an employment, more
welfare dependency, more early school living, more truancy, more criminality, more drug
abuse, more alcohol abuse, more out of rent with birth, more teenage pregnancy, more
dysfunctional values, whatever, that in June to socialization effects within
these things, if you grow up in a neighborhood like that, then your peers, people of
your age, the people that you're free and grow at a higher chance to be criminals or
or gamblers or drug users or alcohol abuse, etc.
And that is why in such a route you find more on this.
You also find a leg of role models really
junk without a drug without an alcohol
prediction and who are not the age followers, etc.
So there's a leg of those are the role models.
And you also have this peer group effect.
And so why are you worse off living as a poor person
in a poor neighborhood, the argument of this culture,
this was, that is because you have these norms,
you have a lack of these role models
and you have this peer group that makes it made that,
well, that's why it's your worst off living in them.
And I also referred to physical structure,
the solution of that works, the argument was, no.
This has been quite an important argument.
Many policymakers have been facing or helping
argue in first-person countries because of this.
Because they were convinced that living in an appornable
group increased the chances that you
found the job-less important thing.
These schools early and because of your friends doing the same,
you up to school because your friends met you so as well that you would
turn into a criminal because this is the example that you have seen most
they have already put that set up.
Okay now even when there would be a link between what is on the left and
the spoon neighborhoods then it can still be wondered whether that what is
the causal relationship between these two. Here on the map you have
She's got her again since we are getting quite familiar with.
You see the poverty level in this neighborhood.
The darker the reds, the poorer the neighborhoods are.
And you see people arrested for drug use or the
or the conversation of authors.
How you see there is that there is a correlation
between over D and the concentration of over D
is neighborhood and use of one of your while there, right?
Go getting the scratch scanner, which more is patterned.
But you also see that in the other neighborhoods where you have a concentration of poverty
that this much less begins.
And I can also wonder to what extent this graph is the result of real drug use or the
policing of these standards.
If you have a police force that is much more on the outlook for drug use instead of the
the name of the Goodswell bank.
It's logical that this will show up in any step distance.
So there are many reasons why one could raise
concerns about the goals of a relationship.
In this case, we could introduce, on the one hand,
and the concentration of over-theon public
on Goods, as Dr. Kritis says, like, how
these statistics came about.
One can also see that for certain drugs,
there seems to be a correlation from other certain health.
So I can also see that you have concentrated poverty that corresponds with a lot of errors
for drug use, but that you also have neighborhood with concentration concentrated poverty
or less, which means.
So there are many reasons why we would start a question whether there is a real causal
relationship, a relationship, a concentration of poverty on the one hand, and all these
other indicators here on the slide on the other hand.
And another argument against this under-class argument would be, well, again, socialization
be these peers to not only live in these neighborhoods.
These role models do not only live in the neighborhood, but where I go back, but also
in the neighborhood, that we can get this role almost 23 or the music that we're going to
So why is focused on the neighborhood again?
Third argument, the social cohesion argument.
Here you see the basic line of thought of this argument,
when ethnic minorities live isolated from native touch,
they have less contact with native touch.
Consequently, they do not acquire
an adequate command of the Dutch language are not likely to adopt
Dutch laws, values, and will not succeed in social recognitions.
So, you can see a mixing of arguments about ethnic segregation and social
economic mobility, saying that well, if you're lived in a neighborhood with a high
concentration of people of foreign backgrounds to speak their mother tongue
and we will be able to speak in touch.
And if you have less contact with native Dutch people,
then you will not acquire an adequate command of language.
You are not likely to adopt Dutch moments and values,
and therefore you succeed in social networks.
And other arguments that has been quite important
In the kind of rethorex and the kind of discourse of policy makers
that are advocating a social mix, same for example,
it's not good that in wall make you have a high-down
situation of firms or in both the larger, high-down situation of workers.
Why is that not good?
Well, these people will not get to speak.
Touch and they will not integrate to use that word.
They will not adopt touch laws and values
and that will make it harder for them to climb to social weather.
Again, one can wonder, yeah, is it only in the neighborhood
that people could get a chance to develop this kind of relationships
with native Dutch human arguments to talk to.
We could look at these research, too.
I'm not going to do all the details that they say about you.
home, that's a place where people develop social networks.
You've got leisure,
you've got digital,
you've got mental health,
social networks,
you've got work,
and you've got the transport between
these three different domains.
So it's important to look at all these domains
and to see what happens between people.
And then you might see that this neighborhood
in which these people live is less important.
Another counter-argument with focus
or is a local culture.
It's only because you have a concentration
of people who are certain ethnic background, for example,
that you can support the show that sells ethnic products
and sell the food, that sells the food from the home group,
where it allows you to have the church or a association
that focusing on a particular ethnic group.
And these kinds of places might be very important.
they will act as a perfected space,
they will act as a safe space,
in which these people feel like they're home.
And this feeling of belonging might be very important
for them to find a life in this new country
where they are living.
The social cohesion argument.
Before the argument, we'll focus on local services.
And we'll say that, for example, in neighborhoods
with the concentration of poverty that you
will have less public and private services.
There will be less shops.
There will be less banks.
And you might also have less public service.
These are examples from Luvibong, social housing
estate that I've been talking about today already.
and the closure of a bank.
And there is no ADM anymore in other papers.
And the argument could go well
if that would be more middle to false people
than there would be higher interest
from banks who have an ADM in the bank
or other shops.
Chicago, food deserts, I don't know
that you've ever heard about this term.
If you look at healthy food, grocery,
shops, American, you find that,
if you see a map with these different racial groups,
remember this self identification in the case,
America that deserve each racial group to self identify
with the United States.
You see neighborhoods, predominantly white,
like Hispanic Asian, a nurse,
and you see that in many of these blank neighborhoods,
which are also luxurious neighborhoods,
you find that it's very hard to find.
Healthy food that's very hard to find fresh vegetables
and fruit, because these shops are so fine.
And so the argument would be that its better degree,
it makes neighborhood, because that will attract
a library set of shops and services to these neighborhoods.
We've already been talking about this,
that the question of course is what kind of shops
and what kind of services do you get
in the case of this end to our advantage of this street
one person said, well,
the people will not feel affordable shops
and they will also not find the products
that apply to five shops.
That's also in gentrifying neighborhoods
and what kind of shops do you find there?
as it shows catering for people who look for the cheapest or possible because they have
only five heroes to spend in the last three days of the month, or visit cafes or restaurants
who try to cater for these incoming, tenured pups.
So it's important to look at the difference in the amount that will result from creating
and so the question is if you mix name routes through these shops and services
cater for these cool people because if there's something case then it will
displace the shops that existed there already and that cater for these
audience. The answer we've also been talking about all of these specialized
services that you might get in neighborhoods of Rhode Island at these ony transfer
or a full shot set of African vegetables or high ingredients.
And the question is if you try to mix the neighborhoods,
do these kinds of shops and these kinds of services still be able to be to remain
or will they also be displaced because this place will be involved by a fancy
see, probably shown that it's mainly
catarities and changing farmers.
So questions around shops, services,
catering for different audits.
A fifth argument that you find in the literature
is a political one.
Start from the observation that many neighborhood associations,
for example are mainly run by middle class.
And that middle class people are much more vocal
in expressing their concerns from the paper.
So I'm gonna say that, well,
by attracting the middle class to a poor neighborhood,
this neighborhood will be higher
for the political agenda.
And I have this quote interprome
and I have read at the end of the excursion,
which I've got a lot in my channel,
for people stating,
"Well, there also gets paid or sliding to this."
To us.
And so the idea is that I'm mixing neighborhoods,
you will put these neighborhoods higher.
Jen, I'm in Belgium, people from outside the youth
with other buildings in Oxford are able to fold
this film not getting case in every country, so if you have a neighborhood with a lot of people
from outside the group, who do not have a say in vocal politics, then why would this
vocal mayors address the concerns of people living? And if these people are not able to
express their needs and to put a stamp on the vocal agenda, but why would you do it?
So the argument is that really class people are able to have these connections with politicians
or at least they will be listened to.
Well, I'm not going to go into that example, but it's out with the enter of highway
that issue of air pollution to be observation
with both of the paper groups lying next to the library
are up.
So one would question what would happen
with this whole issue of the only dates around the highway.
If these neighborhoods would want to,
to neighbors, the voters would come,
the broader than they would be the highest
if they would be the show that they did.
So the political arguments by mixing neighborhoods,
you will put that higher on the political agenda.
Of course, the issue is that why we put the issues of this,
who even, why does that not have priorities
made for the result of the political agenda,
without these middle-class residents.
The sixth argument is a bit different.
The spatial mismatch does not focus so much
on the issue of segregation.
But if you follow these five dimensions of--
We see a benefit it focuses on concentration plus red doe pool people live in which part
of the city are these neighborhoods with the concentration of poverty.
This is a diagram from Cape Town but in old London it's still very much the case.
Where do you have a job of her students in white and where do you have population?
where do people live and where do they, where, where could they?
And most of the drug opportunities are still in the previous new white neighborhoods, particularly
in the central business district of Cape Town.
But most of the poor people in Cape Town are living by far away from these places.
So there is a mismatch between the places where they live and the places where they could
potential, burning.
And so it's not just important to focus on segregation
and the fact that poverty is concentrated
in these more peripheral neighborhoods
in the case of big dive.
The genetic focus then also of distance
between various neighborhoods are
and the places where these people put through.
So there is the spatial mismatch
are focusing on the mismatch between
place of residence and potential places of the world.
Rest in European cities, then to have a better public transport than most American for
cyber.
So one of the other big issues is argument to the whole list through in the case of Brussels
for example, even if you live in a field world, there are good train connections to
of nature places. This is a meant for Brussels, Joe Ben City, you see two clusters, the inner city,
and all these offices, and the area around the airport. Where the poor people in Brussels
lived mostly in this 19th century, boats around the inner city, meaning that there's not so
So much of the spatial mismatch.
If you live in all of make, you can walk to many job opportunities.
Of course, the question that this barely
have most guilt job opportunities.
Or if you don't need all of communication,
then you see that more or less the same clusters
appear.
Of course, as jokes shift towards the airport,
the issue is what are the transport connections
between Wollumbeg, St. Joseph, the Wollus, and Joseph,
and these areas where you find the growth
of most new, or most new jobs.
And in the case of Brussels, the issue will also be,
whether the language requirements for these jobs,
because these are Joseph flowers,
what kind of a touch proficiency to a need,
and also for these jobs that are repulsion, French,
and you also English, so just language wise,
these jobs are already quite difficult.
So the spatial mismatch argument focusing
on the location of these poor neighbors.
So it's not just how mixed these neighborhoods are,
whether poor and rich, they decide
by side, but where do these concentrations
of overty occur?
Last argument statement is each,
And this is an argument that Slater has been writing about
is important to look what happens outside
of these neighborhoods under scrutiny.
And why is it harder to climb the social weather
and body of it on all of the developments
because teachers who live outside these neighborhoods
from where the set of stereotypes or pupils in these schools
and that will look different at the same educational
chances as people going to school in other meetings.
Or if you're both going to this, and you know
what is the post-code report, what made with you,
apply for a joke, then you, okay,
you're one thousand meters.
If you have a driver, a joke, and this is your address
is there, then potential and borders
might already come to the center of stereotypes,
why not too high?
So why would it be good then to create the social mix?
Well, one could create a one-point argue for a social mix
because that will reduce the stigma of attitudes
or the stigma attached to this gap.
Of course, there might also be other ways
to work on that stigma.
You don't need a mix to do that.
You also can make people living outside this neighborhood.
So you can make that more air off.
And what this really happens is silence and the difference.
There's a bit of stigmatization, life of nature,
employers or teachers or police men
who are working in this neighborhood,
but who do not live there,
will be another argument to buy social mix is necessary.
So are people living in impoverished prisons?
Well, doesn't matter whether you are poor,
mostly poor neighborhoods surrounded by people like you.
or whether you live as a poor person in a mixed name.
Just that matter.
And our seventh arguments that I have given down
as to why that could matter.
For each of these seven,
I've also given a couple of counter-audicates.
As to why I creating a mixed,
it should be a bad thing to distract,
to advise that exists already.
are is not necessary because people find peers and role models outside the environment.
For people with a class, people arrive in these neighborhoods, well not create social networks,
different people, this better order, etc. So for each of these arguments, I've given
a couple of counter arguments. What about the privilege? I will skip that. But in
those data spaper you will find many arguments for that. I will get to a small conclusion.
Okay, so when we discuss this ideal of social mix, when we discuss the question of
which is social mixed feasible, is social mixed desirable.
Now, when it's my take on it, I think,
of his home and we,
who has been doing a lot of vertical housing
here in Brussels,
has summarized this quite well through.
The concept of social mixed here runs,
which now legitimizes a good part
of the regional interventions
in the area of housing here in Brussels,
just looking at the Brussels step of the region
and how the idea of social mixed-minded concept
of social mixed-
is occurring to a very non-spading conference,
the gentrification reaches underweight
in the central neighborhoods,
in those neighborhoods where these authorities are doing
in a big effort to attract valid possible products.
Indicates that when there is a mix,
it is only a prelude to the eviction of the most disadvantaged
fire the mechanisms of a completely
deteriorated real estate market.
Really in a city,
where only 10% of the total residential units
our social house, and there is almost no control over the remaining 90%.
And so if you try to attract little class residents to these 19th century industrial labor books
around Brussels, if you do that, then it will push out over the elsewhere. You see that in the
the snap of a tree, where there are these poor people moving out of a gentrifying
nature, started it both to build on to oust, to really get into the hollow, to
shower the water, to my shadow. Yeah, you move over the elsewhere. So when there
is a mix, you can exist for a while, but then it's only a privilege to be a
fiction of most is a fantasy. Because rents will go up eventually. And these poor
people that live there are not able to afford these rents,
they will need to move elsewhere to find the next mistake.
So this social makes feasible in the case of Brussels,
with very little control of authorities on the housing market.
No, this is not feasible, shall we?
Is it desirable?
A second question that I asked.
Even if this eviction could be a forked,
And even if you think of a situation where at much, 25% social housing everywhere, 50%
and you will not evict these poor people from these neighborhoods,
then she argues there is nothing to indicate that these disadvantaged populations would eventually
benefit in any rate from these nips.
F1 because the attraction of this middle league penalties will change the shops for
a regular, will not lead to these heterogeneous networks that these policy makers three
and off.
Yeah, will not lead to the kind of social cohesion that underlies this social cohesion.
does not make the kind of role models that people who
believe in the spendery class argument
who are looking for, et cetera.
And so she's arguing in the case of Brussels again,
it's important to revitalize these studies
and to understand the complexity of the Brussels case
only 10% social housing over the at this moment
concentrated in neighborhoods with quite a critical
very close to these jobs.
And so there are many particularities that we need to understand.
But what is arguing is that kind of social mix
that this person's capital picture tries to create
leads to the displacement of people,
to neighborhoods, to parts of the city,
which are much less connected to job opportunities.
I refined much less jobs and services that paid the for this.
That's right.
So to much worse locations actually.
And even if this kind of mixed could be realized,
she argues, then this is not desirable.
Then this advantage population will not benefit from this.
This will not help them to plan the social better.
As she will draw on all the seven counter arguments
that I've given to substantiate this claim.
So, well, I think when you, I remember that I once asked an exam question such as
"would yourself you choose all the manner of N-word, do another manner of N-word, but
you verbal against social mixed policies or not?"
The question was a bit more complicated.
I think it's important that when you have such a question,
when you have a group for a city already
who has discussed this from an academic point of view,
I think there are a couple of questions
that you need to ask yourself.
Yes.
The first one is whom are we talking about?
Why do we treat?
Why do we want to create a social mix?
Isn't because we say, well, this is the interest
under privilege or I've skipped now most of this at heart.
The class could also be interested in the privilege.
I mean, I'm a member of the original Scout,
one of the richer, richer richest municipalities of Belgium
and some of you said well,
it could be good to have some more diverse
years because people like, for example,
change the way they think about people
they have some of them living close by.
You see that all of the arguments so far have been dealing with the unknown group. So for that reason, I think it's important to ask your question, what about the crucial questions. And in the discussion, seven years that we as next week, there will be one paper that happens together with the real male and post-galbert, they could deal with the question. So we have a chance to come back to the issue.
and we have discussions.
Do we only focus on social economic segregation?
Are we also interested in ethnic arguments?
And you're seeing, for example,
a social cohesion argument, the two are conflated.
So do we want to create a social mix
in the interest of ethnic minorities
or does that have a majority,
that still exists because more and more cities
in Belgium do not have a majority of people.
So we also think about this group,
frankly, to problemate such policies.
Are we interested in the several residents who
are there already, who are we mainly thinking
about few cops for the horizons?
So I think this question for whom
So we want to create a social experience.
And most interests is the first one that you should ask.
A second one is the issue of scale.
I told you last week already, scale
is the crux of the matter.
If you want to calculate segregation finishes,
it matters that we scale, we do so.
In Belgium, we have the straightest small statistical units
for that reason, we find that that's high levels of segregation.
And if you would make these statistical units bigger,
then that would be less segregation.
Your comment about the red square relates to this.
We can create a social mix in this very small neighborhood.
And if you would look at the bigger picture,
if you would look at this A-monch in area of emperor,
as well as all the news found out that there is no social business,
it's mostly relative to a certain level.
So I think scale is a very important issue,
as well as the question where do we want to create a social business.
I think that most of the social mixed literature
is concerned with this disadvantage, neighborhoods.
The focus is on these neighborhoods
and the need to create a social business.
If you would look at all the make, you would look at social economic position of people.
If you would look at ethnic maker of this neighborhood, you would find out that the
whole make is maybe the most social image's name roots of Russell's original culture.
And the most of the homogeneous neighborhoods are white suburban municipalities.
So why are we only concerned with this disadvantage
neighborhoods?
How are we not concerned with the homogeneity
of many of these suburban groups?
Which are better off.
Is there a need to create a social mixed slope or not?
And I've imbed a shout for those who join to enter by
be talking about the way they protest that they
can't stop training against the local asylum center
against any attempts to make this an usability.
One good even argued that most of the literature and most
of the concerns of policy leaders
target only those this advantage neighborhoods,
which are change-refiable, which have the potential
to attract really close newcomers.
Because that's good for them.
Next, then the question becomes rare is this possible.
And then enter, we have been on the triangle,
square, bowling plank.
But if you look at the houses, there are many fancy houses,
which are potential homes for rich families.
If you move more to the north, you only find
very small houses which will never attract this kind of.
Rarely I have debates about social mix,
about the needs to gentrify neighborhoods well.
Only in certain,
you know, limited amount of this is a factor.
So I think this rare question is an important,
rare, are we interested in data social issues?
You know, notice that these discussions focus
of a very limited number of neighborhoods.
Another issue is never discussed in other parts of the city.
It's also important to look at the issue of scaling
already discussed that, here again, many of our maps
only focus on and for the Russell's capital region.
But I've told you that many of these waterbed effects
have consequences in other parts of the urban region
or even other parts on the bench.
If housing prices in Brussels, Europe,
this has effects in
shall I want, this makes us walking around in
my shape of hope and see the poverty there.
And for we go to the proposal,
the filmmaking French, quite far away from Brussels
and we see these effects there,
or need over needed care.
All these municipalities are affected
by this gentrification.
So it's important that we discuss this issue at the scale of at this deep urban region.
So for whom, in whose interest do we want to create social mixed layer?
Do we want to do it?
Which neighborhoods are we actually talking about?
And then I think it's also important to focus on this wide question.
If you want to create a social use to counter-operatively or even to stimulate the
sculptural integration, then I think that there might be many policy alternatives which
are less costly and which may have much bigger effects.
I'm not going to go too much to do this, but you can imagine that you can try to combat
poverty, not through the spatial intervention, but through other kinds of social and welfare
that's correct. Is it to improve the local text bits? We've seen this course from this elder man
who gets, I think for many dozens, it still will be an important one. Why do we find gentrification
important. And why do we want to attract the middle class to the city? It is because then it's good
to learn our views of budget. But then even then, I will always be this very coloring of this is
in the interest of who people have included. And this will eventually help them by the social
that. Create social mixed-to-counter racist or
pluses stereotypes. What will that mean? I guess that would mean that we would
rethink rare and for whom we try to create a social mix. You see that in most
of the policy discourse this is quite absent. If stigmatization is one of
other reasons why living in Poland or for a government or come to a different world makes your life more difficult than other parts of the city.
It's a bit about stigmatization and discrimination.
Now what kind of spatial interventions can be needed to counter these stereotypes.
I think you would create social mixing of the three different ways.
So this is a bit of an open ended conclusion with a lot of questions, but I hope that by giving
your arguments for social mixed and cancer arguments against and by encouraging your
to think about the context in which you want to create a social mixed or not that you
are able to think critically about the effects of segregation and needs to create a social
mix or much.
And five plus seven, I propose that we almost leave it here for now.
We still have time to discuss all these issues next week in the seminar.
All these texts will deal again with patterns of segregation
and the effects are safe.
So I think it's good that we have time to discuss this next week,
Monday for the geographers and the people from planning
and have our students.
Is this information correct?
Next week Monday, we have eight papers in presentations
to discuss.
I don't see any comments.
So I suppose that this is the schedule as it is.
And then next week, Tuesday and Thursday,
we have two other seminars for students from MUSH
and Thursday students from four cities.
Yeah?
Is that correct?
Yes, all your presentations are there.
You find your names.
This is the information that I've learned from the ovens, 10 minutes.
And we will need to be a rather strict, more distracting,
that's maximum, especially having eight presentations in the first
seminar.
But also in the other seminars, I prefer to keep the time and
through limit these presentations to 10 minutes
because otherwise there's nothing applied for discussion.
These are discussions and not presentations.
So, limit your presentations to 10 minutes
include a slide with title, names, email,
I don't know all of you, so it's important
that I'm able to mark the presentations
and connect with the script arise students.
Remember that I need a core report or argument,
a link with the required readings.
Remember that we also expect all students
who have read all the papers of the required readings.
So I suppose that Slater has been read
by thanking all of our gentlemen and dessert.
And then they spoke a gentle vibe of children.
And then important in order to not to lose too much time
with technical issues, I would like all of you
to send to our power ports or ETF or whatever you're going to support your presentation.
At least 30 minutes before the seminar, to my email address, whether we transfer link to
necessary, if you want me to check with the presentation, perhaps on my computer, it's
a seven-year, but I suggest you to do that.
So maybe already evening before, and then ask me if you check with it, the power of
one's bird's room, doing it in a PDF so that the different power of one's versions
things change my eyes to change.
At least then, before the presentation, so there are items I'm to present in the future,
so let me go to the sign with the sorting of laptops and the laptops that can't make
a connection with the screen. Just to make sure that we are all able to present,
let me have time to discuss the papers and then we also allow us to discuss everything
that has been said.
and lost it.
Okay, now I'm going forward to see you next week.
[Music]
(banging)
(laughing)
[inaudible]
[Music]
(speaking in foreign language)
[ Inaudible ]
and we are trying to teach by the information. And then we are going to have a question. And then we are going to have someone with a question. And I guess I am going to say that we are going to do that. And then we have a question. So, we have a question. So, we have a question. And then these people have been added to the list.
Okay, yeah, but I've always did the toughest of one guy.
She had emailed through 40, two or thousands of kids.
She said, "Well, I can't assume the flight."
And it's a good list.
Maybe that could be a main death.
Yeah, who knew her, but I could show her.
If not for next week, then for...
I think it's a good idea.
Okay. Yeah.
I'm wondering if I want to get my work on the other hand.
So yeah.
I think I get the answer from Adam, for example.
That's what I think.
But maybe.
Yeah.
That's what I think.
My mother was in the schedule and I felt like it's the...
But that was the last thing.
And I wanted to schedule for a run.
These students as well.
but also it's things when I see it.
So I don't know how to use these blue key.
Yeah, sounds.
Okay.
So I can go through the window below.
We're on this side.
Yes.
Thank you.
I want to--
Okay.
I'm actually thinking about we have to write for four
[INAUDIBLE]
So the first thing is, can we
call like any project that aims to attract
and the quality of life in a neighborhood like this.
Don't blame the taxi in this kind of project.
Can we call the our social mix projects?
- But they also have a project.
So, we should also say that that's 100%.
That's a little.
Or, or, if still that, not really just.
infr
and so we're seeing that people are too busy, they're important to attract another guy and he's seen this.
So then you can see that this is what things are.
Do you have any few have already some references that talk about Brussels when I feel
I'm also in the presentation I've not shown that there is quite a rich video of
your opinion.
So if I look at this big result I will find some more.
Well I think you will find a lot of all my beautiful benefits from ownership support policies
in Brussels that's where this quote comes from.
And Madhu van Krikeen moving in out of Brussels.
Madhu of his work is on gentrification, but you also see that some of his papers deal with social
mixed and relation to gentrification specifically. So there's a lot of work.
And the other thing that I don't know if I'm mistaken, but I have the impression that
There's not actually evidence that some people actually are like you presented some arguments,
but they're not pretty.
What advice is it's already?
Well, I love superstitions and...
Well, I think that if I'm given an old paper, just why they could show me,
trying to find out who can be the effects and showing that there are some pieces where
people might benefit trust. But even then, especially for all these
only the two best creation of mixed neighborhood. What's quite costly?
Yes. What would have a few wins? Just a nice
structural problem. Yes, if you would use all this money to
a triangle not over a conflict with different.
And so even if it turns out social networks,
I think it's a good experience.
But yeah, so even if it turns out
by creating social mix you improve the situation,
people, aggression groups, and this, what would that be?
So it would try and...
[inaudible]
>> Yes, and back for five. >> Yes, and back for five. >> Yes, I think. >> The military. >> I think it's fine. >> In ruling, schools, schools, schools, schools. >> Okay. >> Thank you very much. >> Thank you very much. >> We have also planned to discuss next next. >> Yes, I think.
[Music]