[ Inaudible ]
[inaudible]
Welcome everyone.
Good evening.
This certainly is my favorite time of the day to teach a course.
At 5 p.m. time we start at 8 a.m. so anyways.
Welcome to our social geography or urban geography depending on your exact type of enrollment.
I am bus fan who often don't know me yet.
And I'll be here, let's say, your lecture for today's session
and next week's session.
For some reason, because I had started the web stream
on, but not for some reason, I received emails
from individual students asking for permission
to gain access to the panop to web stream.
I gave everyone access until a minute ago,
now I'll stop.
So because I have to teach at some point.
So if you receive, let's say messages from your fellow
students who cannot attend, the reason is that they arrived after five,
five, and it gets started. But if all goes well, the recording will be
recorded and uploaded, it went wrong. It appears like you today because of
the pan-up to technical difficulties, but hopefully will manage today. I might
close the window at some point, but it might help to get some oxygen in
here. So feel free to also open windows at the end if you refer.
Well, it comes with two sessions.
As with some other courses, we run, especially,
let's say the big introductory master level courses.
Burbing social geography, urban geography,
is a traumatic course.
So it tries to give you an insight into different, let's say,
teams around, let's say, concerning,
let's say, different takes on urban geography.
I would personally prefer to call this course,
urban theory, because I think we do more than just geography.
But the basic idea is to give different,
sexual and analytical perspectives on how to study or how we can study here.
My role in this course and I guess also in my own research specialty is I'm the cultural
guy so I tend to focus on more cultural issues so I'll be talking you through most
today and next week Monday to let's say cultural approaches to studying the urban.
Today's session, oops, here we are.
Today's session is really, you can see,
an historical overview.
In the sense that I want to go through some discussions
which you might know, or either,
let's say, in generic terms,
or rather specifically around,
let's see how, let's say,
thinking about, let's say,
cultural approach towards urban has been informed,
let's say historically speaking.
So we're going to go through a number
of, let's say, historical steps.
Many focusing on, let's say, the impact
sort of thinking about the post-modern asset. It seems like all TATs seems like all
information, it's certainly in the way that it's not used when this kind of
terminology except maybe a journalistic media but certainly not academically. As
been speaks for the last 10 years I wouldn't say that the post-modern has been
the main obsession for let's say for research but I would argue that much of
what has been discussed from the 1980s onwards more or less around the post-modern
has already is still being let's say dealt with or no using a different vocabulary.
This is what you would often see is that the terminology, terminology is my change,
but if you open, that's adapted more historical answer,
you will see that some of the even-doer terminologies have changed,
then that's the underlying or as a content,
the substance that behind terminology has remained the same over many, many years.
So not everything is new, even though you use new terminology.
So today's more historical session,
we see a historicized approach in the case.
Next week, it's, I mean,
relatively cold urban cultures,
but they are going to sort of give you
a number of perspective,
let's say on a relatively
contemporary approach towards studying
the urban from a culture of perspective.
I will not give a definition of culture.
I mean, I'm not, I mean, so that's a lost task.
It's not gonna work.
and I'm also not going to give a definition,
let's say media scholars or not
that have given definition on what media is still
going to do interesting research.
But please keep in mind that one of my aims here
is also to, if you decide to adopt a cultural approach,
please be very clear and specify
and unpacking and operationalize
in your use of terminology,
because it can mean so many different things.
So we have to be quite specific
and hopefully my lessons will help a bit
to give you, let's say, an insight into the different layers
or different, let's say, lines of research that exist
and it all used a terminology around culture.
So that's what I'm going to try,
let's say, to bring across two days.
So this is basically structure of today's session.
Let's see how far we get.
It's always unpredictable with slides
and then move to today and questions of students, et cetera.
But first I want to start with a very,
let's see, setting the scene,
focusing on the cultural turn
and the humanities and the social sciences.
I assume most of you will more or less know
what the cultural third in the United
Social Sciences is, so will not discuss this in depth.
There are many, many books written on this.
Again, it's a debate, I think that is more or less not finished,
but it has been, let's see, many of the debates we've had
when discussing the cultural third in the United
Social Sciences have now been internalized in everyday research.
So in that sense, it has become, well, naturalized
in very literal sense.
That's the first part, very much setting the seat.
Second part, I want to talk to you about post-modernism
and the city.
There are mainly focused on the work of Fredri Jameson,
not because I think that he's the only one
who is written on post-modernism in the city.
He's not even an urban scholar,
because he actually comes from literary studies
and philosophy.
But his work and his thinking about this
has been a very influential, especially
because it has been picked up by urban scholars
at a later stage.
Among which, the Los Angeles School of Urbanism,
which is the third section, the third part of today's lecture,
because they really have worked, you could say,
with this idea of the postmodern and the city,
and have proposed new ways of studying the city.
As we will see, not everything that they have proposed
was as new as they have claimed,
but still that it has been quite a foundational moment
for the study of the urban, for other studies at large.
To close, now that's closed, and there's a fourth section,
which adopt ups was a continuous partially
under what the LA School of Urbanism did,
but really sort of broadens it,
broadens it debate and has perhaps been more influential also.
And this is literature that's usually summarized
or determined all this around urban landscapes
or the symbolic economy.
And these are terms that you see popping up,
especially from the mid-1990s, early 2000s onwards,
and that is still a very influential
in our thinking on the city and culture today.
Very last part, I will discuss this today or I'll pick this up tomorrow.
It's what I call "Meaning Half-Way," "Hervan interpology, Cultural Studies," and "The
Spatial Turn," by entry point in discussing New Urban.
That's in the culture.
This is true as a spatial angiography as a discipline, whatever discipline it might be.
But there was a parallel debate going on.
What we've seen from the late 1980s, 1990s,
all the words is that let's say some of the concerns
that are in geography or economic geography,
or human geography at large,
has had really started influencing other debates
at the same time as human geography started engaging more
and let's say actively more assertively
with other disciplines.
There are many, many disciplines that could be,
that could be, let's say mentioned here,
but for me, some of the more influential ones
anthropology, urban anthropology and cultural studies.
So where geography is starting engaging more with questions around
and to answer questions.
Traditionally discussed in anthropology or in cultural studies,
cultural studies, anthropology is also starting engaging more with
the spatial concerns of geography.
So this is something that I will close to this,
lecture it or open next week lecture.
And I'm going to first the window.
[inaudible]
Okay.
I'm not sure about you. I'm curious to guys, I'm lazy here. I close the window when I don't
see it. I'm here in your first time.
I asked one reminder, I have a habit of talking fast.
So, if I talk too fast, just raise your hands.
Yeah, this is, I have the very strange habit of talking faster in English than I do in Dutch,
which would be my mother tongue.
Don't ask me why.
If you ask me German, I'll slow down, but that wouldn't help for, let's say, general
comprehension in this class, I think.
OK.
First part, cultural turn or cultural turns.
The slides are all uploaded, so in that sense, you don't have to sort of type like
It's really easy to try to focus on the main elements and try to go to flow of the argument
and trying to develop.
Some of you will notice some of you will not.
It really depends a bit I think on your educational backgrounds.
I would assume that those with the social science and especially the humanities background
will be more familiar with this debate than those that say coming from an engineering
background about it much depends a bit on the specificity also which countries you have studied.
So some take-home messages.
What is the cultural term?
returns, it's part of a wider shift since I would argue late 1970s, at least since this
period that it was phrased as such, in research practices in humanities and social sciences.
So there are various interrelated claims, so that's why I talk about cultural terms
in a way because it's not that easy to identify one single shift in research practices.
One is empirical, and that simply argues, well simply argues, culture is becoming
increasingly important in advanced societies.
Advanced societies being a code word for Western
Europe and North America basically.
So knowledge-based societies, advanced societies,
post-industrial societies, whatever term you prefer.
So this is the first claim being made as to why there is
and or should be a cultural term.
Culture is simply becoming more important.
I'll leave open a question what Dan is culture,
but let's just assume that it refers to the arts,
film media, whatever.
So culture becomes more important.
This relates to the second claim, which is theoretical.
We need better theories to grasp better cultural dimensions
of the social.
Referring usually to symbols of fact, meaning-making practices.
The one that doesn't necessarily relate to the second
principle you put out, no change, let's say,
in a beautiful phenomenon, but simply saying, well,
to really understand these holes for now and a better, we need theories that capture this
decultures, let's say dimensions of these phenomena get it.
But obviously when we talk about the cultural turn, often this comes together.
We say, okay, culture is becoming more important.
And very clearly, in order to really understand this better, we also need other theories
because the theories we have don't really capture this quite well.
So that's the second point.
The third point, again, of course, related is methodological.
So if this is the case or also respective of this,
we need new methods to better interpret empirical data
and/or to interpret data differently.
So either the old data in a different way
or to interpret the better or to interpret data differently.
So it's a time to interpret new data
that we need different methods for this.
A simple example in the current setting
would be if you look at the rise of social media
and let's say data skills, for example,
in that's the last 10 years, is obviously a real method
that also is an ought to be able to investigate
these phenomena.
So there's a classic.
It's a straightforward example of how new phenomena
has emerged as a society right, and we're not always
able to capture it with the same methods that we had before.
So you might be different skills with that methods.
Again, question mark, not saying this is the case,
but this is the idea that the argument is put forward.
Because obviously with the existing methods,
you can still do quite a lot,
or maybe the tweaking ones.
That's important to keep in mind.
So that's the claim,
but also we have to be less successful for classically,
because a lot of this involves less claims
about the cultural term does things better.
But that of course you always have to ask us,
okay, but that will compare to what?
And there's often a kind of simplification
of disciplinary histories,
because then we say let's say within our homography,
it's a, well, we need the cultural term
because we need more qualitative methods before all these old guys just
qualitative methods.
Yeah?
We're just in data crunching.
This is not what we need.
We need to do new methods.
And there's like, yeah, if you look superficially at that history,
that might be the case.
But if you look more closely, you
will see all kinds of different strands in the, I see, the 100 or more than 100
years of urban studies research that actually come very close to some of the claims
here, made here.
So that's the ethnographic research, for example, took place before.
But it's same, so it really leads to a simplification
of often, that's with disciplinary histories.
And you need to be quiet, and it's quite careful.
The same armaments around, let's say,
the industrial and the post-industrial.
The post-industrial is not completely new,
no, but attempts to let's say foreground,
different trends that might have existed
at a previous phase also, but in a last, not
in a sense of dominance.
So this is important to keep your mind.
Yes.
I don't hear anything, sorry.
[laughter]
Was your question going here?
I was very proud of seeing.
[laughter]
I didn't know this one, but...
Oh yeah, the problem was not speaking loud enough, but I'll see what I see.
Yeah, the building is awful, it was... the building works also, yeah, I see.
So yeah, I don't hear anything what you're saying, it's not just...
I'm just checking check check check.
I think we're going to bring these solar mass here.
It's all worked quite well.
The people slowly have things falling apart.
Here's one here, four.
[INAUDIBLE]
It says also not much I can actually hear.
It's all in match.
We're going to go here and do it.
something.
Well, welcome.
And it's all so I'm afraid this is not working on it.
I'm sorry.
That's what you guys are going to do about it.
All right, I'll try to speak a bit louder and a bit slower.
But there's nothing I can do about the building.
We should be building for your solid 5-game.
I'll be able to watch the help.
Anyways.
[ Inaudible ]
>> So these are some of the main shifts that you should understand as being part
of, let's say, the cultural term, the cultural terms.
Yes? Just to give you some quick examples of, let's say,
of the foundational book stat that might act as a reference of,
let's say, exemplifying the cultural term is getting better.
Yeah.
So exemplifying the cultural turn.
Yes?
I'm wondering how people look on this.
I'm not sure if you don't understand anything.
I guess.
Anyways.
Fredic Jameson coming from literary cultural theory,
who I will discuss in some detail,
precisely because some of his elements,
some of his arguments are, let's say,
really foundational things for much of our urban studies
in this particular strand of research.
But you see it also in political science and sociality,
state formation after the cultural turn,
really looking at, you could say,
meaning making practices, state imaginaries,
some terms that maybe now have become quiet,
let's say, natural, really,
to think about what the state is,
but perhaps from let's say,
an earlier institutional point of view
were not so much the case.
And as you see, many of these claims are made.
cultural and economy after the cultural term.
Yeah.
It also does not help.
It can stand in the chair, but it really does not help the acoustics.
So looking at organizations much more from a cultural perspective that is not just about
the organization and let us see the functional matter, but also about again meeting making
practices, ways of behaving within organizations, anthropology and history, history and
sociology etc. You could name many many of these books but at that point in time
there was all around late 1980s throughout the 1990s the these kinds of claims
were made most forcefully in an academic literature. Now to Fredrik Jameson every
year I have to check online if he's not that yet. I don't think he's that
active anymore but you would think he was pretty active until five to ten
years ago, which in itself is quite achievement. He is published in enormous amount of books
and articles, is professor or emeritus professor of comparative literature at Duke University,
and hasn't come, I'll just put some buzzwords here, hasn't become very famous for Marxist
literary cultural theory, for debates obviously around modernity and postmodernity, and also for
the relation to culture and political economy. So even these buzzwords should already give a
a bit of an explanation, let's see,
ask him how you interpret sculpture,
because he has a strong, you see,
marks it, but in a very, less,
it opens matter, but especially this is important.
So we always look at the relation of culture
to political economy,
which is basically a code for capitalism.
So this is, I would say,
I would say is main concern in his writings
at least on culture and postmodernism.
Now, there's a phrase that has become, well, there's also his article, original published
in 1984, which he titled, "Postmodernism as the Cultural Logic of Late Capitalism."
Yes?
So this is really, let's say, a phrase that has become very famous also.
You see it referred to on a regular basis.
Now, there are a number of elements.
I don't know who has read to the article.
I'm not going to ask.
I'm not even going to ask who has actually
managed to finish the article because it's not a simple article.
I'm very well aware of this.
It is worth it.
I mean, I have a drink, sit down, and you
mean you understand it better a bit again.
Who knows?
But it really is--
I'm trying to give you also, let's say,
some foundational original religions,
not just about secular literature of artists
writing about other artists. But this is an article related to book that is reference all the time. So it really helps to go back to the original, to get a sense of what is on you.
Now I picked to do your homework, I picked some as a key quotes from this article which in a way give a good summary of what this claim is about and which shaped I think some of the urban research later on.
First he says course, Martinism is not a style, but it is actually a cultural dominant.
So it is not just a lifestyle question.
No, it is actually something that has become dominant in our contemporary culture.
Second, I am directly related to aesthetic production today.
And this is of course where let's say it is Marxist-state political economy,
the sympathies show.
A static production today has become integrated into commodity production, generally.
So it's really difficult, the argues, to distinguish aesthetic production of production of the arts.
It's in ball, from commodities.
So it basically becomes one, two sides of the same coin.
That's basically what it is arguing.
I think if you start thinking and verily it's quite easy to come up with a concrete example.
I think that makes a lot of sense.
A work of art, let's say painting, is at the same time a static production.
It's about symbolic and reading-making practices.
It's about interpretation, but it also sells a yard market.
It's not due to speculation.
It's both.
Then I started elements.
I'll skip this because it's interesting about there's a very, I say, 1980 sentiment,
where a sort of globalization and Americanization was very much seen as one of the same thing,
mobilization was seen as you can see an extension of earlier history of
Americanization. Yeah. And then it talks about it.
And then again, we're not very important. I say, well, basically, it looks at post
modernism as a third stage of capitalism.
Before it was Annas Bandel was a Marxist scholar actually at this university
one of my years ago, which would then be, yeah, use different terminologies for
it. He refers to post industrial capitalism, he first debate that
of the multinational capital and the consumer capitalism. So you can argue this all here is politically
economically, politically, economically sized, are postmodernism. So postmodernism accompanies
this phase of capitalism. That also means according to Jameson, it only makes sense to talk
about postmodernism from let's say the mid-1970s onwards. There is no such thing, in this way of
reasoning as postmodernism in the 1920s just doesn't make any sense.
Yeah? Because it's so much tied to a particular phase or a particular stage of capitality.
One reason why this article has become quite famous and it's a bit more difficult to understand
now I think is because it does quite an extensive reading and interpretation of one particular
So we're telling, we're just a bonnetman to hotel in Los Angeles.
So designed by John Portman built in the mid 1970s and one of the largest hotels in LA
and to my knowledge, it still is.
So just some pictures.
This hotel for him, it's a bit hard to imagine now, but if you look, represents, you
could say, the culmination of postmodernism as the late logic, as the last logic of late
capitalism.
So what does the argue here?
You will see some of these elements return
and later the base without reference to the hotel
or the specificity of his argument.
It ispires to be a total space, a complete world,
and attempt to not be a part of the city.
So it attempts to be a world on its own.
You may not be a part of the city,
so that the reflector class here, which rebels to see,
outside and achieves a peculiar and placeless.
disassociation of the Bonavantura from its neighborhoods.
Just keep this in mind, some of these altitudes,
because they will return later.
The other, the separate from the city.
So it's quite easy to imagine later,
and I'll give some examples also,
if you think of, let's say,
gain the community-style things, right?
Things that are, let's say, within the city,
but cities are highly unequal.
So you have different elements, let's say,
separate, even though they're formally speaking part
of the city.
This is what he's arguing at,
that this is what we see in the Bonavantura Hotel.
And this becomes a bit more difficult to imagine now,
because it really is, I think, an experience of that time.
I think we now so used to these kinds of architectures
and these kinds of buildings.
But according to them, this becomes impossible to navigate.
Of course, not in a high-risk space,
a lot of our lives skip that, is impossible to navigate.
It's just too confusing in many ways.
You can no longer situate yourself as a subject
within this world, but you're just very,
a very fragmented human being.
That was a kind of, let's say,
It's typical, let's say, literary trope of 1980s postmodernism.
I think this has probably become less central to the debate,
most likely because we have so--
we have become so used to behaving like this in the world.
Again, I want to discuss these details.
I'll skip the first.
This one might be important to remember here,
because again, this shows up and later discussions,
especially when we think about discussions
around cultural heritage.
Yeah.
His story is a space of history, a random cannibalization
of all the styles of the past.
And his idea that especially postmodern architecture
just used different elements for different eras
and combined as into new building.
So it didn't produce, let's say, formally speaking,
something new, but it was more of a reco-lage
combination of all kinds of existing, let's say, architectural styles.
That's a random categorization of the style of the past.
The past has a reference of drag and re-bracketed
reading with nothing but texts.
So this is also, again, something that pops up
in later discussions on what does the culture actually
produce?
And then there's this idea that the post model that-- well,
you actually read the post model phase,
but there's no linear trajectory if there ever was a say between history and futures just recycling of the past.
Okay, now that's Jamesson does that make a bit more sense than what you read the text?
Yeah
okay
Now I mentioned Jameson not because I like my old almost dead white men
But because he really has been inspirational saying for many let's say researchers that came after from different different perspectives also
Yeah, the Mars engine of school of hermies was born with last cities
Let's say cluster or like cluster of activity that came together from the mid-night
It's all worth and we also refer to Jameson
I know she's built on it anymore.
You can see social scientific urban research type of map.
What does the law of science school of urbanism
argue?
I don't think she's struck this idea
that it is a queer and school, but that it's said to argue.
First of all, following Jameson, literally following Jameson,
it looks at the postmodern condition
as a radically new urban condition.
So this is what they call postmodern urbanism.
Main characteristics, again, be aware
Let's say the simplification of disciplinary histories,
because it does have, especially in this,
let's say foundational texts or texts that
try to say really puts, let's say,
the LA school of early on the map
through a number of key publications.
It did have a tendency to then say,
okay, but everything that came before,
in a way it was, it's old hat.
We don't want that.
We need something new.
So again, very, very much a strong sense
of simplification for some of the main characteristics,
itself, itself, and fun.
Beyond Chikawa School, what we see now is not to
see a centric city, but know it's about urban
fragmentation.
Yeah.
It understands LA and Southern California as
privileged cases.
So the priority case for the research, but also as a
prototypical case, in the sense that the understood LA and
Southern California as the future of other cities across
the world.
Look at what we see happening in LA and this region.
This is what we will see happening in cities across the world.
Yes, so it's kind of pre-figures as the future urban developments.
Yeah?
It made a lot of attention to restructuring,
which was like, say, the generic word,
focusing mostly on post-fourdism,
flexible accumulation, the redeveloped of firms.
So we won't go into this because I think you're all aware by now of, let's see, let's see.
Yeah, post-fourdism, basically.
Yeah?
And there's a nice quote from my Davis,
"Riner and Liverpool Riner"
belonging more elastic to the same scene in a way
where we talked about the LA School of Urbanists saying,
well, they're basically politically economists
with their spacesuits on.
Quite sure the food you understand, what he means it,
but it sounds really nice as a quote.
So here's your sense, it's politically economy,
but it's a bit off, it's something else, right?
It's a bit speculative.
Now, I already said it's important again to be aware of simplification of disciplinary
histories and it also applies to the LA school as such.
So it was seen as a coherent school, but it was also soon critiqued by others.
And even by those within working within this domain, or that was said, I say, label that's
been part of the LA School of Urbanism saying, well, actually, there's not one single
claim being made by the LA School of Urbanism.
But actually, there's more diversity within this supposed school.
So there is a diversity within Cohe
in itself of all the histories, longer histories, but it really came to gather at this
point in time.
And I think it still shapes, to some extent, to quite the substantial extent you
current research that we are doing today.
So one important strand to absolute shares become even the most famous one is for political
economy, economic geography, I guess. It really looks at post-war and
complex accumulation, industrial organization, regional development.
So really about the transformation of firms, how firms relate to each other, how they connect,
And what this means for regional development?
The Latinx and the key artist,
they have to mention that perhaps how it starts,
the Christoph
or certain Michael's store,
but most of you will have heard of these names at least.
I heard there was other lines of work.
One thing we would be this probably is
to some extent most relate to the first
and politically calling your place,
because if you look at, let's say,
regional development, the transformation of companies,
there's also an element there.
What does this mean, actually,
local place conditions, a place identity,
but it also has to do with branding elements,
it has to do with, let's say,
local patriotism, or it has to do with local labor markets,
et cetera, yeah?
Yes, that leads to this,
the strand I mean, they're all related obviously.
So what I Jennifer Rolf have been worked
on homelessness, on skilled work, local labor markets,
the classic argument in this literature
is that the transformation of the region,
as a result of less of a transformation
of its political economy,
leads to more polarized labor markets.
So we have, let's say, put in a simplified sense.
We have, let's say, higher earners,
and we have, let's say, very let's see,
if not unskilled, and then it can very low pay
and precariously employ it workers on the bottom.
So it leads to a more polarized labor market.
There's also the argument that has been picked up later
by someone like SARS-CAS-SUSPEN, working on global C's.
So that's important.
And this wraps us, let's, let's,
that's famous but what's emerging now I think more forward force for the last 10 years
is work around environmental justice you know the transformation of the region has also had
effects on the environment at large planning issues but also ecology issues were narrowly
put and this has already received some attention there yes.
He said to say on the space of the kind of march to not that everyone would end up like a
name without any of the things that might have happened to the things.
I'll give some examples.
I'll take later on.
But basically it's about overfactantation.
We would have to put it in a bus word to this idea that, I mean, especially me, for
So those that are attending my lecture on the European series,
there's this idea that it's a compact city,
there's a coherent city, it's historically grown,
and then there's a lot of actually,
it's opposed to modern city, it's almost inverse, right?
It's just like a chess board where whatever you could put
for, actually, not a good example,
because you don't say, "If I have tier rules there."
But, but you just like a game board where you could put
wherever you want, and this is how the city develops.
Yeah? So, and this is what, and so this relates
to urban fragmentation, and the other one's broad,
I would say.
There must be two issues where they argue, okay,
this is actually foreshadowing why the Roman develops.
And they're not completely wrong, of course.
I would simply, I would just argue that maybe LA
was not the first and in parallel of these
to be solved and see many other cities,
where this was also the case,
especially in the global south.
But this is, I mean, that's only a critique
that has been raised towards the LA school also,
because it's only, only on a later stage,
I think, that it started looking outside
as North America.
You said it started, it was from American buyers, maybe West and Europe, and totally
later they started spanning.
And then of course somebody's theories no longer hold or somebody claves in any case.
Yeah?
Yeah.
So there's a lot of diversity.
If you look at it at the same time it must be set, purely, to flee between the mid-1980s
and the late-1990s, various key publications were published that put LA really on the
map of urban studies. So this really helps to think to retrospectively look at this as a kind of
current LA school of urbanism. Yeah, ranging from 1986 special issue in society and space which
is one of the key journals specifically dedicated to LA to books like the city Los Angeles
Urban Theory in the mid-1990s or rethinking LA or studies by Alan Jay Scott on Technopolis. There
many, many of these key books that really appeared
that are key references in the field of our studies
that are still a dealt with or referred to today.
For example, Mike, Mike Davis, and I've
said a lot of academic per se, but his famous book
City of Quartz, which again, is continuously referenced
in many different parts of your studies world and beyond.
This one is perhaps already a partial answer to your question because this shows a bit in a three, I would say, how some of these artists looked at at city development.
I would say in extreme because this is really an article that tries to codify some of the claims of a rate of more subtle manner, but many other orders.
And by doing so, they also radicalize some of these claims.
Not necessarily enough in an helpful manner, I think, but it helps to keep in mind.
So they said they argued that the spatial manifestation,
so maybe all the deer and flusties sort of forgot their names.
They argued that the spatial manifestation of postmodern urbanism was a kind of keynote capitalism.
So basically, it's apparently a board game.
I wasn't aware of that, but basically a very fragmented form of an
infrastructure in which the code in urbanization is occurring on a quasi random
field of opportunities. So basically there is no longer this idea that you have a
city center that it emerges outwards or that particular structures related to
planning or set or not it just it's pretty random. And this also of course
also the end of theory because if you make this kind of flame that does not
really much you can, you can do anymore. So it's also highly that's simplified. So I would
certainly not encourage you to understand this as the core business of the early school of urbanism.
This is almost more a parody of this. Nevertheless, some of the last, the items, literally speaking,
they put on the map of key on capitalism still resonate with us today. Because for example,
We appear at no birth, which you could say there's a lot of reaches still going on unless the ethnic
communities, relation between ethnic groups and, let's say, localities within these neighborhoods.
We have team marks, far side, a lot of commodity commodification of public space.
We have community communities without losing place role.
We have street war affairs, obviously there's violence in the city, which is a classic team in our research.
Spectacle, again, which relates to the commodification of space.
Commanding control centers, which is, let's say, a classic team of
like SaaSka SaaS centers, I did at Global Cities,
it's already actually happens when it comes to both political and economic rule.
So, all these different elements do, well, we're identified by them,
and have played the portal role in later research on the city.
I guess some examples already here. I don't need to go through this idea.
So much my summary of the LA school of realism. I already hinted at the fact that this was not without its critique.
Some of this critique was quite legitimate because one of, let's say, my hobby or is this really more against the simplification of disciplinary histories.
There's a lot of academic laziness involved.
You want to make it claim that you do something
rather than an interesting.
And by doing that, you say, but that
what came before was actually not an interesting,
but you actually simplify that history.
So if you're intellectually, I think, very honest,
you have to be very careful with these kinds of strategies.
You have to be much more, as the honest and open
and respectful also of what came before.
And maybe moderate your own claims towards newness.
This is not what the LA school did.
All right, so that's it.
Some more.
So critics were also abundance and very early on,
raised, let's say, made, let's say,
problems, had the delicious thing had,
raised, let's say, the claims of newness
put forward by LA's good audience.
One being, what's really new here?
Yeah?
You might claim that this is where
it doesn't receive enough attention,
but actually there's already a lot of existing work
on diversity, restructuring, consumption,
into modification or in every poverty.
And especially every poverty has been foundational to
riding on the urban since the mid-19th century.
So there's vaccines industrialization basically.
So what's really new here?
That's the first legitimate criticism.
Second one is the LA school,
it really sort of reduced Duchikago school
to account of Bergus, concentric zone model.
that everything that was written in the 1930s,
which is post-hocks sometimes labeled as the Chicago School,
was about the consent of the solar model.
It's the idea that there's a central,
a business district and that people move outward,
depending on the history and capital also.
Yeah?
There's much more internal of our work,
or there was much more internal horizon
within the Chicago School,
so it does not justify this kind of simplification.
So many of the things that the LA School is now doing,
actually was already happening in the Chicago school.
So let's say the American claim,
there's of course also a struggle you could say
within LA, within the US,
but I can say, well, we've had Chicago
now we move to LA.
This is where the action is happening.
And then many other odds were saying,
well, maybe not quite.
Yeah?
So that's the board key mind.
A third one, this graph from me,
the most interesting or the most relevant critique
is there is truly, I think,
kind of ethnographic voids in a lot of literature and postmodern urbanism. What do I mean by this?
It really relies on a kind of detached reading of the city. This is the most, let's say extreme example.
This is how we see the city. I mean after his anything more top-down than this, I mean it's hard to
imagine, right? It really is like okay, let's see here. This is how we see the city. But in a no-ways
at no stage, do you see any engagement with what people on the ground actually think about the city
the delivered or worked in. So it's a very sort of top-down matrix-oriented
reading of the city, which is labeled as an ethnographic void, which I think
is the most forceful treaty. There's a marginalized agency and
interpretation of ordinary people. And there's no postmodernism from below.
You could imagine a kind of, I say, fragmented urbanism and the
the political lodge of combination of elements by people making, making do, making a living
in the city and combining different elements.
But none of that is part of this discussion.
And so it's much more, much too doubt down, too detached reading.
Last critique, and this I have to relate a bit to this idea that LA pre-figures wider
urban developments.
They're saying, well, LA is actually not that much of a difference.
two levels. First, within LA, existing urban theories before the LA School of Urbanism
are still relevant to explain what happens in LA. LA is not a complete free, let's say,
boards with quasi-random, let's say, attempt to stay in place. Now you can use all the theories
around, let's say, agglomeration, for example, in order to understand LA or in this wider region,
So that's one thing.
The other side is that the group of phenomena
you see in our area are also visible elsewhere.
And not just as a pre-figuring or something
that comes after the other school,
urbanists talked about our aid.
No, it actually something that was already before.
Maybe some cities were even earlier.
And this I think is also to some extent
where especially research work in the global science
really connected to, let's say, okay,
that's much happening elsewhere,
which is perhaps more interesting also and certainly shows let's say that LA is not that special after all
Okay
Wow
[ Inaudible ]
>> Yeah, that's a screen because otherwise there's a lot of ears.
I would say to me that I would say certain strands within geography this is what you see. But if you look at much of this literature, especially work by people like Alan Scott who's in the stop us and they are all working in the kind of realist vein.
right, in the sense of it's pretty straightforward and favorable research.
There's a world out there that's going to study it.
Some of the examples you mentioned might have happened, but I would say that was more, let's
say, visible or more central to the data in literary studies.
Maybe cultural studies, to some extent, and less so in geography.
So I don't think it was necessarily when it came to the other school of urbanism, necessary
much reflection actually on the epistemologically, the pathological dimension, and it
There was more an observation of new empirical facts
on the ground, which necessitated new theories.
I'll call it them.
So I think it's more on that method.
But obviously, as I said, to very good,
there is no such thing as one culture term.
And also no such thing as one post-modernism.
So I think that's-- and if you look at the way in terms
such as the post-modern has been, I say,
discussed with the different disciplines,
you see quite radical differences between what
actually understood by the postmodern in the first place.
They're interesting books written on this also, but yeah.
Okay. Other questions on these first?
Three, was it two more substantial bars?
No. How are we doing time bars?
Yeah, let's give it a few more minutes then we'll see.
Am I talking too fast or is it okay-ish?
I think the fact that it has to be very loud,
it automatically slows me down.
So that helps, no worries.
So I might just start screaming in my lectures
and that I'll slow down my temple.
Yeah.
OK.
So we've got cultural turn.
We've got postmodern, let's say, James Solyan
approach it and then sort of vision on the postmodern. This indirectly or directly influence
a lot of LA school urbanism work. Yeah I think it was not just Jamesson but there are many
of many of us similarities there and there's a related strand which now I want to discuss
with you which I would call as Erwin Landscape and the Civil War of the economy mostly because
this is the terminology that was I mean the difference strands of research but there's a lot of
research around these discounted teams which supposedly refer to actual facts on the ground.
So don't see that something really different from the
Yale School of Urbanists is more let's say developing in parallel.
Perhaps also with different inspirations coming up with a bit more I would argue from
Leslie Culture Studies tradition which also emerged in the 1980s.
Yeah but obviously there are interactions also so just
you know as a clear catch category we'll see it.
If you look at what I now describe as, let's say, one body of literature because for me it makes sense to describe this as a relative
appearance body of literature. There are a number of key guiding assumptions, arguments shaping this kind of literature.
One very similar to Jameson, flexible accumulation, post-fourdism and post-modernism are two sides of the same coin.
So this is your Marxist argument, right? So there's a political economy and the culture is
the supersetive, the other side of this one of the bleecon. But it's impossible to extract.
It just belongs very close to together. And innovation perhaps that this literature introduces,
according to the much of this literature, says, well, we receive the rise of postmodernism also hanging together with the rise of a new middle class.
And this very much hangs together again with just a rise of post-foughtism, post-industrialism,
because it led to new, you could say, work opportunities, new fields of work, new labor markets,
which demand that you could say a type of worker, a type of population that was overall highly educated,
that was knowledge oriented, yes, this is the kind of debate around higher education,
knowledge-based capitalism, and this was very much seen as it's highly educated,
that this is what they should understood
to be the rise of a new middle class.
It's not your class of middle class,
which perhaps may say more fixed,
but in this sense, the introduction that was done here,
say, okay, this rise of the new middle class,
is accompanied by a rise or an interest
in new university aesthetic sensibilities,
sensitivity, interest, preferences.
This idea that there's a new kind of a static emerging
with this new group of people.
recently labeled and commodity aesthetics in a way
that because it was highly driven,
a variety related to let's see lifestyle references.
Yeah?
So I'm interested.
I'm interested in a little bit of an example.
I'm interested.
I work for, let's say, a--
not, I can't talk about the good example.
I'll try to come up with a better example here.
I'll give you an example in a minute.
Yes, so it does really matter.
Look, as the kind of examples I was thinking about,
I'm mostly around, let's say, urban street culture, for example,
which is very much related to particular lifestyle
that really lead to how you identify
with particular lifestyle.
These lifestyle are close to connected to the buying
and showing off particular commodities.
Shoes, clothes, hard work that you associate with it,
a bit higher up, et cetera.
So let's say the second part.
Third one is that culture was key or is key to urban redevelopment.
This has remained, I think, very influential.
I'm doing work on this still.
But there's also this work that was already,
let's say, put forward at the start
being done in the late 1980s.
We've been done on real estate, on artists,
on recresentations of urban space.
If you think now, we've been done on the impact
of gentrification, on city spaces.
How artists play a role in both, let's say,
boosting gentrification, but also being kicked out
of gentifying areas.
That's a classic argument which I was zucan already made in the early,
no, in the mid-9080s.
So not much has changed to the same in that respect.
And the fourth role I think this is something
that was well to begin with, also picked up
more in the European side of discussion,
and which was not really at all really picked up
by the Yali School of Urbanism, is an important role
of the state, staying investing in cultural landmarks,
but also really developing all kinds of cultural economic
policies.
So this is more or less, if we have to give, let's say,
a nutshell definition or a listing of key elements,
what the symbolic economy literature is more or less about.
Few examples.
One interesting article that we have
in the rest of this urban landscape, early 1990s,
where we argue very much along James Sonian lives,
there's widespread agreements that
what emergence of postmodern architecture, culture and philosophy in Western society has
proceeded in tandem with the emergence of globalized more flexible forms of capitalist
enterprise.
For a second part of that quote, postmodernism as the cultural closing of advanced capitalism.
So this is basically James of all over the two sides of the same quote.
I registered a question here because I would question if there was really that kind of widespread agreement.
Yes, there was widespread agreement on this claim within Marx's political economy.
And yes, Marx in political economy became, let's say, especially with geography,
it's pretty not dominant, but central to the debates, I would say, in the 1980s and '99s,
especially in the early '90s and '90s. And this is part of that explanatory logic.
I personally am seeing much to agree with and these kinds of claims by acknowledging actually
that that message cultural expressions are always that easily the other side of the same coin
of the capitalist politically company. So there's more complexity there that is easily
let's say simplified. So this is important to keep in mind unless of course your food
the agreement design, which is possible.
So the point about the rise of a new middle class,
again, in the same article, Box Office
is a crime used for some real crime.
You know, it makes a couple of claims, which
is not specific to Nox, but I think
specific or represent of La Cides wider literature.
First he says, well, and this is the shift
to post-industrialism, the emergence of new class
fractions under advanced capitalism.
So we see dominant classes, but actually change over time.
But so the structure is speaking, I say this hierarchy
remains, but different class fractions
might emerge to become dominant.
This is what now under advanced capitalism,
we've seen the words of new class fractions
or a new middle class under advanced capitalism.
That's the economic argument.
The cultural argument would be this was also
a generalical reaction against modernist aesthetics.
I say, the children growing up in the 1960s
rebelled against their modernist parents
and thus started supporting different ways
of behavior, different ways of cultural preferences.
It's not wrong, it's highly simplified,
but it's not wrong, of course.
So that's the perceived, the socio-cultural audience.
Right?
To this related then, let's say this move away,
this critique of modernism,
really refer more to the kind of lifestyle orientation,
which you can look at positively,
or become a part of everyday life.
This is something that's not just something
that is separate from us.
No, it becomes even more radical.
But you can also look at it more critically,
or just become an out of commodity.
It's just a question of lifestyle,
show your identity, showing off your identity.
So there's a lifestyle orientation.
Self-realization expression, and I
need phrase-phosphology, cultural politics,
true sort of culture, you position yourself
as a citizen in many ways.
We're looking at the imagination that already
into the act of described commodity aesthetics,
a kind of niche oriented consumption
with emphasis on taste and aesthetics,
and hence an increased role for design also.
someone I call a mouse, and they never work,
they specifically focus on urban design,
or design sector as a central sector
in advanced capitalism.
And we can all understand how this works.
I mean, I think we're all parts in a way of this group, right?
So I wear this closing, but not that close.
We can do it exactly the same,
but just a slightly different color, right?
I wear these shoes, but not these shoes,
or I want wooden floors, or not these kinds of floors,
in my house depending on which phase in your life, your life you are.
It's pretty niche but still we have very strong opinions about this.
Don't start talking to me about music.
They have very strong opinions about music.
But if I look at it from a more distance, obviously I have to admit that it's pretty niche.
Yes, so now I sort of, let's see, I established distinctions between what is good,
bad or bad or not good.
Yeah, it's pretty specific.
So I think this is important,
this is really about this initial area consumption.
That has increased, I think, rapidly over the last 30 years.
I think this is not something that we saw
to such an extent if you would go to the 1980s,
for example, early 1980s.
Culture and urban redevelopment, for another strand,
I would say that's really part of this kind of debate.
Even earlier in need, I forgot that it's this early.
One of the earliest probably the first book actually
by Sharon Zuken, who's called "Loth Living."
I guess most of you would also know Sharon Zuken
was done a lot of work in cultural and city.
"Loth Living" was already published in 1982.
She was early for her time, so it's not,
you could say not that typical, but it was really
a foundational book, I think.
And it really shapes still many of the dates
that we're having today around the role of artists,
in particular in urban settings.
So around law of living, which was New York oriented, and there are laughs in New York,
but there are laughs in New York, which of course does not apply to every city, but
structure is sleeping. You can see similar processes, at least in larger cities, I would say.
What did she argue? Okay, we have let's say abandoned laughs, empty laughs, and we see a
re-arpegency of abandoned structures by artists. So early 1980s we're talking about here.
Also New York at the height you could see of its crisis, and let's say at the deep end of this
developed.
But it's the first thing.
A re-occupancy of abandoned structures, where ours.
This is not followed by a new middle class.
Yeah, so the artist move in first is still rough for a rowdy, but then the new middle
class moves in and it gets a bit more, a bit more, a bit more, a sea clean, a bit more
fancy, which she calls a reconquest of the inner city, needing to kind of laugh lifestyle.
There are people living in, let's say, dwellings that do not represent your class fill
that point in time, sub-berber, let's say one family household.
So you have to come up with a new architectural style,
a new way of imagining how to live in these laws.
Besides an also become an increasing trade of conflict
between competing uses.
Those between alt and havences, if the inhabitants,
if they were still there, artists, and a new real-world class.
Where artists use laws also as a production infrastructure
to produce art.
you will have last by and large used these laws
as residential infrastructure.
Yeah, we worked somewhere else.
And then culture is also very early on,
especially even from the early nights,
the age onwards in New York was used to develop
and profit from an emergent real estate market.
So real estate intermediaries, very early on,
realized that our desardest movie in,
selling this area becomes interesting,
becomes visible at the very least.
And thus we can actually use this.
We can explore this.
This is something we can build on.
And we can start identifying this.
We can start selling this for a project.
Now this was early '98.
And if I tell you with this story, it's pretty clear,
I would think, being all being over scholars,
that this resonates, let's put it at those terms,
resonates with discussions you see on an everyday level
and most of the cities that you are familiar with.
This idea that, oh, that's a gentifying area,
this like a proto defvenation of gentrification or cultural gentrification.
So I think if I think of an area such as anyone Brussels such as Saint-Gio to some extent this
logic is followed. I mean I'm not familiar with too many cities but I see several things happening
in Berlin or so on and still see happenings and saw happening and in many other cities where this
is the case, quite obviously.
For this, has been a major strand of research
for quite a long time already.
And it has been refined, et cetera,
but it still shapes the discussion.
So ultimately, of course, there's also, again,
this has also received research adventure.
But also, the main set art is
have become both drivers and victims of urban development.
And similarly, in that time, ours are in development,
which shows our artists were, well, really,
the early, let's say, the movers to move into a certain area
and start developing the area,
to build into development, to love development,
other types of building development.
But then, when the area, the neighborhood
had reached a certain stage of development
and real estate prices, ours then, again,
were in a sense moved out because they could no longer afford to live there.
Except those perhaps that were smart enough to buy at an early stage, but this was rarely
the case.
But then the end.
So they were both drivers and victims of urban change.
And this again hasn't changed that much over the last 30 years.
Except that perhaps this phenomenon has globalized and it has become a much more strategic
government.
Well, they much more than see forceful government strategy.
So this is in a way mainstream urban development by now.
OK.
Looking at the time, let's take a quick break,
and then I'll continue with the second part,
or the last third of the lecture.
(coughing)
(people talking)
(people chattering)
(door closes)
(
)
(audience chattering)
(chattering)
(people chattering)
(people talking)
[ Inaudible ]
(speaking in foreign language)
(people talking)
[ Inaudible ]
(crowd chattering)
(audience member speaking)
[ Inaudible ]
(people talking)
(chattering)
[ Inaudible ]
(audience member speaking)
That's to the lay of race, but it was just so incredible.
[ Inaudible ]
This is what I find in this discussion, because we've been working so far, so there's more and more of that.
(muffled speaking)
(audience chattering)
[ Inaudible ]
(people chattering)
(audience laughing)
[ Inaudible ]
(laughing)
(audience chattering)
(people chattering)
(laughing)
(people talking)
[laughter]
[ Inaudible ]
Yes! I want to see the first one.
(chattering)
(crowd talking)
(people chattering)
(chattering)
[inaudible]
All right, let's continue.
[ Inaudible ]
>> Yeah, okay. Let's go.
So we're still in the symbolic economy part.
And I'm discussing different strands, or what I mean.
This is less identified by me.
So what I consider to be a relatively clear
and body literature will then
this body of literature, there are a number
of different strands of, let's say, research attention.
So before I just finished the part on
let's see cultural redevelopment.
Now in last part within that section,
I would argue really focuses on read presentation
of her misplaced.
Now please understand every strand that I discuss,
I can only do so much in a two hour lecture,
in the mind of the Greeks.
But please understand every strand as potential,
let's say, lives of investigation for yourself.
Or a favor for the master thesis, whatever, right?
Just trying to let's say, hopefully,
give some inspiration as to what possible teams,
possible topics are that you might want to engage with
in more detail.
So this is also for me a bit,
what I see as my role in,
especially for those here and their first semester
on the first year master, what I see as my role.
Just giving a few, let's say, foreigners,
there's a few ideas about what could potentially
be interesting to do more research about.
Yeah?
So one element here is re-placitation of urban space.
This is probably a relatively straight forward exercise
where a lot of attention recently,
especially outside of urban studies, in marketing,
it's true to anything you're boring,
but still there's not a discussion,
but we should investigate the role of media
marketing and putting cities on the map. I should say, no one. There's a lot of
boring research being done in this field. There's also some interesting research
being done in this field. But some of this is very instrumental. So there's this
research that focuses on urban images, what kind of interests do we have in mind
when we think about cities, how it can lead to change geosemages, or some contested
images. And we all will have, let's say, city images in our mind, when we're not
I've got to do the quiz now, but they would ask you to sort of, I would mention a city,
I would ask you to mention the first English that pops up in your hat.
Then it's quite clear there will be a large element of consensus, I think, within the audience.
Paris, Eiffel Tower, I mean something like that, right?
So the couple of cliches.
This has become increasingly important in debates also around urban tourism.
Especially in your experiences, I've always been key sites for tourism.
Yes, so there's the grand tour, there's the upper middle classes,
aristocrats, European elites who have a travel to and around
two different European cities.
But as we come, let's say,
Massified over the last 60, 70 years from the after world for two.
And it was really that same to let it's own development around her maturity.
And, of course, that's it, the whole discussion about her energy
will also fit in here.
Yeah?
This has increased.
It also been picked up where you could say it was, to some
extent, firm driven.
That's the entrepreneur driven.
This has increased.
It's been picked up by most local and national states as
important development strategies for the local national regard,
which has really really with the focus on tourism as the
important driver for the economy.
It's a highly volatile economy, of course.
This is something we now see with COVID to, well,
it's a very clear sense.
It's only everything falls flat,
and that's for locally cars that rely heavily on tourism,
that's obviously is quite a disaster.
You can now be speaking of course,
socially speaking that's another discussion.
That is a nice book also, that's why it's a national here,
not when it's trusted by many people,
but they are greenback, how, you're outside.
Branding to the world, how a Sydney crisis
sold to the world, which traces a bit, let's say, the branding of the York from the 1980s
onwards, our city at the bottom ends being confronted with out migration. I can try to reinvent
itself through its images in order to become, let's say, more attractive again. Open question,
of course, if the branding has played the most important role in the city become more attractive,
what's already has played a role in this.
Okay. Last part in the role of the States, very briefly.
Again, this is the debate that has been picked up,
both in our mistakes as well as our side of our mistakes
for a culture perspective, especially in those
who are specifically on cultural policies,
which is a dedicated field of research on its own.
Which I would say you see a couple of things.
We see strategies aimed at really developing culture industries.
I have myself done research on this older
data around culture industries, which is very much about
local economic development.
It's a data that you actually attract artists, culture
workers, to your city, in order to develop economic economies.
Much research attention has gone into this since the 1990s,
but especially 2000s.
There's also research around large scale events,
world fairs, art exhibitions.
Again, this hasn't much, much longer history.
They transcend also, are we studies as a discipline?
Because if you look at, let's see,
a discipline such as art history
that has done excellent work on, let's say,
art exhibitions and world fairs
from the mid-19th century onwards.
Yeah, so the hour always, let's see,
depends to attract the global or is European audience
to your city.
But again, this has become increasingly
kind of economic strategy. So you want to attract your Olympic games, you want to attract
a biennial or you want to add a biennial etc. There's also been increased in critique because
often there's a lot of investment going into this but what actually delivers tends then
turns out to be quite limited. And more broadly I think there's literature again from the 1980s
onwards, why should we do more for the zuchen on the arts and the urban growth machine as it was
called to the 1980s, certainly, which really focuses on us
seeing art networks, the elite networks, and arts institutions
as local attractors for inward investment and urban development.
So there's a classic example, if you look at the--
in the position of the Google Cloud Museum in Google Cloud,
that's an always-maintured case when it comes to a new place
museum in the relatively rundown city.
simplifying here and this would really boost the local economy.
And to some extent it did.
Again, if many issues attached to it,
what is not complete before us.
So there, this is work that has received a lot of attention also.
Here, one more recent example.
Not sure if the city needed, you could say this.
It was certainly not around rundown city in a sense.
Does anyone notice an example?
So it's M+ museum in Hong Kong actually, which actually was just open I think two, one
or two weeks ago, two weeks ago designed by Star Architects, Herzog in the Miron, and a
typical, you could see an example of a city that is both aimed at attracting and perhaps
improving to the cultural image of Hong Kong, but attracting, let's say tourism to the city,
But also as a kind of advertisement for the C.
And there's some extent in the very little sense,
because the main real insight is one big LCD screen
at the same time next to being a museum.
So you could actually sort of literally see how this is
a kind of commodity style, right?
So a very, very literal manner.
But also for example, big commercial art experience,
So this is our Basel, who developed, let's say,
well, which is now staging.
I'm not quite sure what the current state is,
because also, COVID really messed up a lot.
But what it was is staging annual art fairs,
and Basel, and Miami, and Hong Kong.
Not only did these events attract
well-teated visitors by and large.
Yeah, they also spent there in these cities.
So again, it becomes a kind of local development machine.
Yeah?
Well, recently our Basel also started a so-called
our Basel series initiative,
where we try to have events in different cities,
which in this case, when as I was,
it's one example, which supposedly should benefit our Basel,
because it can globalize more,
but also other things across the world
would be not at an annual artist,
and suppose we benefit from us
in the name of the reputation of our Basel.
And we see these kinds of initiatives emerging
quite forcefully over the last,
especially over the last 10, 15 years.
Okay.
Last section for today, and I'm actually doing quite well
at the time.
So I also won't discuss this,
unless not every bullet point on the slide.
But just as a kind of wrapping up,
to reposition, let's say my debate,
which was let's see mostly oriented within urban geography,
but to reposition again within the broader debate
on the spatial term. As much of what I discussed, what I showed you, graph of concern, or do you go to graph of concerns? But the spatial term more broadly frames that count of the data.
So, just to wrap up, in the late 2020 century, urban geography was heavily influenced by the cultural term. This I discussed.
So I related the base in postmodernism and globalization.
This has had to, in effect, let's say the epistemological and mythological effect was that
there was an increased interest in ethnography, everyday life, imaginaries, re-presentations
or in short culture.
So this really what I think has shaped much of urban geography over the last 30 years.
Across the social sciences, this is how I opened my lecture of the day.
This cultural turn intertwined with increased interest in spatial configurations.
So that's the urban geography has already been introduced to cultural questions, to cultural
disciplines, which I would say is cultural studies and anthropology.
We became more interested in spatial questions.
So there were a number of reasons for this.
One is, I addressed this in some other lectures.
there's a kind of really post 1989 obsession with globalization. On one level and
superficial level globalization is the end of spatial questions because
everything is global. But it actually intensified this concern with spatial
questions because it soon became clear of course that it was a process that
actually had spatial effects and it was spatial process. It was a stretching of
of social relations taking place, which could be and needed to be understood in a spatial
manner.
Connecting A to B as a spatial effect and it leads to a different spatial configuration.
I have social sciences humanities, sorry.
Yeah.
I don't want to be able to fit everything on an already two crowded slide.
I had to sort of, yeah, so across the social sciences and humanities.
So the creative interest in spatial questions.
in spatial questions.
So this of course, where the geography starts becoming
an inspirational discipline for other disciplines.
This is exactly what happens in the '99s especially.
Hence, the increase in interaction
with your own job, your methodology, and cultural studies,
which are already hinted at.
I'm only going to go quickly through this,
but the slides are slightly more detailed
because I added these slides because not, let's say,
the elements I discussed in the previous slides,
the previous one hour and 20 minutes or so,
cover I would say most of what is relevance,
concerning the culture and urban geography
over the last 30, 40 years,
which has already quite a challenge to fit that
into a two hour lecture, but it really misses also some elements.
So, I mean, I proposed, let's say,
quite a day in a way, a linear trajectory
of how previous discussions,
influence current discussions,
and that had an effect on this.
But in parallel, of course, there were also discussions.
And I just want to briefly end at it,
because there's again,
these are almost, and then we've got more or less important,
but we can't really necessarily trace back
to some of the elements to, let's say,
Frannie Jameson, for example.
So there are two core teams, perhaps,
that have also really shaped
into disciplinary urban studies over the last couple of years,
and that we have emerged more forcefully
from the disciplines outside of geography.
But it's definitely that informing urban studies
at large, for me, is a very interdisciplinary discipline
optimistic to elements.
One, informality, second, everyday life.
Informality for those that have studied ethnography
and anthropology, they will become,
well, it will be quite familiar with this term.
This, in the story, I give some examples there.
The religion that looks specifically on
coming from also the development perspective,
or the developmental lists,
perspectives to some extent,
focusing on labor markets, precarious work,
migration, legality, political governance
and conversation, our unpacked this in a minute.
Everyday life, partially overlapping,
but partially coming from where this tends to come,
we're simplifying it from anthropology,
and our company life tends to come from what I would say is cultural studies as a discipline
of the immersion in 1980s, focused very much on agency, community community, women, resistance,
often on local level, often lifestyle, really consumption, identity, media and representation.
So when precisely these terms, those are the newspapers, political rights, there's this
obsession with some of these terms as that they want to critique and then emerge and think
more closely from cultural studies. Obviously, the clinics have never read cultural studies,
but that's another discussion.
Let me see. Now, in formality, I'm actually going to see it because this has become a
special last 10 years of studies. There's so much research taking place now on informality
and the urban. But it's important to keep in mind that this was already a classic team
within urban anthropology and development economics, especially from the early 1970s
on this. An article always references the one by Keith Hart in formal income opportunities
in urban employment in Ghana and in the title itself already makes pretty clear what's
well, where he stands and what the topic is, right? It is really about local labour markets.
It's about local economic development, yeah? But what did Keith Hart and many others
with an argue? There is a lot of, and I think it's something that maybe she was an ominous
lecture for European citizen or urbanising world also picked up on what is registered to
be part of the economy is only part of what is what you should consider as economic
activities.
So we have formal economic practices, businesses that pay taxes and that are registered
as businesses, but there's a lot of employment beyond these formal economic practices.
So beyond governments, beyond firms, beyond factories, beyond large-scale economies.
So this is where the distinction between informal and formal comes from.
So this is important to keep in mind.
This, of course, gets slippery because in some literature, this and this comes together.
And we say, well, I actually did formalist illegitimate and informal is the legitimate, but
that is only partial, but partial, true.
I mean, we can have discussion about what's legitimate.
But that's, for example, we'll all agree that someone taking care at home of their children
that are constantly exploring, but we do.
I think that both the All-Solary that is not illegitimate to the
contemporary, well, far from it, right?
So where has dropped trafficking is probably informal
because it's not registered as such, but many would also
consider legitimate.
Again, we can have a discussion on this if that makes sense
that distinction.
But this is how it comes to the emerge.
And this is interesting because there's one of, not few
concepts, but one of the key concepts that have really
traveled from the global south to the global north. So this is where it worked that
he emerged most forcefully in the research on the global south. And this is what it was
really sort of the travel that says to the global north. That doesn't happen too often
you could say. So I mean in terms such as postmodern urbanism in a way is the opposite
example.
Now an urban anthropology, if you look at informality, it needs a lot of research on opportunities,
but also precarious precarity created by unregulated economic activities.
So there's strong interest in gender dimensions.
So people are working on markets, working at home.
So this is really about, let's see,
what the bread and butter of a lot of urban anthropology,
as well as transnational dimensions.
Particularly this is the mention of the thing
that has been picked up most clearly
in the more cultural work in early studies.
So for example, many street founders
also do transnational migrants here
in a picture of La Amalana and Barcelona.
So illegal migrants are doing working
on the city, and it raises questions of economic survival,
most obviously, but also questions of the governance
of the political identity of these actors
or the cultural identity of these actors.
And with an enormous study, there's
a big amount of research, which has really
led to a boom, I think, of research and informal,
and on formal urbanism.
You know, I pick up some of these elements in my lecture
next week.
Now, that's very brief.
I mean, I could have two, three lectures for sure on informality as a concept, as a practice,
and how it's picked up in different strands of research.
Just as a kind of stepping stone, please understand this as a stepping stone to, let's say,
the more contemporary research that I will discuss next week.
The second strand of research, which has been much part of us in a forced modern urbanism
drag, this is what we call in drag, is the literature on everyday life.
I myself have been partially trained in cultural studies and everyday life was a concept
that popped up that it was regularly used all the time.
From the late 1980s, 1990s onwards, it was really used as a key topic.
What does the term basically entail in most cases?
Because ultimately, it's also not more than a bus work.
There's a lot of theory behind it.
But ultimately, it entails a key concern with lift experiences of people and the meanings
constructed by subjects in their own world. So classic cultural concerns, if you wish.
So most of this literature and cultural studies on everyday life tends to also position
people as active agents, rather than as passive consumers or passive recipients of political
power. So this automatically leads to this kind of debate on strategies for tactics and
So the resistance people can have on the ground
in relation to the structures they are confronted with.
Well, they are confronted with.
I'll skip this part because there's also another part
in anthropology which also addresses it.
And this also makes, I think, the everyday
it truly transdisciplinary concept.
I mean, again, there are not too many concepts
that are truly transdisciplinary.
I try to understand urban studies as a discipline
that is much broader than specific disciplinary debates
because it's just fairly boring to stick to one discipline.
But the everyday has really emerged from the 97,
97 as it truly translates to an early concept.
So again, similar to the postmodern,
I think a question that was raised at the back,
there is no such thing as one postmodern.
If you look at different disciplines
to really be at the standard postmodern,
it's quite substantially different
and sometimes even contradictory,
the same applies to the everyday.
when one discipline or one order says about D every day,
might not overlap to a grade degree
with one another or on the right spot the every day.
So you really have to look at disciplinary specifics
in order to understand this.
Nevertheless, it has emerged as a term, as a concept
that really connects cultural theory
with philosophy, with Marxism,
and Alfred P. P. P. P. with post-structuralism,
with sociology and with aesthetics.
So the many interesting, let's see, Andrew Porns also P. P. P.
So, for instance, specifically, next to the unavoidable hornet in the favor,
the every day, who sees the every day as a side of utopian possibility,
but also colonize but a commodity form, so that's commodity aesthetics once again.
I can only urge you, and of course, honker the favor is great, we all like him, etc.
But there's also a lot of interesting work that has been done by other artists, which is perhaps,
at least as relevant, let's put it in those terms, than honker the favor.
Please, no, no, no, no more papers on the right to the city.
I've read enough of those.
That's, yeah.
For example, Stuart Hall and Tony Jackson,
classic British cultural studies.
Some of you might be familiar with this over there work.
Especially Stuart Hall, I mean, if not, the readers work,
because it's pretty, well, it's very, very good.
For really looked at, looked at,
as he sub-fulchers, and every day
as a symbolic opposition to a dominant order,
I'm just mentioning some key words that talk up here,
that we determine knowledge and the thing which has become internalized in much
of our thinking about urban cultures, resistant style, social practices, sub-told use
code, urban use identity.
Yeah?
Terminality that was not used for the first time by Stuart Halden others, but they really
theorized it.
And they really did something new.
Yeah?
One caveat of course is especially early cultural studies work.
It was highly blind to gender, gender dynamics.
Yeah, this was, I mean, the picture shows it was,
youth subculture was very much around male youth subculture.
Yeah?
This is Washington addressed by a lot of such
as ancient I met Robbie.
It was actually my first huge supervisor
and feminist cultural studies.
But certainly, let's see, you kind of
underlying trend in the early culture studies tradition
that it was pretty blind to gender issues.
or supporting intersectional other intersection issues.
From quite a different angle, but again,
and they are an amazing book, very thin book.
So he's the reader that's very well written.
The practice of everyday life by Michel de Sertou.
I'm at the business translation, obviously.
I think the French is maybe 10 years old
and more of any of the original.
More poetic, but maybe folks in practice, tactics,
versus strategies.
So the idea being that strategies are top down
and people on the street, they sort of engage with this
and develop tactics in order to avoid state strategies
with mostly government strategies.
So tactics are situated, tactics as resisting,
let's say broader structures.
This again has very much shapes.
I'm not saying that everything is good about it
because it's too dichotomous,
but it's a very influential book
that has reshaped much of the data at home.
Could next we will talk a bit more about, let's say,
from the everyday to cultural work and activism,
bit more about DIY organism, where some of the DIY
urbanism literature, for example,
in listening or explicit and first to the cutout
of stuff that is subtorted already in 1980s.
Okay, just to conclude, as I mentioned,
The cultural term is to be understood as part of a wider shift in analytical sensibilities
in the social sciences.
I mean at the very beginning I said okay, the empirical theoretical and the methodological,
these are three takes on how at that point we started looking differently at the
world.
Yeah?
So, urban geography itself as one strand of debate within this broader cultural term was
And here's how you heavily influence by Marxist
or at least political economic interpretation
of postmodernism as the cultural expression
of late capitalism.
Yeah?
You can also phrase differently.
There's very little subtle nuance, cultural readings
of, let's say, symbolic objects such as the arts
in urban geography.
For that, mostly you have to move outside of geography
because it does not have this history
of taking suddenly about, let's say, cultural expressions.
Which doesn't mean it's not good, but it's limited
in that respect.
The work in symbolic economy, and the labels on this,
but it has shifted attention a bit more
to questions of re-presentation,
to urban lifestyles and culture production.
So the postmodern urbanism school
was, wasn't interested that much in artists
producing actual pieces of work in an actual art.
It was most interested in consumption.
Yes, come on, there's studies.
you buy something with which you identify as a lifestyle question.
And we see the last part that I then discussed.
We see an increasing or we saw an increasing
a rough question more, a sort of meeting and a health rate.
Between urban geography, cultural studies and anthropology
as part of a broader spatial term.
So this is the funny thing of interesting thing
is that this cultural term often also
until the spatial term.
And it came as the emerge together in many ways.
The last point I'll discuss is the research and informality
and everyday life and related concerns
as enormously contributed to a development
of a truly interdisciplinary,
transdisciplinary form of cultural urban studies.
I think these are some of the,
some of you see this happening in social science
and science and science,
that are not just at certain concepts, just resonates.
We had research coming from very different traditions
and then we come, let's say, bridging concepts
that bring together very different ways
of thinking very different histories of writing
And this is where most of them are--
well, the most exciting stuff happens I would argue.
OK, next week, this is what I will try to discuss.
So today, my main claim is history matters.
So the history of urban studies that I just
discussed shapes also current research debates
on urban cultures.
And before strands, I will try this class
with you next week.
So it is more.
But I do think that this is pretty exhaustive at the same time
are one on the arts, activism, and urban engagements.
Just one strand.
The second one specifically focusing on culture
of infrastructure and informal urbanism.
Probably a bit more on a culture infrastructure site
than the informal site.
A third one on urban tourism and consumption cultures.
And a fourth one, which links most close
and think to the methodological concerns, perhaps.
It's also as a variable at the same time.
Folks on sensory urbanism.
So different kinds of, let's see,
engaging with German beyond the visual and text.
Again, there's only so much I can do
into two hours that I have next week,
but hopefully this gives you a pretty good overview
of what cultures of urban research
and urban cultures can be about.
Okay, I'll leave it there,
and I'm very fast for today.
Any questions?
No, everyone happy to go home at quality seven
on a Monday evening, then I will see you next week
if I don't see you in the fall.
(applause)
(clicking)
(people chattering)