I'll start recording immediately because I forgot to start recording for the lecture of
clear, at least for part of this.
Let me see here.
[no audio]
[Silence]
Can everyone hear me?
Yeah, I see shaking ass those goods.
I now also open to chat.
I finally found out how to build the chat while
being in a formal presenting mode.
I think it's about time to start.
Welcome to the second lecture for urban social geography,
where I'll be spending the next two hours.
Let's see how much time we need for electric urban cultures.
So as you remember in the last session,
I largely gave an historical overview of what I consider
to be essential, let's say, core coordinates
of thinking about culture in urban geography
and more widely some other, let's say,
related to discipline, starting with a brief discussion,
well, but there are relatively specifically discussion
on Fred O.G. Jameson and his notion of postmodernism,
moving to the shift of, moving to, let's say,
the 1980s, early 1990s debate on postmodern urbanism
and the LA School of Urbanism,
and then shifting to a wider,
but also related to the bait on the symbolic economy.
Those were the key coordinates that I tried to get across.
One of the questions, well,
you can't see the slides.
Can everyone see the slides?
Oh, that's odd.
Thank you for asking the question
because I'm actually screen sharing now.
Let me just see, I'll just stop sharing.
should be able to see this lights. Another sec. Share screen. I'll do it like this
done. So do this. Just a sec. Okay, now see my screen. Except that I can't see
you now just a sec. This is lots. I don't know one near you.
You never see the slides now? I see one yes thank you so I hope that's okay. Perfect. Okay.
Okay thanks a lot. Yeah feel free to unmute sometimes that's easier than working with
sign language. The only thing is I can see you now. Let me see where is that. Just
want to say, oh here we are. Okay, now I see you and hopefully you see me and we see
the slides. You did hear what I was saying, right? So okay, let's keep it from there.
So what I tried to get across last week is what I just discussed. I tried to give an historic
overview of some of the core elements that I thought I think were are important. Thinking
about every culture over the last 30, 40 years actually. Open some people in the waiting room.
My life is so easy. Let me see. Before you start working here, where are we? No, no, no, no.
I'll stop sharing again. I'll admit all again at some point it becomes a bit tricky. Then people
that just have to wait for the next pause, otherwise it becomes difficult. Because with the
session of clear I could actually manage this but since I don't have an
assistant next to me this is what will work with okay next round we'll
we'll go for another ride here we go
Jabs and starts
this is valid that I don't see you anymore
Here we are.
There we are.
Okay.
Getting there.
So, for the third time.
I tried to give an historical overview.
One of the questions I received last week is okay.
Are we going to learn more about actual cultures, so cultural expressions, stuff that
interests us as 20 years, 20 years.
That's what I remember.
So the question to the answer to that question is yes.
In the session today, I will focus a bit more in detail on specific, well, I will always focus on
research on urban culture, but look, assuming in more specifically on research that looks at
actual cultural expressions, but always from perspective as to how this has been done in urban
studies. There are many other disciplines, of course, that focus on culture or cultural expressions
coming from the humanities in particular, but I will largely zoom in on how this has been
in approach within urban studies.
That will hopefully become clear or clearer in a minute.
Before I do so, I want to broaden the debate a bit
beyond urban geography per se.
And I show some of the slides and discuss some of the slides
that I also already mentioned last week.
Because if you look at the way urban geography
has undergone its own cultural term,
as I hinted at last week,
What we saw happening in parallel is that many other disciplines
within the social science and humanities
have also undergone a kind of spatial turn.
So we've seen a kind of meeting health way,
a kind of rapprochement between geography becoming
a more cultural discipline,
but other disciplines also becoming more
becoming more geographical becoming more spatial.
So this cultural, this spatial turn had a number of reasons
as I already mentioned I think last week.
What did I'm being a post-1989 obsession with globalization?
So the moment you start thinking seriously about globalization,
you quasi automatically start thinking about spatial issues
about geographical issues because if it's here,
but also somewhere else,
you start thinking about connections.
The other one being a kind of critique of modernity,
which had really shaped
that they most of the social science and humanities debate
up until the 1970s,
which primarily sort of paid attention to temporal issues
time because that's the very logic of taking in terms of modernity. So what we've seen over
the years since the late 1970s, roughly speaking, is we've seen it's kind of de-emphasizing
of temporal issues and an emphasizing of spatial issues. And this is where the spatial turn comes in.
So this in turn, and this is what I want to briefly focus on for the opening of this today's
session, led to an increased interaction between urban geography, urban anthropology, and cultural
studies. Many other disciplines also, but for me those are some of the core disciplines that really
shaped the future of the research on urban culture at large.
Now there are
A number of core teams in urban anthropology and and or cultural studies that has shaped the late 20th century early 21st century trajectory of what I consider to be let's say interdisciplinary urban studies.
I'm not going to give a review here of urban anthropology or cultural studies. They're both fascinating disciplines.
I heard a lot more than most disciplines.
I mean, I was trained in cultural studies myself before becoming a geography you could say.
But there are two, let's say, teams that I want to briefly flag here, which I think have
a much longer history in anthropology and cultural studies, which have really picked up
in this scenario of studies and shaped this debate up to the present day.
The first debate being around what I lay on here is informality, as it kind of debate
that emerged in anthropology and development studies,
largely focusing on informal economy, labor markets,
precarious work, migration issue of workers,
legality and illegality distinction,
but also the regulation, so the political governance
of infomality.
I'll give a few examples in a minute.
The second core team that I think is important to keep in mind
as a kind of understanding of the history
of research on urban culture is research on everyday life.
That's a term that you don't see the term used that much anymore.
I would say in the last 10 years or so, you still see it a lot, but less so as a theoretical
concept.
But it was a term that was pretty much dominoes in the 1980s, 1990s, 2000s.
Largely used as a kind of shorthand or kind of bus work for referring to issues around
agency, community, community building, also resistance issues, as well as consumption identity
questions and related to representational questions, which then in turn had often a lot to do with how things were represented in media.
So, everyday life refers to many things, just as informality refers to many things, but if you would have to give a kind of nutshell summary, this life pretty much covers the other thing.
Now briefly, if you think about informality within
biologic urban anthropology and development studies,
it's a term that was less used in cultural studies.
It's a classic team, especially from the early 1970s onwards.
The core reference and perhaps the first person
who coined the idea of the informal economy,
that many others, of course,
who did research on the informal economy
without labeling it as such, was key to art
and one of the classic articles,
So one of the first articles there is
the article from 1973, which is a title
"Informal Income Opportunities and Urban Employment
in Ghana."
The article is such that the case
that he is such is less relevant than the understanding
as to what he coined to this article,
or how this has shaped, let's say, subsequent debates.
So hard primarily focused on a number of things.
He focused on actual employment,
so people making a living beyond government jobs,
beyond factories and beyond large scale companies.
You know, say, okay, there's a whole world out there
of how people make a living, especially in Ghana,
but he then sort of extrapolated this
to urban Africa at large.
Say, okay, there's a whole world out there of work
that we actually don't see.
We don't capture it.
We don't see it because we don't have to vocabulary
to really pay attention to it.
So that's the first observation he makes there.
He then makes it, he bases this on a distinction
to informal and formal labor.
It says, well, all vocabulary that we have
is largely catering to, especially for economics,
to capturing, registering, and registering,
and measuring formal labor.
So labor that actually shows up in GDP,
values, et cetera.
Labor that is actually taxed.
And a lot of the labor that we see in our Africa,
you argue it's not taxed as such,
or we don't see it for that reason.
So he introduced this distinction
informal labor, formal economy, formal employment,
and informal employment.
He also then makes a distinction between illegitimate
and legitimate labor where he said, okay,
the jitterments activity, which is not the same
as informal and formal.
He says, okay, we can't have informal activity according
to him, so economically, which is not measured as such,
which is still the jitterments, which he then argues
those are activities that do actually make a contribution
economic growth but at a small scale. So if you let's say sell foods on on a local market but
this is not captured you're not registered as an official business this according to them is
legitimate in formal activity which I think most of us can actually agree with. And then there's
illegitimate informal activity where it says well that can refer to criminal activities but also
to for example to bagging or bribery or corruption, which you consider to be illegitimate.
So there's a kind of four-fold distinction which is really shaped the thing to debate.
And you can question and disagree with some of the specifics of his argument, but the
way he structured his idea has been quite important.
Now, I mentioned this here not because I want to discuss with you Urban Africa or 1973
a key thought, but because I think some of the classical landmarks studies that he and others
have done in the early 1970s have informed the debates that followed elsewhere. Inframality
is an interesting concept because it's one of the few concepts you could argue that has
really seen a concept from the global south to the global north. So where most of us are
very well aware of critiques toward, let's say, urban studies saying, well, it's actually
Eurocentric or at least Western centric. Inframality is one of those concepts which you
you could say, "Start it in the global south,"
and actually has been picked up increasingly
in order to understand also practices
within the global north.
To such an extent, I would argue that it's one of the few
concepts which really transcends this kind of global south
global law divide and really sort of contributes to
thinking in terms of a global urban studies.
So if you look at work, for example, of Ananya Roy,
or Jennifer Robinson, they have picked up
on the informality topic as a way of also thinking about
urban studies in more global terms
without being, let's say, Eurocentric or Western century.
They're all kinds of related terms,
and they all have to do, let's say,
this monetary specifics,
that are pretty much trying to cover the same field,
but I won't discuss here,
such as unregistered economy, black markets,
the non-observe economy,
undeclared work, or the shadow or hidden economy.
And for those, let's say, more trade and feminist theory,
it's quite obvious, let's say,
that the distinction to informal and formal
Washington also maps onto the distinction
between public and private, with public activities,
often being seen as part of the form of an economy,
but let's say private activities such as care work,
being seen as the informal economy,
often also not measured,
and thus supposedly not worthy of attention.
And of course, this has overlapped
and been involved in rethinking the terms of that debate
to an important extent also.
So in urban anthropology,
thinking about informality, you get the research on the opportunities but also
precarries created by unregulated economic activities. I will give some examples later,
but it's quite obvious for example if we fast forward, let's say, to research on
creating cultural industries, and research that has now been done on precarious
precarious artistic labor, for example. It struggles with a similar tension, where
the to a large extent artistic labor is also unregulated, which creates all kinds of
freedoms and opportunities, but at the same time this let's say this unregulated nature,
which makes it very precarious because there's no way you can actually support, well,
let's say where a state or a welfare state of other mechanisms can actually structure
the kind of economic activities.
Urban anthropology and historically speaking has also seen a strong interest in the
gender dimensions.
Of informal works, I've already hinted at this.
Partially in the home situation, partially in mostly females being women working on markets,
etc. So all kinds of gender in the exclusions that are part of this discussion. And again,
they have shaped the debates in the decades that followed. Also important things that
urban anthropology we see in formality being linked strongly to transnational dimensions.
So with the idea that informal labor market informal urban labor markets are often also
highly transnational labor markets. On one level with diaspora connections, people sending back
they are there earnings or part of their earnings to their home country, but also with many migrants actually occupying informal labor markets in in countries in cities across the world.
So there's the transnational connection which urban anthropology certainly was among the first to pay attention to, which I see an increasing amount of research in in urban and interdisciplinary urban studies.
example of the Montevos and Barcelona, for example, who often have an African background and who have
would live in relative, if you precarious situations, well, very precarious situations in Spain,
being sort of legal, illegal, semi-legal in different kinds of statuses and trying to make a living
in this case, Barcelona.
So that's a five-minute summary of a 40-year debate in urban anthropology. So apologies for any
of lack of solities, but my discussion is relatively instrumental here, and that I want to get across them.
The key, let's say conceptual elements, conceptual nuggets, you could say, that that's also
shaped a bit in interdisciplinary urban studies. A second term that I'm sure you've come across
before in your reading is everyday life. Now, both anthropology, but especially in cultural studies,
This notion of everyday life really shifted the bait and signifies in many ways
it concerned with the lift experiences and meanings constructed by subjects in their own world.
Partially emerging you could save in the 1970s as a chronic critique of supposedly structuralism
Marxist theory being more attention to agency so it's part of that 1970s 1980s debate but then also
increasingly moving into a let's say substantive empirical research where research started
being attached to the actual lift experiences and meanings of people. So people's active creative
agents rather than as passive consumers, this is kind of what sort of the broads into disciplinary
sprawling debate of everyday life signifies. Now there are many connections there I think within
different disciplines that have in one way or another tried to engage with everyday life with
or without using the concept, one which I will only hint at, I think here, but which might
be discussed in some more detail by those that follow, not everyone does, but depending
on your program, those that follow urban sociology of Ava Swindeau, there's a kind of
tradition of community studies in anthropology and cultural studies, which historically
has focused on participant observation and extensive theories of field work to really
gain trust and insight knowledge of everyday practices.
So basically an anthropological stance, you could say,
you become part of a community.
And only through this insight knowledge,
you will actually understand the meanings
and interpretations attached to certain practices.
It of course also has a history going back
to the Chicago School with research
on also ethnographic research on urban areas
and various, let's say, urban topics,
such as gangs, I think segregation, lifestyle,
delinquency.
But there's also a rule connection
where a special within our associateiology,
let's say partially in parallel to the Chicago school,
which was always more urban in orientation,
where some classic community studies,
especially in the 1950s and 1960s,
sort of started applying, you could say rural concepts
of classic community studies to urban settings.
So going into a supposed community and a setting
and then focusing on, let's say,
family and kinship relations
or traditions or rituals.
This kind of community studies that a literature has been quite heavily criticized over
the years, largely for being too localist or for assuming community as relative homogenous,
which was already problematic, you would say in a rural setting, but certainly it's problematic
and it's much more dynamic than dynamic urban settings.
It's the idea that communities actually share same values was increasingly questioned.
Because the tradition there often, let's say, focusing on everyday life of these communities
was already established by this kind of, this kind of minutured.
There is somebody waiting in their reading.
Let's see, because every time when I have to, but I might be able to do it like this.
Nope, we're already in the process of this area.
Okay.
more. But I can do this all the time because it's quite interrupting so that I'll now start again.
You can still see me. Perfect, now I'll continue.
So especially from the 1980s onwards, I think we've seen a revival of the community studies
that moved beyond the kind of nostalgic motion of community. And this is where, so to
So again, the everyday life notions, well, returns in a way or becomes more present in
theorizing urban communities.
Some basic trends, and again, I just mentioned them here, but I think they basically
still structured a bit up to this day is that artists started using conflict theoretical
approach instead of collision theoretical approaches.
So looking at, let's say, interactions, obviously social interactions between actors, between
people, but also not sort of assuming, let's say, cohesion theoretically.
But assuming, let's say conflict theoretically, we could say very bluntly speaking, you
could say, instead moving from a dual-kymion perspective to a Marxist perspective.
That's very simplistic, but basically that's what covers to a certain extent the debates.
folks on network ties, local and trans local, I already mentioned this whenever I'm
anthropology, care and support and unequal and changing nervous settings.
And because of the, let's say the interest in, let's say, conflicts and how communities
are constructed, not how we, let's say, are assumed to be, there was increasing interest
to let's say the shifting symbolic boundaries between communities.
So they're sort of the making connection, but also making distinctions between, between
communities and between groups.
And then of course that opens up, let's say, the base
to not just communities as, let's say,
and uply, all the facts of social life,
but more into the base around communities of choice
and elected belonging.
So they can move into sub-cultures or LGBTQI communities,
but also gated communities, for example,
in urban settings, where people choose to belong
to a very separate community.
Now, the everyday is really a striking concept,
and let's say in the career of this concept,
because it's a truly transdisciplinary concept,
perhaps even more so than the informal informality.
Truly transdisciplinary,
maybe with a strong humanity background,
but really connecting cultural theory
with philosophy with Marxism,
with ethnography, with poststructuralism,
with sociology and with aesthetics.
That's precisely what makes this concept
that things so interesting,
was to influence you for research and our recalters.
Now you have to be careful here,
because the simple fact that a concept is used
all these different, let's say, traditions or disciplines, doesn't mean, of course, that
is used in the same way. So if you look, for example, that's, and there's no time to discuss
this here, but if you look, for example, that every day life in, in, let's say, ethnography,
it's quite different than every day life in aesthetics, and quite different than every day life,
let's say, in more post post structural literary theory. Yeah. So you have to be quite careful there.
But for every study is, I would argue, there are a number of approaches, which have really
let's say eternal references in a way, those artists that are continuously referenced.
One is the unavoidable home dealer, Fayetteville. Everyone references home dealer Fayetteville.
We see every day as a side of utopian possibility, but in line with, let's say, its Marxist
credentials also sees the everyday as colonized by the commodity form. So commodification,
logic, also shaping the everyday. That has been, of course, very influential thing.
in our studies to a large extent also because it's pretty compatible with the critical political
economic or studies approach. So people can claim or can become more interested in culture,
but don't actually don't have to leave. Let's say the house of political economy too far.
They can stay pretty close to that kind of debate. But I would also pay attention to other
moral, let's say perhaps empirically minded research, although still very theoretical,
and I will only mention two here, which have been equally at least influential, I think,
in urban studies. One being, the work by Stuart Hall, who is a massive towering figure, I think,
within cultural studies, British cultural studies at least, who looks at the everyday life,
largely true, you could see, especially in this book here, which is an additive book and a
compilation of classic classic papers of the British cultural studies center at that point in time,
the two looks at it to the subculture lens.
And the notion of subculture was coined
by British cultural studies.
And even though subculture is also word,
we tend not to use anymore.
Many of the, let's say, practices that we assumed
to shape subcultures are with us today.
So we might not name them subcultures anymore.
We might talk about the machines or about the networks
or something along those lines.
But the idea that subcultures are, let's say,
every day, but also are also kind of symbolic opposition
to a dominant social order.
This idea that they are one way or another resistance
is very influential, I think.
So if you look at the literature on, let's say,
subcultures, or let's say, neural literature
on protests, movements, or let's say clubbing culture,
it still uses these kinds of discounting for cavalry.
So that then directs attention,
to urban practices of resistance, but also style of fashion, of social practices,
or the particular codes that are used within a community,
added direct citation, I think also to a particular, let's say, generational category, namely urban youth.
Which I think was really, has always been a recent in a way,
but British cultural studies tradition has perhaps directed most of his attention
to, let's say, this particular category of this particular generational layer.
layer. Typical of ever also for British cultural studies at that one in time is a certain
gender blindness. If you look at, let's say the early cultural studies tradition, those that
did research on subcultures, by and large looked at used cultures as you could say, boyish,
masculine used cultures. So there's certainly a certain gender blindness in the kind of
resistant use cultural literature.
However, this has increasingly been addressed
in subsequent work, partially and bachu
this kind of collup cultures literature that I mentioned.
Also by the work of artists such as Angela Megrob
who was part of the Early British Cultural Studies Foundation
and is now a professor at Goldsmith's College
and who has really addressed this kind of literature
and this kind of gender dimension of cultural studies.
Another order, and this is only a book I can,
Well, the other book also, but I certainly recommend you
to read this book if only because it's a very pleasant read.
It's beautifully written.
And it's not a tick book.
I think it has around 200 pages max I think.
It's pretty readable.
It's Michel de Sato and it's--
and it's--
he's written many things on a really live,
but this perhaps the most heavily silent book,
the practice of everyday life of 1984.
The-- having said the term, the English translations
from 1984 if I'm not mistaken.
It might be later that the original Franget is actually
from that time.
I will even look it up.
I forgot.
It's beautifully written.
It's perhaps more poetic, I would say, and less political
than British cultural studies, or at least less
in your face political.
But it has a vocabulary, I think, that has been very influential.
According to the Satoru, society is largely shaped,
and I think the binary nature of it,
the way you phrase it has been criticized,
but still it has been very influential,
but according to the society's largely shaped
by tactics versus strategies,
or strategies for some tactics in that order perhaps,
with a kind of state by a large use French, right?
So the city puts the state very central,
perhaps even more so that the economy
devices all kinds of let's say strategy structures
or does of social life,
against which we assistance as groups,
although you have a relatively individual focus,
devise all kinds of tactics in order to resist,
to avoid, to intervene,
so all kind of creative ways of dealing with strategies,
and sort of turning it around
and doing something else with it.
This is the kind of literature, which, as I said,
the binary nature of it,
that this idea that there is such a thing as strategies,
Let's say top down strategies versus bottom up tactics
because that's the kind of image you see.
It's problematic, it's too simplistic, I think.
But it has very much shaped this idea
that we have, let's say, media, cultures, shaping,
shaping things, but we are also creative consumers,
we can actually change and creatively interpret things.
Does a tool gives a very urban angle to this?
It really talks a lot about, let's say,
walking in the city, for example.
some of the walking literature and walking.
There's a door, it's one of the key artists there.
And it really looks at the key.
Obviously, there's a city which has been designed
and structured and constructed in a certain way.
But we as citizens, we can walk in the city
and sort of adapt and use a different line,
a route of walking, et cetera,
and ways not intended by the designers.
So it is then leads to a kind of literature
and kind of reader reading,
which looks at tactics,
everyday practices, I would say,
practices of everyday life as situated, it's often very local, sometimes as defensive in defense,
yeah, in defense too, but also sometimes opportunistic. You sort of pick up on some structured
elements and do something else with it. So that's the kind of literature and especially kind of
vocabulary, which again has shaped a lot of things, this idea of, of, of, I shaped a lot of research
on every day of life.
Okay.
That's my first part.
I will just go to Quick Loop, but I see no one entering anymore because now I have pretty
much all chat box, not a box is open.
Are there any questions on this first part as a kind of first go on?
I see a question from Vera as James Scott, can you maybe explain this very critical
brief question. I don't see you so you're going to have to sort of speak up.
Now I was just thinking about the work of the de-structure, mission de-structure,
that you mentioned. And actually also James Cotely is from the same period. He published
the everyday life experiences of the pleasant etc. This talk about this
in for politics and matters stuff.
- Absolutely, no, it's very much part of the same reasoning.
So one of the other books that I could have mentioned
perhaps, but it has been less influential
in urban studies, but there's a great book
by James Scott also seeing like the state,
which is basically this kind of logic.
It's the kind of seeing like a state you could replace
that with the de Satoru vocabulary of strategies.
and then you have citizens, people, communities,
these perhaps more community oriented there,
partially shaped I think by the
anthropological background,
which is, which divides all kinds of tactics
as ways of resistance.
Not absolutely, it's that kind of debate.
Yeah, good question.
Any other questions on this first point?
If so, just speak up because that's easier for me
than go through the whole list of people.
No.
Okay.
Then I'll continue with the second part.
Well, yep, indeed.
So a couple of lines of research that I'll say more contemporary.
So, current lines of research within urban studies that focus on urban culture.
Within interdisciplinary urban studies, I think here we definitely move beyond the realm of urban geography,
geography narrowly defined.
And I want to discuss with you today.
The reason why I spend a fair amount of attention
to the previous art, to the previous debates,
is also because as you will see in the discussion
that now follows, is that the kind of vocabulary that these
kinds of debates use are very still influenced,
knowingly or unknowingly, unknowingly,
so by the previous discussions.
So by both issues on the symbolic economy,
postmodern urbanism, informality in everyday life.
So that really still shapes, I think,
some of these current debates.
I will now discuss all possible directions
in this area of studies on urban culture.
If only because culture is such a, let's say,
slippery concept and research has really explored
in all kinds of directions and as let's all kinds,
we could say sub-disciplines,
or let's say certain strands of research
that that would be impossible to do in a two hour lecture.
So I've been quite, let's say,
so lactate in a selection has been purely based
on my own preferences in a sense
that I'm going to discuss with you
the number of strands of research
that I consider to be interesting
or the most interesting strands of research.
Obviously, I also consider to be these
the more to be the more productive strands of research
and a lot of research is being done in this kind of field.
The first strand of research
to discuss with you and again a little pause at the end of this trend is around the arts,
activism and urban engagement. Research on the arts, of course, there's an established tradition,
obviously primarily in the humanities of aesthetic analysis of the arts. So of painting, of music,
of theatre, mostly actually, and increasingly so differentiating into different disciplines.
to your left musicology, you will have tiered studies, you will have a
let's see art history or visual studies and those are established
traditions off the web histories reaching back on the years.
Yeah, urban studies that even as an interdisciplinary field builds on these
traditions but actually it's primarily used as sociological and
or politically economic approach towards the arts and culture.
So some of the elements I will discuss here, they certainly do not capture the
diverse, the offer, let's say research on the arts that is out there. But they do pretty
much capture, I think, what's out there within nervous studies. So the more social scientific
approach towards the arts obviously shapes the kinds of questions being asked. So one
result of this is that we also see through the critical focus on, let's say, the political
economy of the arts, we also see it in many, well, with many
odds, that many in many publications, an interest in the political or
critical potential and practice of the arts.
Yeah?
This is partially also a response to, and doesn't something I will not
discuss in detail here, to a relatively dominant debate on the creative
and cultural industries, which has really shaped the think that the
debate on the arts in the last 20 years, this idea that creative and
cultural industries contribute to, to let's see our, our contemporary knowledge economy that
they are a key economic sectors in, in our, in our current cities. And thus we're the strong focus on
economic dimensions of culture. This interest, you could say the political potential, the critical
potential of the arts is also partially a response to this. There are longer traditions, I will discuss
some of them, but this is a way of also trying to look at the creative industries the big
critically say okay well actually we miss out on a lot when we do not address the let's say the
resistant dimensions of the arts. Now the dream well there are many of course but I'm
summarised in here as three main lines of every research on the arts and I will discuss them
briefly in turn. One perhaps the most established line of research also because it ties in I think
with a history of research in, well, in our theory, basically, and in our history.
There's research on public arts and/or site-specific arts, the terms overlap.
A second line of research is research on artists and urban social movements,
the relation between artistic practice and urban social movements, and of course,
social movements, being established to bait within urban studies also.
And a third literature is literature,
this perhaps the most cultural studies oriented literature,
is literature on popular culture at urban politics.
So it's literature that that's increasingly engaged with,
with Lacy also theoretical,
philosophical literature on the political,
and how public culture plays a role in relation to urban political questions.
And I will discuss, of course, what I mean with the political here,
because it's not institutional politics per se, or if at all.
Now, the first line of research within this section is public art or site specific art.
For your readings, I added an admittedly relatively long chapter by Rosalindoyce, a New York
theorist or apologies for the length of the chapter.
But I included it because it's, well, for two reasons.
goes in the knowledge is a key art theorist, key cultural theorists who very early on I think
understood the productive connections between art theory and urban studies or geography,
critical geography. And erodes in the 1980s and 1990s a few foundational papers on the arts and
the urban. The paper here is called uneven development, public art in New York City. And basically
covers, I could say, a history of dealing with or engaging with public art in New York City
both by let's say local governments, local, the real estate developers, or let's say project
developers and artistic communities. I could have chosen other articles, the many other articles
possible. In the same book by the way, and I think I included the full book. There's also a great
critique the feminist critique of of Jameson and Harvey by way. I think the the chapter is called
Men in Space if I'm not mistaken. So basically she devices that you develop as a feminist ethnographic
critique of Jameson and Harvey. So I could definitely advise you to read this also. But in this
particular paper she basically develops a critique of the intimate utilization of public art.
So an emotion of the public by local governments and developers. So this idea that public
the way it's presented or used by local governments and developers,
since if it goes working more on planning,
in many countries you will have, if you have a kind of building scheme
or a local planning project,
a certain percentage of the budget needs to be spent on public art.
Now, for those who notice in most cases,
there is rarely a lead, in many cases,
there is a lot of, in most cases,
this does not lead to very interesting types of art.
It's a kind of tick the box, exercise,
in some cases, of course it does.
So she develops the critique of how public art
is instrumentalized in order to further,
you could say, the uneven development of New York City.
So it's shaped by elite concerns
and shaped by politically economic concerns.
So public art becomes a kind of legitimation device
for uneven development.
You should briefly refer,
as I mentioned here,
because I like the term pseudo-polar public sphere,
which is a critique of Alexander Klug and Anatyiris
on this idea of how a massian kind of ideal public sphere
as a field of deliberation.
I said, well, actually there's very little actual dialogue
taking place.
But she also hints at him.
This is something that, for example, Nancy Fraser
and other theorists later also developed
in more detail, perhaps, to this idea
of the emergent oppositional public spheres.
Yes, there is uneven development,
but it kind of sued a public sphere.
But we also see kind of oppositional public spheres emerging.
Public spheres, which on top of that,
have a heavy emphasis on, let's say, cultural and aesthetic dimensions.
So basically, often artistic communities
that are related to actors being engaged
in the design of oppositional public spheres.
And again, of course, this especially
for those interested in the arts,
has been a massive influence
in thinking to what kind of role can the arts play
in the urban and in urban development that much.
Now, here's a nice quote, a thing by adoration that summarizes, basically, this kind of
idea and the critique also.
So the idea that art cannot assume the existence of a public, but must help produce one,
and that the public sphere is less a physical space than a social, nullify to consider
a considerable extent, except that the vision is being public and non-public art.
potentially any exhibition venue is a public sphere
and conversely the location of artworks
outside privately owned galleries,
in parks and plazas,
were simply outdoors,
hardly guarantees that they will address the public.
Now, I'm sure that the discord prep needs
a bit of unpacking, right?
But basically what you're trying to get at here
is in the first sentence,
is that we cannot assume that by simply let's say
putting public art on a public square, for example,
We cannot assume that we automatically address the public.
People just don't mind not engaged with it.
People just that might just be there,
but that doesn't really make a public.
We can only make a public if it actually actively
engage with people.
So you actually have to construct a public.
And this is more than what most public arts,
supposedly public art achieves.
So this is the first question,
the question even the first critique she has. The second line is okay we this
actually leads if you think through the logical conclusions of this it means
that it simply putting arts in the out in the open doesn't make public art
but it also means that for example you can have public arts in a gallery
as long as you engage with the public this obviously would constitute public
So she critiques this distinction within much of our theory of that time that relied on this idea that
a critique of, let's say, modern art is that you move out of the gallery and into the public.
She says, "Well, actually, yes, that's a good idea, but it doesn't really make for public art per se."
So this is basically the kind of, let's say, dichotomy she's playing with and that are important.
I think to keep in mind.
Sure, some of the most important thing is to keep in mind to the start that we have in our
objects, but this art object needs actual engagement with an audience, with the public,
in order to become public. That's important to keep in mind here.
bit more concrete she has one very famous example by an equally famous artist, although not at
the time, I think he was still relatively young in his career at that point in time, which is
Richard Serra's tilted arc. This example is also discussed in the paper by Doytchen. Now, as you can
see on the image here, this is quite obviously an intervention in public space, right?
It's a massive piece of work.
It's a 37 meter long and 3.7 meter tall steel plates on fully square, which is in lower Manhattan,
New York.
Yeah?
So if anything, this is a kind of public artwork that you cannot ignore, obviously.
The way this according to Deutsche, the way this artwork has been sort of, let's say,
interpreted or let's say received, it really shows some of the problems of public art as
she made as she sees it.
Some of you could say some of the more conservative voices or sort of use of the public
space, have me criticize this piece of art because it blocks their way of passage, obviously,
If you look at the image, it completely makes impossible the usage of the public square
by, let's say, workers working moving from one building to the next.
At the same time, Deutsche Argyz, well, this doesn't necessarily make it public arts,
and some of the exaggerating claims made by critical, let's say, defenders of this piece
of work.
They have really focused, you could say, on assumptions as the shifts in behavior of
the supposed juices of this space.
So without actually talking to people, without actually engaging with their own interests,
they have assumed that the very fact that people have to sort of re-articulate their, let's
say, everyday practices, that they're led to a more aesthetic engagement with the public
space.
Now, according to Doris, the main problem of the discourse around this piece of art, as
lot of the piece of art itself, this that it relied on a very narrow aesthetic
reading, so ignoring actual uses of urban space to very generic
claims on a static uses of the square. So actually it's a kind of public art
intervention, which refuses to be public because it doesn't engage any sense
with the public. So this idea that the public involves a dialogue
is completely ignored in this sense. It's basically an ultimately
strong artist figure putting an art piece in the public square without actually becoming part and engaging with the public.
This piece was also removed in 1989 after years of critique but as perhaps a side note for the debate here.
The counter example perhaps the oppositional public sphere you can argue that the doji uses and I think this is a bit an artwork that has also been picked up by artists such as Neil Smith who also wrote a
to also roll a piece on this.
It's just of what just goes to homeless vehicle projects.
Also a public arts space,
but a different kind of animal.
So here in this case, a vehicle decided,
I had a lab by the way when looking at this picture
because I'm pretty sure it is the trunk tower in the back,
but that's something else,
which at that point, it's not that less of a,
less of symbolic value perhaps than it has now.
That's a different kind of animal.
It's also public art, also metal in many ways.
But here, it's a vehicle designed by artists,
by the artists, sorry, in singular,
in consultation with homeless people.
And it was seen in a different way.
It was seen as a practical tool
for managing everyday life of the homeless.
So in this thing, which you can't let the expand
when it's placed somewhere,
it was a space for washing, for sleeping,
but also for storage space, for example,
for collecting empty bottles or something.
So all this into one vehicle.
Vehicle, sorry.
This was both an exhibition object,
which was exhibited in USA Classic galleries,
as well as an object for actually making visible
the homeless in public space.
So I think on the basis of this example,
you already feel a bit,
the kind of different approach used towards the public
by this piece of work or by the previous piece,
by Richard Serra, because here there is an engagement
with specific urban users,
highly marginalized to use on top of this,
and thus, implicitly or explicitly,
a critique of uneven urban developments,
because it's a piece of work that is situated in public space
and makes visibly percadia effects of uneven urban developments
on a wider group of, let's say, urban users.
Okay, maybe to wrap up here on this, on this first strand of research.
So these are all examples of site specific art that moved art beyond the exhibition space
into the urban.
So there was a thing within art theory and art history, kind of internal critique of the
art world. We have to move out of the museums, out of the galleries, but also a broadening
or as a result of that also, a broadening of a static debate to either social concerns.
So this then leads to notions such as going by critically, in this case, by a health foster such
that the artist has a nographer, which looks at the role of the artist in the collaborative process,
or the artist has a participant of the reserve, so the artist has an ethnographer.
So the critique of foster is also, and this has been picked up in later work also,
is that the globalization of art market, and this is where I say different disciplinary debates
also become interesting, that the globalization of the art market, there's something rarely addressed
sufficiently, I think in other studies, leads, for example, to commissioning of artists to produce
community-based site-specific artworks, however, without a clear knowledge of the local context.
So we see that by annual logic, for example, the art festival logic, where artists are flown into
particular sites in order to develop community-based work, but they are adding to the community.
So often these are, let's say, all you superficially speaking, public works of public art.
And again, so much of this was foreshadowed, I think, by the work of Dolce also, but of course,
those others at this point in time.
So that's the first strand of research.
The second strand of research is around
artisan's urban social movements.
And of course, I'm making analytical distinction here.
In practice, some of these debates go over lab
and there are interactions.
But for the purpose of discussion,
I think it's helpful to keep them a bit separate.
So the second strand of research
tries to look at artisan urban social movements.
So there's a long, standing tradition obviously
of artists engaging in social movements,
but mostly those have been a research
I would argue outside of urban studies.
Again, we didn't let's say the fields specific debates
such as theater or such as visual studies
et cetera art history.
Within urban studies, I think most of the recent debates
in this area has been the only critique
of the creative class and creative industries
policies as I've already hinted at, or perhaps neoliberal or entrepreneurial urbanism more widely.
So what kind of role you are to play in or part of urban social movements in critiquing,
you could say the neoliberalization of the urban. Now there's a nice paper actually by
a UNist Novi and Kleakkulon, who many of you have seen attended today, who wrote a nice paper
We're struggling for the right to the creative city in Berlin and Hamburg.
I really give a nice brief, brief, but nice overview, I think, of urban social movements.
So it's a kind of literature which I, well, we don't really discuss the thing at our
social geography, that's an important literature, which moves from the history of squatting
and demonstrations against a renewal politics to urban counterculture.
then zoom in on the role of artists and cultural workers in contesting
color-created class and creative industry's politics. Now there's a lot that can be said about
this but what is interesting here of course is that automatically debate becomes you could say
sociological or social scientific because the moment you start looking at artists within social
movements you can no longer look just at their aesthetic expressions but you automatically have to
look at what is practically speaking their role within an often quiet heterogenous diverse
composition of protest movements. So we see artists collaborating with diverse
set of actors and that of course shapes their artistic practice. The role of
artists here, at least this is what no being conno highlights, I like strongly
I think they are definitely onto something there, is that artists to some
extent have a privileged role or a particular role within the urban social
movements because they have access to an experience with media networks and
and the familiarity with communication techniques. So this then leads to a discussion around the role of
artists in how, let's say particular urban conflicts are framed and reframes by artists in often
visual or other ways. And many examples you can discuss here. This is one example discussed also in
the article of the "Media Spake" quote "test in Berlin". For those that know Berlin, you will know
probably also know sort of the history a bit of media. I will not discuss this here. It's a big
urban development area on let's say well there's a southern part of really signed northern part
of Keweisbach partially which really lets us look at the counter mobilization because there's
also the area which is let's say a concentration of artistic and and and leisure and
and clubbing activity.
So here's a one simple example where sort of artists
you could say have been involved in developing
different, let's say, visual aesthetics.
And it says this basically ironically
builds on the B-BERLIN branding scheme.
So those who don't know it, just Google it.
And it uses the same kind of design.
But then changes the kind of language.
And sort of ironically, so instead of being
being creative and being a foyer, but how to translate that.
If I can translate that, being used and thrown away.
So this is a lot of viable.
Yeah, commodifiable is perhaps the closest.
Thank you, very, very good point for me and Basas,
but you're right, commodifiable.
And they replaced it by Zizamesgrystim,
so I saw the Dari-Zizai-Rita-Stun, so it could be self.
Again, difficult to try itself.
So, independent something on those lines, we saw the solidarity and be resistance.
So stop gentrification.
So this is one example.
Other examples, of course, not discussing this particular article, but from other other
sites, of course, this kind of artistic, let's say framing, or political and urban conflicts
ties in with a much much longer history of art and protest.
Most obviously in street art as well as graphic design.
So a couple of examples that are, let's say, illustrative of this,
but certainly not exhaustive.
So on the top right, you see a performance protest of an extension,
extension rebellion, protest in London.
The middle left, I think, has been quite similar to most of you
who think the Black Lives Matter, painted street.
I think this one in the Washington DC.
or to the bottom right, claim state, well, if they're painting, stating the
low to the depth repayments, street arts, intervention, and Buenos Aires.
And I've could have used many, many other examples, but just to give a sense of
the rare sort of artist play a role in urban social movements or at least a
protest if it's less organized than a social movement.
And again, this has a much, much longer history going back many, many years.
Some would argue since the emerged of industrialization in many ways.
So the last,
the last rant within this section that I want to discuss with you
is public culture nerve and politics.
This is, last you could say, let's, around urban social movement,
it also lasts around the art world as such, but more about more broader cultural expressions.
So here we really go back to the classical core of cultural studies that it discussed before
with you. So here is a focus on popular culture as in everyday life, as questioning authority,
but also as imagining political alternatives. So the kind of language that we then use or see,
use and this kind of research is that it's about politics beyond governments and politicians
to become the street politics as a second by the ad call that's also kind of informalization.
This is where the informality that turns pops up again as you see. Informalization of the state
as for example Julia and Boudgo as called it. Nice book by the way.
Again, there are many, many examples here to discuss.
The classic case I would argue in this field of research,
it is hip hop or rap music more narrowly,
which has been studied by now, I think,
by multiple multiple disciplines,
range from musicology, cultural studies,
and anthropology, but also urban studies,
which traditionally has focused,
I think, strongly on a kind of classic cultural studies,
community orientation, urban localities,
So the hood, the ghetto as classic urban teams,
but we also are thinking in a more critical literature,
has paid attention to, let's say, the way
hip hop culture has become, let's say commodified
in its globalization of its cultural form.
But also how it has been picked up by people
from outside of, let's say, the US,
as supposedly the source of hip hop culture.
So that's the classic case.
libraries full of books by now I think on hip-hop. Some more interesting than others, this book by
Marie Forman is quite an interesting example though. Similar research has also been done
on other genres. Typically a lot of attention has been paid to music, we see it in other fields of
activity, also but music has received perhaps most attention and relation to popular culture and
the political. A range of from clubbing culture but also to opera although the political perhaps
less obviously there to punct to jazz to all kinds of other cultural expressions.
Now what all these strands amount to is that they point to different aesthetic strategies to
engage the urban. Yeah, and this is something that, well, has also increasingly received attention
in our studies. In an article about Timon Bayes, I put a reference at the bottom of the slides.
He points to a number of different aesthetic strategies. As I said, as I write here,
they are politically distinct, but in practice, of course, they are messier. Some,
some, let's say, aesthetic practices might be involved in a number of things at the same time.
Here we said, "Okay, we basically have spectacle, grassroots, social work,
are rising the senses and you can automatically see it to how so many examples I've shown before
can be one or more of these things. So let's say for example the Black Lives Matter,
let's say Banner on the street so to speak, in a way you could argue this is grassroots,
you could argue this is also social work, you could argue it's tough somehow it also arouses
the consensus because it's sometimes it questions the norms of what these
trees are for and questions differently say media representations but quite
obviously it's also a spectacle because it's a really sort of traveled
widely and can easily be used in kind of commodification strategy almost of
branding almost particular cities yeah so there are all kinds of different
dimensions and it's in a very good question ultimately to look at concrete
artistic practices to look at what the different dimensions, let's say the relation to each other is.
Okay, that's a long stretch for one slide, but it might also be one in the longer
longer discussions. I'll take a short break, near for questions. So please
just either type them in the chat or just start unmuting and speaking if there are any questions on
this section. Maybe it gives me a chance to do even more.
Wow, that was a pre-prepared question. That was a fast or
unless you type very fast. So Olica Aces a question
or a point. I want to raise attention to your related phenomenon, where an
artistic, creative approach is used in part
of a broader participatory and redevelopment strategy.
Here's some sort of institutionalizing of arts
and their movement is happening.
A small quirky teams of architects, planners, activists,
and artists are leading the process.
And sure, an example, AAF and then there's a website.
Maybe, Olic, you can--
so if I understand you correctly, we won't look at the example.
Now, then, it's your point being that artists
can actually become urban developers themselves.
Olic it.
I don't see you so you have to unmute the weekend.
Now I see you, but your muted.
All right.
Sorry.
Yeah.
Exactly.
Like artists are becoming part of the planning process
or more.
I think that the low threshold approach of artistic
experimental, like creativeness, as being employed
in order to justify maybe participatory processes
or lead to a more inclusion of people
or let them participate in the first place,
but also just to get the people on board
and create some sort of tolerance.
So this one would be like the creative,
what is it called?
The festival of creative urban living in Milton Keynes.
the UK, England.
So yeah, it sounds like coming from a very dry urban planning
background.
This is like a weird thing to do.
Because people who are attending this there
usually not aware of the broader scope
of this whole development that's happening to them.
So that's just interesting to also take a look at.
It's a good addition, something that I don't explicitly
mentioned here, but it's a it's a neurology new trend I think, certainly something that we see
more and more of. I mean it was there before, but that become more visible, I think in the last
10 years. I would still argue though that the same kind of critical vocabulary already introduced
by Deutsche is also necessary for these projects, because in some of these projects and initiatives
at least we do see a relative instrumental or instrumentalization of artists. I.e. not the one artist is
is not the other artists, right?
So we see certain artists standing up
as entrepreneurs, you could say,
and becoming project developers
in relatively uncritical ways.
And I can name some examples also in Brussels
where this is happening,
which actually leads to a fair amount of critique
also within your artistic community.
- Yeah, and I wouldn't say that this is necessarily
like a bad or a good thing.
The teams that are involved are really good teams, but it's just like always look very critical
because also the urban governments try sometimes to use this strategy and not in a very deceiving way.
Yeah, okay, excellent. Thank you. I see another comment or comment literally by VIA. Please unmute.
Yeah, but you already rise this critic from the Dosh, what is her name?
Dosh, yeah. And is also the critic from Zurkin, like this tricky fact of the art,
we also the vehicle of gentrification and stuff. So always super tricky to speak about the
art and its puttain shaw in your run and space, let's say.
but yeah absolutely so I'll give another example later on I think also which which raises this
questions and the article I mentioned by sorry I can go back I can go back. About Timon Bass
I also mentioned some of these ambivalences that are seemingly unavoidable so to speak there's
no pure space in that sense. Okay excellent and then there's Max also has a comment.
I just add on this point that Ulricha raised and a
this theme of institutionalization and instrumentation of art and artists.
I think Amsterdam is actually an interesting example because there is this
municipal policy which could be translated as the
breeding ground policy whereby the city assigns certain buildings as
available for workshops and for artists to work there and often it's also very related to
yeah strategy actually to gentrify a particular area I don't know whether there's any
research done on this plus maybe you know. It has been definitely also by the Amsterdam
College Law Service Strong Service Studies Research Edition at the University of Amsterdam but also
others. No, no, that's been critical. We should be in
none of it. And that one's just a particular case. It's an
interesting case in any case because it's it's very
elastic, advanced, professional and industrialization of
the arts, the urban level. And the bootplasm, the breeding
policy policy policy is yeah, it's it's striking in the way
it's sort of well, use and test positive side effects also,
but the way it little really uses the arts in in relative
classical urban development strategies. That's definitely true. Yeah, not a research
I've been known in that. Yeah. Okay, excellent. Thank you for the comments. They really
add some very important additional thoughts here. Other points, if not, I continue with the
third part of the presentation and that's the another section or direction of research on
on the arts or on culture and the urban.
This is what I would call,
or this is basically my label,
but I think it's what I would call
research on cultural infrastructures and informal urbanism.
So this is where the lesson in the literature on the informal
actually starts broadening to, let's say,
literature on informal urbanism,
which might be a phrase that you've come across
also a number of times.
And this overlaps the thing in recent years
where increasing attention has been paid
to let's think the infrastructure dimension
of urban cultures.
Some scholars have already talked about
an infrastructural term.
I disliked talking about terms
because it's very claiming a new fashion
and it helps to get cited more,
but yeah, there are so all these things built
on all their interests also.
Having said that, there is obviously more and more
attention being paid within our studies
to let's see questions of infrastructure
and not just narrowly defined,
but very diverse types of infrastructure,
as you will see.
Now, to hear one example, I think which is a good example
or it discussed by the team and base article
that I mentioned before, which you discussed in this article
is the work of the Chicago based RSTS targets,
some of you might know him,
where to the left you see a piece that you did
for the document,
well, not by annual, but document a five yearly festival
in Castell, so the document 2013, which I think was in 2012, even correct. 12 ballast for
Ugunot House, which basically is a restoration of an empty building in Castell using labor and
materials from the south side of Chicago. So it's an interesting case because it was a kind of rundown
building in Castell where we had, let's say, where the 30th of the case, the artist had materials,
but also workers moved transported, so to say, from Chicago to Castell to actually renovate the
stability and to actually perform in the building, et cetera.
So here's space and let's say the infrastructure
of this space really emerges a kind of social space,
while at the same time directing attention
to migrant labor and in the case of the SDK,
it's work and the kind of the issues
it engages with with black cultural expression
in a very particular space in Castle.
So there's a very, let's say,
concrete artistic intervention.
To a right, you see, let's say, in a way,
the reference project for the castle, the castle case,
which is a door chest project, the projects in Chicago,
which is basically you can argue,
and it links back, I think, to the previous,
well, addition raised by the Liliq,
but perhaps in a last, let's say,
planar move, and basically this is a kind of urban
development project led by TS to Gaze in the south side
which it could go.
Where it gets started buying up abandoned property
after the 2008 financial crisis
and has redeveloped these buildings with local communities,
with other artists, often creating a mix
of artists' spaces, of community spaces,
of, let's say, local restaurants,
or in this particular case, also a library and archive.
So the Dorchester project.
Now, what's interesting here, of course,
that we are still in the realm of let's say issues around urban
culture but we've started being more and more attention to
where practically literally, materially speaking,
are these located. So this really leads them to the material
infrastructure dimension of urban culture and some of what I
consider to be some of the more interesting, more productive line of
research on urban culture in the last years, as really looked at these
kind of infrastructure dimensions. Another pushing does a bit broader and perhaps also
becoming less local and is orientation towards infrastructure is a book that I added for the
reading for today by Brian Larkin from 2008, Signal and Noise Media Infrastructure at Urban Culture
Nigeria, which is for those that have rats. I don't expect you to have
rat the full book, but maybe maybe the introduction at least, which is an
anthropological study on the cultural work of media technologies.
There's the quote and they're rolling what in producing what we call urban
Africa, focusing on Kano and Muslim city in northern, Islamic city in northern
Nigeria. The lock-in book is interesting because it's just a very interesting
book but also because he flax a number of the base that are, let's say, essential in
research on infrastructures in general or cultural infrastructures in particular.
One being, it's not just about, let's say, pipes, etc. and literally infrastructure,
but also a lot about the symbolic or representational logic of infrastructures.
So what do infrastructures mean?
How are they interpreted?
How are they envisioned?
How are they imagined?
This really receives a lot of attention to think in most of the infrastructure research.
Also, attempts of governments to govern or control these infrastructures, it gives examples of this in the case of Nigeria.
At the same time, also, the unexpected or unintended consequences of infrastructure development.
Governments, for example, or let's say our local developers can have a plan,
I can't have an idea as to why do you want to develop a certain infrastructure, but it doesn't necessarily mean that infrastructure is also used in this way.
So here we're back a thing to perhaps do the all the discussion about strategies and tactics, but transpose to an infrastructure discussion.
And the last element related to this, of course,
is that around these infrastructures,
we see all kinds of informal social practices
in everyday life emerging,
which then are worthy of attention,
but also worthy of research.
So the example here I gave, for example,
you can easily, if I would completely imagine
how around these spaces, social practices emerge
and are developed.
And they would perhaps not exist
without these infrastructures.
And that's the thing, the importance
want to keep in mind here.
Nightly, exactly. It gives, and for me, the most interesting chapter in the book is perhaps
the last chapter, if I remember correctly, on the role of piracy in Nigeria.
So, the example he gives, for example, is how Nigerian video and piracy and circus of distribution
emerged in Nigeria and how this actually relates to a kind of a
perhaps which goes called a full ecosystem of cultural but also obviously economic activity
largely informal in the sense that it's barely regulated perhaps also illegal or
illegitimate or something because it's often at that point in time when you did this research
late 19th early 2000s often copies illegal copies of Hollywood and Indian films
But we're with the same incandel as in Northern Nigeria city,
really emerging literally as a kind of distribution hub for the wider African region.
Yes, so with people on the right for example, selling it on the street,
but also the same people of other people actually moving the goods so
to the speed, the material from one city to other cities, often crossing boundaries.
Now from the 1990s onwards, I think we've seen an increasing production also,
and this is the the the argument developed by Larkin of Nigerian and especially
housing language videos leading to a quite organized system of how is that video film production
but it building on the existing fire and infrastructure. Yeah so again a classic case of informal
urbanism a very slippery or unclear distinction between where when a something still informal when
when does something become formed? Because it has also become part to a certain extent of a formal
registered economy with some business and growing bigger and bigger. But at the same time with,
for example, how has the films aesthetically and organization still been shaped by you to say the
older pirate aesthetics and infrastructure. This is also the kind of research which has received a
lot of attention in recent years, which I have ever labeled here as being part of, let's say,
research on cultural infrastructure and informal urbanism.
Or to give another example of paper I wrote myself to get away with a PhD student a while ago
called Spaces of Open-S Urban Citizenship and Cultural Infrastructure,
to come alive at Istanbul, which focused in Latte in a more institutional way perhaps,
less ethnographic way on the institutional geography of collaboration and support to sustain
local cultural spaces and networks in the shadow of the states. So the argument we develop here is
that in a Turkey and partially also an Istanbul, increasingly being let's say shaped by kind of
authoritarian, semi-authoritarian state in any case, we discussed in some detail how particular
cultural organizations salt and depth of the North Coast as Istanbul, they might know the organizations,
how they act as kind of cultural infrastructures
of, let's say, common life or a different way
when we're saying, "Oh, actually public life in Istanbul,"
largely by actually collaborating with very many other organizations,
but also offering spaces.
And this is what the image to the right shows--
sorry, what this image shows--
offering spaces--
well, sorry, offering actual space in their buildings
to all kinds of different organizations.
So you see a kind of let's say hidden or semi hidden cultural infrastructure,
which doesn't easily show when you look at just the main cultural organizations,
but which really shaped you could say cultural practices in this particular city,
and which is only possible or in any case is made possible by the actual existence of these
actual spaces in the city of Solvindepo. So again, another possible, let's say, entry point,
inter-measage on cultural infrastructures and informal urbanism.
Last point perhaps for this slide, well that's not the last example, is what we see happening
in the research and cultural infrastructures.
Much of the research on urban culture is research that is most, you could say, fundamental,
let's say, basic, basic real academic research, but it also has a strong applied nature.
And the notion of infrastructure has also started, it emerged or started popping up in
policy documents across the world. That has many consequences, not all of them positive, but to a
large extent of things is an interesting development where we let's say cultural policy documents and
cultural actual cultural policy practices did not refer to infrastructure last say 10 years ago.
We see in the last five years or so we see various organizations, very local and regional governments,
actually using the notion of infrastructure in order to pay attention to certain, let's say,
infrastructure dimensions of cultural industries also. So here a few examples on the top left
creative city news, cultural infrastructure, an integral component of Canadian communities.
This is quite strong and again I think it's critique of the creative industries literature,
even among policymakers where we say okay we actually need a wider diversity of cultural
infrastructures that actually connect with our local communities, whatever that may mean but that's
the last 80 a game. Or for example, sustaining London as a cultural capital, why London needs
the cultural infrastructure plan. This again is not a strand of the debate, I think in policy
communities where we see because of the increasing, let's say gentrification and increasing real estate
price in especially global cities. Even policy makers, let's say mainstream policy has started
realizing that if we continue like this, we're going to have no artists left in the city. So we need
need to actually start thinking about the availability of cultural infrastructure in our cities
and to make this available literally in order to sort of keep, let's say, the status of
London as a global city but also as a cultural city. So why London is the cultural infrastructure
plan? It's similar to the bit around cultural infrastructure at New South Wales, which is
this mixed-setting also of the Canadian example I just mentioned and the London example of
available in your space.
Or another example in Brussels, and this is what
I'm partially involved in by a panamanan,
so permanence, the name of the association
pretty much sums it up, which is a practice-based research
I'm also now involved in where we try
to develop an infrastructure for permanently affordable
and about its social and cultural space in Brussels.
So basically claiming a space in Brussels,
which is open not just to artists,
but also to other types of users, such as refugees,
such as social housing, such as university researchers,
et cetera, in order to look at different models of ownership
also, where artists are no longer reliant
and are used on, I say, temporary use,
but they can actually, let's say, permanently,
literally, permanently claim space
through all kinds of ownership models,
partially building on issues around less
the community land trust or social co-operatives.
Okay, that's a lot of information.
Just to sum this up, if you look at the cultural infrastructure in informal urbanism literature,
I see at least the following analytical shifts.
We have moved, I think, from a concern with the informal economy, in anthropology and
development studies and everyday life tactics and cultural studies to informal urbanism.
This is the term that is perhaps the most present now.
It's no longer informality as such, but the phrase informal urbanism you see constantly.
So we've moved to a situation where, sorry, here we are.
And we see continued interest in labor questions,
social and badenness of economic relations
and interrelation of informal networks
and informal institutions.
So all the classic informality discussions.
But at the same time, we see a diversification of topics.
So it's no longer just about,
you could save informal labor markets.
No, it's also about DIY urbanism.
It's also about co-working space.
There's also about urela gardening, about co-housing,
or about artistic interventions in public space.
It's also about squatting.
There's also about self-built housing,
and the list is endless, yeah?
All these kinds of practices, of course,
each with their own, let's say approaches and styles.
You see all these kinds of practice being labeled
as expressions of informal urbanism.
There's a legitimate question to ask,
how useful such a slippery term is,
but it has certainly led to a broadening
of empirical interest.
As already mentioned before, I think the term informal
has really helped to move beyond a global style
first global north studies on cities
and to really look at the informal urbanism
as global urbanism.
Whether the informal in a way has become foundational
to our understanding of cities at large.
And the last point I'll skip for now is less ascension.
Okay, I need a set of water.
questions, please, or comments or additions on this part.
If any.
Maybe I could ask a question about, let's say,
these structures, these infrastructures
growing in the shadow of the state, as you have mentioned it.
So we noticed that actually a lot of communes in Brussels
are trying to set themselves on the, let's say, cultural map.
We are working in urban analysis on the community for her,
that has its own like a very active plan
and wants to be a leader and a new place for art
and culture in Brussels.
- Yes.
- I wonder what your take on that was also working with
with the association that you mentioned,
you must be seeing also a different side of the influence
of local government in Brussels on that.
- Yeah, exactly.
Yeah.
I mean, I mean, asking a question about a city in which
I live, of course, is always difficult
because I can talk about this for hours.
But it's a tricky, I mean, I would say for that
to a logic stance has become a creative or cultural hub
for artists, which obviously is,
despite for municipality.
As often happens in Brussels is not because of the government that we see interesting activity happening somewhere.
Brussels is a city that really relies on strong, let's say,
well, social movements and citizen activity.
And there's also applies a thing to artistic activity for it.
Have we said that what, of course, which is now see happening is that because for there,
It has become, let's say, a concentration,
let's say, for artists, we do see, of course,
that local municipality is increasing also using this
to in a way to brand itself, right?
To, as such, there is nothing wrong with this.
I mean, I don't live in Florida,
we need to look into very specific local details
at the same time, and don't have the feeling
that they have a strong strategic perspective
on the role of arts and culture and the municipality.
So it doesn't, and that's applied,
it doesn't get to my knowledge, move beyond,
they kind of offering of temporary,
intermuse spaces for artists.
So it doesn't get seemed to be a kind of broader,
let's say more substantial perspective on this,
but maybe you already know more about this
through the human analysis
and the work that you've done so far.
I think we definitely see a lot of policy claims for sure and a lot of use of it.
So now indeed it's a next challenge to look into how that actually plays out on the ground
and whether that actually translates into action.
But thank you for your reaction.
Yes, thank you.
Are you a comment as well?
Last year I did a literature study about gentrification in Brussels, especially in the
region of St. John's Mullenbeck.
We saw in the 80s the Commodoto vartists start living there.
So it became very popular to live there and the results was for people, for people need
to move out.
So I guess there is always a small dark sites of this one,
we'll just do gentrification especially in Brussels.
Yeah, I mean, I can only say, in short, yes, to that.
[LAUGHTER]
Yeah, I mean, there are different opinions on gentrification
in Brussels.
I mean, some would say, well, there's
clear gentrification and there's expansion.
If you look at the numbers that might the actual expulsion of people from
Circle Look at these might be limited still, but it's clear that certain areas
are changing rapidly. One of the things we're trying to do, which for example,
the permanent project I'm permanent project I mentioned, is to also think
about spatial because one of the problems is let's say artists move into
certain spaces. They are looking for, let's say, work and living spaces, but in a
way, unintentionally so they then actually lead to a push out effect for
other for adolescent poor citizens in most cases.
At the same time, it's not as if artists are belonging
let's say to an urban elite in general.
So one of the very small level of retries
to do with the permanent project is also
to try to think of, let's say, spaces that are co-owned
and where let's say the move of artists into a certain area
does not automatically translate into the move out
of other citizens.
Realistically speaking, of course, my position on this
is that this can only partially be solved on a project level
because practically speaking, you simply need more social housing
for this.
And most of this is disastrous city
when it comes to percentage of social housing,
let alone quality of social housing.
We're really talking about a few percentages
of the total housing stock, which is social housing,
which is completely different, for example,
in a city such as Amsterdam,
which has also seen gentrification obviously,
but that's the social housing stock.
Definitely helps there with all his own complexities
and problems.
So yeah.
Any other comments?
No, okay.
Then I'll move to the last section I think of the session.
I think we're more or less okay on time, which is good.
So I did, I promised last week that I would also have a separate section on tourism.
I don't.
So I didn't manage to fit it in.
And it's picked up in some of these elements implicitly, I think.
So I'm also less of an expert on urban tourism.
I know the literature quite well, but it's not something that I do research on myself.
But this is certainly also, let's see, another strand of research, which is interesting
from an urban cultural perspective.
However, the last strand I want to discuss with you today is literature which is perhaps
more closely related to the humanities than some other elements that I discussed with you today,
which I flag here as the research on sensory urbanism, visual cultures or sensory urbanism,
and then two examples, visual cultures and sounds.
Brian Locke is text that was on your reading for today already highlighted, I think, how
media technologies and aesthetics shape urban places. So this idea that actually by building
certain distribution infrastructures, by having certain places, you actually shape urban places
through truly technologies and aesthetics. In term, and this you could see is, let's say, the more
experiential, phenomenological or our user point of view, this implies also that places are
experienced through multiple senses, seeing, listening, smelling, touching, tasting. Now,
Historically, most research has focused on the visual dimension.
But increasingly, we also see it, and this
has a long, long history.
I'll give a few simple examples in a minute.
But increasingly, we also see the attention
paid to other senses.
And I'll briefly discuss this to research, which I think
is pretty interesting, but obviously,
in bias, because I tend to like, mostly, or focus mostly
on music and sound myself.
But I'll briefly discuss some of the research
on the auditory culture, sonic cultures, or music and sound.
Now, to start with the visual culture spots,
so remember Jameson.
So this is, let's say, the hotel that we've already discussed
in Jameson text 1984.
Basically, you could say one element of,
if not star architecture, but at least,
let's see various sort of in-your-face architecture.
And within our studies, a lot of attention has been paid to this kind of architecture,
So based to buildings designed to leave a strong visual impression because that is what these buildings do and what they aim to do
Now the analytical focus starting already in the 1980s
Some elements have let's say survived the years others have not has been on cognitive disorientation
But also on landmark statements in a city with emphasis on spectacle and surveillance with emphasis in consumption landscapes and
An emphasis on represitation and global attractiveness
So this is all you can say well rehearse territory within urban studies and which has a long history of of analysis
Now star architecture you literally
Ads value to world cities are aspiring world cities
So the architecture becomes you could say an urban icon in global rankings
It really helps and here is it there is a tourism reference. It really helps to put world cities on the map for tourism and consumption purposes
these sites or the surrounding areas become sites for business investment or also for upmarket
Residential houses. So they literally had value to aspire the world sees true legacy strong visual claims
Now this has this of course has a history, right? This is not we have we should not be naive
Let's historically and leave and pretend that this is something of less in the post for this age
or something that we've only seen since the late 20th century,
although it probably has a increase
and probably, let's say, more,
let's say, professional and strategic attention
is now being a paid to, let's say,
the visual dimension of cities compared to the,
let's say, the decades before.
But it has the much longer history.
The most obvious or let's say a classic example,
of course, being the Eiffel Tower,
which itself was built to put Paris on the map
or to make it more visual again.
Part of, let's say, if a broader exhibition set up,
originally intended temporary,
but has been therefore quite some time,
which now is a classic landmark case in,
or example in, whoops sorry,
around the world when people think about Paris.
Or another example,
so I'm working with two computers here.
So this is sometimes confusing.
Another example, the Opera House in Sydney.
Again, an example, even if you've never visited Sydney,
you will know this building.
The Opera House in Sydney architect,
Jion-Otsan, or another example, which I think by now also
everyone knows, which is perhaps in a way
the more recent example, the Guggenheim Museum in Bilbao,
Spain, which in its very setup was intended to leave
you could see a visual impression.
And you will see that many people visit the Google
NIMU's email bill bow without seeing anything else
or a very little of bill bow as such.
So I would dare to claim that the vast majority of people
that visit the Google NIMU's email bill bow
will leave the city without really knowing much
about bill bow.
Yeah, I mean, there's not a question if they should be.
It should.
But it's clear that this kind of visual attraction
plays a key role.
and has played at the same time in an almost role
in increasing tourism flows towards global.
Or even more recent example, the Elfilam,
the Afro-Hos in Hamburg, 800 million euros,
enormously over budget, which is very typical also
for someone that allowed to start architecture.
But in general though, and not surprising perhaps also
is that many of these buildings are cultural landmarks
that both offer you the same culture
and a design space for tourism and consumption.
So this, as I said, this is well-rehearsed territory,
still a lot of interesting research is being done on this,
but it's quite established in the base.
I'll give some example.
Of course, that leads to all kinds of discussions also
about who has the biggest tower,
I won't go into the masculine connotations
of building the world's tallest building,
but it's quite obvious here, the Gosh Khalifa,
And also a thing in this is perhaps a shift which is new work,
although also not completely new,
is that especially in the same world global cities,
such as New York, such as London,
we see a lot of entice being paid by private developers
to very upmarket elite residential housing.
So this is height one in London, for example.
It is interesting also because there's somebody's space
for upmarket residential housing,
They are built to leave a visual impact.
They are built to attract buyers, multi-buyers.
But let's say they're running jokingly or low.
The sadness of the story in many ways
is that if you look at how, for which period of the year,
these apartments or buildings are actually occupied
by actual inhabitants is often quite limited.
Some of these are just apartments to park, to park like money,
but not necessarily laundry money,
but not necessarily actually lived there for us
state is a substantial period of the year.
Or another example in New York for the 4-23 Park Avenue.
Perhaps less spectacular, but maybe in 10 in a similar direction,
these visually speaking, is this building at the Canal Zone,
the upside tower in Brussels. But the prices are certainly more affordable
than the word the price you will see in New York or London.
Now, what's interesting about this visual culture, especially in sort of new media times,
is that these landmark statements, these are actual buildings, these are buildings very
much, let's say, very costly investments in urban space. But the vast majority of people
will know these buildings, they will see these buildings through social media and online
magazines or maybe let's say a coffee-tailed book magazines. So these buildings play a massive
an important role in city branding and hopefully attracting cultural tourism and also in
circulating on social media. So you've got images such as this where as the local Instagram
is a search for star architecture or spectacular architecture you will see loads of images or even
Let's say in New York using using, let's say, certain space or new builds in New York
and labeling it as best Instagram spots.
And then you get these interesting, let's say, tourists who basically photograph themselves
with the building in the background as it kind of goes, let's say I've been there kind
of attitudes.
But it's quite obvious where sort of the spectacular architect plays a key role not in
in relation to questions actual use,
but Lashi and request in relation to questions of re-presentation,
and how can you actually,
how well these images look like on Instagram
or other websites.
Now, this is,
it's perfectly this is interesting.
These are new phenomena with longer histories,
but very interesting.
Theoretically, you had raised certain questions
about how we should look at city developments,
how we should look at how cities change over time.
This ties in, I would argue with a literature
on what is sometimes called geographies of circulation,
where we really try to understand city cultures
as an effect of circulation.
So not necessarily designed locally,
but actually images traveling between cities.
Of course, also traveling of architects and other experts,
but also concepts, images, plans, best practices.
So where urban culture as such,
perhaps also urban policy as such,
becomes a kind of practice of inter-referencing.
So the city's referencing each other,
or building's referencing each other,
to stake out the claim, so to speak.
Now, all this links back in my view,
although not always recognize the such within the Middle
United River studies, to classic cultural studies concerns
with the politics of representation,
but also to an anthropological interest.
And there's a very nice book and article,
but I am up a duet I already from the late 1980s,
on the social life of objects.
So how do objects travel true space and true time?
Okay.
Last section for today,
because this is our set,
is it's well, well,
it's trial and theory within nervous studies
to really look at the visual
in relation to the urban.
But especially, yeah, the last 10, 20 years,
I guess we see an increasing interest
also in other senses and the urban.
The example, I briefly want to discuss
which you today as a closure for the lecture,
isn't it this research and auditory sonic cultures
to vocabulary tends to differ?
There is a lot of interesting work being done on this still,
sometimes also by practicing artists,
practicing musicians that also write,
such as for example, Brandon Labell,
who were quite a nice book on acoustic territories,
sound culture, and everyday lives.
So you see again, everyday life returning
as vocabulary.
So in chapter three, for example,
which is some of the examples I use here,
where you explicitly build some
of the subtodes to practice a very alive,
and where we develop the view on walking,
not an individual way, as actually just had told
because he had a lot of discussions as a tool
about how you look in relation to building,
how you position yourself in relation to the city,
but where we develop the view in walking through
an auditory or rhythmic perspectives.
And then it gives all kinds of examples,
such as crosswalk signals, warning alarms,
or personal audio, so listening on your smartphone to music while walking through the city,
but also for example sound art or marching bands or protest,
and a role sound place in let's say experiencing and structuring, let's say city life.
It gives the example, for example, of Floriano Humano, Philante Sao Paulo.
I think he actually mentions his Rio de Janeiro, but I think it's in Sao Paulo.
We walked around with a big speaker on his back,
which basically with a voice, speaking on loud,
something like don't pay attention to them
if I remember correctly.
So we're walking around the streets in public space,
don't pay attention, don't pay attention,
which obviously the exact opposite will then happen,
which is a pretty nice or neat intervention,
I think in public space as a kind of art project.
Another example is that we have an active network.
And this is a much longer history, also, of field
records.
People doing field recordings.
There's a very nice website for those
that are into this stuff, which is called Sound Cities.
Just Google it, you'll find it, which has collected, let's say,
field records from cities across the world,
a way you can actually play-- well, it's
that the maps literally on the map of these cities
are where you can play, let's say,
sounds from these cities or from these particular locations
in these cities.
And that's the lesson,
ever growing database,
but there's also active community of sound recording,
field records, recording sounds or cities.
And it's quite nice if you have a bit of time
to, let's say, to go through some of the sounds
and also experience some of the, let's say,
differences in sounds are between, between different cities.
One example I want to just briefly play and I hope there's all the works with sounds.
I'm just going to play it and then you're going to have to tell me if you hear the sounds.
Turn on do turn on the sounds.
It's a very nice piece I think by Finn's Bloom and Mexican artist, Simba Fova-Sun
novel from Mexico City 2015, where we basically manipulated the walking signals of on the street
in Mexico City, and where we replaced the sound of a pedestrian traffic light with the
like, that's a classic sound, with the sound of a donkey, which according to him is a nice
way of well, paying attention to well. First of all, making people think differently or
look differently, right, this is something else than I expected, so it's a kind of intervention,
but also attracting attention to an animal which has largely disappeared from Mexico City,
Cizzies urban space which was different last say 30, 40, 50 years ago.
So I'm just going to look at this works and you're going to have to tell me just do it like this
or something if the sound is okay.
Do your sounds? Okay perfect, no, just kidding.
Good job, Good job.
[SOUND]
[MUSIC]
(screaming)
(music)
[Music]
(singing)
(crowd chattering)
(music)
Okay, so just one small example which I thought is a pretty nice intervention with a lot
of humor.
Fili's bloom also did quite, he's done a lot of work as a sound artist, he also did quite
some interesting work and this is kind of early work if you'd argue.
But where later on he actually worked in collaboration with blind people to actually and
let's say sounds and their experience of urban space in order to sort of make
artistic well artistic projects which is also some interesting work to just
check this website if you're interested in this kind of stuff.
This example I'll move to the very end which is a nice example by the way of
sound and protest and there are many examples of this following the 2011
Fukushima nuclear accident in Japan.
Japan's are actually a wide range of public protests. Here is one example which was a sound demo
organized by Elus Association called Shiroto Noan, amateur revolt, and the organ as a kind of sound
demo protest, which is pretty neat if you like noise, which I do. But since it's a 10 minute video,
I will leave this for the very end and close my... Sorry, that one will come in a second.
and move to my conclusions.
Before I do so, are there any questions
on the section on the sensory organism?
And I know it's almost 8 p.m. so I know it's late.
Yeah, just unmute yourself and start talking
because I don't see anyone in my screen.
- Okay, I would just like to share with you
and with me, can be interested
and the project of Sandoff tourism.
- Oh, that's Mico Sanchez in Lisbon.
He might be the sound of tourism in the city
and it's pretty interesting to his staff.
- Thanks, thanks a lot.
I don't know, Jia, so I'll check it out.
Very cool, yeah.
Okay, thanks.
Are there comments, suggestions, interventions?
Nope.
I will wrap up the new conclusions
and then after the conclusions,
I will move to the Tokyo video,
but there's obviously no obligation to sit
through 12 minutes of noise,
so I just leave it playing for those that are interested,
but I will conclude and say bye after the conclusions.
Okay, to wrap up this relatively intense session,
I think around the different strands of research
on urban culture, what I try to get across
is that research and urban cultures is a thriving
and more perhaps more importantly,
or equally important,
an inter-transdisciplinary field of research.
It's increasingly difficult to distinguish
between disciplines in research and urban cultures,
which perhaps is a trend that applies to all teams,
you could say,
but it definitely thing it applies
most strongly to research and urban culture.
Building on 1980s, '99 is the bait on the cultural term,
postmodernism and urban and the symbolic economy,
and to interaction with urban and topology
and cultural studies,
particularly to notion studies inform informality
and formal urbanist in every life.
What we see is that urban studies is really diversified
into multiple strands of research
dedicated to cultural issues.
It's important to make distinctions here
because different strands have different artists,
have different communities of practice.
But I would say there are three different strands
that are most interesting, but they really might do cover,
and they're not the only strands,
but I do think they cover, let's say 80% of the urban studies
research on urban culture, perhaps with the exception of urban tourism and cultural issues,
which I didn't discuss in detail today.
The first one being the arts, activism and urban engagement, the second cultural infrastructure
to inform urbanism and the third strength around sensory urbanism, a very brief, two examples
on visual cultures and sounds.
That's it from my side for today.
there are no further questions that I will move back to the to this presentation.
Sorry to this video. I have one quick question. I have one question. I have any connections
between Sanzuri Urbanism and Clubing Culture for instance. Limited, limited. I think it's in the
research is limited. I think the Clubing Culture literature as far as I know is largely
your literature that builds on the elastic
classic cultural studies tradition,
focusing on, let's say, youth culture,
popular culture, sociological approaches, by and large.
However, it's, if you look at, let's say,
practitioners in club and culture,
then I think there are stronger connections,
especially those working in, let's say,
electronic music, moving, let's say,
from a minimal techno orientation
who have increasingly moved into, let's say,
modern composition and/or indeed fieldwork type, fields with
course, type of work. There you will see artists who, well, sort of transcend
boundaries who connect these things because they then become, you could say,
sensory urbanists through their practice. But in the research I would say,
less so, they seem to be quite separate. Well, they are to a lot of
stand-quite separate fields. But which doesn't mean that
could actually cannot be made so that maybe then your job.
Well, I'm thinking, I have one example in mind of the
Tbilisi in Georgia where last year there were very big
protests, I have to say, I really don't know the details about it,
but I know there was also some substantial mobilization from clubs
and from people, from artists and people from that scene.
And you saw some sort of collaboration between these people from
top coaches, to say, and more political movements and also using music in public space as a form
of protest. Yeah, that happens, of course. I think in the Berlin example I used before,
I think you also see these examples of public protest and music.
I mean, the classic example of the love parade started.
How would you could say as a political movement,
even though I would argue it was heavily commodified soon after or increasingly so.
But the century urbanism literature perhaps relates more to the experimental
sides and to the sound, not even necessarily music.
And that's the different kind of scene, are you?
although there is overlap obviously. So yeah. Yeah. Thank you. Any other comments, questions?
Perhaps just a very practical question from me regarding the seminars that will follow in the coming
weeks. Yes. And I wonder how the presentations will go. I asked because we were asked in the past
to record the video of our presentation and I wondered if you wanted the same or if we will give
that in person. Yes, the rule would be what remained the same. I think that's how it was
communicated also. So I would actually need to look into the details myself because I've been busy
with the lectures so far. But the idea would still be that the recordings are recorded in advance,
and then we have the... and you was evil to me or you... and I'm represented. Yes.
Right, thanks.
So I'm sorry.
Sorry.
Okay.
Yeah.
That will move to the presentation, but it's 8 p.m.
So this is just when I say the hardcore survivors who want to stick around for a bit longer.
I'm going to say goodbye in any case.
I will also look at it again.
So you can still chat if you want to.
And then thank you for your attention.
And I will see, well, I think everyone of you next week during the seminar.
Alright, so here we go.
[MUSIC]
(whistle)
(upbeat music)
(crowd cheering)
(singing in foreign language)
I'm not gonna lie to my child
It's called a challenge in the dark
[MUSIC]
(gunshots)
(yelling)
Thank you!
It's kinda useless.
Time is the "
(upbeat music)
(crowd cheering)
(Music)
That NSA is the mental mission
M desolate,
tell you
Have been done
supporting a domestic Vesant
Guatemala
(upbeat music)
[MUSIC]
>> [INAUDIBLE]
(crowd cheering)
(Crowd laughing)
No ball experience,
to your goodways,
get it!
(crowd cheering)
Yes,
what better
countryside
Yeah,
consequently,
when I'm late.
habitat,
lodge those in
Soon,
storm waves of
there.
[Music]
I'm not going to miss this place, but I'm going to get a little bit of this.
(cheering)
[screaming]
I'm gonna come out of the breeze
I'm gonna go out of the breeze
(upbeat music)
(crowd cheering)
Think about consistency and pressure
Think about that
Legions and
(upbeat music)
I'm gonna go back to the city of Africa
(whistle)
(dramatic music)
(people chattering)
(crowd chattering)
(upbeat music)
(speaking in foreign language)
(crowd cheering)
(crowd talking)
(speaking in foreign language)
(crowd chattering)
I'm gonna go back there, so don't try nothing, go!
Do it, do it, do it!
I'm gonna go, do it, do it!
I'm gonna go, do it!
Yeah, I'm gonna go, do it!
Do it, do it!
I'm gonna go, do it!
I'm gonna go, do it, do it!
[MUSIC]
Angel, Latin America, and the middle to say that we stand with you in solidarity.
[APPLAUSE]
(audience applauding)
Yeah, I got it.
Talk to the party, we're gonna make it.
Now you're going to go down.
Yeah!
We can get it.
We're going to go down.
Yeah!
We can get it.
(upbeat music)
(cheering)
(speaking in foreign language)
(crowd cheering)
- It got in place.
[MUSIC]
Now, I'm going to be better than what they're about.
If you're new, times, you, is, I want to do it!
[Crowd cheering]
[cheering]
Come on. We applicants!
(audience cheering)
(crowd cheering)
Thank you for listening to this video.
(cheering)
L
(dramatic music)
(music)
[BLANK_AUDIO]
All right, that's it.
Have a great night.
Bye bye.
[LAUGH]
Thank you.
Bye bye.
(birds chirping)
(wind blowing)
(muffled chatter)