[End ---]
Hello, it seems that we are beginning to join this lecture today.
I hope you can hear me.
We're starting in four minutes, but I still would like to make sure that everything is working
here.
If you're not hearing me, let me know in the chat over here,
but I think it's usually working.
(key cl interval increase)
(key cl
hear if not me)
Be safe to hear the
in your
your
even
[ Silence ]
[no audio]
Just to check, can you all hear me and see me?
It's a funny question to add these days, but...
Yes, we can.
It's great.
Very good.
Fantastic. I'm happy that we're not running into technical troubles right away.
Let's start with five past to give everybody enough time to join us.
So grab a drop a drink, tea or coffee or whatever it is that you'd like to drink it this time of the day.
And let's try to make this as pleasant an experience as possible.
So five moments, I'm going to switch up the video for a moment and join you.
Then.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
u
continue the
you.
[BLANK_AUDIO]
you
you.
You.
Go.
you.
that
you
to
happen
to you
you
yourself
to
you
[ Pause ]
Okay.
I trust that you can still see it, you can still hear me.
If at any point you don't, feel
please feel free to,
or yeah, please tell us or tell me in the chat,
which I have opened here just in case.
Welcome, all of you.
I'm sure that you've had that so many times already.
I really wish we could meet face to face
in an actual lecture room at the UB.
But I'm still happy that we are doing it in any case.
And it's very unusual.
Or maybe for you actually already a very normal format by now.
Who am I?
You might be wondering, my name is Voichi Kumbowski.
I am a postdoctoral researcher here at VUB.
And I'm the last of the four white males
to tell you everything about urban geography.
So I come last, but I hope this was not
being a very tiring cause by now and you still have the energy and then will to to follow.
Over the course of the next two lectures, two sessions, I'll be sharing with you my perspective,
my ideas about urban transport and mobility. Well, it's a lecture, so it's very difficult to make it
highly interactive, but I will still try to ask you some questions and I think I hope it's
It's possible for you to try to respond to them not only through chapter basically, you know,
turn the audio on video and I don't think it will be a conversation but at least it will
be nice to hear some other voices, not only mindful two hours and then two hours again.
And of course this is followed by a discussion seminar.
So you will have read or you have read or you have read or you have read or you have
read some articles and I hope you will have a discussion there so that we can make this
is holding a little bit more interactive than it is usually
the case on these online courses.
Right.
I hope you can also see the slides.
Can you not those of you who have the video on?
Do you see them?
Perfect.
Very good.
So excellent.
So urban transport and mobility, it is.
If you have any questions concerning the content,
or I don't know, the quality of video audio,
let me know in the chat.
I'll try to read this as I talk, multitasking
and try to interrupt me if you have any questions.
If you disagree, if you have some burning issue,
let me know and I'll let ask now
and then I'll try to stop and address that.
All right, great.
So what is the plan for the next two sessions?
Today we're going to talk about a historical hegemony
to different main sets of approaches to urban geography
of transport.
And next week, we're going to try to deconstruct all that
to address this in a critical manner
and to understand how to look at urban transport
and mobility from a critical set of perspectives.
So without further ado, today we're going to start
with a bit of a historical overview of the relationship
between transport and the city,
how this relationship evolved in at least two directions,
and discuss as much as possible,
as much as time will allow us to.
This historical hegemony of two main sets of approaches
on urban transport and geography.
So the classical and sustainable perspectives
of urban transport.
But before we begin,
I'm really curious about what your expectations might be.
I imagine that a lot of you in, you know,
starting a course of urban studies or geography
didn't really expect to study transport.
Why would the transport be important
for understanding cities in the geography?
What do you think?
Would anybody like to say something
or type it in the chat?
That's the moment.
We're gonna have a few of these open questions
throughout these four hours together.
Why study transport when studying cities?
Why is that important or not?
- I did actually expect transport to be part
the study because to me at least it alters the way the city is structured, sometimes it's
structured around a specific mode of transport. There's differences between
they call like Harvard cities or cities more in the middle of land something and I think it
makes a big difference with how with a geographic air development. So to me it's actually, I think
I think it's a key factor.
- Right, so we would have some impact on the urban form
on, I'd say, the spatial arrangement of the city.
Why else, there are many reasons as you can imagine,
but what comes to your mind?
- I think it also like Matilda already mentioned before,
one main aspect is sustainability and cities
how to reach the climate goals.
So, it's linked to different transportation systems.
So, to think of, let's say, environmental impact of cities and transport being the big part of that.
Possibly, or being part of the problem, right?
So generating emissions, CO2 and other gases that contribute to the climate crisis.
All right. What else?
I think something has to do with JAPOP PUNTURITIES.
JAPOP PUNTURITIES.
For example, in Lagos in Nigeria, we see people moving for hours
to look for a job and go back again. So eight hours, they're spending in
in causal.
- Right, right.
- So transport is, well,
without transport is difficult to get around the city
and use its different functions
and use different opportunities
that the city might provide,
like employment, education, leisure,
many other things.
All right.
Any last points before you move on?
Does somebody have a great idea
to add this little discussion?
Well, okay.
Well, I think today, yes, it's quite,
actually, is this slide a little bit cut
or do you see it?
Yeah, I think this will be better now.
So today when you open the news,
I think it's difficult to not to notice
the transport is, well, very present, I would say,
in the public debate.
Last year, I'm just taking a few examples here.
last year, you probably read about, and maybe even participated in a witness, huge
protests that erupted in Chile, starting in the capital of the country, which of course
very much addressed fundamental structural issues in terms of how capitalism develops
in this country and how it has its urban or spatial impact.
But the beginning of the protests was so that the final even dropped that actually led
to the option of those strice and these operations
was the increase of public transport first,
and specifically the underground phase.
In Brussels, that's the top right corner.
We've, in the past years,
we witnessed a series of protests in public space
that address the increased presence of the car,
which supposedly these protests claim takes space
from the people, so it'll decrease the quality
of a new life.
negatively impact the quality of living, health conditions,
especially of children.
And then the figure on the top left,
I'm sure that you all know Greta, who
refers to transport, of course, she doesn't talk only
but transport, but she does.
And she makes this very political statement
of not traveling by plane and using one of the trains
to go to her meetings or conferences, at least before,
COVID she did, the idea there is to show us
that there is a necessity for us to engage
in some social and environmental transition
and transport is part of this transition.
So the way that we've moved around,
the way that we've lived,
is essentially unsustainable,
it's detrimental from the environmental point of view.
We need to change that radically, meaning
in a very drastic way.
So really, in a very profound way,
it also in terms of speed of that change in order to address what shared and devices
the main issue today and main problem today which is the climate crisis of the climate catastrophe
that is imminent. It's I think easy to yeah just by following the news to realize that well
something is profoundly wrong with with the way that we are mobile today and that has to change
and indeed the industry or the those whether the key actors in terms of producing transport
is there to, of course, respond with some solutions at least.
So we're being told that at least one of the solutions,
or one of the series of solutions that are available,
are those of platform-based economies of shared digitalised, smart,
gig economy-related mobility or mobility.
So for instance, in the future, living in the city,
we don't have to have a car.
It says, you know, the tremendous demand,
we can rent one through an app.
We can drive electric cars which are readily available in public space in our cities. We can use one of these
electric scooters and many other modes of transport that have
boomed in recent years in many many cities of the global north especially but also in global south.
And Brussels, I'm sure those of you who are from the city of
being there for a couple of months now. You know you can observe many of these different
practices of mobility, very present in the city, and some of them at least being part of a
narrative of some change, of some future, of something that is shaping the way that we live and move
around the city. From a more scientific perspective, one answer why to the question why is that
the transport? Is that quite simply? And I think actually the very first sentence of one of the most
seminal textbooks on transcription of transport geography.
There wouldn't be no transportation without geography,
and there would be no transportation,
no trajectory without transportation.
Transport of transportation in North America
is an essential geographical issue.
The idea is, and again, it's the same textbook,
that transport allows to reduce the distance to zero, of course.
That reduction never really happens, but the idea is
the transport allows to annihilate space and time
that is required to conquer, to cover that space.
But I think beyond that very dry definition
of the relationship between the two,
what's quite important is that, well,
it's very hard to imagine not only contemporary,
but also pre-modern ancient societies without movement
without transport.
It's something that has always been fundamental
for human societies for human settlements.
And today, and that's something that I will try
to show you in these two lectures
and in the discussion that will follow the week after.
Transport is absolutely fundamental for studying the city.
And I think it's a fascinating entry
for studying what cities are today,
what problems might be found in the not only
transport problems, but social problems,
spatial problems, economic problems related
to all different challenges that at first,
at least do not seem to be transport related.
So in fact, they are being negotiated, articulated,
contested, solved sometimes, but more often
unfortunately created through the production
and distribution of transport.
So we will try to impact this relationship
starting by, let's say,
more of a historical analysis.
So I'll start in mid-19th century
in Sootheesen, Western Europe
in what we can identify and pre-industrial era.
And we will bring that analysis to the 1960s, 1970s.
Let's see how much time we've got for this today too.
Well, let's say the beginning of a major crisis
that formed or framed the debate in a way
that it is being framed still today.
So some kind of a setting of a contemporary challenge
or series of contemporary challenges related
to transport and mobility.
So all right.
So the main point here--
I don't want to spend too much time on this historical part
because I don't think this is the, well,
it's not contemporary, so perhaps it's not as interesting
as as many challenges that are happening right now.
The main point here is that urban transport systems
are a very strong and strictly related
with urban form and with a spatial structure.
So the development of cities is conditioned
by the development of what we call transport modes
from walking, so just walking on foot,
to the bicycle, the public transport, and to the car.
And there is a persistently strong relationship
between the intra-urban transportation system
and the organization of the metropolis
as Miller, who wrote one of the most seminal,
again, textbooks on the history of transport geography,
tells us.
And there is a variety of different urban forms
and spatial structures and land use patterns
which are related specifically or very closely
to the development of different transport norms.
And as far as I understand, you've covered quite a few of the most important models of development,
urban development throughout history with Nick.
You can not hear if that's the case and deny the fact if you didn't.
But I think that this was covered at some point.
And the idea here is that in a lot of these models, although not explicitly mentioned,
transport was actually absolutely crucial.
So the idea was both the adjacent unknowns and movement
and mills mentioned that without the development
of different voices moving around the city,
the development of which of course to an extent
erroneously they tried to model or predict
would not be able to happen.
Well, the debate has been there in the
in transport geography until the 1970s, 1980s,
how to model that relationship, how to analyze it,
whether in fact it's more the development of a decision
that drives the development of transport
or the other around with its development
of different transport modes,
that drive the development of the city.
It's not a particularly interesting debate today,
but it's important to acknowledge that geographers
were very early on,
urban geographers interested in the development of mobility.
One, also rather imperfect and symbolic rather than
analytical way of describing this is through identifying
some cycles of innovation.
So looking at different scientific developments
come-- well, some scientists would say
in these kind of crucial moments.
There's a bundle of different innovations coming together.
So at the end of the 18th century, as you can see at the left
inside of the graph, the invention of water power textiles
iron than some 60, 70 years later,
the steam engine rail, production of steel,
et cetera, et cetera.
Each of these bundle of innovations
allowing to, of course, create a more efficient
that you can be faster and more energy efficient
way of moving, of course, not only within,
but also between cities, changing not only the way
that people move, but also the way that the city itself
could be organized in space.
And in this sense, we could,
although of course this is not a perfect robust typology,
but we could come into some kind of agreement.
You don't have to accept it,
and I'm happy if you erase some issues with it.
But we could divide the development of the city
around the development of transport
by identifying four different stages,
I wouldn't call them errors,
but a city that is a pre-industrial city
that largely was based on walking,
since more motorized transport was generally speaking,
not that it was just not there
and having a horse would be an extremely expensive
investment, which means people walked.
And industrial city, which developed around the birth
of what we could identify today as public transport,
first horse driven carts and then motorized ones,
Then the Ford is city which very much developed around the,
not only in the invention, but rather the
classification and the finalization of private vehicles
and private cars.
And then a city of today, the post-F
is city which very much fails on the development of
transport modes that use the ICT information
and information and communication technologies.
And of course aviation, so the city does,
is very much related also to the development of all
typology of spaces related to flying to airplanes, both passenger and cargo transport.
Are there any questions at this stage before we dive into these different four stages?
I don't hear anything. Yeah, yeah. How to go ahead.
The draw we see is linked to a conradive because we saw something like this.
with lessons of Nick?
- Yeah, I would say so.
I think that it's one of the ways of,
I wouldn't say that it's specific,
yeah, that it's completely matches conductance ways,
but the idea is the same,
that there is some kind of development of innovation
within the capitalist system,
which allows to gain some competitive advantage
which allows to create some kind of growth machine,
and then is competitive advantage over time
is lost so that we have to decline until it picks up again.
What I think with contract is still not clear is whether this new wave,
so the one that here in this graph happens after the 1990s, it's very clear.
So as far as I understand, although I'm not especially here,
there is a discussion whether this new wave is with the digitalization
and software engineering is actually materializing,
or whether we've arrived at a global system,
which there is no growth of, at least within industrial production,
but it's rather a financial, financialized growth.
But it's a good, let's say it's a good hand,
it's the idea is more or less the same, the same intuition.
Also, the problem with this clearly is that it's not, I mean,
this kind of way of trying to understand what happened in cities around transport in the past,
two centuries is extremely Western focused or very Eurocentric.
So this would not be a story of cities in most of Latin America, Africa, and South Asia,
and also post-Soviet or Soviet world. So the global south and the global east, as it's
sometimes even called today, it's not really part of this story that is told by this graph.
We will try to address this, but it's, yeah, it's, that will happen at the very end of the last
of the last session to try to decolonize a little bit our knowledge about transport geography
because it's extremely westernized and extremely for a Eurocentric.
Right, let's dive into that.
Right, so the pre-industrial city, right?
Well, I guess it's quite self explanatory. It's not very difficult to understand.
And indeed, the idea is that the city basically is, well,
since there is no motorized transport modes
and having, as I mentioned, having a horse or a horse car,
it's a cost of fortune.
It's an absolutely luxurious good, pretty much everybody
walks.
And since everybody walks, the city cannot be too big for people
to cross it on foot within more than 20, 30, maybe 40 minutes.
So a traditional global northern European city would have,
until, let's say, end of the 18th century,
no more than five kilometers in diameter.
That would mean, of course, here, for example,
you have the map of Brussels from that time.
That would mean that within the city walls,
which existed for military purposes, for defense,
there had to be a very high density
of different functions of different users.
And for other reasons that we know how to dive into today,
a grid street pattern was also very common
from middle ages onwards.
Also very importantly, since these, well,
not maybe since, but as these different functions
were mixed, maybe this mixity was allowed partially
also because of the fact that the division between work
at home, a division that is absolutely fundamental
for a lot of writing on transport geography
that focuses on that morning and evening commute
from home to work and work from home.
That did not exist.
Most people worked from home.
Most people did not have to move to reach.
We can say they implement the employment
that they had or to engage in some kind of productive activity
that would be remunerated to gain some kind of salary
or profit.
Things-- and this is all Brussels first.
Brussels, the map of it, and then a view of the city center where you obviously, well,
you basically see a lot of pedestrians and not much else in terms of mobility modes.
This began to change with a series of inventions. First, a steam engine, an electric engine,
both, well, the invention started at the end of 18th century and moved also to the 19th
century, then the bicycle, I'm moving very fast in time,
and the bicycle was invented in the '60s of the 19th century.
I think, 1867 more or less.
Of course, all these inventions first
being curiosity, again, very luxurious goods,
bicycle being something that was much more used first
as a form of pleasure before eventually becoming
a mode of transport for many workers.
although it meant is that they gradually led to mechanization
of land transport systems.
And we see that gradually happening here.
So these different inventions,
particularly steam engine and nature also,
the discovery and discovery of the machines
that allow to produce electricity meant that
towards the end of the 19th century,
it appears a completely different mode of transport,
which revolutionizes cities of the time,
which is that of first a host around streetcar
and an electric streetcar,
which started to be introduced in European,
Western European cities, around 1890s,
and then became extremely popular by the 1920s.
That led to, well, we moved to this second state,
let's say, to the industrial city,
Let's do a huge revolution of how cities could be conquered by its inhabitants,
how they could be managed, navigated by its inhabitants.
That also allowed, or led to the decision to engage in construction of a number of underground
tramways, as they went for a school, the land of the ground systems first,
in London in Asia, early as 1863, then Budapest in 1896,
and the first Northern American system in Boston in 1897.
And that marked the beginning of, as I said,
a revolutionary change in a golden era
of the development of railway transport systems.
As railway networks expanded tremendously
and became the dominant land transport
for both passengers and for freight.
And that was valid or is valid
for both interurban and intraurban transport.
Why was this invention revolutionary?
Well, of course, because increased speed
allowed to cover increased distance.
So suddenly, for instance, the idea of still living
within the very medieval perimeter of the city
was or started to be questioned.
It's the idea of expanding the city to the suburb
or connecting the villages and the suburbs
to the city proper began to make a lot of sense.
So that led was one at least one of the ideas
why in a number of cities across Europe,
city walls were demolished.
And we see that here in Brussels.
So first, horse, drone, cart.
I think it's a photograph from the 1890s.
So end of the 19th century and 1910,
I think it's a green whale in Brussels, you already see.
I think that's, is that a horse, really in trumbly.
I think it actually is already, it's an electric one,
although I don't see the cables.
I thought it was an electric, but I think it might still be
pulled by a horse, although you don't see that from,
well, the trander is heading in our direction,
does not have a horse pulling it.
Right.
So I already mentioned this in a little bit.
So a revolution in urban travel, a breaking mode
that allowed to rethink the air reform,
made an impact on it in a great way.
Breaking this idea of a compact, dense,
medieval city, allowing to extend what was considered
to be a city to up to 20 or 30 kilometers in time,
if you think that the previous,
let's say model of a city had up to five,
This was an expansion of four to six times.
But also a PS in this process.
Of course, it's not all related to transport,
but it's happening more or less the same time.
And it makes a big impact on what transport is
in the city and what it role is,
is that this expansion of the urban form in space
allows for some specialisation of different functions,
especially economic functions.
And what it also creates,
or contributes to the creation of,
is the creation of a working class,
the Office of a specific group,
a social group of course, very diverse internally,
but a group that sells its time for a living,
that of course with the industrial revolution,
does that not in any more at home,
but actually starts what we start coming,
commuting to its workplace,
where things have been produced
the profit is being made and where the salary work is exchanged for money for a salary.
That separation, as I mentioned, being absolutely fundamental for decades of analysis of transport
to come. So, focus on this commute from work to home and vice versa. Moving to the next,
something, good to see you. Moving to the next stage of urban development, you can put it
very roughly. Of course a fundamental invention of the car, not only the invention of the car
proper because the vehicle itself, I mean we can go back to the first diesel engine invented
in the 90s of the 19th century, pheumatic tyre, four stroke engine, and a few years later,
and that led to the construction of the first automobile, as they were called back then in the
in the 1890s, but it was fundamentally the
classification of the current invention of this particular model,
which I'm sure you've--
or a lot of you probably have heard about already--
the model T by Ford, which began to be produced in 1913.
And famously, Mr. Ford said that this model is available
in any color as long as it is black.
The idea being that with unification of--
universalization of the model, getting rid of any options of any customization of any personalization.
And also, the implementation of today is being called Taylorism. So reaching a near automated
way of producing this vehicle with very strictly measured time for every single activity that
that was part of the production process.
The final price of the production and the final price for the consumer
could be reduced as much as possible,
meaning that this product, this commodity,
could be available to white masses.
And that does begin from the 1910s already,
but especially from the 1930s, when indeed the price started going
significantly down, the era of the automobile,
the era of a mode which I'm sure that if you
know, turn on the news about Brussels or any other Western European North American city,
but that debate also is very, very present in Minneapolis, Latin America and South Asian
cities. It's a mode that is very much on the agenda whenever you talk about, whenever
you hear about transport. And we're going to talk about that, I guess, tonight, if not,
in a week is a very well, is a very present mode of transport in our cities and also very
problematic mode of transport in the tracks, a lot of constipation, a lot of anger, and
a lot of creative and critical thinking in terms of what's the alternative to the automobile.
So it's been almost a century now that our cities, if we think about it from the global
north, are, I don't know, benefiting or suffering from that, from that long, you tell me.
from 1913 to 1927 Ford managed to build 15 million units, 15 million
vehicles, making it the second most produced current history right after
Volkswagen Beetle, which was also, they began the production a little bit later,
but also ended period between the first and second world war. So why, well,
this we've covered already mostly, but well, the most important thing here is
in the last bullet points.
I mean, why is the car such a revolutionary
and such an important mode of transport
to be mentioned here,
is that for the very first time mobility,
motorized mobility is an individual exercise.
It's no longer only a motorized or a horse-drawn street
car that allows you to cover long distances
of taking a train, a suburban train
that takes you to the factory and back.
But it is an individual vehicle,
an individual product that allows you to reach unprecedented levels of individual mobility.
And of course, that immediately had a very important impact on the way that the cities are planned and imagined.
Well, without running the risk of maybe a little bit of drawing some kind of caricature,
This impact starting from especially the Second World War when it was a very strong narrative
of the need of modernizing cities, especially in North America and Western Europe.
A lot of cities became basically a perfect space for driving around a space in which huge
amounts of infrastructure for this individual car base mobility was built.
This process started a little bit early in the US and the 1940s and 50s already and after
the Second World War, that narrative was started to be very present in Western European
specifics.
Both of these images, by the way, come from a really wonderful film by Jacques T. I believe
is called Playtime from the 1967, which I really recommend.
He watches a great critique of this idea, this framing of modernity, which also very much
changes on the idea of having a car of driving around.
And well, moving to more serious stuff,
I mean, accommodating the car in a city meant
that serious infrastructure had to be built.
A serious self had to happen in cities at the time
for the car to receive this kind of space.
Some of the most important projects happen in the US,
As I mentioned on the left hand side,
you've got the Franklin Delano-Rousville Drive
and open in 1966 in New York.
On the right hand side,
the infamous Pont de Morandean,
and you know, in Italy 1967,
which unfortunately collapsed,
I believe, two years ago,
which also symbolized, of course,
it's a terrible event,
but for many,
it was a very powerful symbol
of this infrastructure crumbling
and an important question of what to do
with these relics of modernity or past modernity,
whether they should be, in this case, rebuilt or maintained
or invested in, whether this is something
that we want to graduate dismantle
and stop subsidize his maintenance of these infrastructures
is undoubtedly very costly.
And the next slide, does anybody have a clue
where this city is?
- Chalua. - Very good.
Well done, yes, this is the...
I don't remember the name of the road, but...
Yeah, yeah, it's in the next slide, so I'm so silly.
I mean, Bez is our nine built in 90,
or opened in 1976.
I don't know if you ever had the experience of driving this,
but it's really a time-canny.
It makes me personally feel as if I was in some Chinese
or other Asian city where you were here.
on this elevated platform, almost gliding through the city.
So it's really one of the, I think,
most extreme or more extreme cases,
at least in this part of Europe,
of really plowing through a city
to build this motorway ring route.
But Charlie, wow, it was not the only one.
I mean, we are, after all,
or I don't know where you are right now,
but most of us are in Brussels right now.
And Brussels was definitely also a playground
for many of these ideas.
And the idea of bringing the car and opening the city
to the car, like in American cities,
at least that was the comparison use in Belgium,
became particularly strong
and particularly potent among the political class
that decision makers around 1958.
What happened in 1958?
I guess you've heard that date before.
Any non-belgence?
1958, why is that important for Brussels?
The X-word, the X-word.
- That tell me.
- The Atomium.
And why would the Atomium be, well, okay,
the World X-flow, symbolized by the Atomium,
and why would that be related to the car?
You really don't have any ideas?
I mean, if you're opening a World X-flow
for the very first time in Belgium and inviting,
I don't remember how many people actually visited
the X-plain at the end,
millions of people visited the city. Why would Car be important?
Would the Car be important in that regard?
For putting Buzzum on the map?
It's worth it, Buzzum on the map.
The connection to go into it.
It's also the message.
It's to serve the idea of, I mean, not the idea, the problem of congestion is to bring
these masses to the Expo and back is to allow for a better communication but also to put
Belgium on the map to show that Belgium is a modern country. To show that it's on you know cutting
edge and being cutting edge in 1958 in Belgium meant opening the city for the car and building
huge infrastructure or started least to build huge infrastructure that would accommodate this new
modern US-like American way of mobility or moving around the city.
So yeah, some things that are quite unthinkable today, we're going on at that time.
So this is Gaborne Plus, I think it's in the 1960s. So of course, Expo was a symbolic event.
And it didn't really, it was not just tipping points.
There were a lot of dynamics happening in the time
and the export was maybe more of a symbolic moment.
But it is around the time that the level of authorization
at the level of ownership of cars in Belgian households
and similar processes are mentioning Belgium here,
but similar things were going on in France
in Germany in the UK.
It went through the roof.
So it was very, very common back then
to invest in the car as a symbol of advancing
as a household as a symbol of social mobility,
not only a physical geograph,
but that of course meant that more and more space
had to be given to the car
and as the car became more present,
more people pulled the car.
So the circle was closed and there was a vicious one.
In Brussels specifically,
well, one of the most important interest structures
built the time is the Petit Santu,
so the ring road that surrounds the Pentagon of the city.
I'm sure that you've all been there.
So essentially,
the framing of it,
right, the actual shape of the Pentagon comes
from the city walls,
the second walls of Brussels coming from the 14th century,
completely destroyed,
which defined it as the re-center of the city still.
And until the 1950s,
it was very much an urban bulldog
which one could stroll and walk very much like in the drawings rather than photographs that I
showed you at the beginning from the city of walking city that was very much defined by the
pedestrian mode of moving around. In relation to the 1958s, I had to be gradually transformed.
So a series of first tunnels were built and the surface was raised to open to the car.
It took 20 years of work, which is not a very unusual thing in Brussels to do.
So two decades of extremely heavy work and very destructive work,
whole neighborhoods had to be relocated, destroyed, rebuilt.
So opened in 1976 with 15 tunnels surrounding the city.
Also quite importantly, and that's maybe a bit of an extreme story that
not necessarily happened also in France or in Germany or another,
Western European cities.
But what was very crucial in rehearsals is that the engineering team,
so the engineering officers, consultancy officers,
we call them today, would receive personal bonus on top of the salary
for every kilometer of an underground tunnel built.
So that led to creation of a huge push to build underground infrastructure for mobility,
both for cars, but also for railroad and metro.
And that led to a creation of very important expertise
in building these underground tunnels,
which of course, once you have that expertise,
you of course want to keep building more
because that's what you are very good at doing.
And that problem in Brussels,
well, problem situation exists until today
where we have huge teams of engineering,
specialists who specialize in building underground,
in steep and about the transport company in Brussels.
Half of the company is responsible
for metro for its maintenance and construction.
So you can imagine that what you want to do,
of course, is to keep building a metro,
which is what they are currently doing in Brussels.
Moving a little bit or zooming out a little bit from cities,
the large scale diffusion of the car
or the automobile as a mass consumption project,
of course, was strongly also influenced
or maybe also led to a dynamic,
to the emergence of first nationwide highway systems.
The first one created was of course the one in the US.
The American interstate highway system,
which began to be not many completely built from scratch,
but the first framing of it and continuous gradual addition
to the network in 1956.
Which was, of course, back then that symbol of modernity,
that in many other places, Belgium being one of them
influenced the definition of the idea
of what was modern or was cutting edge wars,
technologically advanced.
Today, of course, it's not the US anymore
that it's leading country or the leading power
in terms of the development of transport, technology,
and highways in particular.
That system that American system has been
by now surpassed definitely by the one in China.
The national trunk highway system here,
I have a little bit of an old graph,
but by 2011, as far as I can read it, well,
but already 2009, the total amount of kilometers
of motorways in both countries,
US and China was equal.
And the one in China, of course,
was rising still very steep.
But you can see that this, I don't like the term,
let's say the catching up on this idea of following a little bit in the
footsteps of what the Americans did in the 1950s. In China happened in an
extremely short time which not only because of the construction of the
motorways but this was a very important part of the construction boom meant
that from 2006 to 2007 onwards now the situation is a little bit different
because of the ongoing crisis and also other problems that Chinese
economy suffered from, but the consumption or the demand for concrete in China was bigger than
in all other countries around the world combined. So this was really a boom of an unprecedented
scale and we will see a few other graphs down the lecture which show us that while in many
cities and many countries don't know what we might be thinking that we are moving away from the
the current right now, but that's the idea that the other parts of the world that did
not experience this development at the same time as local North are now definitely contributing
to not even I would say persistence or vulnerability, but actually it's continuous rise
in the global scale. What was very important going back to the Belgium context of the
in the 1950s and 1960s.
It's also difficult to say what was first the car
or the suburbs or the suburbs in the car,
but the two were extremely strongly linked
with one another.
Having the car, and as I mentioned,
as I explained, the car became a very common popular
and cheap commodity.
Not only did you find how you moved to work
and you move around the city,
but actually it's again,
redefine what the city is.
So suddenly areas which would be normally considered rule
become accessible and become interesting for people
to settle in.
The idea also being that you have more space,
more freedom,
you are close to your close to nature, et cetera, et cetera.
These days it might feel like it's something of the past,
something that is not interesting to many urbanites
of today, but back then it was absolutely
way to the way to go, the way to live, the way to think that one should invest as a household
in a home market, in property market. The special results of that, the double dynamic of
motorization of one hand, suborganization of the other, was that if a pre industrial city had a
more or less 10% of its space devoted to transport and mobility. An industrial
modern city has between 15 and 30% and that's rough estimates from Western Europe to up to 60%
in some American cities of space will be given to mobility infrastructure which is principally
highways and parking lots, which of course is a huge spatial cost.
And, well, another development, of course, is that the commuting area that we start to call it,
so the actual definition of what a city is, regardless of administrative limits and different boundaries,
of course, this would be often divided into some municipalities and all, it goes up to 100 kilometres in diameter.
So suddenly what is a city becomes,
it stands becoming a little bit vague in the sense that the old urban course,
of course, do not hold all the functions anymore and we start seeing cities,
expanding at least in economic terms.
Well, without running into the risk of simplifying things a little bit too much,
But what happened in a lot of cities, both in North America and in Western Europe, is that as the car became more and more popular and as moving by car became absolutely common.
And if you basically had a middle-class job, that's what you did. You lived in the suburbs and you created through the office job by car.
Trans-and companies, or mass transit companies,
probably transport companies,
started to run into serious financial difficulties.
So traditionally, when they were actually set up
in the 19th century, 1910s, 1920s,
they would be private companies very often,
private railroads bringing workers
to the suburbs in Darchle, bringing the bourgeois
and people who wanted to enjoy leisure
outside of the city and then back.
As they started to run into trouble in some countries,
and that's usually the case in Western Europe,
they would be nationalized.
They would be taken over by the state
as an important part of military infrastructure,
but also an important part of mobility infrastructure
and kept, but they enrolled the societal role
with definitely declined,
so they would become something not necessarily
for the middle class, but rather for the working class.
Belgium here is some sort of an exception
because a lot of commuting here,
due to the fact that the railway system was traditionally
been very dense, happened and still is happening
very much through public transport.
But that's definitely not the case in the UK, for example,
or definitely not in North America.
But, and sticking to North America,
in a number of cities over there,
the process that happened was inverse.
So the decline of public transit did not
lead to any investment by the state.
either on federal or on the state-state level,
but rather eventually dismantling
of public transport systems happened.
And a very particular story is that of the general
modus company.
So one of the main producers of these masks
come on with these with the cars.
Who threw out the 1940s basically bought
a number of public transport companies,
massive companies as they are called over there.
and purposely led to the decline.
Why?
Well, the idea was quite simple.
It was basically the derivative of the competition
that public transport could have posed
to the individual ability to the car.
So the idea was to push public transport out of the market.
And again, I just saw the comment from somebody.
And again, yes, the idea of course
was that this was also framed by the discourse
of modernity and advancing as a society.
I forgot to mention that we will be taking a break
in both today and in the week.
I don't think that sticking to the stream
to ours is a helpful thing to do.
So we will take a break actually in three minutes
probably for about five minutes.
And just in case you're getting a little bit tight.
But this total decline or some would even say it is up
I would even say a disaster in terms of what happened to mass transport, mass transit,
sorry, public transport was not always the case.
So as I already mentioned, in some countries, public transport networks actually were
taken over by the state and even invested in.
And one important thing that happened, or a symbolic project that happened is that of Copenhagen's
fingerplant from 1947.
So basically there, the decision was made to create an alternative, or maybe not a substitute,
an alternative parallel to car commuting.
Basically suburban rail, which follows the shape of fine figures.
Corridors that would not only be transport corridors,
but also along which a number of different functions,
especially residential, but also economic work,
related functions would be placed as well.
And that was, as far as I know, one of the first plans
that try to achieve what we call
transport-oriented development, or development
urban development that happens around, or in this particular case,
along transport corridors to allow for different mobility
options back then, maybe, environmental issues
were not so much on the agenda, but the idea
was that people would be able to get more efficiently
to work, not only by car, but also by suburban rail.
In our lovely Brussels, well, things were not so easy,
Well, things were a little bit in between.
So on the one hand, the car was definitely the king.
And actually it's one of the slogans in Brussels
sent it academia and public debate.
Car it became the king around the 1950s
with the expo of the 1958.
And still very much is a very present
and very privileged lot of transport.
But public transport, of course, did not
disappear on one of the particularities of Brussels
is that unlike in Sharawa, for example,
or many cities in Germany or in France,
especially Trang was, for example,
were never completely dismantled.
And you would see, and I can't think of any specific names
right now in France, but there are cities in which
Trang, way network existed, you know, 1940s, '50s and '60s,
and then was completely dismantled to open a surface space
to the car.
So what happened in Brussels is that the Trang was basically
put on the ground, so you see on top left,
Rinalalwa, which is that magnificent open waterway these days.
And you see a tram trying to plow its way
through the city, standing in a traffic jam.
The idea, well, of course, the city has packed
the spaces limited with the rise of mobility
and the individual mobility.
And the rise of an hour of course, traffic jams happen.
The decision there was made not to make more space
the tram would make to make more space for the car. So a strategic decision was to put the tram
first underground, creating a very particular mode of transport made in Brussels called pre-metro
kamitho, which then eventually as it was actually planned was converted into a full scale,
as we call it in Brussels, heavy metro metrolu. You can actually see a pre-metrol still,
and that's line three and four in Brussels at Tramline that goes from north to south of the Pentagon,
which as you probably have heard is now well will soon be converted into a proper
metro of once and a new metro line from the gallery knob and northwards is constructed.
So you get for example C, I don't know if you ever had a chance of you know noting that the
platforms and although this is a trans stock the platforms are actually much much wider than
and usually would be in the case of a tram
and they are much longer.
Basically they were built,
I think already back in the 70s,
anticipating a proper metro, we are now in 2020.
So if I need a metro, it's happening,
although well, it's a controversial project to sit at least.
Let's take a little break here,
not longer than five, six minutes.
So grab another tea, you're a coffee,
and I'll see you back in four, five minutes, all right?
Great, I'm going to see you in a moment.
(keyboard clicking)
(keyboard tapping)
( door extension)
(keyboard clicking)
(vehicle stupid clicking)
( Rank Joh Biden
(
/
transparent language)
Welcome back all of you. I hope you grabbed another drink or whatever it is that you are
having. Grab another notebook to keep helping things, although of course you've got the
recording of all this. And I can see that some people are asking questions. I might also
ask you with up to now, up to now everything has been clear or you've got any questions
about what I've been talking about. If yes, please raise your hand, just speak up. But I think
it's an interesting question that Mika asked here in the chat, whether in need what's happening
right now is that we have an increased desire for what we could say is a pre-industrial city,
a city of walking of short distances, density of uses, mixes. Does anybody have an opinion on this?
Would you agree? Would you not agree?
Or maybe Mika, whether he or she is, has an opinion?
It's me. Yeah, I wasn't sure if it's really linked to the pre-industrial city, but when you explained
how it was looking, how it looked like.
I thought about actually it's exactly what today's planning is about.
Like this mixed use, this like, and narrow streets where you workability and short distances.
And I mean, maybe it's also really a European perspective.
I'm not sure about that. I thought maybe it could be like a new role model of today's planning.
Does anybody have an opinion on this? Would anybody like to react?
I can compare it for example in Antroop. I live in the center of the city.
but we see that the place for private cars is reducing.
For example, they put parking lots under undergrounds for making some leisure activities or parks
or something else. So we see a movement, I guess, when we focus on that. And definitely in Brussels,
depending on the policy now, it's more ecological
minus and we see more opportunities to reduce
parking lots and more movements like for example in Anspaklam.
In the Kitton years it's called the pedestrian area of Brussels.
Yeah yeah.
We couldn't imagine I guess 20 years ago so we see different movements.
Yeah, there is definitely some kind of shift happening.
I mean, we are not in the 1960s or 70s, not where what is right now on this slide.
Things have moved on. The presence of the car is definitely put on the question.
But is this about going to a three-industrial city?
What would be the problem with that?
Or would be the risk of just to revert into walking, let's say,
if that's what the pre-industrial city was about.
as anybody have, you know, an opinion on this. There was no wrong answers here.
We tell you saying that new mobility plans are aiming in the best of use of all technologies
we have now with maximum inclusivity. Yeah, I guess so. Proof is in the, you know,
well, it depends on how they, of course, implemented and it's the idea, of course, is that
that everybody is included and we use all the technologies we have.
In practice, we will see that it's a little bit complicated.
Maybe it's also the light when we were looking at the metro system that it's more about underground transportation.
So like separation.
Okay.
Transportation systems.
Somebody else started talking. Who was that?
Yeah, that was me. And also what I wanted to bring up was this idea of Brussels is a productive city where industries or small businesses are still located and where people can have, you know, can find jobs almost in their neighborhood that it, you know, especially maybe jobs that don't necessarily pay so well that wouldn't be interesting for other people to to commute into the city to. And I think these kind of businesses are a bit under pressure from.
the reduction in space that they have on, you know, to organize these productive activities.
So I think, yeah, space in front of their, in front of the street, to actually do their deliveries.
And I think as a tension there in the kind of city, you want, and the way you want the service,
different neighborhoods and different areas. So one of the cases was like these smaller construction,
and supplies kind of stores, maybe in the area of LAC and,
like not far from the canal,
serving a kind of secondary places where,
you just wouldn't go to Brico
for those kind of materials, you would go to your neighborhood
and that's becoming harder to maintain
in an urban environment that gives more space to walking
to buy claims and so on. So that's on the one side. It doesn't mean that I agree, but it's,
I think one of the pressures that is being felt by that group.
I guess what's important what you said, and to relate it also to what I was talking about
before and what Vitali there is, the right thing is that there is some with each of these
technological shifts. Of course, they are very, I mean, it's a very broad sketch. These things
when all happening in sudden turns, it's a process.
But space is valorised in different ways.
And for example, if we see here in this slide, as I mentioned,
clearly space became very limited with the rise of the cars.
And the decision was made of the space is extremely valuable.
And it should be given to the modes that
is the most efficient in terms of speed,
as the most rational mode also, not only economically
or temporally efficient.
So other modes like public transport, I haven't even mentioned cycling there,
had to disappear or be moved elsewhere.
And I think what's happening right now is some kind of
revolarization of space.
But space is always limited.
So if you take it, I mean, if you give it to one or some set of users,
which I think also, perhaps we will have time to talk about it next week,
has a clear class component.
So there is a clear middle class idea behind opening central airman spaces to walking, cycling,
and public transport and taking it away from the car.
So if you give it to these kind of users, you have to take it away from others, in this
case, the car.
And I think an important question is to ask, well, if we want the car to disappear from
the city life, from Russell's, who is using the car, right?
me who is dependent on it. For example, these businesses, small shops that, I don't know,
either, well, I mean, the productive activity requires accessibility by cow. But also, I think,
probably you've heard right now in this pandemic crazy times, people are talking about 15 minute
neighbourhood and the idea of how the pandemic has shown us that we can, well, since we
essentially, and many of us stop a lot of activities. We start walking around and cycling and all that.
So the idea that maybe we could use this to reorganize the cities around 15 minute
perimeters walking perimeters within which we can all find all the users and functions that we need.
But I think an important question there is who actually lives so close to a good school,
a good job and all that. And in Perasos, many other cities, there will be a lot of people who need to
to find employment quite far from where they live.
And a lot of them would have to go by car
to get to that job.
So what, you know, what then,
I will continue with the lecture,
but I hope there will be space for more questions.
There was one point that I want to make
that is, you know, I don't want to say
a main conclusion of this historical trajectory,
but I think an important point
to keep in mind, you know, this is that
it's not just a descriptive, you know,
to the force of what different modes of transport
were there and how it impacted the urban form.
I think this is something that is maybe
a little bit interesting, but essentially,
I don't think it's very critical
and doesn't really allow us to understand
too much about how the city functions are functioned
in the past.
I think what's very important though
is that with each of these shifts,
with each of these turning points and dynamics
that led to shift in terms of how people move.
We're getting closer and closer to the situation
that we have today, which is that transport
is absolutely crucial not only for the development
of cities, but for the development of the socioeconomic system
in which we live today on the global scale,
which is of global capitalism.
So it would be impossible for the current socioeconomic relations
to develop to the point that they have developed
without transport and without the development of transport
and vice versa.
So outside of the capitalist system,
they probably would not have been such a push
for development of individual mobility, for example,
and the visual mobility by car that is propelled
by fossil fuels with all the geopolitical
and environmental atrocities and impacts that this produces.
Essentially transport or transport geography is a discipline required space not only to be conquered physically in terms of distance basically moving from A to B would become as fast as short of a time as possible, but also some kind of imaginary and cartographical colonisation of concrete of space.
If we go back to end of the 18th century, for example, in Europe, well, the majority of
people who inhabited, well, maybe eight of the 17th century to be a little bit less controversial,
but the majority of people who lived on our continent and definitely the majority of people
who lived on our planet did not live under jurisdiction of any state or any state administration.
They essentially lived outside the state structures. Of course, states and administration existed,
But most people lived in villages in areas where once in a while, a tax collector would
maybe show up or be quite easy to avoid the encounter with that kind of gentleman,
rather not gentle moment, I'm afraid.
So it's at this point, and I think transport is absolutely crucial for understanding of
why this happened and how this happened, that there happened or the beginning to happen
in a strategic expansion of state infrastructure and state administration.
predominantly related security reasons and search for different forms of capital,
for instance, slavery, so trying to reach different places where bodies could be snatched,
taken into captivity and then sold or propelled into productivity.
But for the state to be able to organize this process, it had to develop its
cartography, it has to develop its dominance, its knowledge, its control over space.
And here we see a map of France in the 1632, which is essentially, well, we've seen some roads,
we see some cities and connections between those. But this radically changes with the
development of state's interest in terms of the resources, as I mentioned, bodies, people,
but also of course other natural resources would anything that you can mine and I don't know
it's not especially here in terms of who you can be interested in as a state but what essentially
happened is that from a natural space, a space that was inhabited, a space that was lived,
we started moving into a fire name of abstracted of of absolute space that is very much related
to the consolidation of states infrastructure as a way of organizing social and material order
that is on the ground to bureaucratically govern it to rule it from the distance, from a very top
down perspective. The example of France is very interesting because literally over there the decision
was made of course not immediately in one meeting but progressively it was a state bureaucracy
a rather decision to divide the state in more or less equally shaped areas, the departments
based on a regular grid. On the left hand side you see there's some kind of conceptualization of
this. On the right hand side we see a result which is the actual, the eventual division. I think one
of the first ones in the French territory. I think today of course it's not exactly the same that
has developed for different historical reasons.
But the idea was very important.
The Ministry of Reform of the 1790
would replace an old feudal tribal, even division
of territories into--
it would be your place with abstract bureaucratic logic
that would be applied in a more or less the same way
in each of these territories, each of these departments.
this week in skip.
What was very important in this development
is that the state needed very much universal,
I don't know how to put it, a reliable system
of measuring space and other related phenomena,
such as, for example, time and quantity.
It might be very difficult for us to imagine this,
but the unification of measuring systems
of time and space and quantity was something that took a very long time and it was definitely not
in place until end of the even 17 or 18 centuries. So it took a very long time to actually make sure
- sorry - make sure that all inhabitants of a given nation state of a given territory would actually
subjugate themselves to the usage of a unified - that's the word I was looking for - unified
metric or measurement system. So for example the unification of the metric systems in Germany took
place in as late as 1868 in Austria in 1871 and Hungary three years later in Russia in 1919
and in China only in 1959. What does it mean? It means that there exist of course ways of measuring
but there will be culturally dependent or there will be spatially dependent. So a particular
unit of measurement, a foot, an elbow would mean different things and different villages.
It would mean different things at a different times of the day or year. It would mean different
things whether it would be the activity of selling or buying. For example, you would sell
a small bag of rice and buy a big one. There was a difference between that's in many pre-colonial,
African communities, kingdoms. There will be a division between strong measures for selling
goods and weak measures for buying goods. So there was a huge diversity of different ways of
measuring space, measuring time, and measuring quantity.
All that in all the, and also because of, and again,
this is a two-way dynamic, the development of the transport
system and the development of state as an institution
or a set of institutions that had to control space,
quantity, and time gave way to a unified system,
of which transport is absolutely central in here.
I mean, the symbolic one meter, which is, of course,
huge upstream agreement that we are in, that this is what one meter is, and the same could be said
about the kilogram of the second and many others. Moving a little bit more, going a little bit
more into transport here, I mentioned time and for example as late as in the late 18th century,
distance between particular cities and as a result travel times between particular cities,
such as in Germany, we're not fixed or set.
So in 1881, German railways or different kinds of German
railways because there was no one national system
followed to five different times us, which
were different not by one hour but by a different amount of minutes,
which meant that basically one area, I guess,
the archaea color coded, would be five or seven minutes ahead of the other one,
which meant that the passengers had to do the calculation themselves.
it was all an oral agreement and an ongoing discussion between the passengers and the staff
to understand what time things would happen, what time the train would depart, leave, etc.
And as I mentioned, this integration of measurement system, integration of different modes of
of transport networks allowed the state to control,
to consolidate the territory, and to basically be able
to develop socioeconomic relations that we take today
very much for granted.
This was absolutely crucial.
I mean, the reason why I'm making this a bit of a digression
and the departure from historic trajectories
that this was absolutely crucial, this colonisation of space
and colonization of what we consider to be
a very much of a social or good consideration,
social activity, movement and transport is,
was absolutely crucial for the development of,
again, what we take very much for granted,
the global networks of YS, cables, railroads,
highways in this particular case,
I already showed you that map,
allowing transport to lubricate the capitalist global system.
And today, this colonization of space,
if we can call it this way, it's no longer a national matter,
it's no longer nation-states that are propelling this process.
It's something that has happened very much on the global scale.
What was very important in this very long trajectory
started very quickly at the end of the 17th century.
Now we are in 1950s.
What was very important is that the whole science developed
around this colonization of different measuring systems
of different ways of living and interacting with space.
And this size, on this scientific field,
I think we can call it a set of neoclassical perspectives
on not only transport, also on economics, on social life,
which in transport itself is very much present,
is very much dominated by, on the 100 transport engineers,
on the other and the transcoli economists.
What I'm talking about here is basically the main, say,
and I will not talk a lot about this,
but basically if you went to a master degree,
which I'm very happy you did it,
but if you went to a master degree in transport management
or logistics at any technical university,
this is very much what you would be learning today,
which I guess at this time of the day or night,
which we are a bit more boring, I hope,
and what I have to offer, but hope there is no regrets here
in the room today.
But if you want to be an engineer,
and if you want to be an economist to go rose,
this is basically what you learn.
Why is it called Neoplastico Transport?
Well, very much it relates to Neoplastico Economics,
which deals with a cold, blooded analysis,
a study of distribution, production of goods,
outputs, and income through.
And that's absolutely crucial supply and demand.
So a system which has to be an equivalent equilibrium,
which essentially looks at transport as a part or a separate market in which transport
is a good commodity which is offered in the market, passengers being its consumers.
What is important here?
There are two main principles, which very much today, again,
in academia, but also very much in the world of practitioners.
So the world of those who plan roads, who build roads,
who claim that we need a new metro line,
we need a more to way, or that this or that particular mode
of transport is absolutely essential
for contemporary cities to thrive.
So these two dogmas say that on the one hand,
transport is an essentially rational discipline.
It's a discipline that is rational because it has to be developed by experts.
It's a top-down discipline that requires it to top-down cartographic vision of space,
which can reduce to its absolute universal measures.
That also means that there is a science behind it, which means that it's not an issue that can be fully open to a public debate.
It's a part of urban life that has to be developed by experts and only experts can have the final word in terms of decision-making, in terms of how transpose develops, why, and using what modes.
There is a very strong prediction there in this field of knowledge,
transport geography or transport economics and engineering are essentially objective sciences.
They are much more on the side of science and sciences and humanities for example.
They purpose being pursuing objectivity and truth.
It's a quote from another very important textbook on transport geography.
The idea being that we can arrive some kind of absolute truth in terms of what is good transport
and what is bad, which essentially are translatable, transferable from one locality to
went out. So if we go back to the 1950s, if the US cities develop motorways and develop
car infrastructure, which is efficient at rational, this is a solution that can also work
in dense medieval European cities such as the ones in Belgium to just Brussels, for
example.
Crucially, this line of thinking and that maybe didn't develop in the end of the 17th
in the 19th century, but was definitely a result of this process that I called the colonization
of space. This field of thinking and producing transport is consolidated itself around the
1930s and 40s and that propelled measurements and engineering studies that allowed to construct
these interurban and intraurban motorway systems. And this very much continues today following
a rule of predicting demand for mobility,
predicting passenger flows or traffic flows
and providing necessary infrastructure for it.
So basically most of transport,
most of what transport models do is predict
where would these flows go and provide
essential infrastructure and extension of a road lane,
a construction of a new motorway,
construction of the new metro line, you name it.
So that's one part of the rationality of transport.
The other part is that the assumption is that the user itself
and it's, yeah, the user itself is also a rational being.
It's a homo, economic, it's an economically minded being
that almost on a regular basis, on a daily basis,
conduct some kind of economic analysis in terms of what is an efficient way of reaching
an destination B from point A in terms of time, in terms of cost, being, making pragmatic
free and very much utility-based choices in terms of how to move and where to move.
So in other words, a market, a market that is being governed by the laws of economics,
very much in this line of thought are being compared to the loss of physics. A lot of these models
would have, for example, illusions to gravity, so gravity, models that in a natural light way
pulls, flows of passengers to some destinations rather than others because for example, economic
and connectivity is present in an area. So that's principle of dogma number one. Number two is that
But there is this very strong conviction and funny enough, still not fully proven, but the
conviction is very much there, that investment in transport infrastructure, of course,
that part is not controversial.
Least of high speeds, leads to low and travel times, leads to lower transaction costs
if you want to move from A to B or sell for some goods, it's basically cheaper, leads
to economic development.
So the better infrastructure we have, the higher or the better
the growth of a locality.
So if you want the city to be economically prosperous,
wealthy, you need quality transport infrastructure.
So that very much is underpinned by this quarter
that I already mentioned earlier today,
that the unique purpose of transport is, in fact,
to limit, to reduce space and time that is needed
to cover the space to zero,
so that that is the unique purpose of movement in the city,
which also means that the travel time itself
is an unproductive activity,
because from the monetary perspective,
if you want to go from A to B,
well, you want to get there as quickly as possible.
The time of getting there itself
is not a valuable activity.
Now, there are, I mean, there was a flurry of problems here,
starting from the fact that if you actually ask people
through studies, what they do when they take the metro
or where they cycle, which is such a complicated
and multi-faceted activity.
They often say that this is actually a very important part
of the day, that commuting on public transport, for example,
allows them to catch up with friends, to read,
to relax, to meditate, cycling being,
as I mentioned, multi-faceted activity
that allows people to get relaxed, work out,
get an endorphin kick and all that.
And that's so much more than just moving from one place to another.
But again, without trying to draw some kind of caricature,
I think it's important to understand that this way of thinking about transport
leads us to a formulation of an absolutely fundamental problem
in inverted commons that a lot of engineers, transport engineers,
and transport economists recognize.
And that problem is congestion.
if you focus on fluid flow of passengers, cars,
whatever the transport mode is,
any obstruction to that flow,
any obstruction to that model is a problem that has to be solved.
And that problem has to be solved
because otherwise the system is irrational.
So that's number one.
And the second reason is that,
unless you do that, you can
the economic growth, economic development of the locality that you are in in in charge of.
As I mentioned this this beneficial, supposed to be beneficial relationship between
transport development and economic development. So better roads, I mean better transport,
better exchange of goods and services. That of course works to some extent. I mean you can
you can see that having theoretically at least from scratch in in many cities in many countries
from the global south. But then this relation has never really been theorized, it's never
really been proven. And it will be extremely difficult to make that claim in cities that
are postmodern, such as Brussels or many other cities in the global north, but actually increasing
the global south. So addition of infrastructure, especially road infrastructure, current
infrastructure, and it's anticipated impact in terms of economic growth, economic development,
It's a very controversial issue that, well, it's not really, we don't have any tangible
proof or the tangible enough to say with certainty that this is the case.
But it's an argument that you can hear a lot, including in Brussels and Belgium.
Is this clear?
Do you have any questions?
This is usually where people are scratching the hands a little bit, so I want to make
sure that you are okay.
nobody is running anything in a chat, no angry comments, I keep advancing here then.
So what happens when you believe that what you do is rational and it's very important
for society, for economy?
Well, you essentially engage in developing more and more and more elaborate and complicated
mathematical models that try to predict.
not only to describe what's happening
but actually trying to predict what is going to happen.
What is now happening very much in the business
of transport economics and transport engineering
is modeling human behavior.
So trying to predict where people will be interested
in going and not anymore,
where they are actually are heading
and where these flows are being distributed
in an urban environment.
What's crucial here is that this field is extremely,
not only extremely technical and quantitative,
whether it's very descriptive,
so this logic of transport supply and transport demands
is devoid of any social, cultural, political relations.
When I say that a transport user
is homo-economic, is considered to be
a this rational utility-based person or figure
that makes these rational choices
in terms of whether or how any issue of gender,
an issue of class, of ethnicity, of age is at best mentioned,
but given a very little weight,
if we are talking about modeling,
so these different aspects can be given
different weights, given different importance,
importance, different levels of importance.
And these issues are quite simply not there.
And of course, we will be discussing this a little bit.
I mean, these different critical approaches,
such as some anti-capitalist Marxist, feminist,
and eranical theory, social theory,
the exposure to those in engineering programs
is close to none, which basically means
that without trying to be too critical
about their genius who are trying to do their job,
basically they are really not aware
of the complexity of social relations
and spatial relations that are happening in cities.
So everything that you've learned with David Barson Nick by now, this is simply not there.
A city, according to this vision, is essentially a model that can be constructed,
calculated and put in place, and you can predict what will happen tomorrow, the day after
based on that, in any city in the world.
Now that thinking has a very, yeah, very, very strange way of imagining the city.
Essentially if a city is or any urban space is more of a field of application, then actually
a site of any dynamics or conflicts or contradictions, different interests in terms of what
should be happening in that space and that society.
And I'm sure that you've all come across
many even these drawings over similar ones
from from the Go was here and his friends and allies,
who basically imagined that this is exactly what should happen
in a modern city, that these models,
not only related to transport in this case
also to housing or generally economic development
should be literally applied in a city.
So the idea there wouldn't be that
in order to for that model to be as efficient as possible,
everything in the city, especially its medieval,
pre-industrial remnants would have to be raised.
The city would have to become a black empty slate
on which this model could be applied.
So even though this maybe wasn't its most extreme
in the 1950s and the 1960s,
when these urban motorways were being constructed
when, as I showed you, urban trunks and Brussels were being put
underground and a lot of heavy construction offers,
destruction had to be done.
This thinking is still very much applies.
This, if you tune into engineers from construction offices
in Brussels or elsewhere in Belgium or Northern Europe,
the idea is that planning still has to follow some rational rules
of solving congestion.
in Brussels, for example, we have a Belgium-a-log stand
and debate about what to do with the Ringo
Brussels, the Ringo, who has to be expanded or not.
Every single time there is an engineer talking
on the radio and the news, what their solution would be
is to answer to the infrastructure,
because basically if you have traffic jams
that generates lost time, that's the tremendous economy.
You have to expand an infrastructure
in order for the flows to be more fluid and unobstructed.
This modern new classical thinking also,
Well, you're thinking about fluidity of flows
and removing barriers to these led
to a separation of different modes of transport.
So this is why we would have overpasses,
food bridges that would allow
or well separate pedestrians from cars, for example.
So allow the cars to have a smooth space infrastructure
for movement while pedestrians would have to
across it over an ordinary.
And that of course also that line of thought
would be very much related or very much inspired
also by the development of individual mobility
via the car, right?
So the car being not only this extremely free mode
of transport also very rational and very fast
while you're moving around.
Now, we arrived to the 1970s, let's say,
and something very important happened around that time
Would anybody have an idea of being in the pictures?
What, what I have in mind?
Not change the way that we look at the car,
the change the way we look at the transport.
- Your prices?
- The oil prices, I guess somebody already mentioned
that in one of the classes.
So the oil trucks in the 1970s,
when first in the 1973,
the organization of our petroleum exporting countries.
So essentially the Persian Gulf countries in the United
in Nolimbago and the 1979 Iranian revolution took place.
That's not something that you can easily model.
That's geopolitics for you.
And what basically happened is that the global oil prices
went through the roof, not maybe for a moment, for a longer time.
And then they went down a little bit to a level
that allowed, of course, for car-based mobility
to continue, but what basically happened was that on a global
scale decision makers, people who were in charge of designing
transport infrastructure, realized that this limitless mobility
by car has its economic cost, so all that fossil fuels might
not be as available as they used to be.
But also around that time began to begin some kind of,
as moved to this slide already,
reflection on different externalities
are different also social and environmental costs
that are related to carvests mobility.
This environmental cost being, for example,
predominantly noise, of course, accidents,
health related issues, mostly related to pollution
that is created by an individual cast.
And at a run at that time,
I mean, maybe it's also difficult for us to imagine,
but until the 1970s, the idea that a car has to be efficient
in terms of its fuel consumption,
not has to be safe in terms of making sure that if it hits,
other vehicles or if it hits pedestrians or cyclists
it has to be more or less safe
and there are these different areas of the car
that absorb the energy of the impact.
That was all essentially not the day
with some exceptions.
A car was the cars were not efficient
from the economic perspective,
from the environment of the perspective either.
What changed is that, well,
I'm again moving very fast
in these developments.
What changed is that there was first a reflection
on the environmental impact of the car itself.
And the general reflection on the questions
to sustainable development of development
that allows future generations to benefit
from the same resources from the same opportunities
that we are benefiting from today.
So some kind of beginning of a reflection
in terms of the planetary limits of the growth
that our societies are,
of the societies at the time where we're engaging in.
And also an idea that cities are absolutely crucial
for that in that process that in order
to arrive with sustainability of the development
of the planetary level, cities have to also be
transformed in order to become more sustainable.
Why is that important that we arrive to today
to contemporary situation?
Well, it's important, and this is, as also the title says,
this is the, let's say, another set of also very dominant
and very, very important,
and I was hegemonic perspectives on transport,
sustainable transport.
This is because transport is recognized today.
It's one of the most important sources of contributions
to pollution here.
We see that it's at least 14% of CO2 emissions
on the global scale as the direct emissions.
And also, while the graph, I would say that it's a little bit
controversial because you also could add much more in terms of the
different other related cost of construction and the way
that housing is constructed as a function of availability of
transport. But let's say we stick to the 40% of global emissions
being related directly to transport, which makes transport one of
Well, here I'm a little bit wrong.
That is the largest single source of global transport
emissions because you immediately see that industry is at 21%.
We also boiled to different sectors and all that.
But what's very important with transport
is that this definitely one of the fastest,
it's not the fastest rising contributor to emissions.
So every year increases the highest among all
the economic sectors globally.
So global climate problems are essentially
increasingly transport problems.
This is, let's say, we may not point of departure,
but one of the main reflections of this perspective
on the issue.
What also is very important is that,
as you see on the left hand side,
the global proportion of people living in urban communities
is rising.
So if in 2010, we were already after this magic
threshold of 50% or more of people living in cities
as opposed to the countryside.
In 2030, the projection is that it will be 60% of people living in cities and that will go up to at least 67 in 2050.
Of course, this is a mantra that I'm sure that at least those of you who follow the master in urban studies have already heard before.
We are living in urban society that's, you know, our planet is essentially an urban, an urban planet, planetary urbanization.
There's a lot of concepts flying around.
But it's important and it is a fact that increasingly the global population becoming more
and more urban, it's in the cities that a lot of these problems will have to be addressed.
So the urban mobility is not only that transport is crucial for solving the climate
crisis, but it's the urban transport that constitutes definitely a very important challenge
that has to be addressed.
So we see that as the right-hand side-craft, that urban mobility, the Manfob, and mobility
is rising almost exponentially. And that's expressed in trillions of kilometres per year here,
it rose from 2010 to 2030 by 68%. Now we might think that with all the reflection on externalities
that cars have, and produce the environmental and social aspects that are very detrimental to
to our lives, that we are moving away from the car. This is a perspective that we already had a short
charge on that. There is a shift. We start to look at urban spaces a little bit differently. We
want less cars to be present in it. But in fact on a global scale, if you look at the on the left
hand side as a cumulative figure, so the global number of all registered cars, the rise is ongoing
and it's huge. And that's also seen in the graph on the right hand side where we see
non-commulative yearly amount of cars being sold on a global scale. So we see that every year
the amount of cars being sold is rising 2019 being some sort of an exception. We have a little
bit of a drop. But what the graph doesn't not show is the amount of SUV, so the sports utility
vehicles they are called, which went through the roof in 2018 and 2019.
Their contribution environment is speaking much higher, a few times higher than regular
vehicles.
What also you can see over there is that in orange, if you see that the contribution, which
can call it this way of the European Union countries in terms of the number of cars sold,
is more or less stable.
So here we don't see an important price.
If you look at India in grey and in China in blue, here the difference between 2005 and
2019 is significant.
So there is a lot of economies, some call them developing economies, I'm not really a fan
of the word, but a lot of nation states, a lot of societies where the levels of motorizations
were relatively low and this commodity is definitely becoming more and more available.
It's not exactly the same process that was happening in Northern Europe or North America,
or Western Europe or North America in the 1940s, 50s and 60s, but it's definitely a
steep rise of modernization, of mobility levels, which raises a lot of environmental
questions, but also ethical issues in terms of whether this is something that we now
with our Western Northern ISA, looking at very critically, in fact, it's something that
these people, these societies have the right to engage in it.
As we did, it was our parents,
our grandparents did some decades ago.
But what is very important here,
I'm going to skip this one slide,
is that this debate, if we can put it this way, shifts its attention.
So we're moving away from the problem of congestion,
the problem of unobstructed flows,
the problem of rationality, the problem of economic development.
We see that this economic development has its environmental
price, if we can put it this way.
And a very important and very pertinent symbol of that mobility
and transport is the car.
As the important contributor to that cake, in terms
of pollution, in terms of externalities of transport.
And next time, so we still have a bit time for questions, maybe discussion,
we're going to talk about specific examples of how transport develops along this line of thought.
But, and I think it will be, well, it's definitely not the only thing we're going to do,
because as I will also explain in a week, that perspective also is extremely limited in its lack of
and social and also spatial understanding of the city.
So a simple critique of the car as the problem
is also leading us into a number of traps,
which mean that our understanding of how people enjoy
or do not enjoy mobility because of the class,
the gender, the ethnicity, and many other factors
is extremely limited.
So I put a little bit of a car here.
I wonder if you have any questions,
any points of discussion.
We still have 12 minutes,
so we might as well use them.
- I might try to initiate a little discussion here
about popularity of cars and
endless mess that we are now seeing
of a lifestyle on high speed and etc.
I observed a curious thing that on TV in Belgium,
at least, I don't usually watch TV,
but I happened to watch 41 night with my friend
like a generic Belgium program.
during the advertisement period, all the odds,
a vast majority of them were about cars.
And in all ways, they were trying to sell either lifestyle,
a ecological idea that new cars can be in the green,
et cetera, but I was wondering if we might ever arrive
to this thinking that we should not be advertising this anymore,
as we don't advertise cigarettes or alcohol on TV and media,
in whether that makes sense or doesn't.
It's an interesting thought.
We will actually come back to it next time,
but they wonder if somebody has already, you know,
an opinion on this, should advertising cars
or sale cars should be banned because it's
but for society.
And we're going to give an ad to this
that I've been watching Belgian TV for a long time
as I'm saying, Belgian.
And there always used to be park commercials,
but in the last two years, actually most of them
have been for SUV cars, or like there's been a bit shift
to making commercials for SUV cars, which I
have found really strange.
- Well, yeah, I think it's happening.
I was considering to put another graph
that shows the increase of SUV sales in the really,
maybe before 2015, it was,
this market hardly existed.
It really became a thing in the last two years,
at least in Western Europe.
I think it was a little bit different
in Eastern Europe, Russia, Ukraine,
some cultural reasons also really bad roads
and a lot of rich people.
But, okay, but that seems that if you tune in
to the mainstream culture, if you show TV
and advertising in between programs,
the cars are still very much there.
Well, maybe not regular cars, but more SUVs, as you say.
I think it's an interesting observation.
Anybody else has some thoughts on this or another things?
I think it would be quite hard to prohibit the advertisements if there's no real alternative
for the car, for example, in flanders, yeah, there's an extreme suburbanization and its
mobility is not that good to get to different places such as work or leisure. So yeah, I think first
a better alternative for the car needs to be installed. And what is that alternative?
Yeah, maybe better public transport, safer also in cities, but also in just down safer bicycle
lanes or, yeah.
And yes, like car sharing more,
if not really an alternative for cars,
it may be less having each household having two cars
or three.
And in Belgium, there's also the big problem
of the companies having giving cars to their employees,
which has sparked the bait.
- Yes, in Belgium in fact,
most of new cars being sold,
a so-called company cars, which are
paid for by the,
I mean, for those who do not know
who are not from Belgium,
it's a system that allows you to get a free car
from your employer,
and it's basically a way of giving somebody a salary bump
because a tax free bonus,
if you increase somebody's salary,
would have to pay tax on this. You don't pay tax on the company car. But then why do you think
people, well, because it seems that I described some kind of a shift of thinking and some
reflection on these environmental problems that the corporate uses and all the new
senses that it causes, but it seems that people still drive. Why do you think they still do it?
Why is it still so popular?
Maybe I can refer to this. I think there's like
exactly what you were talking about before like certain
yeah certain
factors which which cannot be
somehow persist before like like our planners cannot um sorry um like you
certain things you cannot plan and like it's an individual approach that
the symbol of the car is still like deep in the mind of a lot of people that they
it's like a day routine that you get into your car and drive to the to your
working place. And I think that's exactly the problem that it's certain changes in the transportation
system cannot be made by planners or transport transportation planners, but have to be made in
in the society or in the symbolism of a car. So it's a mindset, it's some cultural
How do we choose sociologists would say that's a way of imagining how we interact with the world or how we move through it?
But I think the example of the company power also shows it something else. It's not exclusive. That is also a policy.
That there are a number of political instruments that make it.
I mean, if we go with that simplified logic of making a rational economic choice,
How do I go and what do I go?
It simply makes this decision more simple, more rational.
It makes sense to have a car from an economic perspective as well, in many cities still.
If I could maybe add to that also that's structurally, there is a lot of government as well,
policy support not just like the company cars, but as we saw these days with the crisis,
I think to try to boost, not to allow our automobile manufacturing, automobile companies,
crumble because of the employment opportunities that they provide. So,
strangely enough, actually some of the financial loss or some of the new
funds for the stimulate the economy have been directly towards individual car owners
purchase of different people. So I think when you when you see that it's
being imperative a big push if you can have access to that as well.
Yeah. I think singles with aviation, I don't know if you follow the London news, but
one of the first, maybe not first, but one of the only discussions in terms of some economic
package for stimulating the economy in Belgium was towards the aviation companies.
The argument being is that these industries create jobs and these jobs are valuable.
Well, I'm not saying whether this is right or wrong,
but the argument is there that these modes of mobility also produce employment.
I think that relates a little bit to this aspect of economic development, this anticipation,
that this way of moving around our cities or societies in general is very important for the economy
to keep growing, to keep persisting.
Are there any other comments? We're from some people who haven't spoken yet.
Do you have some thoughts?
Some comments?
I was also thinking about security. The use of the car is still
Like, yeah, done by many because maybe it's the most secure way of moving around in some cities.
And also, like, as I'm thinking, like, as a woman, as a girl, like, moving around the city at night,
usually like, I mean, not here in Brussels because I don't have a car here in Brussels, like, back home.
I would go by car at night. Just because like, yeah, it's not very secure to move around with,
like probably transport or even by bike. So I would say like yeah it's a matter of security as well.
And it's more like a structure problem to change so I guess more steps have to be taken in that sense.
Yeah it's a very good point. It's existed before the pandemic and now it's become even more
more of an issue. So any data shows us that, especially the upper middle class or upper class
people have bought themselves a new car to separate themselves from the danger of interacting with
others. And this danger would be related to maybe criminality or general lack of safety, especially
at night, especially for women perhaps. But now this sense of danger and the car is this kind of
bubble that allows you to separate yourself from whatever danger society holds, it's even stronger.
I think what's important also, we will talk about this a lot next time, is that this goes
very differently for different people. I mean it sounds very obvious, but whether you look at
the situation from a class perspective or from a gender perspective or from a racial perspective,
I think all these three also ages very important. All these four then
the blind person is very much. The way that people arrive through a decision in terms of
why they go where they go and how they go, it's very different from cluster class from
gendered gender etc etc. So this homo-economic paradigm is extremely problematic there.
But so is, I hope I will convince you of that, this direct critique of the car,
because different people use the car for different reasons. And not always, it's an individual choice,
but also there are some structural issues that play, also indeed, some cultural inertia,
some ways of being that were installed and promoted for decades, which now we are of some of us.
living in city centres, critical of things are quite different if you're from a
different class and living in different areas of the city. I don't mind taking one
more or two more questions but it's age already so we are very free to leave
if you want to. I don't want to take too much of your time.
Well, great.
I'm glad this is working from the technical perspective at least.
Yeah, I will see you next week.
Can I add a last question?
Yeah, yeah.
The last question about the excursion that we have program.
I know that in COVID times, well, it's not happening.
No, no, I was told that, yeah,
was trying to do it, but it's not possible, unfortunately.
I wish we could do it.
The idea is for those of you who are in Brussels next semester,
but all of you will be, right?
Well, I mean, let's say, well, we don't know, of course,
what happens in a few months.
But the idea is that if in spring, we are more or less
to more into face-to-face meetings,
we do the excursion then. We imagined with David Bas another is what would happen if we meet with
40 people and tried to keep distance. I think this would you know we would hit YouTube very quickly
I think trying to walk through the city in this arrangement. So no and also in December I mean it
would be very strange. From ice greens in the end we would definitely try to keep together
just to keep warm. It's cold right? So we will do that in spring I hope. It's a nice excursion.
from what I've heard. People usually enjoy it. Even though it's only about transport.
But yeah, I'm sorry about that. I wish we could do it. Yeah, this is the reality we're living in.
I hope you've got a great rest of the week. I'll see you all next week. The links are there,
So it seems that everything is clear and working. So that's brilliant.
Enjoy and have a good, have a good week.
Thank you for the lecture.
Thank you very much. Bye bye. Bye bye. Bye bye.
(faint fartling)