to be recording automatically, but it is now.
Thanks for reminding me.
So double rationality, the rationality of the discipline,
which is taken as some kind of field
deriving from natural sciences, alluding to laws of physics,
which apparently help to understand where people go,
how they move around the city.
and the rationality of the people themselves,
of the users, of passengers, drivers,
who make rational, economic choices
in terms of where they go, how they go.
How does this apply to the city?
Well, basically the city's approach as a clean slate.
So it's social, political, spatial complexity.
It's seen, if it is seen, it's seen as an obstacle
to these principles of rational planning.
If it's not seen, then basically, well,
this planning is applied as if on a clean slate,
which in this particular slide,
maybe this is a bit of an exaggeration.
He's a plant from the Copusia,
who was really very back then,
and was called the Boul, the courageous,
in terms of proposing to actually
demolish all the neighborhoods
or all cities to give way to this rational modern planning.
But a lot of these planning principles have been applied,
I'm sure that you've been to, maybe even lived in cities
where whole neighborhoods, if not whole cities,
have been designed according to this principle
of rationality, speed, modernity.
That of course focused on, or framed the car,
the private vehicle as the ultimate,
most rational, most liberating mode of mobility,
mode of transport.
We also arrived last time to this growing reflection,
starting from the 1970s and then through the 1980s and 1990s,
on many different problems related to car
and automobileities.
So there's wider social phenomenon related
to a classification and commodification of private cars.
So a lot of social issues have been raised
and primarily environmental issues,
second-rate with regards to automobileity
with regard to the car.
And to be frank,
I think in a lot of transport debates, whether in academia or on activism or in policy,
you in Brussels I think is quite apparent in many other Belgian cities too.
This is where we are.
This is still very much the dominant paradigm in terms of how policy is being framed and
how research is being done.
Paris considered to be something detrimental to the quality of urban space, to living,
because of its environmental effects,
the pollution, noise, accidents, that it causes,
it's a very dangerous mode of transport.
For those, of course, who are outside of the car
and clash, collide with it.
Or it's spatial footprints, right?
So the spatial impact of the infrastructure,
the amount of square meters that have to be devoted
to this particular mode of transport,
nor the for it, to be able to move around the city.
So I'm thinking here,
but all there have been multiple ways, the parking lots,
junctions and all that that has to be present
in the city for the car to be a valid,
useful of moving around.
So this is what we did last time.
A bit of an, I'm not an introvert,
but what happened also,
throughout the 1970s and '80s,
is that in the global north, at least,
in so-called developed countries,
such as Belgium, but also across the point in North America.
Cities have entered into a post-40s era,
and I'm sure this has been covered a lot by David
and probably a little bit by Nick.
And here I'm going to focus much more
on the transport related impact of that shift.
Of course, it was not something that happened over a day
and it's difficult to tell or to pinpoint
when did 40 cities conclude the existence,
and we moved to post-40 and there's more of a longer process
that happened over a long period of time,
at least a couple of years, if not decades.
But what's very important there is that if you go back
to these curves and that are somewhat similar
to the contractives, waves of different innovation waves.
1960s, '70s and '80s brought first the innovation
and then the massification, the spread of ICT technology.
So different modes of different instruments
of telecommunication, and also a big development
of aviation of air, which was used both.
I mean, of course, it existed already in 1930s,
40s and 50s, but it's in the 1970s
that it really became a common or more common than ever
way for people to move around to travel, of course,
not within the city, but between cities and countries,
and also to move goods.
So this really propelled or gave constitute
a really big step in terms of globalizing both traffic of people as an of goods or trade.
And that's coincided with a general shift from industrial to service economy,
ongoing sub-organization of not only housing but also a number of other economic functions that
were traditionally related to them because also moved to the suburbs, which created
polycentric mosaic-like patterns of suburbanization. So the suburbs were no longer
these residential areas from which people committed to the city center, but actually a lot of jobs,
a lot of productive activity and service economy would start being located in the suburbs themselves.
So creating all kinds of constellations, which for example could be called the suburban downtown,
so H-Cities that comes from the work of a famous job of a soldier,
analyzing the development of Los Angeles in the 1980s and the 1990s.
The paradigm of this could be seen, I mean, or the symbol, not a paradigm of this transformation
could be seen in the particular space or a type of space of an airport. If back in the 1970s,
as you can see in this image, the airport would be a very functional place, a place of arrival,
the departure and around the small area would be devoted to the airport. This over, of course,
a number of decades has completely changed. So you see that development of one of the most
important efforts in the world's people, which is the airport of Amsterdam. What's very important
here is that the airport is no longer in addition to the city but actually increasingly a central
space around which or in relation to which the city develops.
So what kind of a city has, what kind of an upwards city has,
has repercussions in terms of what kind of class of investors
and productive activities it can attract.
To have an important airport hub is increasingly
only, well, it's already a well-established point
of the agenda of open marketing of open development.
And airports are no longer just airports.
when you can see here in the slide that around C-pop,
we've got a number of other activities.
So business district, office spaces, residential hotel.
So it is sort of neighborhood in itself
that is built around the airport itself.
This is important, why is it important?
Well, there is a number of things at stake here,
but the most important thing here is that this change
of typology of different spaces and relation to these different modes of travel.
So, coming into telecommunications, aviation means that travel patterns are becoming more
and more complex.
The globalization of world economy and the centrality of the city and global economy means
that there is a number of productive activities jobs basically that have in 24/7.
It's the paradigm of going to, I mean, of most people going to work at eight o'clock,
in the morning and then going back in the afternoon, of course, it's a lot of people still
do that, but there is plenty of jobs that happen overnight that require transporting
infrastructure that is provided in places and at times that were not needed, there was no
demand for in the past. So in other words, this making of the urban economy more flexible
and more precarious has repercussions in terms of making transport and mobility also much
much more flexible or the demand for, much more flexible,
way of moving, which of course means that it's way more complicated and way more difficult
to design transport systems than before.
Since people move, if we can put it in a very blunt way, in much more complicated ways than
ever before, at very different times, in different spaces.
Just to give you an example, I mean, traditionally, there's haven't been, so the
airport of Brussels will be considered, of course, as a very important space that had to
be connected to the city, primarily to receive passengers
there and from.
And increasingly, around that area of the city--
and I think you covered that with David, quite in detail--
there is a whole hub of business and productive activity,
which of course attracts a lot of middle class workers
who would go to that area daytime.
But then the development of the city--
sorry, of the airport--
means that there is a high demand for workers
and logistics, for example.
I have to arrive at the airport at 3 o'clock in the morning, which raises questions in terms of provision of public transport to the area.
A lot of these people would, for example, reside in working-class neighborhoods of Brussels.
So there is a question where the night-time public transport should be provided to the area,
but then get the current paradigm of public transport by nighttime in Brussels.
This mode of transport is mostly provided for leisure activities.
So for people who go out and enjoy cultural activities
or socializing and want to go back home
and do a clock three o'clock in the night.
But not for people who actually need to reach
they jobs at that time of the night.
In very, let's say weird or previously
not so present areas such as the sub-item area
or other locala fees around that and that's not that hard.
Okay.
So having said this,
So a quick reminder of what we did last time
and a quick cover of this shift from four this to post four
is the paradigm of urban development
and its repercussions for the cities
and transport in them.
Here's what we are going to do today.
So we will discuss perhaps have a little discussion.
Actually, I'll be trying to ask you some questions
and engage in some exchange here.
What is the sustainable urban transport
different sustainable perspectives on imagining transport and developing it.
And then we will engage in a progressive deconstructing of the paradigm and analyze what we
can identify as critical approaches to transport it, mobility that built on a number of
perspectives that you already heard from David and Bass and Nick about.
All right.
Last week, what you had to do, and many other things that are done out of you had to do
with students of Master of Nursing Studies and Geography,
is to read paper by David Bannister on Sustainable Mobility
Partly.
I wonder whether you still remember anything from that paper.
This is not an exam, so don't worry if you remember things
that were not exactly what you remember,
but it's exactly clear, maybe things a little bit fuzzy.
But does something ring a bell from that piece?
If somebody asked you today before this particular lecture,
what is sustainable urban transport?
What comes to mind?
Does anybody want to share the thoughts on this with us?
That's a cool look with silence.
Come on, does anybody remember what
a banister says in this paper?
That's all right.
Okay, well, it's not how to put it.
It's not the most fascinating paper I've ever read,
but for transport geography, it's absolutely fundamental.
So this is really something that you see being referred
to for what was it written 2011, right?
So nine years in this is still a very, very important piece
of writing that really defined almost a whole field
of research and transport in mobility.
What's important here-- and this is important when
we keep thinking about the last lecture
in the neoclassical paradigm of developing transport--
is, well, could be summarized in the number of parts.
So if you think about this image that I showed you
from the corpus year, and this modernist rational approach
to planning cities around transport,
Here, the assumption is that we have to ultimately break with the small
function of planning, separation of functions, keeping residential areas on the one side,
and productive activity jobs, offices, industrial activity,
on the other side, and then leisure somewhere in between these three,
in between these two. Here, the idea is that we really have to
engage in planning cities that are much more mixed, which different functions are
allocated much more closely to each other. Why do we have to do that? Well, because this increases
a possibility of engaging less in mobility, of basically moving less in the city, which has of course
very good implications or potentially good implications in terms of the environmental impact of
transport. So the idea is that if we make cities more mixed, in terms of the functions, and on
top of that more dense, we might arrive at a situation in which people don't have to travel such
for our distances, all they don't have to travel that often.
And potentially, and that's the second point,
we can also facilitate some kind of a shift
from the mode that we all want to disappear.
I'm thinking as a sustainable urban transport plan
right now.
So the car towards public transport, collective mobility,
on the one hand, and on the other hand,
so-called soft transport mode.
So walking, cycling, to profoundly challenge
and hopefully end the domination of class in cities.
So this is, it goes beyond the critique of the car.
How do we, maybe not get rid of the car,
but how do we limit its presence?
Well, we make cities more dense, more mixed,
and we make public transport
and other different modes of moving around more attractive.
Well, of course, there are important cultural
and social barriers to this.
So there is some kind of social inertia
and you mentioned it in our discussion at the end of the last lecture,
people are used to driving.
They, of course, had been also told for a couple of decades.
Now that I mean buying a car is something not only perfectly normal,
but maybe in context such as Belgium or Brussels,
a perfectly rational choice.
Also, well, if we follow the neoclassical line,
I mean people make rational economic choices.
It's been simply quite profitable and economically reasonable to have a car.
So to instigate some kind of a social transformation,
we need to pay more attention to how people make these choices.
And this perspective starts adding a number of psychological analysis, for example,
in fact, to this equation. So it's not only an economic choice in some kind of an economic
decision that people make when they take a car or some other amount of transport,
But there's also different social aspects, psychological aspects that impact,
that make an impact on this. And this means that sustainable urban transport scholars, planners,
activists are much more attentive than the neoclassical colleagues in terms of how people
engage in different lifestyles, why do they practice certain travel behaviors that is called,
which also leads to a lot of studies on inclusion and transport or exclusion from it on accessibility,
the two different transport modes or accessibility
through transport to different urban functions,
which progressively over the 1990s, 2000s,
and after today, questions this paradigm of seems
to question this paradigm of top down planning and policy.
So this figure of some neoclassical rational expert
is not necessarily what it's still there,
but it's not the only god-like figure
that made these liquor who see a life decisions
in terms of, here we will go the motorway,
and here we will build some residential neighborhood
et cetera et cetera.
Where is the city in this paradigm or in this perspective?
Well, the city is an outcome of the sustainable
transport paradigm.
It's a sustainable transport in sustainable city
is an integral component of what Jacob's calls good city
or what David Bannister in the article he had to read,
identifies as urban viability, vibrancy, vitality.
There is a lot of words about a lot of writing about
the attractiveness of the city or its livability
or its resilience, that's a bit more recent.
So there's a lot of keywords which identify a city as
ultimate benefactor of this shift
towards sustainable transport.
So there is talk about maintaining economic performance
of the city since, well, we remember that
new classical scholars have essentially tried
to theorize this relationship between economic growth
and development of transport.
So it's still there.
We move away from the carbon.
So the cities still continue to develop.
The economy is continue to thrive.
which you've social cohesion so presumably everybody is on board,
there is no loses of this process.
It's all, of course, environmentally friendly.
We arrive at urban environments which provide better health
environments or not facilities, but basically more healthy
for the residents.
And all this in the spirit of participation,
so everybody is on board and this political process
does not exclude anybody.
Well, if you think about this, I mean,
I'm, no, my intention is not to be ironic here.
I think that, by the way, the slide,
I mean, the image here is from this visualization
of Boula Varnspak in Brussels,
so the central avenue that crosses the Pentagon
from North to South.
And if you remember how this street looked like
some years ago, this kind of vision is something
that we might all want to subscribe to.
I mean, who doesn't want to live in a city that is all these things economically performing
and socially cohesive environment friendly?
I mean, it's a perfect city to see.
The problem is, well, before we move to the problem, there are a few.
I'm sure that this rings a bell, and I'm sure that you know a lot of different practices
which are trying to policies, practices that are trying to achieve these things to make
the city more environmentally friendly in terms of its transport, economic performance,
inclusive, cohesive and whatnot. I am curious what examples you know. So this is maybe an
easy question to answer compared to the previous one. Does anybody know any practices of sustainable
transport, basically? Is it my question?
Could you consider the construction of bike lanes, for example?
Yes, very much so. I mean, it's promoting a different mode of transport than the cars, right?
One of the soft modes cycling. So we absolutely yes.
What else?
I see it, Antwerp. I'm leaving
here next to it, about 1 kilometer of the opera in Antwerp.
And two years ago, it was for passengers.
Very difficult to cross the roads.
And now they made a tunnel.
And they made a huge space for COVID transport and passengers.
So you can see now, and then a big difference,
a clear division from what's what's unusual until the 90s.
So you mean that there was less space of well, the current
for starting to be a
is now the human life by public transport to the world.
Yeah.
The the car was still
like they said it was the boss.
Right.
of the car was very important.
We see now we shift there.
And the shift basically consists of creating some infrastructure for pedestrians
and public transport to somehow buy.
Now for a meeting place for the opera.
Okay, okay.
Okay, very often.
Just to this.
Can you hear him?
Yeah, I just just right before the lecture I read about Paris with a more
restrictive policy about banning
There are parking spots in cities in in order to achieve the 50 minutes city the so-called
Human city air right so restricting
Restructing current infrastructure or transforming it into different type of infrastructure for either either different modes or for pedestrians
So creating some urban space, okay.
What else?
Maybe developing bus rapid transit.
That's not all that in America.
Yeah. Does everybody, or is this somebody who doesn't know what bus rapid transit is?
It's a funny question to ask to a screen, but, oh, you know,
we don't tell me that it's switched again.
I have to stop sharing this screen, but perhaps you want to explain what bus rapid transit is,
I'm sure that there is somebody who doesn't know.
I can help in case your definition is not perfect.
Well, what it has.
Yeah, you know, what I have as an example is this lanes that they're just for bosses.
So they're developed a rapid lane that it will only go for bosses.
It's supposed to work better around the city.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, it's essentially creating separate lanes for buses, but what's quite specific about this or quite particular is that it kind of imitates or replaces an underground system, so a metro system, which is of course very expensive to build.
So the idea is that instead of engaging in all this digging and creating this very costly and invasive infrastructure, you can just create some separate lanes for the buses and have an efficient.
public transport system which is metro like.
And that's, I want to say common, but well, a lot of cases first emerge in the global
south, right?
So in South America and in South Africa, but there are also cases in global, in
the global north and western European.
Okay, there is a lot of these different policies and a lot of different, a lot of different
practices and ideas.
It seems.
So let's quickly go over, let's try to put them together
into some kind of coherent typology of different things
that cities can do in order to make this transport
more sustainable.
So the first thing is to tackle the problem, right?
So if the problem is the car, then how do we deal with the car?
Well, we can either improve the technology of the car.
And this means reducing emissions,
making it contaminate the little bit less.
So cleaning the engine technology,
substituting for of petrol,
these are vehicles by electric vehicles or biogas,
or whatnot.
Creating the construction of cars
so that they cause less casualties in case of accidents.
So this is something that today we take for granted
that cars have these crash zones
and crashes are being done in safety tests.
But this was virtually non-existent in the 1970s or '80s.
So that's one thing.
So basically it's trying to make the car
a better vehicle for the city.
Well, here, the immediate problem is that I mentioned
that last time among the type of vehicles
that see the number of sales go up.
Most, I mean, most rapidly in the last two or three years,
our SUVs, the sports utility vehicles,
which are basically these massive Jeep-like cars
which are extremely dangerous for pedestrians.
And if you also turn to one of the most important
or marketised inventors of transport technology, Elon Musk.
I mean, it's a guy who does electric cars, but also if you paid attention to that,
I don't know if you noticed that in the news.
I think it was early this year or last year that he produced this massive truck,
like American style pickup truck, which has not been tested in terms of its impact on
pedestrians in case it actually clashes with one. But there is, on the one hand, the industry
tries to reinvent the vehicles to make them more safe and very many friendly. On the other hand,
there is still a push for creating gigantic vehicles which simply cannot achieve that with the size
and the you know it's audience or the audience not simply looking for this. Okay so that's the car.
And the other thing that of course can be done is to restrict the accessibility for the car
to the city as a whole or to its different area specific zones right. So we can
And for example, imposed these destructive pricing instruments,
such as congestion charging or perage,
which was a more stud stolen and Dutch,
which was very recently announced in Brussels,
but it existed in several other Belgian cities
in one form or another for quite a while now.
We can think of reducing physically the space for the car,
so basically making roads more narrow,
so cutting some lanes,
reducing the number of parking areas.
And then, as it was mentioned earlier,
replacing this infrastructure,
replacing this space with other uses.
So opening this space, too, for example,
pedestrians will non-motorize traffic,
creating these so-called pedestrian zones,
or shared spaces.
And here have one from London in this slide.
And also, the famous congestion charging steam in London,
which means that in a specific central area of London,
you pay 12 pounds to enter every time you do that, right?
Okay, what other things can be done
to tackle a lot of mobility?
Well, of course, if we want the presence of the car to go down,
we need to propose some alternative to the car.
Our obvious alternative is public transport,
and here's sustainable perspectives on transport basically
keep emphasizing the importance of increasing the quality
of public transport,
increasing the accessibility of public transport across the urban or suburban space.
And indeed, faster rapid transit is one common example of how this can be done actually
quite inexpensively. Also, the reinstallational urban trumps in many cities in the global north
that got rid of the tram to create space for the car. If you remember my slides from last
time, that's what partly happened in Brussels in the 1970s. It's a very common way. It was a very
common phenomenon, common phenomenon, sorry. In France where a lot of cities,
tramphet work was quite simply dismantled. So here, since the 1990s, 2000s,
we see the return of the tramp. Urban for the finicular, so gradient,
skable cars, plenty of other modes, basically, of public transport. And also
promoting the notion of multi-modality, right? So creating different options for
users so that they don't have to simply choose between the car and something else,
but there's something else is a variety of different options from which one can choose,
depending on where they go with whom, what they feel like using in a particular moment of time,
what corresponds better to the behavior to the lifestyle, right? If the lifestyle and behavior
is what we pay attention to much more than before. And then finally, what's important in this
and port volume of different solutions or tools,
if you will, is reducing the need to travel.
So I mentioned already that here the idea
is that we make cities more dense, more mixed.
So perhaps we don't have to travel so often and so far.
And in planning for geography,
the idea here is to progressively
linked urban development with transport development.
So the idea of transit oriented or transport
the development emerged within this paradigm.
So for example, fostering some activities
and development around the development
of new metro stations or railway stations
or whole transport corridors.
A little bit like what I showed you last time
with COVID-19, right?
The finger, the five finger plan,
which was one of the first ideas
of linking transport development
at urban development.
And many other things that, well, quite frankly,
I'm much more interested in sharing with you
the critique of all this, then this itself.
Because this is very easy to find this plenty
of different publications on this.
I mean, basically, if you follow any of these websites
which deal with, well, these are called magazine
these days, follow urban policy, city lab,
the Atlantic, Fox, or whatnot, sure that you know
more than I do.
I mean, this is what they say.
I mean, this is what they promote a lot, right?
So the car is the problem.
So any time a big northern, also in the global south,
this is picked up a little bit.
But any time any city,
an important city does something in terms of curving
or vulnerability,
this is very often picked up at this kind of media
and hailed as a radical intervention,
as a radical step to reinvent the ability
to give cities back to the people,
to make cities more sustainable green attractive,
et cetera, et cetera.
Now, I'm not saying that this is all bad
and that this is problematic in itself.
But there is a number of critical questions
that ask us critical geographers
really need to be asking about these practices,
because they're quite simply, well,
they are not really taking full stock
of the complexity of cities that they're being applied
for one.
So, well, the first immediate problem
is that the word sustainability
or the term sustainability has already been picked up
by the industry, the paradigm, that sustainability,
in principle, wanted to criticize
and to have some critical cutting edge over.
So for instance, the oil industry
and the current industry, both claim to be extremely sustainable
these days, in terms of how they produce soil,
and in terms of how they produce vehicles.
I mentioned already this idea of reinventing the car,
which is a more sustainable mode of travel in cities.
But the deeper problem is that, and I will show that in a moment,
that the kind of questions that sustainable urban paradigm asks about the city
and the solutions that it tries to bring are essentially,
I mean, they can only reveal some transport reality to a point.
So it's very quick, I think, that we can read some kind of a wall.
And this debate between, let's say, the neoclassical engineers
and economists and the anti-car proponents
of sustainable uponities is not a very productive one.
And very importantly for this course said, for you,
as I don't know, I've been geographers
for a certain planet of the future,
the relation between transport and the urban in this debate
is very weak.
So conceptually, but also empirically,
this kind of thinking about transport and mobility
simply does not tell us a lot, I think, about the city,
which is why we're here tonight.
Right, so, though let's be constructed
and explore some critical stuff about it basically.
So, I wonder whether you can already pick up
some critique of this from Elena Vania
in her colleague, T. Riebrenak.
I'll be stubborn with the readings today.
Does anybody remember something from the reading for today?
I do.
It's been, since I read it, but I know that she has like identified two main principles
of critique, which is first that the alternatives that are being proposed by the automobile
industry and no specific plans, they are not very like sufficient and reducing the
out to mobile impact in certain cases. You can say something wrong and then secondly,
well it's sort of a very exclusive sometimes discussion I think, but yeah,
I it's not very present anymore, but I would like to pose another question for that paper. It kind of upset me anyway.
Oh yeah.
You can do it right now.
Okay.
Well, go ahead.
Yeah, if we're at it, like I basically I liked her way of like introducing her thoughts and like structuring the paper, but I was a bit like put off just
methodologically in the way that she links empirical evidence that she produced herself to theory
that is oftentimes very theoretical and based on very personal beliefs and attitudes which I
like also support in a way, but sometimes I found that did make her arguments less striking,
and I was just wondering because we are like still in the beginning of all of our
like urban critical research careers, how that is to be done.
If you have an answer to that.
I don't know. I mean, I don't have an answer to that question.
Well, I would agree with you that maybe methodologically this is not the strongest paper.
It's an analysis of plans and it's not very clear exactly what she's made with this.
Maybe it's true that her convictions are a little bit stronger than her in periods. In this
particular paper, I picked it because it's summarises a few things a little bit better than others.
But I really like what she does, even though the best work that she's done in French,
I think which makes it not accessible to everybody here.
But yeah, I think your first point in terms of what's in the article,
it's spot on. It's also there in the title. I mean, she maybe,
again, she risks being maybe a little bit
and engaging in some kind of exaggeration, right?
It's not every single sustainable urban transparency
that leads to the processes that she describes.
But there is a tendency for these policies to create some inequalities and for deep politicizing the debate
so
It's not exactly clear who these policies are supposed to be for they are these
Obvious a little bit again in this kind of neoclassical
Direction rational tools of now dealing with
With the car is the problem, right?
So in fact, the power relations in transport or in transport policy have not really changed.
It's just that the focus has shifted significantly and now this is what the planets are doing,
as opposed to what they were doing in the 1970s and '80s.
Let's dive into this.
Whoops. Great. So what are the, and that's my individual, how to put it.
my personal top five of the reasons why sustainable urban transport paradigm is not exactly the
you know doesn't give you a complete view of the relationship between transport and the city.
And also with some I think quite practical theoretical, empirical recipes for how to get out of this
roadblock pan unintended. So the first issue with a lot of the writing on sustainability is that it's
it's still very much focused on technology.
So there is a lot of attention given to technological solutions,
where social and political innovations
and some brought about political activity,
organization, engagement of people as political agents,
not just the consumers and customers that have to be now
convinced to shift from one mode to another,
from the car to something else.
This is not so present.
And well, this comes from the guru himself.
Elon Musk, who is, despite, of course,
some obvious critique, was his personality
and how he carries himself in media,
he still is very much the hope for many
in terms of transitioning from carbon heavy
modes of mobility to electric vehicles,
which according to the industry
are the thing of the future.
So according to Elon Musk, as he says,
I think public transport is painful, it sucks.
Why do you want to get on something with a lot of other
that doesn't leave where you want it to leave,
doesn't start where you want it to start,
doesn't end where you want it to end.
It's a pain in the ass.
And so that's why people like individualized transport
that goes where you want and when you want.
So the idea here is not to engage in
collectivizing transport, for example,
and making this a more common service
or a more common experience to break
not only the paradigm of dependency on fossil fuels
the car, but the tendency on the visual transport, making this basically a less individual
activity, which is a social political activity as well.
Now to the contrary, here the idea is to develop a better technology within the power
and a more than a visual transport.
And you don't mask, I mean, he's doing a lot of things, but one of the other things
in Tesla and the production of electric vehicles that he does is boring tunnels on the Los
Angeles to basically create some parallel motorway system if we can call it this way, that bypasses
congestion. So actually the focus here while might apparently be on making transport sustainable,
it is essentially to solve congestion, which is an extremely, as I explained last time, new
classical formulation of the problem. Another issue, and that's from an envious paper, but I think
It's not from the one that you had to read for today, but from another thing that I that I like from here is this
focus on
the individual as
not only well
I'm to put it not only is the source of a number of transport problems, but also as a solution to to address these problems, right?
So
the idea here is that
Essentially, we can convince people to change the habits,
to change the lifestyle related to transport and mobility.
And in this way, we can solve a number of issues related
to this field of urban planning or urban policies,
which means that within the sustainable paradigm,
a lot of policymakers, a lot of trans-foods, they hold us,
would rather than engage in the politics of transport,
they would engage on the pedagogy gets related to it.
So it's suddenly the challenge is to make sure
that people engage less in behavior
that is identified as bad behavior, for example,
driving or living in the suburbs, flying around,
and switching to what is considered to be good
type of behavior, positive behavior.
So, cycling around, walking,
living in a city center, living in these dense,
mixed urban areas that don't require
that you engage in mobility so much.
And while this, of course, is not a problem in itself,
I mean, it's good to think of why would people
stick to particular ways of moving?
What's very detrimental, I think, to the debate
and to ultimately solving some issues related to transport
is putting these different ways of moving
and different behaviors related to movement in a hierarchy
where clearly there is a moral component.
So this good and bad behavior, I think this is something
that can actually antagonize people against one another
rather than try to think of transfer problems
as common societal problems.
That's issue number one.
And issue number two is that in this discussion
about individual behavior, engagement with analyzing
and anonymity addressing structural causes
behind transport and mobility is not so present.
So if we focus on the question, why would people drive?
and why would people, for example, even in specific ethnicity or gender or class,
trying more than others, it is very important to also understand what is the structure
behind this, what is the general policy that allows people to obtain access to a vehicle
that allows a parallel or occurring structure which very often, and that's the case definitely in
Belgium, it's often absolutely free to use with no taxes to use motorways,
or with cheap parking, etcetera, etcetera. So this perspective is in itself not a problem
to look at you know why people engage in particular, the type of behavior and other,
but it's very important to also understand structures behind this.
What Alejandro and Nia also writes a lot about and many others as well, but as I said I'm really
quite convinced by writing is the uneven geography that is being produced by these different
sustainable solutions. Some of these asking a question in the chat, so let me read that.
So maybe there's something in between. For example, self-driving cars and apps like Uber
would be able to create smaller vehicles that can be shared as public transport. So in a sense,
in between but in between of in between what and between private I mean in
really individual transport and and collective transport you mean
Rudy do you want to explain whoever you are?
Hello Rudy are you with us? I hope you didn't just write the comment left
Maybe the connection is not very good on your end.
Well, yeah, I mean, clearly in recent years, there's
been a rise of expectations towards this, shared mobility
laws, right?
So a number of practices which allow you to get access to
seemingly collectivize transport like Uber.
I mean, essentially you don't own the vehicle, but it's just
not even a phone call with a tap on your phone away.
But there is a number of issues with this.
So there's a question whether this actually replaces individual transport.
So do people have less cars because Uber is expanding in this city
if we're focusing on Uber industries?
There is also a lot of studies that show that Uber actually adds to congestion.
So there are more Uber develops in the city or it's counterparts
are different, are the competitive platforms left in China.
There was a huge company called DDE that essentially does what
it was with us.
So there are more of these companies developed in your city.
There are more, what the total number of vehicles, the car stock,
increases, which means, and that's a problem in a lot of Chinese cities,
you basically have more traffic jams.
So these cars are in traffic all the time.
They keep looking for customers.
they have a mobile, which means that you add to the problem that you try to solve, which
when you try to solve again adding more to these shared platforms.
And also the big issue with Uber, if we are focusing on this for a moment, is that the
working conditions of course are quite terrible.
So the idea there is that essentially there are exceptions to this, but in most cities where
Uber operates.
We workers are not really workers, they're contractors, which means that they very often
go in debt to actually get the vehicle that they're driving, that they have to pay back
to Uber, because it's offering also these services.
This means that they work for a long hours.
Unlike regular taxi drivers that have to actually clock in and out, this is much more
regulated in terms of how they work for a lot amount of time and also what knowledge
of the city they have. I don't know how often you've taken Uber in your life, but it's
often the case that these drivers are exploring the city along. I mean, they just learn
as they drive, which I understand they might come from a very difficult situation that
this is the only way for them to get access to a more or less decent way of making money.
But there's a question of safety, there's a question of ethics in terms of inviting such
your practice in our cities. So there are a lot of expectations for these platforms and indeed
there is a question, does this maybe set between public transport, collective transport and
individual transport but I would say that these hopes are still not really fulfilled.
Okay, that was a bit of a delay question. Let's go back to an even geography of sustainable transport.
So what is the problem here? More often than not, the application of the sustainable tools,
different policies, infrastructural measures to deal with mobility,
especially quite exclusive. What does it mean? Well, on the one hand, it often happens that
a lot of these measures are applied in a specific area of the city and more often than not,
This is the central urban core, which has to be saved from the car, which the car has to limit its presence,
which in no way contradicts or prevents further maintenance at least, if not development or further
infrastructure for the cars in more peripheral areas. So you can think of cities in which in the city
centre you've got restrictive parking regulations, you've got a lot of pedestrian areas.
It's simply not easy to drive around.
I think transport is definitely a more logical thing to do and to use to get into.
But the farther you go to the suburbs, the more
month I lay in streets or highways you see, or actual proper highways, a lot of parking lots,
all the infrastructure that actually well belongs to the 1970s and 1980s.
And that is, I think, situation not only in Belgium or in Brussels specifically,
But in a lot of these cities that are supposedly have achieved a great level of policy in terms of dealing with with with cuts of Copenhagen, Vienna, a lot of French cities that boast these tram renewal programs.
As long as you are in the central part of the city, this old looks very coherent and very
well inverted, common, good from the sustainable transport perspective.
But the farther you go from the city centre, the more actually the more cars you see, the
more it actually resembles the problem that these policies try to solve.
Another inequality is of the vertical kind, meaning that it often happens that the investment
in these kind of sustainable tools comes at the cost of putting the current infrastructure underground.
So you can think of any case in which the specialization of an urban avenue or pull-over,
that means that the cars have to be put underground parking lots or the highways.
And this is often the problem in the so-called Car-Free Cities. The cities that are often picked up
by international media and praised for having addressed head-on the domination of the
cars and dealt with the problem of opportunity. A specific tool that I think we can see this
uneven geography in is a question in the chat. An example for Rudy's question from Berlin,
great. Let me go on with the congestion charging while you're discussing Uber in the chat.
this is perfectly allowed. So an example of this uneven geography can be found in
congestion charging, which is one of the let's say one of the most classical tools of sustainable
transport paradigm in terms of limiting the presence of the cars. The idea is simple. It came from
Singapore in the 1970s, which was developed as a very new classical tool of planning,
basically the problem was congestion and the idea was to convince to encourage drivers to use the
car off peak, so to minimize the traffic, the traffic jams in morning and afternoon or evening peak hours.
And progressively this tool, or perhaps with a shift of velocity behind transmit from the
neoclassical sustainable perspectives, this tool was picked up by the sustainable narrative. And now
It not only allows to solve congestion, but actually it allows to limit the presence of the
current city, which of course supposedly makes a positive impact on the urban environment.
And this tool has been put in place in the number of cities in Europe.
So you hear sea pictures from Oslo, but actually this exists in pretty much all
Norwegian cities and towns. So a system of tolling gates in London, which is probably the most
important or the most known case in Europe, in Milan, but you also have similar policies and
instruments in Stockholm and Sweden. And then recently also in Brussels announced with a lot of
pump and circumstance this idea that now it will cost the user the end-user money to enter with
a car to the Brussels capital region. So while this gets a lot of attention and this policy is
is discussed as a very efficient tool
in terms of limiting the presence of the current in cities.
There is questionable evidence.
I'm not saying that this policy is a bad policy,
but it never works.
But basically, it's supposed productive results
in terms of limiting the car are not exactly
there in the evidence.
So the results are quite mixed.
On the one hand, we see that in a number of cities,
traffic, of course, diminishes.
But since it's the delimited zone,
it's quite particular.
So it's not a whole agglomeration that actually
has the access to the car limited.
We see that the traffic often moves from, of course,
the zone in which the congestion challenge
is applied to the outer areas.
In London, for instance, it's quite clear
that there is significantly more traffic around that zone.
It's the same case in Madrid, which essentially
followed a very similar principle.
There is also very questionable evidence
about what happens with the funds that are being raised
through these systems.
So while very often, these policies
are put in place with this narrative of saving the city
from the car, of making some kind of societal transition
to post-car society, in cities like Oslo or London,
funds from these schemes.
And in all that's very clear, in London,
maybe a little bit less transparent.
But at least part of these funds goes to actually maintenance
and construction of current construction.
In all it's very common practice
to put these congestion charging areas
or booths, if you will,
to actually subsidize the construction of specific
transport infrastructure, road tunnel or bridge.
It's done in a very transparent way.
So in a sense, it's basically asking the transport
the car user to contribute a little bit more,
because of course, this contribution is already there
through tax system, to the construction,
to the financing of the construction
of transport infrastructure of current infrastructure.
And finally, the impact of these schemes
on overall quality of the city,
not just on a quality in a specific area,
is quite limited.
So, yeah, I said it basically.
So despite the narrative of these practices
saving urban environment,
it's not exactly clear that this is the most obvious thing
to do to limit the smog in a city,
especially when these areas are quite,
especially limited.
The problems that immediately emerge
from policies like congestion charging is that,
well, it leads to some social segregation.
And so we expect that all people react to this policy in a similar way.
They will reconsider whether they want to try or not, whether they want to enter,
into the zone by current or not.
But in fact, of course, those who do not pay from the vehicle,
and in particular in Belgium, this is a policy that is very widespread.
Half of new vehicles sold in Belgium are so-called company cars,
which are received for free by employees from the company
as a way of giving them tax-free salary bonus basically.
So for these people who do not pay for the vehicle itself
and often whose consumption of the vehicle will gas,
or any kind of fuel they put in the car insurance,
this is all paid by the company very often.
This very often basically is included in the package.
So the congestion charging is actually not covered
by the individual, it's covered by the structure
that provides the vehicle in the first place.
While of course those who do not have a job who might be seeking one,
those who are from lower working class background who might also be doing very difficult,
complicated irregular trips that require entering and leaving in different times of day,
because they need to get to a job that quite simply requires getting by current.
Going back here to this example of somebody working logistics,
public transport between Mollenberg or Savantam, for example,
at three o'clock in the morning being simply not there,
you have to have a card to reach this kind of activity
to be able to access the kind of urban function.
And then ultimately, what it does to mobility
is commodified.
So it's an essentially neoliberal service.
You pay as much as you use.
It's not a common system anymore.
The idea is that everybody pays not according to the means
but according to the ultimately the price decided by the market.
So again, not to say that this is a part of good idea
but to say that there is quite simply a lot of questions
a lot of them quite clearly related to critical geography
that should be asked about these policies.
It's already passed seven.
So it's just we take at least 500 break
before we can continue.
So get a little bit of a drink.
whatever it is that you are you sipping to make through this lecture.
And I'll see you back in in for five minutes, all right.
Perfect.
Always.
you
got
I
you
(soft music)
(soft music Applied)
(soft music
(soft music Ultra-
(soft music)
(soft music fades)
(soft Zoom music)
(soft music Totally)
(soft music)
[ Silence ]
Okay, let's try to resume.
I'm going to share my screen once again.
All right.
Where are we?
All right
I suppose you hear me and you see me
Great perfect so
Continuing with the uneven geography of sustainable transport measures
Here you have a very simple
or even a map or a scheme that shows a little bit how this limitation plays out in space.
So also, I don't know if you've heard about that, but also is one of the most
-marketised cities in terms of its alleged fight against the car.
It's leading some kind of a war against the petrol fuel vehicles.
And basically there is this area in the city in which to which access is not only restricted
in terms of extra payment, right?
So there was a cube.
At several layers of this congestion charging,
and then the final one is this ultra inner city
in which cars propelled by gas or fuel.
I'm not allowed, there's only electric vehicles.
But then when you look at the whole
of the migration of the city is quite clear that,
I mean, this is a very small area.
So we are actually talking about quite specific zones
of the city, which as I mentioned,
supposedly saved from the car and as opposed to be made more pedestrian or people friendly.
Same idea or same limitation can be seen in Madrid which, until recently, had also quite a restrictive mobility area.
This has changed with a change of political majority, it does not matter, but this area still exists over the rules.
have changed to some extent.
The idea is that Madrid, which was called in worldwide media,
as an anti-car municipality, a municipality that takes
some radical measures to limit the presence of the car.
In fact, well, it does serve, but it does so
within quite limited designated area,
whereas you see that in a general map.
There is a whole current structure around it,
multiple motorways both around and from that central area.
So there's a question with the automability
is actually being properly challenged
or is this more of an urban policy that focuses
on valorization of specific areas of the city.
And here it's you don't have to be a smart critical geography
to ask if this is not part of some revitalization strategies
that try to increase rent and profits
to gentify quite simply a specific areas of the city,
the limitation of car traffic being part of that policy,
to beautify the area, to make it more attractive to tourists,
to specific type of investors, while limiting mobility
of this kind.
This we've covered.
And here we arrive to the well, to a case of such a policy,
limiting presence of the car, the Pietonier in Brussels,
which I'm quite sure.
All of you have already experienced and seen.
So, well, this map you've seen quite a lot before
and show Brussels with its zone 30,
so the limitation of speed there.
the Petonier marked in red at the moment of installation, the biggest pedestrian area in Europe.
I wonder whether you've got any impressions of this place before I show you my take on
or share with you my take on what happened over there. I imagine you have been to Lippetonia,
but do you have any any interesting thoughts about this? Do you like this place? Do you think
It's not so great. I don't know. I don't have a very deep thought about it. I don't think
but it's definitely nicer than it was. I mean, I lived in the center for like five years ago
or like five years ago, like long ago, but like it was really horrible. Like when you cycle
through like downtown it was really awful because like the road was just disgusting like
you don't you didn't really want to be there. I mean it's a bit I don't know I don't have
the feeling it's very much it's it's very true for what it is you know like for like I don't
know it doesn't really feel like a downtown it feels a little bit provincial but like at least
I'm definitely happy with that it's much better than it used to be.
It's definitely an improvement, but it feels the big city vibe a bit.
Okay.
But those of you who didn't see it before it was changing to a village scenario,
I think it's the slice you see in the top image how this street could look like on a Friday afternoon,
quite regularly.
So full of cars for full lanes.
And then, well, the situation, that's of course pre-covid.
Well, I don't know.
I probably right now, if you took that picture,
would be quite similar.
Anybody else who has some impressions
of how this transformation looked like?
Somebody who loves this, somebody who hates this,
and for whatever reason?
- I agree with you, everyone,
because it was a place.
And when I passed, when I studied in Brussels,
I would have passed with my girlfriends.
I don't want my girlfriend to let alone,
or they had to place some years ago.
But one frustration, I guess from,
I followed the top process.
And what I know was it was very difficult for transportation,
like like M.E.B. and the steep public transport,
to pass because the lane was cut.
- Yeah.
- So they waited for four, four, two hours to go to another place
when it set to us, five minutes was two hours.
- So you need to affect it the other modes of,
of trying to not only the car,
but also public transport.
- Yeah.
The victim was public transport and I guess in,
in Brussels, it's very important to,
when you have a prestige project like that,
You need to consider all of transport modes and not only pedestrians.
- Praise each project.
- I think also it's an important thing.
Also like an element to add maybe is that it's terrible
if you go by bike.
It's really not made for bicycles.
Like I tried cycling through it and I mean, right now
it's not so busy and it's all right.
But like on days when there's lots of tourists,
of course lots of people use the area.
So then it's really not nice to cycle there.
- Yes, I share these impressions.
I mean, these are not only impressions
and the fact is that this area was redeveloped
but without any bicycle policy in mind.
So there is basically, I'm not,
I'm the last person to say that what was there before
was great, but you can vaguely see it
on the right hand side of the top picture
that there is actually a bicycle lane.
Not a great one, but there was one.
Now it's simply not there.
somebody's writing something in the chat.
Why did they take down the larger trees
to be a traditionalization of Boulevardless?
But I find the landscaping quite poor.
Well, so there was a number of things at stake.
I mean, let's cover that first.
It was announced in January 2014,
the municipal authorities of the city of Brussels.
So we said, "Meel, Brussels 1000,
"and ours that they want to expand
"and existing pedestrians."
So you already had some streets,
especially towards the Commonwealth of London,
were not open for the class.
And the context of that-- and that's quite an important thing--
is that there was a series of protests
called Under the Slogon of Picnic the Streets,
a movement of some spontaneous civil disobedience.
Basically, people would occupy space that would normally
be taken by cars.
You see that in the top picture, normally a lot of cars.
So right in front of books, there
would be basically some kind of an action.
people would just sit down and enjoy their son and manifest that they want allegedly
this space to be for people, taken away from the cars. This space should be freed from
the cars to make the city centre of Brussels for sustainable, more attractive and more
livable. The project is launched in June 2015, so that's one of the
three is closed. And there is an eight-man test phase without any infrastructural change.
So at first, to go a little bit to the question of design, there is no design change. Basically,
the street is closed and there is as many people call it a sea of asphalt.
I mean suddenly you can walk on this on the street, which place a little bit,
of course, on people's imaginary that suddenly you realize how, how huge this
infrastructure given to the car is and what could happen in place of this infrastructure.
Well, and then progressively after this eight-month phase, we see some kind of
infrastructure development, so an actual change of the built environment.
The problem there is, is that, well, there was a quality of design that has been put in
the question.
I'm not a designer or landscape, but a lot of people have criticized the way that this
looks like.
The immediate limitation is that, right underground, we've got a canal towards the end
of the bits of the year, and we also have a metro line, of pre-metroline, which runs
right under the surface of the street.
So it's not, for example, possible apparently
to put large trees over there, which already
starts making an impact in terms of how the space is done.
Well, there were very high aspirations
when Pitunio was announced.
It was not only supposed to be a transport project,
or according to some scholars in Brussels,
or even politicians, it was not a transport project,
or a mobility project.
was an urban renewal project which by closing this Paris like Boulevard because actually
it is in its architecture very much an inspiration of Parisian boulevards. A closing of it to
motorized traffic was supposedly a step towards getting the city center or the city as such
out of the climb to put as the mayor of a moistel mill of the particular moistel
said that Brussels, the Belgian and European capital would finally enjoy a truly dynamic,
pedestrian, attractive and friendly inner city, like many other international metropolists.
The Plas de Guacare, which is located in the northern part of the Piedtagnier,
and that's the famous square famous I'm not sure, but the characteristic one with the Coca-Cola
and signed that lights up. It was compared to Times Square, so the idea was to make this project
It allowed Brussels to become an international city
to create this prestige project,
as it was, I think, very rightly said,
that would put Brussels on the international map.
It was not just a question of getting rid of some
correlated new senses.
And of course, the moment that plan was unearthed,
there were a number of critics.
So there were shopkeepers that were upset,
claiming that they would use customers
because people could not drive into the shop,
residents, a number of citizen organizations.
What were the issues that they would mention,
and even the problems that they would note about the project?
Well, they very much relate to this
and the geography that I was talking about.
So if you look at the map of the Pizzo here,
in red UCDs, at that time Europe's largest
pedestrian zone, I think now it's been surpassed by Ghent
and other cities.
Brussels is certainly not the only city in Europe
or in the world that engages in these policies.
It is, of course, the main central axis is cut, but you see that you can actually drive around the city center.
So you've got this area which is pedestrian friendly if we can put it this way, where cars mobility is extremely limited.
But in fact, you can quite easily drive into the Pentagon, as we call it, and drive around.
On top of that was also very clear is that a particularity of Brussels,
which is a very high presence of underground or multi-story parking lots,
is largely unquestioned.
So actually this day, today, there is about 19,000 parking spots within the
pendant, within the Struk City Centre of Brussels.
The original plan of pedestrianising will advance.
a lot included the creation of additional 1,600 parking spots.
So the idea would be that, of course, we give this space to the pedestrian and we allow this
space to be somehow reclaimed from the car.
But in fact, the cost of this, or the price of this, I don't know how to call it, is that
we actually add to the current infrastructure.
So we definitely do not want to make this be less accessible as it was called by the cars.
And then as one of you mentioned, there was an immediate conflict with a public transport
operator, the most important one in Brussels, Stephen McAvill, who basically saw their
lines pushed out of the zone.
So suddenly the buses that would cross that area have to have to have these stops relocated,
which means the accessibility for people who rely on public transport is somewhat reduced
right.
Well, that's some years later. I think that picture is from 2018, as I remember checking on Google.
Well, those are kind of a pushback, right? So the cars that were at first,
definitely not allowed in Petonier now in some circumstances, in some situations, can actually
enter. So you can actually see, and that's taken directly from Google, I didn't have to go to the
Petonier and wait for a track to enter. You actually see, of course, the delivery vehicles,
but also public transport you see over there in the back of the picture as she does a bus
making a turn and entering a petrion. And whenever I'm there with friends who are not from
Brussels, I mean they are really surprised to be on the pedestrian area with public transport
buses and trucks and taxi drivers and other vehicles who in exceptional circumstances actually can
enter. Which question is a little bit this, I mean is this a pedestrian area or is this a pedestrian
area but without really getting rid of all the costs.
The question of making this a prestige project and putting Brussels on the map,
I mean there is an argument there to be made and some local critical
geographers have made it myself included that this in fact indeed is not a
transport project in the mobility project. It's clearly a project of
of re-valorizing this particular part of the city, it's quite clear that as you go down
southwards down Boulevard of Stau and Boulevard of Le Monier towards the South Station
Government of Medi, those of you who have been there, I'm sure, I'm sure noticed it,
those of you who haven't, that's where we will go on the excursion that I hope we will
do.
In spring, you see that this is one of the poorest neighborhoods in Brussels, one with
very high youth unemployment, especially when there was a very precarious, tightly knit,
but very vulnerable local economy.
And any kind of change in built environments puts this economy under huge pressure, especially
when the narrative around Kaitanya clearly includes this idea of bringing big grants, tourism,
to the pedestrian area making this a place of facilities, of consumption, of continuous festival.
So for example, the ultimate for comments of the city of Brussels famously said that
the objective here is not to change mobility. The objective is to create a commercial
promenade, new brands which are not yet present in Brussels are coming. There is a real craze
and you can feel it. For the current Brussels 1000 May not the one that had to step down because
of some corruption scandal, the aim of the project is to keep or bring the middle-class
to Brussels to increase its tax base. So suddenly the idea is not just to or not at all to actually
get rid of the cars or allow pedestrians to enjoy in some kind of newly created area,
It's a very urban project in a very twisted way.
So the idea really is to create a new space and your neighborhood perhaps of consumption,
of leisure, of 24/7 shopping, which also, of course, uses or engages with the narrative
of sustainability and livability, and is somewhat related to mobility and transport, but to a limited
extent. Okay.
Can I still add something to that?
If you go back to that slide, you see that there is almost only white people there.
So the people that you talked about that you see on the lower slide, like the owners
of the PC market, owners of the 5.50, basically all people with a color, they don't
feature in the marketing of the city about the project.
It's a very good point, of course. That's a very common issue with these visualizations
and imagining of future.
Everyone's super white. But there's one black man on the right.
But there's also no people with disabilities, very few old people.
Yes, it's not a very diverse image. It's a good point. And also in no way does it correspond
the actual reality of that neighborhood and the kind of services.
Absolutely not.
Well, I mean, yeah.
Well, I'm really just teed it up.
So we cover some important stuff until we finish.
No, no, but thank you.
It's a good comment.
There is, of course, all issues related to participation
and no actual change of power in the P
is a very good example of how these sustainable ideas
can be applied without changing at all questions of who actually decides and for whom transport
policies are being made. So very often the sustainable discourse focuses when a
demandance participation of users of the of the of the of the projects. It basically
imagines that the main idea is that it will consensus to inform people of the decisions that
are rational, that are good practices, best practices in terms of achieving sustainable
mobility, protecting the environment and whatnot.
So as a Flamish actually scholar once wrote it in 2000
about the problems of sustainable transport policies.
That's the last bullet point.
These policies include a harmonious and conflict
of only vocabulary that ignores and silences
the deeply contested ways through which the transport system
is continuously shaped and transformed,
and which inevitably results in a variety of winning
and losing interest groups.
in the case of the Kit-Wun-Ye, but that's, I think,
the case in many other sustainable transport projects.
This idea of winners and losers is swept under the carpet.
So in theory, everybody gains,
but those who are clearly upset are not heard,
are not really listened to and often are mocked.
So again, we go back to this moral geography
of bad behavior and good behavior,
of silly shopkeepers who don't understand
that this is a project that they will benefit from,
bad car drivers, they want to access the city,
versus good consuming middle class pedestrians
or cyclists, not so much on the case of duplicating method.
Cyclists are also part of the vision.
And in all this, to make this point quite short,
there is much more impact,
no, not impact, much more focus,
much more emphasis on the success of these practices,
rather than on the interaction with complex social,
spatial phenomena that are there in the city.
So there was much more focus on the transport part
of transport project rather than on the urban part
of the purchase.
Well, we don't have a lot of time to deal with,
okay, what could be done with this hegemony
of neo-Neoclassical on the one hand, that's last week,
and sustainable on the other.
That's today, perspective on transport, but let's try.
So what would diverse critical approaches
to transport and mobility be?
On the one hand, the new mobility paradigm.
So that's another reading for today,
if you manage to read it, that's great.
If not, I encourage you to have a look
because that's an absolutely fundamental reading
for mobility scholars these days.
I mean, many shallering John Aria
to very important figures in this field of geography
or any kind of discipline that deals with mobility and transport.
So here, we've got a bit of a shift of attention,
shift of focus, and it's really putting,
it's shifting away from transport as an infrastructural phenomenon,
for example, to a mobility as a social and political phenomenon
that's an respective built on diverse disciplines
from sociology and political studies to a geography
and anthropology.
And it really explores a lot of issues
cultural studies scholars for example, would deal with looking at a number of phenomena happening in
cities. So different representations and meanings of mobility, sensations, experiencing
experiences of mobility. Everything that happens on this might for level of what people,
what kind of practices and norms are being observable, being practiced in mobility related spaces
in public transport for example, in these pedestrian areas. What cultural codes and norms are related
to optimability. The problem with this particular approach is that well it looks very much at the
micro level and whenever it engages with structural issues around mobility it runs the risk of
being quite descriptive. So it mentions a number of issues, race, class, inequality but there is not
so much over methodological depth in terms of exploring these issues. And also it's a constant that
that is quite Western in a sense that they developed
in the global north and in rather specific areas of it.
And it only now starts engaging with situations
with empirical context, indigo global stuff.
Another approach, another avenue for doing critical research
by the trust of mobility is building on the traditions
of urban political economy of transport, right?
So looking at the city as a social and political construct,
which by no means, by in no way,
is governed by some rational laws of supply and demand,
like in the new classical paradigm,
or which does not really look at people as consumers
that have to be convinced to drop or to disengage
from unwelcome or bad type of behavior
and standing engaging in good type of behavior.
But rather looking at people at urban inhabitants as political agents who do not make just rational decisions in terms of how they move,
but have a political potential to shape the urban reality, to change how transport and mobility is organized in the locality in this city.
And when you look at critical urban geography and a lot of names that I'm sure you've already heard or maybe even read from before,
David Harvey, Neil Smith, Edward Sarger,
Dave all contributed to conceptualizing
to exploring this lane between
and for structural development
and social spatial distribution of public services.
So transport has been there to analyze
the critical development of the city.
But absolutely foundational readings there
or the first step towards critically exploring
the relationship between the transport and density,
come from feminist geographers who would arrive
and that's the reading that you also,
I think was assigned for today.
Susan Hansen's work on deconstructing this
behind the divide between the home and work
and attaching women with domestic situations
and apparently imagining them as less mobile beings
while attaching this mobility potential to predominantly male subjects and male situations.
And also, well, a very important part of that is to understand the homework
relationship in the homework commute, which I mentioned last week is absolutely the most
well, it's a foundational focus of transport geographers, analyzing these mobility
patterns related to the move from work to home. The feminist geographers already in 1980s
demonstrated that this way of looking at transport and also this way of engaging mobility is
fundamental for maintaining capital. This is something that is the cornerstone of the
of the capitalist system in cities or outside of them. What emerges from this is understanding
Transport and mobility is not just an infrastructural phenomenon or something that has some
environmental repercussions and some social ones and here I'm thinking about sustainable approach
to mobility, but as essentially a form of capital, mobility is a potential that is unevenly
distributed as any form of capital around a cross-society across its different spaces and across
it's classes, which leads to understanding and challenging different structures, social, political,
economic, that stand behind what makes transport unsustainable in the first place. So it's really
asking you a question why are people moving in particular ways not because they are used to a
particular lifestyle because they have some cultural norms but understanding a political and
economic system that enables, for instance, the domination of the car and trying to address the
the system as a result rather than looking at how people can be convinced and
all how situation in terms of mobility can be changed in specific areas of the city.
It's looking at things much more, much more broadly, much more structural always.
Right. So, and here I attached the geography to the end of this, to this slide.
So you can look at these different studies if you, if you're interested in
transport and mobility.
There is a line of research that is looked at the transport
and mobility as a way of reproducing existing social,
political, economic interests, regulatory frameworks,
power relations regulated by the market on the one hand
and by the state, and very often contested by from the bottom
up.
There is a lot of research, for some reason,
the references are not showing up.
But if you're interested, I'm more than happy to send you
that something is stranded with my slightly.
But there isn't ongoing work already going back to the 1990s
that shows how neoliberal policies that affect urban culture,
provision of housing, urban environment,
are also extremely present in provision of transport
and mobility, how in a natural transport
is increasingly commodified.
And for example, congestion charging,
and as I mentioned today, it's part of that.
It's turning, and we could think public space
that an urban motorway or an urban street
is, it to a commodity that has an additional price
that I can touch to it, which as we consume,
we have to additionally pay for, depending,
as I mentioned, not on our means, but basically
on our demand.
There is also a fundamental issue that many geographers dealt
with, that is of transport related inequality
and exclusion, so basically trying to understand,
to what extent transport enables movement of some people
while restricting that of others.
This will skip.
And of course, well, it might seem very obvious today,
but if you look at what was being done in geography,
now in geography or transport geography in the '80s,
the '90s was definitely not the case.
There is now a rise of research, which
looks at the questions of class and the questions of race
and the question of gender is absolutely fundamental
for understanding transport systems in cities and beyond them.
And one of them is this, well,
maybe not such a foundational reading,
but still something that is very important
and really define the agenda of research
into transport for at least this decade.
Of course, there's more recent stuff
that also has been written,
but I think this is quite a nice introduction
with the question of gender and mobility.
And here, we see that as with the questions of race
and the question with class, but this
is something that was already quite established
and if you'll already, there is an inseparable relationship
between gender and mobility.
That, on the one hand, transfer of mobility
mean development or some kind of opening
of accessibility to different opportunities,
breaking this supposed paradigm of the domestic female
and the work-related male, but actually mobility
is something that opens this paradigm,
that gender on the other hand affects travel reasons
and patterns in terms of the complexity,
in terms of the frequency and regularity,
and in terms of why actually people engage in movement,
why is they actually move around the city?
And perhaps one critique that could be made
the paper that I ask you to read for today is that the approaches women as a rather unified category
that can be maybe not reduced but summarized in terms of particular mobility patterns that
half of humanity engages. I think that's a little bit risky always. But what clearly I think is
interesting in this kind of line of work, as I said, there is a definite follow-up and work that
explore these questions in much more detail and it's much more fine to you to
sophisticated. But we see that without considering the agenda component we
basically missed the fact that in many urban contexts women engaged in a
completely different way with mobility. They conduct trips which are
much more complex, regular because they quite simply are related to
diverse, care-related activities. They would be much more inclined or
or perhaps forced to bring other people along to act as drivers for other passengers,
and because they engage in quite simply more activities than male subjects.
In this way, I'm simplifying here, of course, a whole lot,
but this way of approaching transport and mobility,
uncovers not only differences in terms of how people move,
but differences in terms of power relations that are there behind movement
and transport, which in my humble opinion is maybe a little bit there in sustainable
approaches to mobility, but it's quite simply not pronounced enough or it does not really show us
in full depth the the multi-level structure of power relations that are there behind
behind transport and mobility. Now what's left, we are running out of time so I don't
don't want to talk about everything, but what's also important to remember is that, well,
besides questions of transport workers, because so far we've basically talked mostly, if not
only about passenger transport users, people who use transport. There's a question of transport
labour, but also very importantly, a lot of research done on transport and mobility is a vehicle
for some contestation, discontent and struggle.
And I started these two sessions with Greta Tundberg,
with protests in Chile and other places.
And year in, year out, sometimes month in month out,
you see that transport is used as a very important subject
for a lot of very diverse movements and social groups
to express the discontent with whatever it is.
sometimes quite directly capitalist system,
and that's the case with Gilles-Jon,
who quite symbolically would occupy
roundabouts across rural or suburban France,
and sometimes symbolically,
and that's an East Jerusalem,
Palestinian activists attacking the light rail,
and kind of traumway stations,
as a symbol of Israeli colonization in East Jerusalem.
Sometimes this would be protest against
some kind of the surface level policy, like the increase of public transport fares or policing
and that's the case in New York City, or the construction of one of these underground parkings
related to the Piotonier that would add to the number of parking spots in the city while
supposedly actually opening the city for the for the people. This we will have to skip.
The very last point that I want to make today, I mean I still would like to give us maybe
10 minutes for your questions and maybe some comments.
If you still have energy to do that,
is that, and that's perhaps related a little bit
to this question of neoliberalization of transpose
and mobility, is that what we see is that
despite these different theoretical approaches
and critical questions that people,
critical geographers are asking,
we see a process of standardization
of transport policies.
So if you are a transport engineer and transport economist today,
there is really distancing towards unifying experiences
of different cities into a portfolio of best practices,
which are then transferable from one or currently
to another.
There's a huge business behind it,
and not only in terms of think towns and big consultancy firms,
but a whole flurry of events,
which you can learn from experiences of others,
which you can learn about what your city should be doing.
And some scholars have engaged with that,
studying specifically the policy mobility
of these best practices and recipes
in the field of urban transport.
But what's perhaps quite important to be to be added to this
is that, well, the story of policy transfer is quite long.
I mean, the tradition of deploying Western worldviews,
Eurocentric concepts and theories and methods
in a more or less unchanged way
in some other geographical contexts in Africa, Asia, Latin America,
is a very long story and the story as a name and its colonisation of coloniality.
And this is something that really is there to be done by the future generation of critical geographers,
or the transport geographers, or urban geographers. Is that of decolonising this body of knowledge
which pretty much everything that I have referred to in these two sessions comes very much
from the global north that reflects my own education, that's something that I think I still have
to do myself, is to really start looking at transport reality and start defining,
formulating questions about this reality in terms of transit mobility, not from our global
will know them perspective, but also that of the South.
And just again, it's just a simple example
of what this could mean in practice,
is looking at the question of informality in transport,
which traditionally, that's a slide from one
of these classic reports commissioned,
I think either by UN or the World Bank
on informal transport, looks at informality in transport
as something that means bad quality,
in terms of safety of passengers, speeding, environmental impact,
basically some alt-ricutty vehicles,
which are a way to be transformed into modern, Western,
formal public transport system.
The kind of we know from northern cities, like Brussels
or many others in Belgium, France or Germany, whatnot.
But, and that's something that has been done quite recently
is in process, is actually understanding our experience of transport and mobility in our formal
environments is very much something that can be informed by these informal experiences of the
Google South. An example, well, if you ever are at Garlic Media these days unfortunately this practice
is on hold because of you know what, there is a flurry maybe not but at least a few informal
transport practices that you can find in the Galdimi area, these informal taxis, vans that bring
passengers informally somewhat illegally from the south station to Sharlowar Airport to the
Brussels south Sharlowar Airport and to Paris, which exhibit very strong similarity with
many other informal practices that you can find in cities across South Asia, Africa and Latin America.
And then finally, while these practices of course attract whenever they do, they attract very negative
attention of the media, of the police, they have treated as something that is illegal and be unfair
to formal regulators that pay taxes and have to operate within the legal framework of, in this case,
the Brussels capital region, there is, and here we go back to the beginning of the first session,
A number of practices which are proposed by the transport industry,
transfer the mobility industry, Uber and many other app-based practices,
which are essentially informal practices, which try to operate in the insertices of the system,
somewhat legal, but also not to the full extent. If you think, for example, about what Uber does
to its workers or what is the spatial impact, if we can put this way or these
East Kudos, which operate in public space, but very often literally occupy the space, the paving
and whatnot, without necessarily making this system officially legal or recognised.
Well, here we pause our little write of two sessions. I apologise for this bit of a fast
pace ending to the second session, but I realise that we run out of time for discussing
things a little bit more detailed way, but we still have eight minutes for some
questions if you have them, maybe some points that you you have in your in your
head right now something that you want to share. This is the moment.
And maybe I'll stop sharing my slides.
Do you have some questions, some comments?
Well, it's perfectly fine if you don't, of course.
I mean, it's quite late in the day I understand it.
And it's definitely a suboptimal experience to do that through Zoom or any of these platforms.
Oh, right.
Vitaly is asking about transport labour.
There's also one more technical question.
Well, quite simply the concept of transport labour looks at labour relations and conditions in transport.
is trying to change the emphasis a little bit.
I mean, if you look at the literature
on the neoclassical or sustainable side,
and the dominant focus of, I would really say,
99% of the studies is on the passenger
or the driver or the consumer.
The question of what working conditions
are shift to sustainable transport intervals, for example,
It's very rarely asked.
And that I think can lead us into some dead end situations,
in which, for example, we really give a lot of hope
and we build a lot of expectations
towards some ability practices like Uber,
like the electric scooters or whatnot,
without really understanding that,
and that comes from transport-level literature,
that the main innovation that Uber brings to the table
perhaps is not connecting drivers and users,
because it existed before.
And I mean, informal transport without the app, of course.
But it exists in most cities in the world,
in a global, some global nodes
and cities being an exception rather than rule.
But the actual innovation is degrading
transport, degrading working relations
to end of the 19th century.
Basically, a worker has very few rights.
doesn't have to write the unionized collectively bargain.
And it's not even recognized as a worker.
It's basically some kind of free atom contractor
who in spare leisure time engages in driving people
around the city, which we all know from now
the whole body of work on Uber is definitely not the case.
And these people are full-time workers,
not just hubists who try to make some spare money
on the side.
So yes.
That's what's transport labor is about.
Some technical questions.
Let's address those.
For the next discussion,
Seminar is at the same way of working with PowerPoint and voice over.
Well, the way I understand you did it in other discussion
Seminuses that you basically recorded your presentation,
which then either you sent to me,
I think that's probably a better solution.
solution and we basically listen to and then we have a discussion in which you facilitate
it, right, as those who discuss the paper. So it's not exactly a voiceover. I mean,
so you don't present the PowerPoint's life, the ideas that you pre-record the presentation
with your fellow students. And will the exam be online as well? Yes, the exam will be
online and we are meeting with Basnik and David to discuss exactly how this will be
down most likely will be in well obviously since we will not be in your rooms it
will be an open book exam so you will have access to the slides and all that so
but since we haven't done that before it will be a classic exam we are
discussing how to do this so that it's challenging enough for you and also
not too difficult right so it's with the voice of an indeed. Has the Belgian
Brussels government have taken any action to prevent informal transportation. Do you know how
relaxed they are towards this? Well actually I researched these navets as they quote.
"Nelgo from midi to the shallower airport and no, the Brussels government is definitely not happy
about these informal tax, the situation there is that these men, all of them are are are are
Cameo, official taxi drivers, so they have a taxi license, but what they basically do is that
make more money, they offer individual seats in the vans and they taxi. And that's precisely what's
illegal. So you cannot, as a taxi driver in Brussels, you cannot basically stand there on the street
and try to approach potential passengers, offering them individual places in the car.
It has to be the whole car that is rented.
Well, it's a bit ironic, but what happened a few years after this practice
got into the focus of, I don't want to say, public debate, but basically these drivers
started being harassed by police and there was a legal procedure against them.
Flitco, I don't know if that name rings a bell. It's a company that runs the official bus
from me to Shalawa Airport, started exactly that. So they're basically now
offer well now it's standard but they started offering a van service which goes door to gate
as it's called and it picks individual passengers and individual seats are offered. And for
some reason this is perfectly legal whereas the taxi drivers are partly engaging in an illegal activity.
So just as a rebound you know why Flipkuh implemented this in a non-competitive way
why I mean is that they're actually more expensive than the Navet,
they're like informal and a bit. Because I think they have a very different customer target.
So people who would take a Navet, that's also from my own work, they would be very often
of immigrant backgrounds, so there's a lot of people from Eastern Europe, from Maccribe,
who are quite simply used to do this mode of transport for them. This is a very common thing to see
and use in the country of origin.
And also, the drivers of the Navet
would basically find the customers on the spot itself.
So you walked towards the bus.
I don't know if you've ever had that experience.
But whenever I had to walk to the bus of Flikko,
they would try to approach you and convince you to write with them.
Whereas I think people who use the internet
with access to a website who can know how to book a ride,
with a credit card to book a right, that's a different target group.
So maybe that's why if people can offer prices
which are not exactly competitive on the economic front.
Well, what it means that's the last sentence about an event
is that informality in this case,
it's some kind of a front for, in this case,
state institutions to define what's legal or not.
I mean, for them to decide that the naviet,
this informal drivers are informal and therefore legal.
I mean, it's an arbitrary decision
to decide that this is informal, whereas Uber is formal.
Or actually in the case of Uber,
and Brussels authorities,
the regional authorities pretend that Uber does not exist.
So they don't chase it away,
but they also don't promote it,
which is a perfect playground for Uber.
They are, they, that's exactly what they want.
They are not interested in being recognized as an official public transport service, for
example, because that would mean having to comply with a lot of regulations, which they
are of course not interested in complying with.
In your research about this, do you know if like Uber drivers partner up with the like
informal Navet drivers to actually try convince clients to use the informal Navet rather
than the Flipkop for example.
No, I don't know.
In this particular case, they definitely not.
I mean, the event drivers, as most taxi traffic
and bus will be hate over, they really
don't like that it exists because it basically
eats into the market.
I'm not saying that taxi drivers here are some angels
and most, I don't know, fun people to work with or on,
But they can also offer services which are overpriced
and try to rip off tourists and all of our young people
who come back home intoxicated by taking a very long route
or whatever.
With Uber, of course, the advantages
that you know the price before you get into the car,
more or less.
But in this case, no, there's definitely no collaboration.
I've said that there is some conflict even.
You've probably heard about not already
happened at least three times massive strikes
of taxi drivers against some kind of effort
towards regularizing Uber by the Russell's
and capital region authorities.
Any more questions, comments?
Well, it also goes without saying that at some point
will be picking topics for your master thesis.
And you are very welcome to pick some related
to transport and mobility, either supervised by me
or by other people.
There is some more in our team and in different departments
as well.
But I don't know if I succeeded, probably to some extent,
but not fully.
But if there was one thing that I really wanted you
to understand about transport and mobility
is that at least from the critical geographical perspective,
it's a really, really diverse field.
There's plenty of things to do.
And there's plenty of interesting things to do.
So I really look forward to seeing your research topics
and hope that at least some of them will be related
to transport availability.
If you need some little push or some encouragement,
we are always there to help you with finding
some interesting literature for inspiration or whatnot.
So, I really, really hope we meet in person one day.
I hope it's not too far in the future.
I really hope that we can do an excursion,
even though it's on the transport, it's interesting.
People say, so voila, I really hope that we can do that
in March, April, May, the latest.
So, until then, I wish you all the best with everything
and with the exam.
Good luck. Don't get discouraged by this online paradigm. It will be away soon. I hope.
So we will be in touch with you about the exam. Don't worry about it.
Enjoy. See you later.
[BLANK_AUDIO]